译者导读

这是一本关于信心与毅力、绝望与拯救的灵修名篇，凝聚了圣徒们历经艰辛、不畏挫折的属灵智慧，旨在指导心怀基督的信徒们不断完善自身修为及内心体验。

本书作者托马斯·厄·肯培是中世纪著名哲学家，推崇信心要与上帝“神秘的合一”，才能达到重生和新生。该书在基督教教内流传甚广，几乎成为必读的“圣书”之一。书中不仅涉及神学知识，还引领跟随基督的信徒们敬拜主、祈求主。在效法基督灵修生活的过程中，作者倡导谦卑地认识自我，内心纯洁简单地靠近主，不要轻信人言，却应谨慎从容地遵照神的旨意深思熟虑。智慧莫大于行事不草率，处事不固执。在研读圣经中，追求圣灵的益处。遇到难以理解的地方，不要急于研究讨论，可暂时搁置，顺其自然。如果你渴望获益更多，就应谦卑、纯一和信服它，不要自视博学。要在宁静中聆听圣人的话，乐意接受先贤的教导，因为他们的话都出于心中美好的缘由。

它教导人们若要得享心中真正的宁静，必须克制情欲而非放纵享乐。沉溺于世俗情欲的人，心中难存宁静，只有虔诚灵性的人才能永享内心安乐。不要自视比他人都强，更不要炫耀你的财富，或是倚仗朋友的财势自命不凡，而应赞赏上帝的恩典。主赐予你万物和他自己。不要因身材优美、体格健壮而自傲，极小的疾病就能打倒你，甚至摧毁你；不要因天赋聪颖、能力非凡而自视清高，那样就会冒犯主，因为这一切都是上帝赐予你的。我们应当审视自己，而不要计较他人过往的行为。论断他人，不但徒劳无获，而且常常出错，很容易犯罪。但如果我们时常反省自己，就能获益匪浅。我们判断事物常受个人情感的左右，会因为个人目的而很难正确作出判断。倘若我们能以上帝为自己意向的目标，我们就不至于因尘世思想的矛盾而轻易被迷惑。

本书中基督的平安、喜乐、安慰与丰富，如同早春之花雨，滋润着信徒们的心田。希望“内心生活”的灵性结晶让每一位读者在爱与荣光中体验并获得与神相谐的智慧。

第一卷　精神生活的劝言

第一章　论效法基督

主说过：“跟从我的，就不在黑暗里走。”[1]

基督用这些话劝导我们，如果渴望摒弃内心的盲目，追求真正的启迪和自由，就跟随他的脚步，像他一样生活。首先，让我们先考量耶稣基督[2]的生活。

耶稣的教导超越了一切圣人，无论谁拥有了圣灵，都能发现隐秘的天赐之物。然而，尽管许多人经常听到福音，却往往未受其感召，因为他们缺少基督的圣灵。若要理解并领略基督话语的乐趣就必须倾注一生跟随主。

如果你缺少谦卑的态度，就会触怒三位一体的真神，那么即使学识再渊博，侃侃而谈其中的道理，对你又有什么意义呢？高谈阔论不能使人正直或圣洁，有道德的生活才能使他亲近上帝。我宁愿具有痛悔之心，而不知痛悔的定义。如果没有上帝的恩典和慈爱，即使你能默诵全本《圣经》和所有哲人的教诲，这一切对你又有什么用处呢？除了爱主，侍奉主以外，“虚空的虚空，凡事都是虚空”。[3]这就是至高的智慧——无视凡世的事物，每日都更接近天国。

追逐尘世的荣耀、人间的地位尽是徒劳；追求肉身的享乐、现世的回报不过枉然；不追求道德高尚的生活而一味祈求长寿，没有任何意义；不为来世做打算而一心顾念现世，只是白忙一场；不向往永恒快乐的所在而痴心于转瞬即逝的事物，无非黄粱一梦。

应时刻提醒自己，“眼看，看不饱；耳听，听不足”。[4]莫分心于有形之物，尽力爱怜无形之物。受制于本能的人终将腐化纯洁的内心，失去上帝的恩典。

第二章　论谦卑

人都有求知的本能，但如不敬畏上帝，知识本身又有什么用呢？对主而言，侍奉他的谦逊农夫胜过高傲自大通晓天文地理的知识分子，因为他忽略了探究自己的心灵。真正了解自己的人必定能认识自己的卑微，而不是陶醉于别人的溢美之词。如果没有爱，纵使我博古通今，无一不知，也不能在上帝审判我的功过是非时助我一臂之力。

要节制过度的求知欲望，因为那会带来不安和欺骗。有学问的人总是期望展现自己的才华，渴望他人赞赏自己的智慧。但学问对内心仅有很少的甚至是毫无益处。其实，如果一个人整日忙于无论任何一种事物，他都不是一个聪敏的人，除非是忙于那些能够进一步救赎自己的事情。长篇大论并不能充实心灵，只有道德高尚的生活才能令你焕然一新，内心纯洁才会对主信心倍增。

你的知识得越详尽完备，所受的审判就越严厉，除非你生活得更崇高圣洁。所以，不要因你有一技之长或博闻多识而唯我独尊，而应该尊重你所了解的知识。如果你看起来博学多才见多识广，也不要忘记在许多领域你仍孤陋寡闻。因此，莫沾沾自喜，要承认无知。为何当许多人按照《圣经》律法比你更明智完美时，你要凌驾于他人之上呢？倘若你渴望在认知或学习中受益匪浅，就要乐于默默无闻，微不足道。

正确认识自我，谦卑评价自我是最高深珍贵的教训。自视若无，却总是称赞他人大智大德。你若见到他人公然作恶，或心怀鬼胎，不要高看自己比他好，因为你不知自己能这样蒙受神恩到多久。我们都是脆弱的人；一切事物比自己都更坚强。

第三章　论教导真理

受真理而非符号言语教导的人，将感到无比幸福。我们常常为自身的揣测和观察所误导，而不能有所发现。当我们最终受到审判并不是依据这类知识时，关于那些深奥难解的事情的冗长辩论又有何价值呢？最愚蠢莫过于忽视有益且重要的事，却刻意关注古怪而有害的事。我们真是“有眼却不能看”[5]：“属”和“种”之类的概念与我们有什么关系呢？

受教于永生之道的人要从无常和易变中被救出来。万物之源为我主，世界的一切皆源自他之名，他是一切的创造者，我们都受教于此。若无我主，我们就不能正确领悟或判别任何事物。但若有一人，视万物齐一，将万物归一，并于一中窥得万物，则其心性坚定，能追随上帝一同获得宁静。

噢，真理的主啊，请在永恒的爱中将我与你合而为一。我时常厌倦自己的所读所闻。我所奢望追求的仅仅是归于主。因此，所有的老师请保持沉默吧，所有的受造之物[6]都在你面前静止吧；噢，主啊，只有你的声音。

人的内心越纯洁简单地靠近主，越能多角度深入地了解事物，不费吹灰之力，因为他沐浴着上天的智慧之光。纯净、简单、稳重的人不会因为工作忙碌而心烦意乱，他因为上帝的荣光而奋斗，努力远离自私的追名逐利。有什么比内心不安分的激情更能妨碍和伤害你的呢？善良且虔诚的人对于事情的轻重已了然于胸，无论身处何种情形，都不会使自己限于罪恶的诱惑之中，而是睿智判断，谦卑应对。还有比战胜自己更激烈的斗争吗？这应该是我们奋斗的重心——战胜自我，每天都变得更强大，向神圣迈进。

现世一切的完满都伴随着某种缺憾，所有的知识亦夹杂着晦涩难懂。自视卑微比钻研学问更容易靠近上帝。然而求知本身，抑或关于任何事物的知识本身并无过错，因为认真学习是上帝认可的好事；但我主更赞许天性善心，圣洁生活。但由于许多人宁可努力追求知识，忽视圣洁的生活，所以他们经常误入歧途，虚度年华，一无所得。我们若能像研究学问那样据理力争，摒除邪恶，播撒德行，我们中间就不会有那么多罪恶和丑闻。审判之时，不会问我们已经得知什么，而是我们的所作所为；不会看我们如何口若悬河，而是如何圣洁地生活过。请告诉我，那些当时的博学之士现在又身在何处呢？别人占有他们的位置，却对他们毫无挂念。他们尚在人世时，可谓举足轻重，但此刻已无人问津。

啊，现世的荣华转瞬即逝！只有这些人的生活如同他们的学问那样令人景仰，那些研究和阅读才能得善果。但现世又有多少人徒劳追求学问，皓首穷经，忽视了服侍我主。因为他们只愿伟大而放弃谦卑，迷失在自己的幻想中。真正的伟人对上帝心怀大爱。真正的伟人内心谦卑，不慕名利。真正的智者将尘世万物视如粪土，只为归向基督。真正的学者因神的旨意而放弃自我的意愿。

第四章　论慎行

我们不该轻信人言，而应谨慎从容地遵照神的旨意深思熟虑。唉，这是人性的弱点，常评说别人的短处，却不发现他人的长处。但完人从不轻信他听到的每个故事，因为知道人性本恶，而且易于在言语上陷于过失。

智慧莫大于行事不草率，处事不固执。耳食之言不应奔走相告。向睿智善良比你优秀的人虚心取经，而不要刚愎自用。有德行的生活遵从上帝，使人睿智且阅历丰富。越自视低微，遵从上帝，越睿达明智，内心平和。

第五章　论读圣经

在圣经中我们所寻求的是真理，并非华丽的辞藻。阅读所有神圣的文字时，都应读出当年它们被写下时蕴含的精神。因此，我们在圣经中当找寻灵魂的食粮，而非美丽的语言。既应诵读那些浅显易懂的书，也应阅读那些高深奥秘的卷册。不要计较作者的权威或学问的水平，而应怀着对真理纯粹的热爱去读书。不要追问是谁的言论，只要注意所说的言语。

人固有一死，但神的圣言将与世长存。

上帝用不同的方式与我们对话，却不与人亲近。有时我们读圣经，也受到好奇心的搅扰。遇到难以理解的地方，不要急于研究讨论，可暂时搁置，顺其自然。如果你渴望受益匪浅，就应以谦卑、纯一和信服的心去读，不要自视博学。自由发问，然后在宁静中聆听圣人的话，耐心聆听神父讲述《圣经》中的寓言故事，因为它们总是劝人向善的。

第六章　论控制欲望

无论何时放纵自己的欲望，内心立刻就会感到不安。骄傲贪婪的人绝不会得到平静。贫穷谦卑的人才常享安宁。人若还未完全摒弃自我，就容易被极微小的事物所诱惑，且无法抵制诱惑。精神脆弱、沉迷感官和肉体享乐的人很难摆脱贪恋尘世的欲望。因此当他尝试脱离这些欲望时，他就感觉非常痛苦；若遭到反对就勃然大怒。但假若他如愿以偿，又立刻因屈服于自己的欲望而良心不安。期望从情欲的生活中寻求平静，只是徒劳无功。想要得到心中真正的宁静，必须克制情欲而非放纵享乐。沉溺于世俗情欲的人，心中难存宁静，只有热忱、属灵的人才能永享内心安乐。

第七章　论避免妄想和高傲

信靠人类或受造之物是非常愚蠢的。出于对耶稣的爱而去服侍他人，现实中过着贫苦的生活，不要引以为耻。不要自以为是，而要完全相信主。尽己所能，上帝必保守你美好的意愿。不要依赖你自己的知识，或是轻信任何活人的智慧，而应遵从上帝的恩典，他帮助谦卑的人，却让高傲的人懂得谦卑。

不要炫耀你的财富，或是倚仗朋友的权势自命不凡，而应赞赏上帝的恩典。主赐予你万物和他自己。不要因为你身材优美、体格健壮而自傲，极小的疾病就能打倒你，甚至摧毁你。不要以为自己天赋聪颖、能力非凡而自视甚高，以免冒犯主，因为这一切都是上帝赐予你的。

不要自视比他人都强，以免你在上帝的眼中变得更糟，只有主了解人的心。不要为自己的善行而居功自傲，主的评价不同于人；取悦于人的行为常常触怒我主。假若你有何优点，要记住他人比你优点更多；所以要保持谦卑。居众人之下对你并无损害，但你若自命不凡，只会事与愿违。只有谦卑的人常享心中的宁静，而骄傲的心则尽是傲慢与嫉妒。

……

第十章　论避免多言

尽可能避免公共集会，谈论世俗琐事，即使出于善意，也不免惹祸上身，因为我们极易因尘世的虚荣而腐化迷惑。我经常后悔没保持沉默，恨不得未曾与人在一起。我们为什么总那样乐于滔滔不绝，喋喋不休，甚至当我们良心不安时仍不停止呢？我们乐于交谈的原因是想从谈话中寻求慰藉，放松紧张的大脑。并且我们乐于谈论自己喜好或厌恶的东西。但可惜这些交谈徒劳无功，表面的安慰常常让我们失去了上帝赐予的平和内心。

我们应该儆醒祷告，否则便虚度光阴。假若遇到合适的说话时机，可以谈论有价值的问题。习惯不良且忽视灵性进步是我们放纵自己多言的主要缘由。但若和一些志同道合事奉上帝的人虔诚地谈论属灵的事，那对于我们的灵性进步具有极大的推进作用。

第十一章　论内心平和及灵性进步

我们如果不忙于关注别人的言行，就可享受极大的平和，因为那本就是与我们无关的事。人如果总是关注他人的事情，并且总是寻求机会闲逛，而很少甚至几乎不省察自己，他怎会享受到长久的平和？心意纯一的人受到祝福，因为他们要享受极大的平和。

为什么有些圣人是那样的完全且善于沉思？因为他们都曾不屈不挠地克服自己世俗的欲望，因而才能无拘无束、至诚至深地跟随上帝，并将自己全然地献给他。但我们深受欲念的牵制，贪恋过往的世俗之事。我们很少彻底纠正一个错误，内心也没有热切追求进步的愿望，所以我们总是停在原地，麻木不仁，或者不温不火。

我们若全然忘我，摆脱内心纠结，就能够品味到圣灵之美和神圣的沉思经历。事实上，最大的阻碍在于我们没有摆脱情欲的束缚，也没有遵循圣人完善自我的道路。我们一遇到小麻烦，就一蹶不振，寻求人间的抚慰。

如果我们像顽强的勇士守卫战场一样坚守本心，就不会失去主的帮助。因为主总是援助那些顽强作战，信赖他恩典的人。主还会提供给我们赢得胜利的机会。倘若我们认为只要表面遵守宗教仪式，宗教生活就能进步，那么我们的信仰即面临绝境了。让我们剪草除根，脱离情欲的束缚，我们就会得到灵魂的安宁。

如果我们每年根除一个错误，我们很快就应该成为完善的人。但我们常常面临相反的境遇，皈依之初比多年之后更善良，更纯洁。我们的热情与德行本应与日俱增，但如今，只要能保存当初一部分的热情，就很不容易了。要是我们起初就痛下决心，便能轻而易举、身心愉悦地完成任何事。

摒弃旧习固然不易，克服自我的意愿就更困难重重。但你若不能战胜微小容易的事，又如何在大事上获得成功？起初就要克制自己邪恶的倾向，摒除不良习惯，以防它们渐渐使你陷于更大的困境。假若你能了解自己向善的努力能为内心带来多大的平静，能为别人带来多大的喜悦，你就会更关注灵性的进步。

第十二章　论逆境的价值

我们时常遭遇苦难与逆境是有好处的，因为患难使人警醒反思，提醒自己在世犹如逃难，不应对世上的事物产生依赖的情绪。有人时常反对我们，也是好事，即使我们出于善意却仍受人诋毁误会。这些会帮助我们学会谦卑，克服虚荣，因为当受人轻视，遭人误解之时，我们将更愿意寻求上帝，请他见证我们的本心。

因此，人应当全心全意信赖上帝，就不必再向他人寻求慰藉。当一个有德行的人深受苦难、诱惑，或恶念的困扰时，他就应比任何时刻都清醒意识到他需要上帝，如果没有主，他就无法行善。而后，当他为自己的命运长吁短叹时，就会诚心祷告。他厌倦尘世，渴望死后解脱，身归尘土，与上帝同在。然后他才确信此世并无完全的平安，抑或完美的平和。

第十三章　论抵制诱惑

我们在尘世生活的每一天都要经受磨炼和诱惑，正如《约伯记》中说：“人生在世岂无争战。”因此我们每个人都应谨防诱惑，谨慎祷告，否则魔鬼就要趁虚而入；因为魔鬼从不休息，遍地游荡寻找可吞吃的人。没有人能够完全圣洁，免受诱惑，任何人都不能幸免。

尽管诱惑往往带来麻烦和痛苦，却令我们受益匪浅，诱惑使人谦卑、洁净，指引我们成长。所有圣人都曾遭受考验，历经诱惑，并获益良多；而没能抵制诱惑的人逐渐堕落，一败涂地。世界上不存在万能的圣律，也不存在什么世外桃源，能够使人免于苦难和诱惑之虞。

没有一个生活在世上的人能够完全远离诱惑，因为人性本恶，诱惑便与生俱来。当一个考验或诱惑即将离去，另一个就接踵而至；总该磨炼自己，因为人类早已失去了原初的幸福恩典。许多人尝试逃离诱惑，结果却愈陷愈深。单靠逃避，我们是无法战胜诱惑的，唯有忍耐和真正的谦卑才能使我们比敌人更加强大。

只避免表面恶行，却不拔除自身的恶根，收效甚微。事实上，诱惑不久后将卷土重来，他会发觉自己的情况更加糟糕。依靠上帝的帮助，逐步攻克，耐心忍受，你将渐渐战胜诱惑，这种方式远胜于自己的盲目强求。对抗诱惑时，要常请人指导，对于正遭受诱惑的人切莫责备，应予以安慰，正如你身处诱惑时希望别人给予你的那样。

邪恶的诱惑都起源于缺少恒心和不信赖上帝。就像一艘无舵的船在波涛中来回颠簸，同样地，一个马虎大意背离目标的人易受多方诱惑。火以炼铁，诱惑以炼义士。我们常常不知道自己能承受什么，但诱惑能使人流露本性。面对诱惑时，刚开始尤其需要提醒自己谨慎行事，因为假如我们在它初次叩响心门的瞬间，就将它拒之门外，这样就更容易击退敌人。诗人奥维德（Ovid）说过：“病要诊得早，事后弥补必定为时已晚。”起初心中只有一个邪念，然后又加以想象形成一幅生动的画面，继而产生愉悦的感觉，紧接着就产生作恶的倾向，最终就顺从于行动了。可以说，敌人步步为营，占领了我们的心，都是因为我们没有在最开始就坚持抵制。怠惰而不抵抗的时间越长，我们就越发软弱，敌人却越发强大。

有的人在皈依主的初始就遇到强烈的诱惑，有的人在人生临近结束时才遇到。更有些人几乎一生都在遭受试探，还有的人只是受到轻微的诱惑。这是主凭借着他的智慧和公义，衡量每个人的情形，为他所选择救赎的人们而安排的。

因此，我们遭受诱惑时不应心灰意懒，相反，应更加热忱地祈祷，求上帝赐予我们力量，帮助我们战胜一切的患难。就像圣保罗所说：“在受试探的时候，总要给你们开一条出路，叫你们能忍受得住。”[7]因此，当我们面对审判和患难时，让我们谦卑地俯伏在神的手下，因为主将拯救并提升这些谦卑者的精神。在这些审判中，一个人的品格可以得到检验；高尚的品德得以保存，善良的品性得以证明。顺境中的虔诚和热忱没有什么大不了的，但是若遇逆境仍能坚忍，德行就将大有长进。有的人在遭受大诱惑时得蒙保守，却在日常小事上抵不住诱惑，这是因为主要让他们保持谦卑，不要盲目信赖自己，而要意识到自己的脆弱。

第十四章　论切勿妄下断言

审视自己，但要避免评判他人。论断他人，不但徒劳无获，而且常常出错，很容易犯罪。但如果我们时常反省自己，就能获益匪浅。我们判断事物常受个人情感的左右，会因为个人的目的而很难正确作出判断。倘若我们能以上帝为自己一向的目标，我们就不至于轻易地因尘世思想的矛盾而感到痛苦。

我们时常受制于内心的冲动和外界的环境，无法自拔。许多人完全是按照个人的喜好来行事的，尽管他们自己没有意识到这一点。当事情进展如他们所愿时，他们就心境平和，但是一旦稍有不如意，他们就立刻痛苦郁闷起来。同样，观点的差异通常只会引起朋友邻里间，甚至虔诚的信徒间的争执。

旧习惯很难破除，没有人情愿放弃自己的观点，而甘心听从别人指教；但是倘若你太过信赖自己的理性和勤奋，甚至胜过信赖归顺上帝的美德，那么你就很难得到上帝的智慧。因为上帝要人们完全顺服于他，只有对上帝热忱的爱才能帮助我们超越自己。

第十五章　论因爱而行动

任何目的，哪怕是出于对某个人的情感都不应该成为作恶的借口。但是对于需要帮助的人，有时需要放下手边的好事，从事另一件事。因为这样的选择并不是放弃一件善事，而是把它变为更好的事。若没有爱，外在的行为都将无益，但一个行为只要以爱为出发点，即使它只是微不足道的举手之劳，也能硕果累累。因为上帝关注人们心中的爱有多深，而不是他的成就有多高。

越有爱心的人，做的事情越多。越能做好一件事的人，做事越多。比起自己的意愿，更看重他人幸福的人必能行事完满。有些事表面上似乎出于仁爱，但实际上却是出于世俗欲望，毕竟我们很难完全摒弃本能、自我意愿、对回报的渴望以及自私自利。

具有真正和完全仁爱之心的人不图私利，只是希望上帝的荣耀赐予一切事物。他毫无嫉妒之心，不贪慕个人的利益，他也不追求自己的享乐和满足，却渴望在上帝的恩典中得享幸福。他将任何善事都完全归功于上帝，而不是自己，因为万物都源自上帝，所有的圣徒都因为上帝而享有圆满和平静。真爱的火光若在心中闪现，他就会确信世俗的一切都是一场虚空。

第十六章　论包容他人的过错

无论是自己还是他人，若存在非一己之力所能改变的弱点，就要耐心忍受，直到上帝颁布旨意改变这一点。想想看，这些弱点或许对你有更大的益处，因为这是在锻炼你的耐心，如果没有这些考验，我们一切的善行就显不出伟大的价值来了。无论你何时面对这些阻碍，应向上帝祈求帮助，并求他赐你安之若素的力量。

若有人经过一两次警告仍不肯改过，就不要与其争辩，将这一切交由上帝处理，希望主的旨意得以成就，他的名字照耀着他所有的仆人；因为主知道如何化恶为善。要尽力耐心容忍别人的过失和弱点，因为自己也有很多过失，同样需要别人的容忍。如果你自己都不能按照自己的愿望塑造自己，又怎么能期望他人完全照着你的意思行事呢？我们总是责备他人不完美，而自己的错误却不加改正。

我们责怪他人时义正词严，却不愿自我纠正。我们责难他人滥用自由，但我们自己却不愿受到束缚。我们要求他人遵守法律，但我们自己却不愿受法律的制约。这充分证明，我们很少将自己与别人以同样的标准来衡量。假若所有人都是完人，别人身上的哪些方面还需要我们看在上帝的份上予以包容呢？

但是现在上帝是这样安排的，让我们可以为彼此承担重任。因为人无完人，所有人都有自己的过失和责任，没有人能于自身获得圆满，也没有人能独身成为智者；因此，我们必须彼此扶持，互相安慰，互相帮助，互相教导，彼此共勉。患难时方显一个人真正的价值；困苦没有打垮他，却彰显了他的真性情。

……

第二十三章　对死亡的沉思

你人生的日子很快就会过去：因此，要想清楚你灵魂的处境。今天一个人还在这儿；明天他就将离去。一个人若不在人们的视线中，他很快就会被人们所忘却。人的心是多么愚蠢刚硬，只顾眼下，却不想未来！应当规划好所有的思想和行为，把今天当作你离开的日子。倘若你无愧于心，就不会恐惧死亡。并且尽管如此，远离罪恶也胜于逃避死亡。假如说今天的你还没准备好面对死亡，明天的你便能准备好么？明天依然未知，你怎能妄下定论？

如果我们不曾自省改过，长寿对我们而言有何益呢？唉，长寿往往会增加我们的罪恶，而不是善行！

向上帝祈祷我们曾经有过一天好好度过的时光吧！许多人总是反复计算着他们已皈依了上帝多久，但他们的生活却几乎没有改进。假如死亡令人恐惧，那么长寿就更加危险了。时常提醒自己死亡将至并为之做好准备的人有福。倘若你曾看见一个人死去，请不要忘记，你终将走上与他同样的路。

每天早上都要提醒自己，在黄昏之前可能离开人世；晚上也不要以为自己必定会再活一天。时刻准备着，才不至于让死亡在你毫无准备的情况下带走你。许多人都是突然间毫无征兆地离开了；因为在我们不知道的时候，耶稣基督就会到来。当你的最后时刻到来时，你就会对自己过去的一生拥有完全不同的态度，深深悔恨自己曾经那样漫不经心。

一个人若能在此时就了解他在死时所想达到的标准，他该是多么幸福明智的一个人啊。这些都将保证我们能够幸福终老；对世俗不屑一顾，热切渴望内心圣洁，乐于遵守法纪，勤于忏悔，时刻顺服上帝，克制自己，为耶稣的爱接受每一次审判。当你健康的时候，你可以行诸多善事，但是当你病情严重时，能做的事就极其有限了！遭受疾病能改过行善的人不多，正如常常外出朝圣的人少有能成为圣洁的人。不要依赖于亲朋好友，也不要拖延救赎灵魂的时机，因为人们很快就会忘记你，这个速度绝对出乎你的意料。最好及时弥补，在此生多积善行，而不要依靠别人的帮助。你如果不关心你自己的灵魂，以后还会有谁能关怀你呢？此刻的时间是极其宝贵的；此刻就是接受一切的日子；此刻就是获得救赎的时刻。但是很可惜，你虚度了让自己求得永生的大好光阴。终有一天，你将渴望拥有一天，甚至是一小时的工夫用来弥补，可是谁又能知道你能否如愿以偿呢？

亲爱的朋友，你若对死亡常存畏惧之心，你就可以令自己脱离极大的危险和恐惧了。有生之年多努力，到面临死亡时，你就不需要恐惧了，而且能得到愉悦。现在就要学习如何面对世上的死亡，然后才能过着与基督同在的生活。现在学习将一切世俗的事物看得淡薄，那时你就可以自由地走向基督。现在依靠忏悔战胜你的肉欲，那时你就能得到救赎的希望。

愚笨的人哪，你连生命里多加一天都不能保证，为什么还奢望长命百岁呢？多少人受了这样的迷惑，但是在毫不知情的情况下就被死亡掠走。你经常可以听见这样的消息，某人遭暗杀，某人溺水而死，又一个人从高处跌下，摔断颈椎，另一个人正在进食时猝死，还有人在玩游戏时死去。有人死于火，有人死于刀，又有人死于恶疾，还有人为盗贼所害。这样说来，死是所有人的结局，人生转瞬即逝，犹如泡影。

你去世后，还有谁想念你？又有谁为你祷告呢？亲爱的朋友，现在就行动，尽己所能，努力去做，因为你不知道你将何时离世，也不知道你死后的遭遇如何！现在还有时间，赶快为你自己永生积聚不朽的财富吧。除了灵魂的救赎，除了上帝的事，不要关注任何其他的事。现在就与上帝的圣徒们交友，效法他们的行动，到了生命结束时，他们就会迎接你进入永生的家园。

让你自己成为此世的过路人，世上的一切事物都与你毫无关联。使自己的内心完全超脱一切，仰望着上帝，因为你在此生并无留恋之所。每日都向上帝祷告，祈求去世时你的灵魂会幸福地走向主。

……

第二卷　内心生活的劝言

第一章　论内心生活

主说：“神的国就在你们心里。”[8]你的心要从属于主，舍弃这痛苦的世界，你的灵魂必得享安宁。要懂得忽略外面的事，专心致志于修炼内心，你才会觉得主的王国走进了你的心。因为神的王国在圣灵中充满了平安和喜乐，并且与邪恶的人无关。如果你的心里已经为基督准备好合适的位置，他就将走进来为你提供慰藉。基督的一切荣耀和美好都源于内心，所以主也乐于常驻内心。主时常走进属灵之人的内心，带去甜蜜的话语、宽慰、平安及超乎寻常的友情。

信奉上帝的灵魂，请准备好你的内心迎接神圣的配偶吧！他将走向你，留在你心间。因为他曾说过：“人若爱我，就必遵守我的道；我们要到他那里去，与他同住。”[9]所以，你要欢迎基督走进你的内心，并且要拒绝一切其他的闯入者。你若拥有了基督，就会富足充实，心满意足。他无论在何事上都会忠诚地让你依靠，因此你不再需要依靠他人。人易改变，也易令你失望，但是基督却永恒不变，坚定地守候你，直到终点。

不要完全相信或依赖软弱而且终将离去的世人，无论他对我们多么有益，多么亲近，也不要因为他时而反对你，就过分忧愁。今天与你同盟的人，明天可能就变成你的仇敌；人易变，犹如气候变化万千。只能完全仰赖上帝；单单崇拜热爱我们的主。他会保护你，为你的周全安置一切。在这世上你居无定所，无论在哪里，你都只是一个陌生人、一个旅人。除非你的内心属于基督，否则你将永远无法享有安宁。

这里并非你的栖身之所，你又在这里寻找什么呢？你真正的家应该是在天堂，因此不要忘记，尘世的万物转瞬即逝。一切终将消逝，也包括你自己。请不要迷恋世上的一切，不然你可能受其束缚，随之灭亡。但愿你所有的思想都能与上帝同在，你谦卑的祷告都能无休止地传向基督。如果你不能思考上天的安排，就该沉浸在基督的爱中，欣然栖身于他神圣的创伤里面。因为你若虔诚地探索主的创伤和那宝贵的血痕，在痛苦中你也能感受到强大的力量，你将无视他人的鄙夷，甚至很少在意那些诋毁自己的话语。

基督在世时也曾遭遇蔑视，在穷苦的绝境中，被家人朋友抛弃，任由他的敌人侮辱。基督甘心承受这些苦难，你还要抱怨吗？基督也有许多仇敌和毁谤他的人，你还希望所有人都成为你的朋友和恩人吗？你若不承受苦难，你的耐心何以达到极致？你若不愿意面对异议，又怎能成为基督之友呢？你若要与基督同在，就要与基督一同受苦。

如果你曾经完全了解过主耶稣的内心，并且感受过一点他炽热的爱的滋味，你就会忽略自己的得失，并且欣然接受你所承受的凌辱；因为耶稣的爱，可以令人看轻自己。内心真正热爱耶稣真理的人，能够免于过度欲望的束缚，他能够自由地走向上帝，在心灵中超越自己，愉悦地享受安宁。

真正了解万物的人会按照事物本来的面目判断它们，而非遵照他人的说法而妄下定论，因为这种智慧并非出于人，而是出于上帝。过内在生活，不过分注重外表的人，不需要特定的地点，或是特定的时间，随时随地就可以祷告。注重内心生活的人容易集中精神，因为他不受外物所累。他不被任何表面事务所扰乱，并能顺其自然，随遇而安。内心规划合理的人，不会因别人乖戾的行为而困扰；人之所以会分散注意力，是因为无法克制自己想对外界的好奇心。

你若内心刚正，纯净无瑕，万事都将向好，让你受益。但是你若时常感到不安，那是因为你还未完全舍弃自我，未曾割断对世俗之物的依恋。对于受造之物自私的留恋，会玷污和束缚人心，其危害超越一切。你若排斥所有外来的慰藉，就能沉思神圣的事，而且内心常常享受极大的喜乐。

第二章　论谦卑顺从上帝

不要过多在意谁赞同你，谁反对你，而应努力工作，并且相信无论你做什么，上帝都与你同在。应当问心无愧，上帝必定尽力保你周全；得蒙上帝庇佑的人，不能被任何恶意所伤。你若能静心忍耐，必将得到上帝的关爱。上帝了解什么时候该如何帮助你，所以你应当完全信服他。上帝足够强大，能够帮助你，使你免受迷惑。别人了解并揭露我们的缺点对我们是有益的，那使我们更加谦卑谨慎。

如果一个人谦虚接受他的缺点，就容易安抚朋友，并和产生矛盾的人言归于好。上帝保护且拯救谦虚的人。主乐于安慰谦卑的人，眷顾谦卑的人，并给予他们恩典。谦卑的人虽受耻辱，上帝却使他得享荣耀。上帝将他的奥秘透露给谦卑的人，亲切地召唤他们走向上帝。谦卑的人即便遭受苦难，却依然平静，因为他信赖上帝，而非这尘世。若不能将自己看作众人之中最卑微的那个，则不能自诩已经取得了什么灵性的进步。

第三章　论善良平和的人

首先，你要保持自己处于平和之中，然后才能为他人带去平和。比起博学的人，内心平和的人可以做更多的善事。冲动的人，常把善事变为罪恶，而且容易听从邪恶。但一个善良平和的人，却能化万物为善行。平和的人，不猜疑他人；但是内心不知足不平和的人，却疑心重重，困扰不堪，他自己不平和，也使别人不安宁。他常说不该说的话，应该做的事却没做。他总是关注别人的责任履行得如何，却忽略自己应该完成的事。所以，你应当先做好自己的事情，然后才能适当地关心他人。

你能轻松地为自己的行为找到借口，却不愿意谅解别人。更公正的态度应是：谴责自己，原谅他人。你如果希望别人宽容你，你就要宽以待人。看看你距离真正的爱心和真正的谦卑还有多么遥远，那样的境界要求我们在面对除自己以外的任何人时，都不会恼怒或愤慨。人们都喜欢与善良温和的人接触，这不足为奇；因为人们天生愿意享有安宁，与志趣相投的人交往。但是如果能与顽固不化、目无法纪或与我们不同道的人和平相处，那更是莫大的恩典和值得称道的好事。

有些人能保持自己的内心平和，又能与他人相安无事。也有些人自己不够平和，也不能给别人带去安宁；他们常骚扰别人，但是更多地自寻烦恼。还有些人自己享受平和，而且尽力使别人也得享安宁。但是，在这痛苦的一生中，我们的平和不在于远离困境，却在于谦卑忍耐。最能忍受困苦的人，才最能保守自己内心平和。这样的人是自我的征服者、世界的主宰者、基督的挚友、上帝的后嗣。

第四章　论内心纯净和目标简单

简单和纯净犹如一对翅膀，使我们超越世俗的事物。我们的目标必须简单，我们的感情必须纯净。简单使我们靠近上帝，纯净使我们领悟和享有上帝。倘若你的心完全摆脱了情欲的束缚，你就能随心所欲，积善成德。倘若你一心一意遵循上帝的旨意，为他人谋福利，你就能时常享受内心的平和。如果你内心忠诚，那么世上一切都将成为你的活镜子和记录圣德的书。任何微小卑贱的事物都体现了上帝的良善。

如果你的内心善良单纯，你就能轻易看透领悟尘世万物。内心纯净的人能够洞察天堂和地狱。一个人内在如何，他就会如何判断事物。尘世如果真的有何喜乐，内心纯净的人一定是最有可能享有的。若是存在痛苦烦恼，良心乖僻的人最有可能了解。一块铁放在火中，便炼去了锈斑，变得炽热明亮；同样，一个人若要完全皈依上帝，便就要抛下一切的怠惰，改过自新。

一个人如果内心开始变得冷淡迟钝，即使是微小的劳苦也能使他烦恼忧虑，并且渴望尘世的慰藉。但是如果他有一次完全克服了自己，勇敢地踏上主的路，那么，先前视作负担的努力，也将变得微不足道了。

第五章　论了解自我

我们不应过度信赖自己，因为我们常常缺少善意和悟性。我们的内心本就缺少光明，况且我们时常疏忽这仅有的光明。此外，我们常常不知道自己有多盲目，常行恶事，却掩饰自己而罪上加罪。有时我们冲动行事，却以为是出于一片热忱。我们责备别人的小过失，却无视自己犯下的大罪过。我们常抱怨别人给予我们的痛苦，却不顾我们给别人带来的烦恼。人若能公正判断自己的德行，就找不到借口严厉指责别人了。

属灵的基督徒把自身灵魂的修炼看得高于一切。勤于提升自我的人不轻易论人短长。如果你做不到不对别人的事妄下定论，专心反省自己的话，你永远都不能成为真正有灵魂的、虔诚的人。倘若你全神贯注思考上帝和你自己，外界的一切都很难影响到你。你的心若不深深自省，你又身处何地呢？你若历尽世事，却疏忽了自己的灵魂，对你又何益呢？如果你渴望心中安宁，与上帝一致，你就要将尘世抛诸脑后，全身心自省。

如果你能使自己摆脱世俗之事的困扰，你就能获益匪浅。但你若念念不忘，就要受到极大的干扰。除了上帝和上帝的事，不要让任何事物在你心中占据重要的位置，使你大喜大悲，心向往之。将一切看作脱离于万物的虚空慰藉。爱上帝的人轻看尘世的万物，因为一切在上帝面前都一文不值。只有上帝是永恒无限的，存在于万物之中，带来灵魂的安慰和内心的愉悦。

第六章　论问心无愧的喜乐

善良的人内心喜乐在于其问心无愧。如果你问心无愧，必定时常体会到喜乐。无愧的良心能够忍耐承受，且在困苦中依然喜悦，但是邪恶的良心就常常惧怕不安。如果你的心不责备你，你就能得到安宁愉快。除非你是做了善事，否则不要过于高兴。邪恶的人得不到真正的喜悦，也感受不到内心的平安；因为上帝说过：“恶人必不得平安。”[10]尽管他们认为：“我们正享受平安，我们不会遇到麻烦，没有人敢伤害我们。”你不要相信他们，因为上帝立刻就将被触怒。他们的事业即将消失，他们的计划也终将溃败。

对于真正热爱主的人而言，在困难中心怀喜乐，并非难事，因为这种喜乐是在基督的十字架中的喜乐。人们得到和被授予的荣耀都是短暂的，而且世俗的喜悦总伴随着忧愁。善良的人将荣耀深埋在良心中，而非挂在嘴边。圣人的喜乐源于上帝，也就在上帝那里。那才是真正的喜乐。追求真实永恒光荣的人不在乎尘世浮华。那些追求俗世名利的人或是内心看重它的人，并不热爱上帝的荣光。真正享受内心极度安乐的是那些不以物喜不以己悲的人。

良心纯净的人懂得知足，内心平和。受人称赞并不能使你更加圣洁；被人诋毁也不至于贬低你的价值。你仍然是你自己，言语不能改变你；你在上帝眼中就是你自己本来的面目。如果你注重自己的内心，就不必在乎别人怎样评价你。人们以貌取人，而上帝更关注人的内心，人所看到的是行为，而上帝往往更注意你的动机。谦卑的人常常行善并且虚心低调。内心纯净虔诚的人，不会寻求尘世的安慰。

如果一个人不再寻求外界的见证，就说明他已经完全信赖上帝。保罗说：“蒙悦纳的，不是自己称许的，乃是主所称许的。”[11]属灵的人在心中与上帝同在，而不受任何外来情欲的束缚。

第七章　爱上帝胜过一切

了解爱上帝的含义并且愿意为主而看轻自己的人有福。你应当为你所热爱的耶稣抛下自己所有的爱，因为主希望我们爱他胜过一切。受造之物的爱是飘忽不定的；只有主的爱才是永恒真实的。信赖尘世之物的人必将与其同归于尽，只有深爱基督的人才能永存屹立。爱主，做主的朋友吧！世上万物都会改变，只有他决不会离弃你，也不会让你走向灭亡。你终将脱离尘世万物，无论你乐意与否。

无论生死，都要紧靠着主，完全相信主，即使所有人都无能为力，他依然能帮助你。你爱的主不容许有人与他竞争在你心里的位置，他要独占你心中的王座。如果你能清空你的内心，不让任何受造之物占据，主就很乐意与你同在。如果你发生任何事都信赖其他人，却不交托与主，结果必定枉然。不要相信和依靠随风起舞的花草，“因为凡有血气的，尽都如草，他的美荣，都像草上的花。草必枯干，花必凋谢。”[12]

如果你以貌取人，必定受欺骗；如果你希望从他人身上寻求利益和慰藉，反而容易失去它。倘若你无时无刻不在追求主，你必将寻求到主。但是如果你谋求一己之私，你也会如愿以偿，只是所得之利会损害你自己罢了。因为人若不追寻主，他承受的伤害将超过全世界所有仇敌联合起来所实施的打击。

……

第十二章　论十字架的路

“舍己，背起十字架，跟从我。”[13]很多人认为这句话似乎太苛刻。但是，还有更严厉的话呢：“你们这被咒诅的人，离开我，进入那为魔鬼和他的使者所预备的永火里去。”[14]因为此刻愿意听从十字架教诲的人，就不惧怕通向永生的审判了。当主审判万众之时，这十字架的标记就会出现在天堂。那时，凡在此世效法基督承受痛苦的人，都将坦然地走向主，接受审判。

所以你们为何惧怕背负那引领你走向天堂的圣十字架呢？在十字架里包含着救赎，它是生命，是抵御敌人的保障。十字架里灌注了天堂的喜乐、精神的力量、灵魂的慰藉。十字架之中蕴涵着至上的道德和完全的圣洁。除了十字架，没有可以救助灵魂得享永生的方法。所以，背负你的十字架，跟随主吧，你就能进入永生。我主已经背负着他的十字架踏上了前方的路，他已为你死在了十字架上，渴望与他一同死在十字架上吧。因为你若与他同死，也能与他同存，你若与他一同承受痛苦，就必将与他同享荣耀。

看看万物是如何在十字架中演化、相互依存的。除了圣十字架和克己之道外，再无其他的路可以让你得享永生和实现真正的内在平安。无论你去哪里，如何努力，你都找不到一条比圣十字架之道更崇高更稳妥的路了。即使你能命令万物听从你的意愿和决断，但你仍无法摆脱痛苦，无论你是否情愿；所以你还是要寻找十字架，因为你总是要承受身体或精神上的痛苦。

有时是上帝远离你，有时是邻人困扰你，但更有甚者，是你常把自己当作沉重的负担。任何救助或安慰都不能拯救你或减轻你的苦楚。但只要它是上帝的意愿，你就必须承担。因为上帝要你忍受痛苦，即使没有安慰，所以你要完全从属于上帝，在痛苦中变得更加谦卑。只有亲身经历耶稣痛苦的人，才能真正发自心底同情主。十字架永远等候你，无论你身在何处。无论你逃往何处，都不能躲避它。因为你无论身在何方，都要表现自己，找寻自己。仰望天空或俯瞰大地，关照外界或感悟内心，无论你走向何方，你总能找到十字架。你若希望得享内心的平安和永恒的冠冕，就必须时刻保持耐心。

你若欣然背负十字架，它就会助你一臂之力，引领你到达期望的目的地，那里再无困苦，尽管那目的地并非在此世上。你若心有不甘，十字架就变成你的重担，令你受累，可即便如此，你依然无法逃避。你若舍弃一个十字架，你必然会找到另一个，或许是更重的一个。

你想逃脱世人无从躲避的重担吗？世界上哪有不背负十字架或者不曾经受痛苦的圣徒呢？就算是耶稣在世时，也经历了十字架的困苦，他说：基督必须受苦，之后从死里复活，才能享有他的荣耀。既然如此，为何你不踏上神圣的十字架之路，而另寻他途？主一生都在承受十字架之苦，最后以身殉道，你又怎能及时行乐，寻求安逸呢？

如果你想逃避磨炼，另寻他法，那你就大错特错了，因为任何生命都充满痛苦。十字架的标记无处不在。在圣灵中越有进步的人，常常背负更重、更多的十字架，因为他对上帝的爱越深，他被放逐尘世的苦楚就越痛。

但是这些人虽饱受折磨，却并非毫无宽慰，因为背负十字架的过程已经让他们受益匪浅。因为自从欣然背负十字架的那刻起，所有的苦楚都变成了被上帝慰藉的希望。肉体承受的痛苦越深，内心就因上帝的恩典而变得愈发强大。有时因为热爱上帝，效法他的十字架，以至于渴望历经困苦，舍弃无忧无虑的生活，那是他相信自己为上帝承受的痛苦越多，将来就越能取悦于上帝。这并非来源于内心，而是源于基督的恩典，这恩典能够并确实给予胆小者力量因此在平常想方设法逃避的事，现在凭着赤诚之心，竟能勇往直前，全力以赴。

人并非天生愿意背负十字架，热爱它，严于律己，完全屈服，放弃荣耀，忍受耻辱，看轻自己，任人轻视，忍受所有的痛苦与损失，不慕名利。如果你完全信赖你自己，就不能自己实现这些目标。但是如果你依靠上帝，你就能从天堂得到力量，自己的意志将能掌控尘世的肉体。如果你用忠诚武装自己，佩戴十字架的勋章，你就不必惧怕仇敌魔鬼了。

请你像基督善良忠心的仆人，勇敢地背负起爱你且为你而被钉死的主的十字架吧。要作好准备，忍受悲惨的一生中的各种患难和痛苦，因为无论你在何处，它都与你同在，无论你躲在何方，它都将找寻到你。苦难必然存在，任何方法都不能令你逃避，你唯一能做的就是忍受。如果你想成为主的朋友，与他同在，就要欣然与主同饮。让主来安慰，按照他的意愿安排。但你应准备承受痛苦，并且把苦难当作最大的安慰。“因为此时的痛苦无法与将来的荣耀相提并论”，即使是你一人独自承受了所有。[15]

当你达到一定的境界，痛苦之于你，就因基督而变得甜蜜，可以接受，那么你就功德圆满，因为你已经找到了此世的乐园。但是只要你还在因受苦而烦恼，并且企图逃避受苦，你心中就不得平安，无论你走到哪里，你企图逃避的苦难将如影随形。

你若磨炼心性——正如你必须要做的那样——甘愿受苦和死去，那么所有事情都会变好，你也能得到心中的平和。纵使你曾像圣保罗一样，被带到第三层天，也不能因此保证你自己不受苦难。主说：“我也要指示他，为我的名必须受许多的苦难。”[16]所以如果你想爱主，而且长久地服侍他，你便只有承受痛苦。

希望你配为上帝承受这样的苦辱，这对你是何等荣耀啊！对于所有的圣徒是何等的喜乐，对于你的友人也是莫大的启发。尽管很少有人乐意受苦，但是所有人都会对隐忍赞不绝口，由衷钦佩。你的确应当为主承受一些痛苦，因为有很多人正因为世俗的原因更加痛苦。

你要确信自己应当过一种将死的生活。越能够舍弃自己，就越靠近上帝。除了那些为了上帝甘心受苦的人们以外，没有人配得上了解天堂的事。没有什么比为上帝欣然受苦更能取悦上帝、有益身心的了。假如你有机会选择，宁可为主受苦也不要享受许多的安慰，只有这样你才能效法基督，比肩圣人。人生的价值与属灵的进步不在于享受多少欢乐慰藉，而在于承受多少艰难困苦。

如果有比受苦更好的方式救赎人类，那么主必定早就用言语和生活启示我们了。对于跟随主的十二使徒和所有愿意皈依他的人，他都一视同仁，耐心教导：“若有人要跟从我，就当舍己，天天背起他的十字架来跟从我。”[17]所以在反复思考，权衡利弊后，我们得出了最后的结论：“我们进入神的国，必须经历许多艰难。”[18]

第三卷　论内心安慰

第一章　主如何与我们的内心对话

“我要聆听上帝与我内心的对话。”能够聆听主与其内心对话，并得到主安慰的人有福了。能够愉悦地倾听神的低语，不顾尘世的声响，只要关注内心的真理教诲，不用理会外界喧嚣之音，这人的耳朵也真有福了。不必张望外来的事物，只需注视内心的事，这人的眼睛真有福了。全身心地投入上帝怀抱，将自己从尘世纷扰中解脱出来，这样的人有福了。哦，我的灵魂啊，想想这些有福的人吧，克制感官上的欲望，就能听到上帝与你内心的交谈。

你爱的主这样说：我来拯救你，赐予你平安和生命；与我同在，你就能享有平安。不要关注那些暂时的事，而要真心寻求那永恒不变的事。昙花一现不过是诱人的陷阱。如果你被造物者抛弃，那么一切受造之物对你又何益呢？因此你应远离所有的事物，专心修缮自身，努力达到主的期望，忠诚地服侍他，这样才能得到真正的恩典。

第二章　真理如何无声地启示我们

门徒：“主啊！请说，你的仆人在敬听。”

“我是你的仆人，求你赐我理性，那样我就可以明白你的圣约。”“求你使我的心跟随你的话，倾听着你的话语如甘霖般滴下。”以色列的百姓们曾对摩西说：“求你和我们说话，我们必听；不要神和我们说话，恐怕我们死亡。”[19]主啊，我祈求不是如此，我愿和先知撒母耳[20]一样，谦卑而诚实地说：“主啊，请说，你的仆人在敬听。”不要让摩西或任何其他的先知和我对话。主啊，只要你亲自向我说话，因为你启迪指引了所有的先知，你足以完全地指引我，且无须他们的一臂之力。然而如果没有你，他们一无是处。

他们固然可以说教，但是他们不能赐予圣灵。就算他们说得再动听，你若保持缄默，他们也不能感化人心。他们教人字句，但是你启发人的思维。他们讲述谜题，但是你能揭示所有的奥秘。他们只是传播你的诫命，但是你却能指导我们遵守。他们指示了方向，但是你却赐予我们力量，让我们勇往直前。他们所做的只是表面的，只有你才能教导启迪我们的心。他们浇水灌溉，但你却让种子结出累累硕果。他们高谈阔论，但是只有你才能使人醒悟透彻。

因此，不要让摩西和我们对话，而是你啊，主，上帝啊。因为你是永恒的真理，否则，只得到表面上的警告，却没有赤诚的真心，恐怕至死，我还是一无是处；否则我将受到谴责——因为我听见了却未奉行，明白了却未热爱，相信了却未坚持。所以，主啊，请说，你的仆人在敬听。“你有永生之道。”求你向我说话，安慰我的灵魂，让我的生命归于你的赞美、你的荣光和永恒的尊贵。

第三章　论虚心听从上帝的话

基督：我儿啊，请听我说。那是甘美无比的话，超过这世上所有哲学家和智者的学识。我对你们说的话，是灵魂，是生命，不是人的理性所能测度的。上帝的话并非让人为了虚无的欢乐而引用，却是要你安静地谛听，谦卑而热诚地接受。

门徒：能够得到你的教诲，并且受你的律法教训的人是有福的，主啊。你使他身处痛苦仍得安息，在世上不至于孤苦无依。

基督：我从古时起教化众先知晓谕世人，直到今日仍未放弃，但是许多人对我的声音不闻不问，犹如顽石。大多数人宁愿听尘世的言语，却不喜欢听上帝的话，他们遵从自己的肉欲，却不取悦于上帝。尘世的回报低微卑贱，昙花一现，但是人们趋之若鹜；我的应许神圣高尚，长存永恒，但是人们都冷淡对待它。有谁曾无论何时都小心谨慎地服侍我，像对待世界及其主人一样呢？海说：“西顿（Sidon）啊，你当愧惭”；[21]你若问其原因，请听我慢慢道来。

为了微小的利益，人们可以千里迢迢，不辞劳苦；可为了永生，人们甚至一举手，一投足都感劳累。细微的酬报就可令人不懈追求，分文之财就可令人萌生羞耻的争讼，微小的回报和虚荣之心就可令人昼夜不息地辛勤。但是对于永恒的益处，无法比拟的奖赏，至高的荣誉，无边的荣耀，他们却吝惜些许劳作。懒惰抱怨的仆人哪，你应感到愧惭，世人冲向毁灭，比你奔向救赎还更努力呢！世人在虚空之中比你在真理之中更加全神贯注呢！世人有时在他们的希望中受挫折，但是我的应许绝不落空，我也不让信赖我的人无功而返。我所应许的，我必赐予，我所说过的，我必成全，只要人忠诚地爱我，亘古不变！我必赏赐所有的善人，维护一切效忠于我的人。

将我的话谨记在心，认真思考其中的含义，因为当你面临诱惑时，他将使你受益匪浅。如果你读到不理解的地方，在我降临之时就会明白。我面见我所选召之人，有两种方式，一是试探，二是安慰。每天我都教授他们两个功课，一是纠正他们的过失，二是勉励他们在德行上有所进步。“听见我的话却不屑一顾的人，必将在末日受审。”

祷告虔诚的恩典

门徒：主啊！我的上帝，一切美好都源于你，我是谁，我怎敢擅自向你说话呢？我是你的最贫穷卑微的仆人，是最微小的虫子，我的低微非我所能意识，非我言语所能表达。但是，主啊，求你不要忘记，我不过是虚空，一无所有，也毫无所能。只有你是善良公正、单纯神圣的，你无所不能，赐予万物，只让那邪恶的人空手而归。请不要忘记你的慈爱，主啊，让你的恩典充满我的心，因为你也不愿意见你创造之物毫无意义。我怎能度过这悲惨的一生，除非你的仁慈让我更加坚定？求你不要抛弃我，也不要迟迟不来，请不要收回你的安慰，否则，我的灵魂将一片荒芜。主啊，请指引我遵行你的旨意，指引我在你眼前过着有价值且谦卑的生活；因为你是我智慧的源泉，只有你真正了解我，在我未来到这世上之前，甚至在未有天地之先，你就已经认识了我。

第四章　论真理和谦卑

基督：我儿啊，探索真理的道路上要赶在我先，并常常本着一颗单纯的心寻求我。赶在我先寻求真理的人，我必将保护他免遭邪恶荼毒。真理将帮助他抵抗欺骗和恶人的中伤。如果真理让你获得自由，你们就真的自由了，人们的浮词妄语都不能伤害你。

门徒：主啊！这话是真的，就让你所说的话在我身上实现。愿你的真理教诲我，保佑我，最终救赎我。愿真理协助我脱离一切邪恶的私欲和不尊法度的爱，我就能完全自由，走在你的前头。

基督：真理说，我会将取悦我的事指教给你。你要忧伤悔过你犯下的罪，不要因为任何善行而骄傲自满。你事实上仍有罪，为许多情欲所困扰，按照你的本性，总是趋于幻想，易于堕落，失败，被征服，不安乃至分裂。你没有可夸耀之处，倒有许多不齿之事，因为你比自己想象的更加软弱。

对于自己所做的事，切不可自命不凡。除了永恒的事物，任何事都不可看得伟大，或珍贵，或妙不可言，或夸强说会，也不要把什么事都当作神圣崇高的、值得称赞追求的。让永恒的真理成为你仅有的至高喜乐，让自己极端的无用时常困扰你。没有什么比你的罪恶更令你惧怕，谴责，逃避；这比失去所有的事物都痛苦。有的人在我的眼前行为不忠诚，他只是出于好奇心和傲慢，希望了解我的奥秘，想明白上帝的至高之事，却忽略拯救自己的灵魂。当我拒绝他们时，他们的傲慢和好奇就会陷入诱惑和罪恶之中。

你要敬畏上帝的审判，担忧触怒万能的上帝。不要企图调查至高者的方式，而应努力省察自己的罪过，已犯下多少罪，又有多少善事仍未完成。有些人的虔诚，只停留在书本、绘画和其他有形的载体上。有的人口中敬畏我，心中却远离我。但是也有人在悟性中看到了曙光，净化了内心的欲望，且全心追求神圣的事。这些人厌恶世俗之事，甚至连满足基本的自然需要也不情愿。不过就是这样的人才能真正领会圣灵所说的真理。因为圣灵教他们看轻世俗，爱慕上天，舍下尘世，渴望天堂。

第五章　上帝之爱，奇妙无穷

门徒：天父，我主耶稣基督的父啊！我赞美你，因为你曾记念我这卑微的仆人。慈悲的天父，所有的安慰都源于你！万分感激啊，因为你时时安慰我这不配享有安慰的人。将所有的恩典和荣耀归于你，你的独生子，圣灵保惠师，从此刻直到永远。主上帝啊，爱我灵魂的主，当你来到我心中时，我的内心欢呼雀跃。你是我的荣耀，是心中真正的喜乐；你是我的希望，是我患难时的避难所。

但是因为我的爱还很脆弱，德行并不完善，我仍需要你来安慰我，赐予我力量。祈求你时常造访我，用圣律指引我。求你让我摆脱邪恶的情欲，治愈我内心的混乱的情绪，净化我的内心，使其洁净无疵，我就能仁爱待人，勇于承受，并坚持不懈。

爱拥有万能的力量，是伟大而且完全的善行；唯有爱可减轻重荷，唯有爱能抚平坎坷。即使背负重担也不以为重，承受痛苦也甘之如饴。耶稣的爱神圣崇高，常能促使人们作出伟大的事，激励人们不断追求更完美的境界。爱使人积极向上，不为低贱的事所累。爱使人渴望自由，超脱一切世俗的欲念，这样他们内心的曙光就不至昏暗，也不会为昙花一现的荣华所束缚，或是为任何厄运所阻碍。在天堂或尘世，没有比爱更甜美、更勇敢、更高尚、更广阔、更愉悦、更充实、更美好的事物，因为爱源于上帝，超越万物，只能永存于上帝。

爱令人飞跃欢乐，自由奔跑，不受拘束。爱令你舍弃一切，又得到一切，停留在超乎万物的至高者之中，所有美善都出自那里。爱并不看重天资，却将一切的好处归于上帝。爱不存在任何界限，它却热烈地超过一切的边界。爱不觉重担，不计劳苦，不懈尝试，认为一切皆有可能，能够成就一切。因此爱令人伟大；这有点奇怪，却的确有效；但没有爱的人，就畏怯不前、一败涂地。

爱常警醒，永不沉睡；虽辛苦劳累，却不会累垮；虽受限制，却不受困；虽受惊吓，却不混乱；它犹如灼烧的火焰，炽热的火炬，飞腾直上，锐不可当。那些爱上帝的人非常了解上帝的声音，出乎心灵的热情是上帝耳中强烈的声音：“我的主，我的爱，你全是我的，我完全属于你。”

祷告

主啊，求你对我的爱更加深刻，使我能用心感受，体会爱的滋味是何等甘甜，使我溶于你的爱，浸透在你的爱中。唯愿你的爱包围着我，令我超越自己，以一种热情地、超乎想象的神奇方式。我愿歌唱爱，我愿跟随我所爱的主直到至高之处。愿我的灵魂沐浴在你的赞誉中，为爱欢呼赞扬。我愿爱你甚于爱自己，就是爱自己也只是为了你。我愿意遵循你身上闪耀的爱之准则，去爱所有真心爱你的人。

爱是短暂的、纯净的、温柔的、快乐的、愉悦的，爱也是勇敢的、耐心的、忠实的、谨慎的、坚忍的、刚强的，而且不谋私利。无论何事，人若为一己之私，那时，他的爱就不纯粹了那他就放弃了爱。爱是小心的、谦卑的、正直的、不浮躁、不矫情、不虚荣，爱是冷静的、纯洁的、坚定的、安静的，而且不束缚于感官的冲动。爱是温和的，顺从的，对己自卑，对上帝热心，并且充满感激，寄信心与希望于他。纵使遭遇苦难，也是如此，在爱中仍要承受痛苦。

不准备受苦，或不坚守主的旨意的人，不配称为爱主的人。爱主的人必须要为他所爱的主，甘心忍受一切艰难苦楚，不因身处逆境而背弃他。

第六章　论真正爱主之人的证据

基督：我儿啊，你还不足称为一个勇敢明智爱主的人。

门徒：主啊，你为何这么说呢？

基督：因为你一遭受一点麻烦，就舍弃了你当初的使命，而且急于求得安慰。勇敢爱我的人，面对诱惑时，必坚定不移，也不听仇敌狡猾的劝诱，无论是顺境或是逆境中，都真心对我。

有智慧地爱人，不重视所赠送的礼物，而在意赠送者的爱心。比起礼物的价值，他更重视感情，认为所有礼物都不及他所爱的人。同样，一个品质高尚的爱我的人，也不留意于我所赐的恩，而是认为所有的恩典都不及我。如果有时你不能如愿地靠近我和我的众圣徒，也不必因此失望。要知道你有时享受到的美妙情感，是我的恩典与你同在的结果，那是让你提前体会一下天堂的滋味，但是你切不可过于依靠这种感觉，因为它转瞬即逝。但是，抵抗邪恶的思想，拒绝魔鬼的暗示，才能彰显德行获得赞誉。

不要让任何特殊的幻想扰乱你的心，徒增烦恼，要坚持你的志向，且始终忠于上帝。有时你可以体会至高之处的愉悦，但是很快又回到惯常的虚空状态，请不要沮丧。因为这并不是故意刁难，而是顺其自然，只要你不喜欢这些，你就必定尽力抵抗，这就成了你的奖赏，而不是损失。

你也许知道你的老仇敌仍在竭力想尽各种方法来阻挡你的善行。使你不能虔诚静心，不能敬拜上帝的圣徒，不能敬虔地思考我的痛苦，不能有效审视你的罪，不能守卫你的心，不能坚定向善的志向。它（魔鬼）还令你产生邪思恶念，使你感到厌倦和沮丧，然后就疲于祷告和读圣经。它们最不喜欢人们谦卑忏悔，假如可能，他们会阻止你领圣餐。你切不可相信它们，虽然它们常常安设欺骗的陷阱，你也不必要理会它。当它用罪恶和不洁的思想暗示你的时候，你可控诉它，对它说：“滚开！你这个邪恶的幽灵，羞愧吧，你这丑污的恶鬼，离我远一点！不要把这些话常常带到我的耳中。你邪恶的诱惑者，离开我吧！你与我毫不相干，因为耶稣会像一个强健的勇士与我同在，你会惊慌失措的。我宁愿死，或受各种的折磨，但决不愿随从你。闭口静默吧！即使你再纠缠我，我也不再听你了，主是我的亮光，我的救赎，我还怕谁呢？”“即使万人起来攻击我，我也不惧怕。”“因主在帮助我，救赎我。”

像优秀的战士一样战斗吧，尽管有时因力所不及而致失败，但要更加勇敢，信赖我取之不尽的恩典。但是要防备骄傲自满或虚情假意，那误导了许多人，甚至令他们跌入几乎不可挽救的混沌中。希望这些因傲慢自负而失足的人令你警醒，永远谦逊卑微。

第七章　论谦卑地保守恩典

基督：我儿啊，应隐藏因虔诚所得的恩典，这对你稳妥有益；切不可因恩典而自吹自擂，大言不惭。最好谦恭虚己，唯恐自己不配得此恩典。你不要过于依赖眼前的美好，因为它很容易就变得冷清。当你享受恩典时，应感怀不蒙恩典时的可怜穷困。灵性的提升并不完全在于是否得蒙恩典，而更多地在于失去恩典时你能否以谦卑舍己和忍耐的心承受一切，不放弃祷告，也不忽视其他日常侍奉的职责。你反而要更加愉悦地尽力完成眼前的事，切不可因枯燥和担忧而心生懈怠。

许多人都因事情不如其所愿而焦躁懒惰。人生之路并非由自己掌控，一切赐予和安慰都属于上帝。何时该赐予谁多少都是依照上帝的旨意和喜好进行的。有些人过于切望恩典，鲁莽行事，反而害了自己，因为他们没有考虑自己的软弱，感情用事，缺乏理性判断，奢望完成力所不及的事。因为他们所做的事超出了上帝的旨意，因此他们很快就错失了恩典。那些希望在天堂结巢的人，孤苦无助，他们应当在贫苦和羞耻中醒悟不该靠自己的羽翼飞翔，而要信赖我的庇护。那些希望侍奉上帝但没有经验的初学者，极易遭受欺骗，迷失自己，除非有贤明的领袖指引他们。

如果他们不肯信赖经验丰富的人，固执己见，他们的结局非常危险，除非他们不再一意孤行。自以为是的人大多不愿意虚心接受他人的领导，比起学富五车却心高气傲的人，知识浅薄谦卑向善的人更胜一筹。宁可天资鲁钝，也不可恃才傲物。享受恩典时纵情欢乐，全然忘掉过去的贫弱，这样是不明智的，因为如此便会失去对主的敬畏之心，洋洋自得以为能永守主的恩典。同样，在艰难困苦中，过于绝望而不再信赖我的人也是糊涂的。

和平时觉得自己高枕无忧的人，必将在战争中惊慌失措。你若始终谦卑谨慎，适时调整自己的内心，你就不易陷入危险与罪恶之中了。最好的建议就是当你内心的奉献精神高涨如火时，该想想它消失时，你会怎样。当热情冷却时，不要忘记那光还会回来，这是对你的警告，也是因为我的荣耀，才暂且收回我的恩典。

这样的考验比起凡事如你所愿更为有益。因为人的德行并不在于他所见的表象和所享受的舒适，也不在于他如何熟读圣经，或是如何高贵。而是真正地扎根于谦卑之中，和对上帝的真爱中；在于常常纯净诚恳地追求上帝的荣光；在于谦卑诚恳地虚己，且乐于为人轻视，乐于蒙受屈辱而非得享荣耀。

……

第九章　只有上帝是我们的完美结局

基督：我儿啊，如果你想拥有真正的幸福，你就应该把我作为你至高的完美结局。完全信赖我，将洁净你的内心，不至于无节制地倾向自私和尘世的事物。因为无论何时你寻求自己的利益，你都将立刻变得凄凉孤寂。所以将万物都归于我，因为万物都源于我。你要知道万物都出于至高之善，都源于我，万物终将归于我。

犹如清泉的源头，无论长幼贫富，众生的生命之水都源于我。甘心乐意服侍我的人，必将得到恩上之恩。但妄想从我之外的事物寻求荣耀，或为一己之私而欢愉的人，必不能享有真正的愉悦，他的心不会更强大，却要承受多方阻碍和折磨。所以你不要将美好归功于自己或是任何其他人，而应归于主。若不是因为主，人将一无所有。我已将万物全赐予你，但是我的旨意是你终将又归于我，我要你心怀感激，并准确地描绘我的恩典。

这就是忠诚，在它面前，虚荣心毫无立足之地。如果你心中充满天恩和真爱，必然不会狭隘，也不只爱自己。因为上帝的爱能超越一切，提升灵魂力量。你若真正明智，必定只取悦于我，只期望于我；因为除了上帝以外，没有人是良善的。唯有上帝当受赞美于万有之上，受称颂于万有之中。

第十章　论侍奉上帝的喜乐

门徒：我主啊！我还要说，不能缄默无言，我要向至高无上的上帝、我的主、我的王说：“主啊！对于敬畏你的人，你的恩典是何等丰盛啊！”但是对于爱你的人如何呢？对于全心侍奉你的人又如何呢？你赐给爱你的人的恩惠令他们妙不可言。我们已经看到你的慷慨，当我不存在时，你创造了我，当我陷入迷途远离你时，你又引我归来可以侍奉你，让我爱你。

爱的泉源啊，亘古不变，我将如何诉说你呢！我怎能忘记你，在我鬼迷心窍、迷失方向之后，你仍屈尊降贵，将我记在心上。你超乎想象地爱着你的仆人，你所赐的恩惠怜悯都超过我所应得。我应如何报答你的恩惠呢？因为并非人人都享有这种恩典，舍弃一切，摒绝世俗，过着虔诚的生活。我应当侍奉你，这并不出人意料，因为受造之物都应该侍奉你。我侍奉你不足为奇，但可喜的是你不嫌我地位卑微，肯收纳我做你的仆人，把我列在所爱的众仆人之内。

我所有的一切都愿给予你，包括我自己。由此看来，不是我侍奉你，反之，却是你服侍了我。看看你已为众生创造的天地万物，他们期待着取悦你，依照你的旨意每日运行。远不止此，你又命令天使保护人类。但是还有超乎一切之上的恩典，那便是你亲自守卫众生，承诺将自己赐予人们。

我该如何报答你这数不清的恩典？哦，我愿能终身侍奉你！哪怕至少一天，我愿为你做些有价值的事。因为你理应得到万人的侍奉、一切的荣耀、永恒的赞美。你就是我的主，而我就是你卑微的仆人，应当全力以赴侍奉你，且孜孜不倦地赞美你。这是我衷心的愿望，也是我超越一切的渴望，我若有不足，我恳求你补全我。

能够服侍你，因你而轻看其他一切，这既是极大的荣誉，也是极大的光耀。至高的恩典将赐予那些心甘情愿服侍你的人。那些因为爱你而摒弃一切尘世快乐的人，必将得到圣灵最甜蜜的安慰。那些因为我主走向窄门，离弃世俗的人，必将享有真正的内心自由。

服侍上帝令人无比喜悦。他能使人得到真正的自由和纯一的圣洁。侍奉上帝何等的神圣，它能使人和天使一样，为上帝所喜悦，为魔鬼所畏惧，又倍受众圣徒所敬仰。服侍上帝值得我们永远追求，因着这工，我们就可得至善的赏赐和无边的福乐。

第十一章　要省察节制内心的愿望

基督：我儿啊！你还要学习许多未曾了解的事。

圣徒：主啊，那是什么事？

基督：你的愿望要完全取悦于我，不要爱着自己，要认真遵循我的旨意。时常有各种欲望鼓动你，猛烈地催逼你，但是你要考虑清楚这些愿望是为了你自己的利益还是为着我的荣耀？若是因为我，你必定接受我所安排的一切，但是若有自私的意念杂于其间，那么，它就会阻碍、烦扰你。

所以切勿太过热衷于没有得到我允许的愿望，否则你将来会后悔，或令你之前喜爱和渴望的事变为你所厌恶的。因为并不是所有看起来美好的情感都可追寻，同样，并非所有看似反感的事都应立即舍弃。有时美好的意图和努力也要加以克制，以免不合时宜的渴望会扰乱你的内心，或是因为缺少自我克制而冒犯他人，或是因为别人的反对，而倍感困扰，陷入迷茫。

你必须坚强勇敢地克制自己感官上的欲望，不顾肉身的喜好，竭尽全力抑制肉欲，使之精神化。要纠正掌控你的欲望直到它顺从自如。要学会知足，从简单的事物中寻找快乐，纵使身处逆境也不怨天尤人。

第十二章　学习忍耐抵抗情欲

门徒：主上帝啊！我知道我们最需要的就是忍耐，因为此生中要经历许多考验。因为无论我如何热切地寻求平静，也不能逃脱挣扎和痛苦。

基督：我儿啊，的确如此。我的旨意不是让你寻求一块没有痛苦和诱惑的净土，而是要你在为诸多诱惑所困扰，身处险恶逆境之时，寻求平静。假若你说：你不能受痛苦，那么你怎能承受炼狱的大火呢？两害之中取其轻，为着要逃避永恒的惩罚，你必须现在竭力为上帝而忍耐生活中的苦楚。你是否想着世人都没有或只经历微小的痛苦？问一问生活最富足的人，你就发现事实并非如此。

但你也许会说，他们享有许多乐趣，并可以随心所欲，痛苦就显得无足轻重了。但即使他们可以随心所欲，这又能持续多久呢？这世上的富人将会像轻烟般消逝，他们快乐的回忆也将烟消云散。即便在此生他们也不能完全脱离苦痛、忧愁和恐惧去享乐，因为他们忧愁的种子常常生发于喜悦的事中。既然他们毫无节制地追求快乐，就不能毫无羞耻和苦痛地享受这些快乐。这一切的快乐是何等的短促、虚浮、混乱而低贱啊！可是人是多么的盲目糊涂，所以他们全不明白，好像愚钝的兽类，只为了贪享那堕落生活中微小的欢乐，却丧失了他们的灵魂。所以，我儿啊，不要放纵淫欲，唯我独尊。“要以耶和华为乐，他就将你心里所求的赐给你。”[22]

你若想得享真正的喜乐和我完全的安慰，就必须：轻看尘世一切，脱离低级的趣味，才能享受恩典，并感到富足的安慰。你越远离世俗的舒适，你体会到的安慰就越甜美、越有力。但这并非立刻就能实现，起初你难免有些忧苦和折磨。旧日固有的习惯必须顽强抵抗，你要步步为营，最终战胜它们。肉体会怨恨你，但是你应该要靠着心灵的热情约束它。魔鬼可能试探引诱你，但是凭借祷告，它必将落荒而逃。你也可以通过有益的劳动阻拦它的来路，使它无隙可乘。

第十三章　论谦卑顺从，效法基督

基督：我儿啊，那些不肯顺从的人，必将失去上帝的恩宠。人若寻求私利，就必失掉公福。凡人若不心甘情愿顺服尊者，那表明他还未完全克服他卑劣的人性，它仍时常挣扎和怨恨地反抗他。所以，你若想抑制你的欲望，就要赶快学习顺从尊者。因为你若守卫住你的内心，就更容易战胜外来的敌人。如果你的心灵不与圣灵一致，那么，你就将是自己最顽恶的敌人。你若想战胜自己的血肉，就必须诚实地轻看自己。因为你若仍溺爱自己，就不情愿让自己完全屈服于他人的意志。

我是万能而又至高无上的，我创造万物，尚且为你的缘故愿意谦卑地顺从于人。而你不过是尘土，为上帝的缘故服从于人，又算得了什么呢？我曾成为众人里的最卑最贱者，就是要使你学我的谦卑而克服骄傲。你只不过是尘土啊，你要学习顺从；泥土啊，你要学习谦卑，俯伏于众人的脚下。你要学习破除己意，绝对顺从。

你要努力克服自己，不容自己有丝毫骄傲。表现得顺从谦卑，让众人皆可行走于你之上，像践踏街道上的泥土一般。虚无的人啊，有什么好怨诉的呢？污秽的罪人啊！你常常得罪上帝，多次应得地狱之刑，对于谴责你的人还有何言可答呢？但是我已经饶恕了你，因为你的灵魂对我而言极为宝贵，所以你要知道我的爱，要常常感谢我的恩。你还要不断地努力达到真正的自卑、顺从、耐心忍受他人的藐视。

……

第十七章　我们如何完全信赖主

基督：我儿啊，让我的旨意指引你。我知道怎样对你最有益。你的思想只不过是凡人之见，你的判断也常受自我情绪的影响。

门徒：主啊，你说的不错，天意的安排胜过我对生活的规划。人若不完全信赖你，必难得平安。主啊，只要让我的意志坚定不移地顺从你，我愿听候你任何安排；因为你对我的旨意，都是美好的。假若你的旨意要我身处黑暗，我赞美你；假若你的旨意要我身处光明，我也要赞美你。你若赐我安慰，我赞美你；但是你若考验我，我还是赞美你。

基督：我儿啊，你要与我同行，就应该如此。你应该如享乐一般甘心受苦；你应该如获得富贵一般愉快地享受贫穷匮乏。

门徒：主啊，为了你，我将欣然接受你令我遭遇的一切。从你的手中，我愿意平心地接受福与祸，甜与苦，喜乐与忧愁，我将为一切遭遇而感谢你。求你保护我远离罪恶，我就不怕死亡与地狱。我祈求你永远不要丢弃我，也不要从生命册上涂掉我的名字，这样，一切的苦难，就无法加害于我。

第十八章　痛苦如何得以忍耐

基督：我儿啊，我从天堂而来就是为要拯救你，我替你承受忧患，并非出于必须，而只是因为单纯地爱你。因此，你要学习忍耐暂时的苦难，不生怨恨之心。从我降生之时到死在十字架为止，我无时无刻不在承受痛苦。我缺乏在世生活的必需品，常听见有人诋毁我，我忍受侮慢、凌辱。我施恩于人，却得到忘恩负义的报答；我带来奇迹却遭人亵渎；我教诲真言，却受斥责。

门徒：主啊，既然你都可以为了实现圣父的旨意而一生忍耐，那我，一个不堪的罪人，岂不更应该遵照你的旨意耐心忍受？为了救赎自己的灵魂，我应该依照你的旨意耐心担负起这腐朽的生命。尽管此世艰苦，但你的恩惠使之有益；因为你的榜样，和古圣先贤的指引，软弱的人，也乐于忍受。如今的安慰远远超越古律法时代，因为那时天门仍旧关闭，天路晦暝不通，寻求天国的人也寥寥无几。那时正直而应当得到救赎的人，也不能进入天国，直到你受难的那天，用你神圣的死亡救赎了我们。

我对你充满无限的感激，你指引了我和所有信徒踏上了那进入你永恒国度的神圣真理之路。你的生活就是我们的方向，我们效法你的忍耐，向你走去，得享冠冕圆满。主啊，若你未曾走在我们之前指引我们，谁有勇气追随呢？如果没有你的光辉作榜样，又有多少人会畏葸不前？如今，我们虽然常常听闻你的教诲和神迹，却还是漠不关心，若是没有你的光明指引，我们现在又会怎样？

第十九章　论忍受创伤和耐心的证明

基督：我儿啊，你在说什么？想想我赎罪之功和许多圣贤所受之苦，就不要抱怨了。你还没有抵抗到流血的地步；和先圣们所受的种种困苦、诱惑、磨炼相比，你承受的微不足道。所以，不要忘记别人所受的沉重苦难，你就会忍受自己的微小困难了。如果你自认为所受的苦并非轻微，或许是因为你没有耐心忍受吧。因此，无论苦难是大是小，都要耐心忍受。

你愈充分准备迎接痛苦，你的行为就愈加明智，你的奖赏就愈丰盛。你的内心愈勤于准备承受痛苦，你就愈觉得它容易忍受。不要说：“我不能忍受某人所强加于我的那些。”也不要说：“我也不该受此冤屈，因为他所做的事极大地伤害了我，他指控我的罪行是我连想都没有想过的，也许出于其他人，我会接受，将这视为理所应当。”这样的想法实在愚昧，因为你无视忍耐的美德和赐予你这一美德的上帝，却只计较得罪你的人，以及你所忍受的恶行。

如果只是甘愿承受自己认为好的苦和自己所喜悦的人带来的苦，那不算真正的忍耐。真有忍耐之心的人不在意是谁带来痛苦，不论是尊者，是同侪，或是下人，也不论是善良圣洁的人，或是乖戾邪恶的人。无论困扰他的痛苦有多严重、有多频繁，无论那痛苦从何而来，他都欣然接受，认为自己受益匪浅，好像那些痛苦都是上帝的恩赐一样。

如果你想要获胜，就要时刻准备战斗；未曾经历磨难，就不能享有忍耐的冠冕；你若拒绝苦难，你就等于拒绝冠冕。因此，你若渴望冠冕，就必须勇敢作战，坚持到底。没有劳苦，无所谓休息；没有战争，也无所谓胜利。

门徒：主啊，让你的恩典助我一臂之力，完成我天生办不到的事。你了解，我只能承受微小的苦，每当轻微的患难加身时，我便很快地跌倒了。以你之名，我祈求你，能让我以苦为乐，因你而受苦，这将对我的灵魂大有裨益。

第二十章　论自身弱点和今生的考验

门徒：主啊，我要忏悔我的罪孽，承认我的弱点。我经常只因一点小事而忧愁沮丧。我决定要勇敢行事，但是一旦遇到微小的诱惑，我便立刻感到窘困。有时原本是一点小事，最终竟因此变成更大的诱惑。当我认为自己稳妥无忧时，却几乎被一阵轻风吹倒。

主啊，求你看顾我的卑微和弱点，这些你全都知道。请怜悯我，拯救我脱离泥潭，我就不至于深陷其中，一蹶不振。在你面前，我常感灰心惭愧，那是因为我总是轻易跌倒，无力抵抗情欲。尽管我并非完全屈服于那些诱惑，但它们不断地困扰我，我十分厌倦过这矛盾冲突的生活。我亦深知我的弱点，因为邪念易于闯入我的内心，却挥之不去。

全能的以色列上帝啊，深爱信徒灵魂的主，祈祷你顾念你仆人的劳苦和忧愁，求你在所有的事上助他一臂之力。求你赐予他天上的勇气让他更加强大，以防我那邪恶的旧敌——那仍未完全归顺于灵魂的肉体，将会占得上风。因此，只要我一息尚存，就要在苦难的此生与之战斗。唉，这是何等悲惨的一生啊，患难愁苦无休无尽，陷阱和仇敌随处可见。一个患难或诱惑刚过去，第二个又随之而来，甚至有时先前的战斗还未结束，新的仇敌又出现了，数不胜数，防不胜防。

此生如此痛苦，多灾多难，我们怎能爱慕它呢？它带来多少死亡与疼痛，又怎能被称为生活呢？但是人们仍然爱它，多少人仍然追求其中的乐趣。人们虽然常常指责世俗的虚伪浮华，可是仍然不肯舍弃世俗，因为肉体的情欲还具有很强的支配力量。这个世界有其惹人喜爱之处，同时也有可憎之处。肉体的情欲，眼目的情欲和今生的骄傲都深深吸引着我们，但紧随其后的痛苦忧愁也足以令我们心生厌恶。

顺从世俗的人，他的心已被扭曲的快乐所占据，以荆棘中的生活为喜悦，这是因为他未曾尝过上帝的甜蜜和神圣的欢愉。只有淡薄世俗，虔心顺从圣律的人，才能品尝些许上帝许诺给一切弃世者的甜蜜，才能知晓这世俗是何等的荒谬和虚伪。

第二十一章　何以安息于上帝，超越一切

门徒：主超越一切，又在一切之中。啊，我的灵魂，因为主才是众圣徒永恒的安息。

祈祷

最敬爱的耶稣啊！祈求你使我超越一切的受造之物，在你那里得享安息；超越健康和美丽、超越所有荣耀和名誉、超越权力和尊贵、超越知识和技艺、超越名声和赞美、超越喜乐和安慰、超越希望和前途、超越功绩和欲望，超越你赐予我们的所有恩典，超越心中能设想和感知的所有喜悦与激动，超越天使、天使长和众天军，超越一切有形和无形的事物，超越上帝本身之外的一切。

主啊，我的上帝，你超越了一切；唯有你是至高无上，无所不能，最富足美好的，你给予他人最多的安慰。你是最美丽、最光荣的，一切美好都源于你，无论过去，现在，还是将来。因此，除非我能见到你，完完全全拥有你，否则和你相比，你所赐予我的，启示应允我的一切都极为渺小，不尽如人意。因为，我的心不能安息，也不完全满足，除非它安息在你那里，超越一切恩典和受造之物。

耶稣基督，我灵魂的伴侣啊，纯洁的爱人，创造万物的神啊，但愿我有自由的双翼，可以飞向你，安息在你那里。主啊，上帝，我何时才能完全解脱，享受心中的宁静，亲眼看见你的荣美呢？我何时才能被你想起？想起我因为爱你而忘却自己，只记得你，以一种不为人知的、超乎一切感官和想象的方式？而现在我仍时常叹息，为悲惨的命运而闷闷不乐。因为在这痛苦的山谷中常有祸患困扰阻挠我，引诱迷惑我，使我不能自由地走向你，获得你赐予有福之灵魂的拥抱。

耶稣啊，你是永恒荣耀的光辉，带给朝圣者灵魂的安慰。请听我呐喊，倾听我的忧伤。在你面前，我口中默默无声，让沉默替我言明一切。主迟迟不来，要拖延多久呢？主啊，请来到你可怜卑贱的仆人这里，令我心中喜悦，愿你伸出手来，拯救你可怜的仆人脱离苦难。来吧，主，快来吧！若没有你，我将得不到喜乐的时光，若没有你，我的餐桌就没有客人，因为只有你是我真正的喜乐。我生来不幸，好似身负镣铐的囚犯，直到你出现，用你的圣光驱散我的阴霾，像朋友一样关怀我。让别人追求他们所喜爱的吧，至于我，没有别的东西可以或将会令我欢喜，唯有你，我的上帝，是我的盼望，是我永远的救赎。我将不再沉默，也不会停止祷告，直到你的恩惠再次降临，内心因你的声音再次欢跃。

基督：看啊，我在这里，我听到了你的呐喊，来到你身边。你的眼泪、你灵魂的渴望、你的谦卑，和你心中的忏悔，打动了我，引我到你面前来。

门徒：主啊，我曾经呼唤你，也渴望你。我决心为你舍弃一切，因为你最先触动我，让我寻求你。所以，主啊，愿赞美归于你，因为你善待你的仆人，赐予他们众多恩惠。你的仆人在你面前还有什么可说的呢？他只能谦卑俯伏在你面前，永远承认他自己的罪孽和邪恶而已。因为你无与伦比，胜过天堂和尘世一切的奇迹。你所做的全是良善，你的审判客观公正，你掌管着万物一切。愿赞美荣耀都归于你，啊，智慧之父！愿我的灵魂，我的肉体以及一切受造之物都同声赞美你。

……

第二十三章　论得享安宁的四件事

基督：我儿啊，我现在要指引你获得安宁和真正自由的办法。

门徒：主啊，我恳求你，请指引我。我渴望了解啊。

基督：我儿啊，要决心实现他人而不是自己的意愿。

总要愿意取少，不可贪多。

总要喜居低位，处身众人之下。

要常常祈求上帝的旨意能够完全成就于你身上。

这样做的人将永享平和与心灵的安宁。

门徒：主啊，你这简短的训言，包含了完善内心的全部奥秘。我若能忠实地遵守此言，定不被烦恼所困扰。无论何时我感到内心不安和沮丧时，我发觉那是因为我背离了您的箴言。万物都由你掌管，你总是渴望不断完善我们的灵魂。祈求你多施恩于我，帮助我遵照你的旨意，进而实现我的救赎。

抵抗邪念的祷告

主啊，我的上帝，求你不要遗弃我；请记住我的需要，因为我心生邪念，灵魂充满恐惧，求你快快帮助我。我要怎样克服它而不受其损害呢？我要如何击败它呢？您曾说，“我将先于你，让傲慢之主谦卑地俯伏于地。我要打开牢狱的门，启示你那长久隐藏的奥秘。”主啊，照你所说的成全吧！但愿一切的邪念消失在你面前。这是我的希望，也是我的安慰，能够在患难时投奔你，深信你，从心底呼唤你，并耐心地等候你的安慰。

祈求内心曙光的祷告

慈悲的耶稣啊，请你将光芒照耀我心，驱除我心中圣所的幽暗。求你压制我心中任性的想法，击碎那些猛攻我的诱惑。求你与我一同战斗，征服兽性的恶欲。使我能够依靠你的能力，获得平安，并使赞美你的声音得以重闻于纯洁的内心圣殿。请命令狂风和暴雨、咆哮的大海、怒吼的北风都平静下来吧。求你发出光辉和真理，普照大地，因为若非你照亮我，我就不过如未经铸型的无用的泥土一般。求你从天上沛降恩霖，滋润我的心；求你赐下虔诚的甘泉，洗涤大地，使它结出善良完美的果实来。求你启迪我因罪而负荷沉重的心，让我全心全意仰望天堂的事，人若曾体会过天堂永恒的滋味，就不会留恋世俗的享乐。求你救我脱离邪恶之物产生的短暂慰藉，因为这都不能真正安慰我，让我如愿以偿。请用爱让我与你紧密相连，因为只有你能让爱你的人得到灵魂的满足，如果没有你，这尘世便毫无意义。

第二十四章　论好奇心之恶

基督：要避免不必要的好奇心。我儿啊，不要多管闲事。那些事与你有何干呢？你跟随我吧！别人是好是坏，所言所行，与你有何关系呢？你无须担心他人之事，只要你对自己完全负责，所以你为什么要给自己找麻烦呢？我了解每一个人，普天之下无所不知。我明白每一个人的情况——他的思想、他的欲望，以及他的目的。因此，你要完全信任我，心中坚守着宁静。让麻烦的人困扰自己，承受报应，因为他不能够欺骗我。

切勿祈求青睐，渴望关注，或与人产生特别亲密的感情。因为这些事使你分心，充满不安。你若常常打开你的心门等候我，我必乐意和你说话，向你启示我的奥秘。请时刻准备，守候和祷告，最重要的是，要谦卑自守。

第二十五章　论内心长久平安与灵性真正进步

基督：我曾经说过：“我留下平安给你们，我将我的平安赐给你们，我所赐的，不像世人所赐的。”[23]人人都希望得到平安，但是却没有人关注那些能真正带来平安的事。我的平安与谦卑温柔的心同在，所以你若想获得平安就必须忍耐。你若肯听从我，遵照我的旨意，你就能得到真正的平安。

门徒：主啊，我该怎样做呢？

基督：你要谨慎对待你的一生及你的所言所行。专心致志于取悦我，只追寻、渴望我。不要轻率判断别人的行为，也不要在没有托付你的事上找麻烦，如果你遵照我的意思，就不会多受精神上的困扰。但不要设想你此生毫无困扰，或不必经受身心的痛苦，因为，只有永恒的安息，才能实现真正的平安。所以，当你觉得没有困难时，切不可以为你已经得到了真正的平安；当你不遭反对时，也不要以为万事都将如你所愿；即使一切顺意，也不要以为万事完美无缺。当你承蒙恩典，心中火热幸福时，你切不可傲慢固执，自以为独享上帝盛宠，因为这并不证明你真正爱主，也不决定你灵魂的进步。

门徒：主啊，那取决于什么呢？

基督：取决于你全心遵行上帝的旨意，无论大事小事，现在或永远，都不妄自擅行。如果你完全照此行事，那么无论顺境逆境，你都将同样愉悦地感激上帝，并欣然接受上帝安排的一切。你要勇敢坚强，坚定不移，即使内心失去安慰，也要准备迎接更大的考验。不可自以为义，以为你不应当遭受如此的痛苦，而是要相信我的一切安排都秉承公义，并赞扬我的圣名。这样的话，你就踏上了真正平安的圣道，我必将再与你相见，赐予你喜悦。只要你心怀谦卑之心，我必允诺你此世得到极大的平安。

第二十六章　论自由之心的优越

门徒：主啊，一个寻求完善的人必将时刻关注天堂的事作为首要任务。只有这样，他才能在世事纷纭之中，逍遥无累，不像毫无才智的人不知道危险正在降临，而是拥有强大的自由内心，不留恋于外物。

最慈悲的上帝，我恳求你保护我脱离尘事世务的缠累和肉体情欲的沉溺，以及一切灵性的障碍，使我不被它们打败击垮。我并不祈求免于世俗所追求的虚荣，而是祈求能远离那烦扰、妨碍灵魂的痛苦，那是对所有尘世之人的诅咒。它们常常阻碍我的灵性，让我不能随时获得灵魂真正的自由。主啊，我的上帝，求你为我将一切肉体的安乐变成痛苦，因为这些时常引诱我离开对你永恒的爱，并利用一时的全部欢愉，邪恶地引诱我。主啊，求你不让血肉之躯战胜我，不让尘世暂时的荣耀欺骗我，也不让魔鬼和他的诡计陷害我。求你赐我力量可以抵抗，赐我耐心可以忍受，也赐我恒心可以坚持。我不求你赐我世上的一切福乐，只求你赐我圣灵的丰盛恩典，用你的爱取代尘世一切的欢乐。一个热忱于上帝的灵魂不愿意过多关注吃穿用度和其他生理需要。求你使我有节制地享受它们，不至于过分在意它们。完全不顾这些东西固然是不对的，因为身体本身需要存活；但是贪多纵欲，却为圣律所禁，因为那样，肉体便要反叛灵魂。所以，我恳求你，请你于方方面面指引我，管控我，使我总能自律节制。

……

第二十八章　抵制诽谤

基督：我儿啊，若有人诋毁你，说你所不愿听的话，不要放在心上。应当认为自己比他们想象得更严重，也比任何人都更软弱。如果你的内心世界足够强大，就不至于受流言蜚语影响了！大智之人，在被邪恶纠缠的日子中总是保持安静，而且全心向主，不为人言所动。

不要让他人的言语影响你心中的平安，因为不论他们对你的批评是好是坏，你都不会改变自己本来的样子。真正的平安和喜乐只在我里面。那些不急切地取悦他人，也不怕触怒他人的人，才能获得真正的平安。心中一切的不安和纷扰，都源于纷乱的情绪和没来由的恐惧。

第二十九章　患难之时如何祈求赞美上帝

门徒：你的圣名应当永远受称颂，主啊！我知道正是因为你的旨意，诱惑与患难才会降临到我身。我不能逃避患难，但却必须投奔于你寻求帮助，化患难为喜乐。主啊，我心中忧痛，心绪不宁，正深受痛苦。

亲爱的父啊，我还要说什么呢？我正在困难之中，求你救我脱离这日子。我之所以遇此患难的日子，正是为了你的荣耀，我深知只有你才能救我脱离这苦海。你的慈爱，请救救我，主啊！我如此无助，又能做什么？没有你的帮助，我能去往何方？即使受此考验，主啊，请赐予我耐心。你助我一臂之力，我将无所畏惧，无论承受多少苦难。

此刻正处苦难，我衷心祈祷，主啊，“愿你的旨意成就。”这些痛苦乃是我所应得。我必耐心忍受此患难，直至安然度过这暴风雨。我的上帝，慈悲的主啊，你曾多次救我，我知道你的全能可以消除对我的考验，减轻我的痛苦，我就不至完全崩溃。考验越艰难，至高的主啊，你就越容易改变我的道路。

第三十章　切求神佑笃信主恩

基督：我儿啊，患难时，我是赐予你力量的主。你若内心挣扎就要到我这里来。最能阻碍你得到天上的安慰的，是你太过迟缓的祷告。因为你在求我之前，总是先向外物寻求慰藉，期望他们来消除你的困扰。直到所有外物都于事无补时，你才想起我是救世主，所有信仰我的人都能得到救赎。除我之外，再无有效的帮助，再无明智的忠告，也无长久的救法。但是，现在暴风雨既已过去，你就要在我的慈光之中恢复你的力量。因为我在此会将一切恢复原状，不仅丝毫未变，而且还要慷慨地、足足地加赐于你。

对于我，有何难成的事么？难道我像是不履行诺言的人么？你的信心在何处？你只要坚定不移，坚持不懈，勇敢、忍耐，到了合适的时候，安慰自然会降临于你。要耐心等候我，我必来救治你。诱惑不过是考验——不必担心恐惧。忧虑只会给你徒增烦恼，“一天的难处一天当就够了”。[24]为将来苦恼或欣喜都徒劳无益，因为这些事也许未必发生。

人的内心常易受这些假象的欺骗，但被恶魔的言语欺骗则可证明人精神软弱。魔鬼欺骗你时并不在意此事是真还是假，也不在乎击垮你的是对现在的留恋还是对未来的恐惧。所以，不要令你的内心因此而纷乱或害怕。只要信赖我，完全信赖我的慈爱。当你以为自己离我甚远的时候，常常就是我最靠近你的时候。当你以为自己将要一败涂地时，常常就是你将得到丰盛赏赐的时候。事与愿违并非完全的失败。你不可任一时的感觉模糊自己的判断，也不要忧愁绝望，好像所有的希望都不复存在一样。

如果我暂时让你承受些许的患难考验，或带走你所渴慕的喜悦，请不要认为我已完全抛弃了你；因为这是走向天国的必经之路。毫无疑问，历经艰难比万事顺意，更能锻炼你以及我所有的仆人。我知道你心中的秘密，在凡事顺利的境况中，你就会骄傲自满，沾沾自喜地认为自己比实际的样子更好。正因如此，有时让你身处窘境，对你有益无害。我可以收回我所赐予的恩典，也可以选择何时重新施恩于你。

我所赐的安慰，依然归属于我，当我收回时，也并不是取走属于你的东西，因为一切至善与完全的恩惠都是我的！我若加你痛苦，或是任何困难，请不要愤愤不平、垂头丧气；因为我能迅速帮你，将你一切的苦楚化为喜悦。尽管如此，我却深藏不露，你应赞美我。

假若你睿智聪明，正确判断，你永远不会绝望或气馁。反之，如果我用苦难折磨你，不放过你，你应该感到高兴和感激，并以忧患归为喜悦。我对我亲爱的门徒说过：“我爱你们，正如父爱我一样。”[25]我差遣他们出去，决非为让他们享受尘世的快乐，而是要他们艰苦奋斗；并非为让他们赢得荣耀，而是受人藐视；并非让他们悠闲自得，而是辛苦劳作；并非让他们放松休息，而是耐心地孕育累累硕果。

第三十一章　论放弃万物寻求造物主

门徒：主啊，我还需要更大的恩惠，求你使我达到没有任何人或事物可以阻碍我进步的境界。因为如果有任何事物拖累我，我就不能自由地走向你。那些渴望自由飞到你面前的人说：“但愿我有翅膀像鸽子，我就飞去，得享安息。”[26]有谁能比目标纯一的人更能获得安静呢？有谁能比不留恋尘世的人更逍遥自在呢？所以，执着于精神的人应该超越万物，完全舍弃自己，清楚地认识到任何受造之物都不能和造物主相提并论。除非一个人能超脱万物，否则他就不能全身心关注上帝的事。我们之所以很少看见沉默好思的人，就是因为没有几个人能完全超越昙花一现的受造之物。

若要超越自己的束缚，就需要承蒙更多的恩典，提高自己的灵命。除非具有超脱的心，无累于物，且完全与上帝合而为一，否则他的所知所有都毫无价值。如果一个人除了关注唯一至高永恒的上帝之外，还留恋其他的事物，他的内心就必将保持卑劣低下。因为除上帝以外，一切事物都是虚空，也应该被视为虚空。一个虔诚受教于上帝之人的智慧，和一个博学勤读之人的知识，有很大的差别。源于上帝的神圣启示比刻苦学到的知识要高贵得多。

有许多人渴望沉思带来的恩典，但是很少有人不辞劳苦地践行沉思所必需的要求。如果我们致力于外形和感觉的事物，却不顾完善对自己的约束，那将是很大的阻碍。我不知道出于何种原因，是何动机，我们这些所谓属灵的人常常致力费心于琐碎日常的事物，却极少专心致志于思考自己的内心生活。

唉，短暂的思考过后，我们便立即停止，转而去关注外在的事物，而且我们也不曾细察我们的生活究竟如何。我们不关注我们的热爱究竟所在何处，也没有因我们整个人生的罪恶而感到愧疚。正是因为人们的恶性，上帝才引洪水而来。如果我们内心败坏了，所产生的行为也必定邪恶。这也证明人类内在力量的薄弱；只有纯净的内心才能生出神圣的果实。

我们常常谈论一个人的成就，却很少关注他生活的原则。我们常常问他是否勇敢、俊美、富有、聪慧，是否笔下生花、声如天籁、兢兢业业，但是他是否虚心、忍耐、温柔、虔诚、属灵，却无人问津。人的天性只知看重人的外在，上帝的恩典却看重人的内心品性。表象常常误导他人，令人失望，而关注内心的人才能得蒙恩典，不至于受欺骗。

第三十二章　论舍己与弃绝欲望

基督：我儿啊，获得完全自由的唯一办法就是要舍弃自己。那些只求私利、自爱的人，都是作茧自缚，是自己欲望的奴隶。他们贪心、好奇、不满足，游手好闲，为凡事所扰，却不服侍耶稣基督。这必然不能长久，因为凡不属于上帝的事物都必归于灭亡。

遵循这简明的箴言：舍弃一切，你才会得到一切；弃绝欲望，你才会获得安宁。你要好好思索这句话，当你做到时，你就会明白其中的一切。

门徒：主啊，这不是一日之功所能成，也不是儿戏之事，这句简短的话语包含了所有完善灵魂之道。

基督：我儿啊，听到这完善灵魂之道，不要感到胆怯沮丧，远离你的目标。而要更加勉励自己，要全力以赴追求这一崇高的目标，至少要用心尝试。我真愿意你能达到那样的境界：不再爱自己，只听从我和我所指派的神父的旨意，这样，你就一定能令我喜悦，你的整个生活也必将充满喜悦并获得平安。但是你还有许多事必须割舍，你若不将它们完全献给我，就不能从我这里得到你祈求的东西。我劝你向我买火炼的金子，让自己拥有天上的智慧，舍弃尘世的事物，变得真正富足。要对尘世的智慧不屑一顾，不试图取悦于他人或是你自己。

我说过，要把看似贵重荣耀的事物换成人们不屑一顾的事物。但是天上真正的智慧对于他们似乎一文不值，几乎为他们所遗忘。因为这种智慧不自大，也不求在尘世受人尊崇。固然有许多人在言语上尊敬它，但是在他们实际生活中却无足轻重。然而，这是一颗宝贵的珍珠，只是没有人认识它的价值。

第三十三章　论人心无常

基督：我儿啊，不要信赖你的感情，因为它瞬息万变，不能持久。你在世活一天，你便一天身处在改变之中，即使你自己不愿意，也无可奈何，所以你有时快乐，有时悲伤；有时安静，有时烦躁；有时虔诚，有时冷淡；有时热切，有时怠慢；有时严肃，有时轻浮。但是真正的智者和熟知圣灵的人，却以不变应万变，不顾暂时的感觉和兴致，总能集中全部心志于那正直至善的目标。因此，在变幻的世态中，他能始终如一，坚贞不移，他的心只归属于我。

人的目标愈纯一，他愈能稳妥地度过人生的风波。但很多时候，这单纯的目标受到迷惑，因为人们的注意力总是随时为眼前有趣的事情吸引，能完全超脱自私和牵累的人，在此世上绝无仅有。犹太人到伯大尼的马大和马利亚的家中，并非为耶稣的缘故，却是要看拉撒路。[27]所以，你们的动机要纯一、简单、正直，那才是唯一能够通向我的坦途。

……

第三十六章　不顾无稽之谈

基督：我儿啊，你要全心全意依靠主。只要良心证明你是尽职而且纯洁的，就不要畏惧他人的无稽之谈。如此受人批评，乃是美好而且快乐的事，一个谦卑、信赖上帝、不依靠自己的人，对于这样的批评丝毫不以为意。很多人高谈阔论，不要理会他们。况且，我们不可能让所有人都满意。圣保罗[28]也曾想努力取悦上帝面前的所有人，造福所有人，但他很少关注别人怎么诋毁他。他竭尽全力，担负起造就人、拯救人的重任，且坚持不懈，可是他仍旧无法逃避被人批评和藐视。所以，他就把一切交托于无所不知的上帝，以忍耐和谦卑替自己辩护，抵抗那不公正的指控、子虚乌有的谎言和诽谤者的无稽之谈。然而有时他也起来回复他人的责难，以免祸水因他的缄默而被引到弱者身上。

你为何畏惧必死之人呢？他今天还在，明天就会消失。你只要敬畏上帝，就不必恐惧他人了。人的言语或行为又如何能中伤于你呢？他不能伤害你，却只伤害他自己罢了，而且无论他是谁，都不能逃避上帝的审判。你只要面前时刻有上帝在，就不必与毁谤的言语相争辩。即使目前看来你似乎被击败，且蒙受不应得的羞辱，但请你不要怨愤或动怒，免得因急躁失掉本应得的赏赐。相反，你要举目仰天看我，我能够洗雪你一切羞辱和冤屈，并依照每个人的德行，赐予恩典。

第三十七章　舍己如何带来内心的自由

基督：我儿啊，你要舍弃自己，才会寻见我。不为自己选择什么，也不寻求私有，你就必常常受益匪浅。因为当你毫不留恋地舍弃自己而皈依我时，就会得到更大的恩典。

门徒：主啊，我要多久舍弃自己一次呢？又当如何舍己呢？

基督：要不断地舍弃自己，每时每刻都舍己，小事大事都舍己。我对你没有别的要求，只要你完全超脱自我：除非你完全舍弃个人意志，否则你如何归属于我呢？我又如何成为你的呢？你愈早舍己，对你就愈好，你愈完全真诚地舍己，就愈能取悦我，你受益也就愈大。

有些人不肯完全奉献，因为他们不完全信奉上帝，所以总为自己打算。还有些人起初完全奉献自己，但是后来受了诱惑，就重回原来的状态。因此，他们的德行没有丝毫进展，也不会获得内心真正的自由，或是我的恩典，除非他们先完全归顺，并且天天奉献。否则，他们与我之间就不会建立有效的联系，更不会持久。

我曾经多次和你说过，现在我将再说一次：你要舍己献身，才会获得内心的平安。舍弃你所有的一切，不求所得，不计报酬，只要你坚定地信赖我，你就必然得享我，并得到内心的自由，心灵也不会被黑暗所蒙蔽。努力实现此事，虔诚祷告此事，只期望如此——你就将超脱一切的自私，纯洁地跟随耶稣，向你自己死去，却向我永远活着。那时，一切的妄想、恶念、忧虑都将化为乌有；那时，一切恐惧与不安都将离开你，迷乱的情欲也将灰飞烟灭。

第三十八章　合理安排我们的俗事

基督：我儿啊，当你应对一切外界的事物时，都要努力使内心获得自由，成为自己的主人，令万事万物做你的奴仆，绝不可受制于他们。只有这样，你才能做行动的主人，而不会沦为它们的仆人或奴隶；你才能成为一个真正自由的人，一个真正的基督徒，享有上帝之子的自由和天命。因为上帝的儿子们必定超脱现世的事物，思考永恒的事物，在他们真实的光明中看待俗世和天堂的事物。尘世的事物不能牵累他们，相反地，他们却能使尘世万物依照上帝的旨意服务于他们，因为上帝所造的万物无不遵守一定的秩序。

无论在何种情况下，都要坚定不移。不要和凡人一样凭借外表和道听途说来判断事情，却要像摩西[29]一样，无论何事都进入会幕[30]，求问于上帝。有时你能得到上帝的回答，当你从那里回来时，不论对于现在或将来，你都将了然于胸。摩西每逢有疑问的时候，就必进入会幕求助于上帝，每逢遇到天灾人祸，就借着祷告祈求上帝保护身处险境、虎狼环绕的自己。所以，你也应以他为榜样，效法他，从心底虔诚地恳求上帝的帮助。我们在圣经上读过，约书亚和以色列人受基遍人的欺骗，那正是由于他们事先没有求问上帝，轻信了基遍人动听的言语，被他们虚假的虔诚所误导。[31]

第三十九章　不必过分忧虑

基督：我儿啊，你要将所有事都托付于我，我必将适时为你安排妥当。你要等候我的安排，你必将发现一切都为让你受益。

门徒：主啊，我时刻准备将所有事都交托于你，因为我的判断毫无价值。只希望我不必那样忧虑将来的事，全心奉献自己，只求你的喜悦。

基督：我儿啊，人们常常不遗余力地设法得到他们想要的东西，但是当他达到目的后，就开始动另外的念头了。因为人的欲望并不是一成不变，往往从一个目标转向下一个更高的目标。所以人若能在最小的事上舍己，绝对令他受益匪浅。真正灵性的进步在于舍己，凡是舍己的人必将获得真正的自由与平安。但是魔鬼总是与善为敌的，它不停地试探我们，日夜埋伏等候，欺骗陷害那些不积极防备的人。所以，“总要儆醒祷告，免得入了迷惑”。[32]

第四十章　人类毫无良善值得夸耀

门徒：“主啊，人算什么，你竟顾念他，世人算什么，你竟眷顾他？”[33]人有何功德，配受你所赐的恩典呢？主啊，即使你舍弃我，我也毫无怨言。即使你不应允我所求所想，我也不与你争论。我实在只能这样想，这样说：“主啊，我一无所有，我也不能做任何事，我自己毫无良善，一无是处。除非你指引我的内心赐予我力量，否则我将变得不堪一击，无助绝望。”

主啊，你亘古不变，永远良善、公平和圣洁，要求万事都良善、公平和圣洁，且以智慧安排一切。但是我却容易倒退，难于进步，不能恒久如一，时常改变。然而，你若愿屈尊伸手助我，我必将改过自新；因为只有你能不借人力就帮助我，赐予我力量，我就不会多变无常，而是全身心归属于你，安息于你。尘世的任何人都无法安慰我，我若能完全舍弃人间一切的安乐——无论是以此增益我的虔诚，还是因为自身需要迫使我追寻你——我就可完全信赖你的恩典，愉快地享受你赐予的新的安乐。

每当一切顺意时，我必将感谢你，因为一切都得益于你。在你面前，我不过是虚无，一个软弱无常的凡人罢了。因此，我有何值得夸耀的呢？有何令人尊敬的呢？难道夸自己一无所有？可见自夸毫无意义。空夸实在是罪恶，无聊之极，因为它使人不能获得真正的荣耀，夺走了他神圣的恩宠。所以只要他自鸣得意，就不会令你喜悦；只要他渴望受人称赞，就失去了真正的美德。真正的荣耀和喜悦在于令你荣耀而不是他自己；应因你的名喜乐，却不是因为自己的力量而沾沾自喜；除了因为你的缘故之外，不要因其他受造之物而高兴。愿颂赞归于你的名，而不要归于我；我将尊崇你的作为，而不是我自己的，我将称颂你神圣的美名。我不渴求尘世之人的赞誉。只有你是我的荣耀，是我心中唯一的喜乐。我将时刻赞美你，以你为荣耀，至于我自己，除了我的弱点之外，别无可夸耀之处。让犹太人彼此求得荣耀，而我只寻求上帝赐予的荣耀。因为一切人间的荣耀，一切尘世的荣誉，一切世俗的尊贵，若与你永恒的荣耀相比，都不过是虚无和愚蠢罢了。该受赞美的三位一体的真神啊，上帝啊，真理啊，慈爱啊，愿赞誉、尊贵、权力和荣耀都归于你，永无穷尽。

第四十一章　论轻视尘世的虚荣

基督：我儿啊，你若看见别人享有荣誉，步步高升，你却受人轻视，你切勿因此沮丧悲伤。只要全心向主，世人的藐视就不会令你忧虑。

门徒：主啊，我们是盲目的，易受虚妄之事物的欺骗。如果我认真审视我的生活，就会发现没有什么人曾经得罪过我，我有何权利抱怨呢？但是，因为我常常得罪你，所以理应承受万人的攻击。所以，羞辱、藐视是我该得的。但是对你，主啊，你应得到颂赞、尊贵和荣耀。除非我准备以愉快之心，乐意受任何人藐视、厌弃，甘心被人看为完全虚无，否则我就不能得到内心的平安和安稳，也不能得到精神上的启迪，而与你完全合一。

第四十二章　平安不取决于人

基督：我儿啊，你若将平安寄托在你的爱人或朋友身上，你的心将始终漂泊不定，为他所累。但是你若信赖永恒不变的真神，即使朋友离开你，或死亡，也不能使你忧伤。你对于朋友的感情应当建立在我的基础上，凡你所敬所爱的人，你都要因为我而爱他们。如果没有我，友谊就没有力量，也不会天长地久。凡不是由我赐福而结合的，他们的爱情必不能真纯。就你自己而言，你应当因自己对所爱之人的感情而羞愧，以至于你会放弃一切友情，应甘心乐意避免一切人间的友谊。一个人越远离自己在尘世中的安慰，他就越靠近上帝。越轻视自己的人，在上帝面前就占据越高的地位。

凡自以为善的人，必得不着上帝的恩典，因为圣灵的恩惠只赐给谦卑的人。你若能完全克制自己，令自己不沉迷于尘世的爱恋，我必将丰盛的恩典赐予你。你若留恋受造之物，就必见不到造物者。你要学会在任何事中都因为爱上帝而克制自己，那样你才能得到上帝的智慧。即使是极微小的事，你若沉溺于其中，不能自拔，它就能阻碍你达到至善之境，玷污你的灵魂。

第四十三章　警惕世俗虚空的知识

基督：我儿啊，不要让人间美丽巧妙的言语动摇你的心，因为上帝之国不在乎言语，只在乎主的权能。要谨记我的话，因为它能燃烧你的心，照亮你的思想，使你产生悔过之心，带去一切安慰。永远不要为了让自己看上去更睿智、更博学而学习，要为了克服折磨你的原罪而学，因为这样你会收获更多，远超那掌握复杂问题的能力。

当你博览全书，涉猎广泛时，且要回归最本质的真理：我便是知识最初的源头，教会人类知识，使人类更加清澈醒悟，这是人所不能教的。凡是我所教的人就会很快地成为智者，在属灵的人生中进步。但是那些好奇人间奇异之事，而不在乎事奉我的人只会遭受痛苦。当合适的时候到来，万师之师，天使之主，基督就要显现，他将聆听所有人的人生事迹，考察他们每一个人的良心。那时他提着灯在耶路撒冷搜寻，黑暗中隐藏之事都要显露出来，众说纷纭也将终止。

我是启发谦卑之心的上帝，使谦卑的人豁然开朗，顿悟永恒的真理，胜过十年苦读。我的教诲默默无声，亦无纷纭众说，不求显达尊贵，没有困惑人心的辩论。我教导人轻视尘世之事，了解现世的困扰，寻求永恒之事，躲避荣誉，承受伤痛，寄一切希望于我，除我以外别无所求，且热爱我超乎一切之上。

曾经有一个人全心全意地爱我，学习我神圣的奥秘，富于激情地赞美我。比起这精深学习，舍弃一切让他获益更多。我对有的人教以平常之事，对另外的人又教以深奥之事，对有的人我用神迹和象征，但对那些已经开蒙的人，我会揭释我的奥秘。

一本书只有一种声音，但读者所获，却各有不同。只有我教授真理，找寻人心，鉴别行为，公正审判每个人。

第四十四章　论避免分心被扰

基督：我儿啊，你必须对许多事情不屑一顾；所以，当视自己为已向世界死去的人，世俗亦已将你钉在十字架上。此外，你应掩耳不听外面的事，却只思考使你平静的事。不理会有争议之事，不干涉人家的意见，置身事外远远胜过与人不断争辩。只要你享有上帝的恩典，全心全意执行主的旨意，和上帝之间有密切的关系，你就会很容易忍受表面的溃败。

门徒：主啊，我们怎么到了这个地步呢？我们哀伤尘世的损失，为蝇头小利而奔忙，却忽略了灵性上的损失，并很少想起这回事。我们只关注微小或甚至毫无益处的事，却忽视了那最要紧的事。如果人们的精力集中于外在的事物，还不迅速悔改，就将堕落其中。

第四十五章　切勿轻信他人

门徒：主啊，求你在患难之时帮助我，因为人的帮助是徒然的。我常常沮丧，以为我自己能找到忠实的朋友，但是，实际上并非如此。但有时我丝毫没有期待会找到忠实朋友，却出乎意料找到了。所以，信赖人都是徒然的，只有你才能拯救我，主啊。无论我们身处怎样的境遇，都将赞美你，主啊，我的上帝。

我们是软弱无常的，容易受欺骗。无论是谁都不能在一切事上谨慎地保护自己而不陷入迷惑或被欺骗。只有信赖你，专心寻求你的人，才不易于挫败。无论他遭受了多大的苦难，他也不会深陷其中，你会第一时间拯救他，安慰他；因为你从不背弃信靠你的人，直到永远。共患难的朋友人间少有。但是主啊，只有你是永远忠诚的，无人能及。

圣徒（圣阿加莎）真是一个智者，他曾说“我的心坚定地扎根在基督里”。我若真能如此，就不会畏惧任何人，不为任何言语所动摇。我们不能预测未来之事，不能避免将来的祸患；而且，可预知的事情尚且常常将我们伤害，至于那些防不胜防的事情，岂不更加严重地伤害我们么？对于不幸，为何我们不早作准备呢？为何我们如此信赖别人呢？我们不过是凡人，虽然我们被人称作天使，可我们还是很软弱。主啊，我可以信任谁呢？除了你之外，还有谁呢？你是真理，不欺骗人，也不受欺骗。但是人都说谎，软弱、无常、不堪一击，尤其易于在言语上犯罪，所以，我们不应当轻信那些看似真实的事。

主警告我们当防备世人，真是何等的智慧。而且人的仇敌常常就是自己家里的人，所以若有人说“他在这儿”，或“他在那儿”，不要轻率相信。我的痛苦经验教导了我，我只希望自己能吸取教训，更加认真，克服愚蠢。有人对我说：“记住，我所告诉你的，不得说与旁人。”于是我缄默地保守秘密，不料他自己却不能保守，把我和他自己一齐出卖了，按照他自己的主意行事。主啊，求你保护我远离这种人，不让我落在他们的手中，更不让我自己犯同样的过失。求你使我在言语上诚实、可信，远离巧舌之人。我所恶于人的弱点，我应当竭尽全力使自己避免。

不论断他人，不轻信人言，也不散布消息，这是何等的美德和安宁啊！知心之友不多，我们应时常寻求察看人心的上帝。我们不要人云亦云，而要祈祷我们一生，不论是内心的或是身外的，都照你的旨意成就。

轻视表象，改进生活，陶冶灵魂，而非迎合世俗，就必然获得上天的恩典。

许多人因为公众的名气、轻薄的赞扬而深受其害。只有在此转瞬即逝而又充斥着诱惑和争端的一生中静默保守，才能获得最有力的恩典。

……

第五十一章　无力从事高级工作，就应承担谦卑的任务

基督：我儿啊，你不能自己总保持善良的愿望和沉思的乐境，你不时将会受原罪的驱使，堕落于低级的生活中，承受现世的苦楚和重担。只要你是凡人，你就不能避免心中的疲倦和忧愁。所以，你此生将时常由于肉体的负担而悲哀，因为它使你不能完全致力于属灵的生活和神圣的沉思。

这样的事一旦发生，明智的办法是投身于卑微的外在事务中，借善行重塑自我。同时坚定等候我的来临和恩眷，耐心忍受灵魂的孤苦无依，直到我再度来临，解除你一切的痛苦。那时你必将忘记之前的劳苦，得获内心的宁静。我将在你面前揭示圣经的妙处，你的内心将遵行我的诫命，获得自由。那时你会说：“现世的苦楚，若比起将来要属于我们的荣耀，就不足介意了。”[34]……

第五十三章　上帝的恩典不赐予恋慕尘世的人

基督：我儿啊，我的恩典是宝贵的，它不容许尘世的安慰与享乐和它混为一谈。所以，你若愿得到此恩典，就必须先扫除遇到的所有障碍。要寻找一僻静之地，喜爱独居，不与人谈话，只向上帝热诚祷告，那样才能保持灵魂谦卑和良心纯洁。你要将全世界视为乌有，乐于事奉上帝，胜于一切。因为你不能一面侍奉我，同时又享受尘世的欢乐。你应该远离你的亲友，不依赖此世任何安慰。正因如此，使徒彼得曾劝告基督的信徒将自己视作现世的陌生人，如同客旅寄居一般。

人若丝毫不受尘世事物之累，他在面对死亡时，必定坦然无惧！灵命弱小的人不能明白丝毫无累的心境，追求名利的人也不能知道属灵之人的自由。但是人若想成为真正属灵的人，他就必须舍弃所有人，无论是朋友还是陌生人，还要防备自己胜于防备他人。你若完全克服了自己，就会轻易掌控一切。完全的胜利就在于征服自己。因为能控制自己的人，能使感性屈服于理性，而理性又屈从于我，这样的人既能征服自己，又能掌控世界。

如果你想达到这样的完善境界，就应勇敢尝试，根除恶源，舍弃一切隐藏的私欲和尘世的嗜好。因为这些万恶之根会引发其他恶行，我必须努力克服。只要此祸根得以清除，永恒的安宁就将随之而来。但是极少人竭尽全力完完全全地舍己，或完全超越自己；因此他们仍无法自拔，也不能在灵性上超越自己。凡是愿意自由地追随我的人，他就必须禁绝一切败坏的情欲，克制对尘世的恋慕。

第五十四章　论神恩与人性有别

基督：我儿啊，你要谨慎观察神恩与人性各自的驱动力，二者虽受不同原因驱动，表现却如此相近，即使是内心受圣灵光照的人，恐怕也很难辨别。事实上，凡人都渴望善行，他们在言语行为上也尽力表现德善，所以很多人被此表面的善行所欺骗。

人天性狡猾，许多人受其诱惑、欺骗，只求达到自己的目的。但是神恩却是纯朴的，绝无丝毫罪恶的倾向，亦无半点欺骗，她所做的一切仅仅是纯粹地爱上帝，她最终的目的就是在上帝那儿得到安息。

人性不愿被压抑、被审视、被征服，不会轻易顺从或心悦诚服。但是神恩却努力克制自己，抵抗肉欲，喜居人下，甘心臣服于人。她并不期望享受自己的自由，却喜爱受管束，也不愿意统治其他人。只求常常活在上帝的旨意中，因为上帝的缘故，欣然俯伏于众人之下。

人性只求自己的利益，估量自己能从他人身上攫取多少好处；神恩却不图自己的利益和方便，讲求大众的利益。人性渴望荣誉，喜欢受人崇拜；神恩忠实地将一切荣耀都归于上帝。人性惧怕羞辱和藐视；神恩喜欢为耶稣的名受辱。人性喜欢空闲和肉体的安逸；神恩从不游手好闲，而是欣然迎接工作的到来。

人性喜欢稀罕美丽的事物，憎恶粗贱的东西；神恩喜欢简单朴素的东西，不轻看粗针大线，也不厌恶衣衫褴褛。人性看重尘世短暂的事物，获利则喜，损失则忧，不肯耐心忍受一点轻微的委屈；神恩看重永恒的事物，不受俗物之累，不因损失而忧，不以恶言而辱，因为一切财富与喜悦都已被安放于天堂，绝无损失之虑。

人性贪婪，乐于索取，不思奉献，喜欢将外物占为己有；神恩仁慈良善，慷慨大方，不求私利，且易于知足，又深知奉献比索取更为有福。人性使人倾向于外物——肉体、虚荣、心神不安；神恩将人引向上帝和善行，弃物、避世、恨恶肉体、禁绝交游，不与众人相见。人性渴望寻求外来的安慰，满足感官上的逸乐；神恩只追求上帝的安慰，喜悦至善而胜于一切有形之物。

人性行任何事都只为一己私利，不做无报酬的事，一旦施恩于人，必求相应或更高的报酬，或是称赞恩惠。但是神恩不求尘世的回报，除了上帝之外，也不望得其他报酬，不求生活所必需之上的享受，只求能助其获得永恒的事物罢了。

人性喜欢呼朋唤友，夸耀自己尊贵的地位和高贵的出身，谄媚权贵、逢迎富豪、称赞与自己相似的人。但是神恩甚至亲爱仇敌，不夸朋友众多和高贵的出身，若非具有相当的德行亦不足重。神恩爱贫嫌富，与正派之人同道，厌恶权贵，喜欢诚实人，疏远诡诈者。神恩常常鼓励善人更进一步，追求更大的恩典，通过善行成为像上帝之子一样的人。

人性每遇困乏必生怨言；神恩却坚忍不拔，忍受贫穷。人性只为自己努力、奋斗，将凡事都归于自己的利益，喜欢为自己解释争辩；神恩把一切归于所出的上帝，不将任何长处归于自己，不妄自尊大，不争执，亦不固执己见。无论是内心还是知觉的力量，都归功于永恒的智慧和上帝的旨意。人性好奇，打探秘辛，喜听新闻，爱出人头地，满足于轰动一时。人性渴望受人认可，赢得赞誉和敬仰。但是神恩却不关注新闻和稀奇的事，因为这一切都出于人类古老的堕落行为，而世上没有新奇而恒久不变的事。

神恩教人如何禁绝感官，避免自满虚夸；如何谦卑地隐匿值得称羡的事；如何在所有的事物和知识中，求得好结果，并寻求上帝的赞美和荣光。神恩不愿受人称赞，只求上帝因其恩惠而受称颂，因为上帝所赐给人类的一切，皆出于纯粹的爱。

神恩是超然的光，是上帝的特别恩赐，是被选召者的记号，也是救赎的凭据，它使人脱离尘世，专爱天上的事物，脱离肉体，变成属灵的人。因此，人性愈受克制，神恩就愈加丰满，这样，内心每日领受上帝的新恩，每日都成为更像上帝形象的人。

第五十五章　论人性的堕落与神恩的力量

门徒：主啊，我的上帝，你曾照着你自己的形象创造了我，又赐予我得救所必需的恩典，使我可以胜过诱我犯罪堕落的本性。我感觉到在我肉体中，犯罪的冲动与内心的原则格格不入，常常把我掳去服从肉体的情欲，我实在无法抵抗情欲，除非你的圣恩浇灌我心，助我一臂之力。

主啊，我需要你浩大的恩典，才能战胜那自幼就倾向于罪恶的本性。因为自从始祖亚当开始，人性就堕落，因罪而败坏，惩罚留给了全人类，所以你原本所创造的善良正直的人性，现在却变成堕落软弱的象征了，因为一旦被遗留下来，就倾向于深陷罪恶。仅存的能力不过是炉灰中的星星之火罢了。但这能力便是天赋的理性，它虽然受黑暗的蒙蔽，仍具有鉴别真伪善恶的能力。但是它力量微弱，不能实行它所认可的善行，也无法享受真理的全部光明，或是他自身的健全发展。

主啊，我的上帝，当我要内心随从你的戒律，深知你的诫命乃是良善、公义、圣洁，既谴责罪恶，又避免犯罪，但是我的肉体仍履行了罪恶的律法，服从了感性而非理性。所以，当我立志为善时，却发现自己无力遵行。我常常立志做许多善事，但是因为缺乏神恩相助来克服我的弱点，任何轻微的阻力，都令我沮丧挫败。所以，我虽然知道完善的路，也清楚地看见我应该做什么，但是因为受着堕落的本性所压制，在完善的道路上步履维艰。

主啊，一旦开始、持守并完善一件善事，我是多么急需你的恩典啊！若没有你的恩典，我将一无所成；但若是在你里面，借助你的恩典，一切将皆有可能。啊，真正的天恩啊，没有你，我们的德行毫无价值，本性的禀赋亦微不足道。主啊，没有你的恩典，任何艺术、财富、美丽、力量、聪明、才辩，都不值一提。因本性的禀赋为善人恶人所共有，但是恩典和爱心，却是赐予承蒙你选召之人的特殊恩典，凡带着这尊贵标记的人，就配享受永生。恩典如此神圣，若没有它，说预言，行神迹，以及高级的思考，都将毫无价值。若没有爱和恩典，即使有信心、希望，以及其他的德行，也必得不到你的喜悦。

最神圣的恩典啊，它使心灵贫穷的人在道德上富足，使物质上富足的人心中谦卑。求你降临我心，让你的安慰充满我心，否则，我的灵魂将因内心的疲乏而枯萎。我恳求你，主啊，使我在你面前得此恩典，因为你的恩典足够我享用，纵使我得不到本性所渴望的事物，只要你的恩典与我同在，无论承受多少诱惑困苦，我都将无所畏惧。

你的恩典便是我的力量，我的导师，我的帮助。它比一切仇敌更强大，比一切智者更聪慧。你的恩典是真理的教师，教规的导师，内心的曙光，痛苦的安慰，它能驱除忧愁，赶走惧怕，培育忠心，驱使忏悔。如果没有恩典，我只是枯干的枝子，不结果子的树，只配为人所毁灭。所以，主啊，愿你的恩典常常指引我，跟随我，使我不断地献身善事，奉你的儿子耶稣基督之名。

阿门。

……

第五十七章　凡事不必沮丧

基督：我儿，在患难时的忍耐和谦卑，比在顺境中的快慰和热心，更能让我喜悦。你为什么因为微小的困难就这样忧愁呢？即使比这更大的灾祸，你也应该不为所动。随它去吧。它并非你初次的错误，也不是新奇的事。你若活得长久，它也不会是最后一次。在没有遭遇苦难时，你是勇敢无畏的。你能够劝勉他人，但是当患难忽然临到你的门口时，你自己的智慧和力量，却不见踪影。所以你要注意你自己的弱点，这弱点你常常可以从小事上体会到。然而，这些锻炼会令你受益匪浅。

让挫败感尽可能远离你的心，一旦遇到困扰，不要因它长时间地沮丧失望，驻足不前。你若不能欣然领受，至少也要勇敢担当。即使你被迫忍受，愤愤不平，也要克制自己，切勿让怒言出口，伤害基督的孩子们。你的愤怒很快就将平息，你内心的愁苦亦将因神恩重返而化为甘甜。主说：“我是活着的，随时准备帮助你，赐予你比之前更大的安慰，只要你信赖我，热心地向我祈求。”

你要心存善念，坚定决心经受更大的考验。虽然你觉得常常受苦受试探，但是这一切对你并非损失。你是人，不是上帝；你是人类，不是天使。你怎能期望永远保持德行不受诱惑呢？这对于曾经堕落的天使和乐园中的始祖都不可能。我是上帝，我将赐予绝望的人们救治与安慰，赐予承认自身弱点的人们神圣与荣耀。

门徒：主啊，你的话应受赞美，它比蜂蜜和蜂房更甘甜纯美。若非你用你的话支持我，我将怎样度过这受难忧苦的日子呢？只要我最终得到天堂的救赎，这般痛苦又算得了什么呢？求你赐我善终，赐予我脱离尘世的极乐之路。我的上帝啊，不要忘记我，指引我走向天国的正路。阿门。

[1]《新约·约翰福音》第8章第12节。——译者注

[2]据《圣经》记载，耶稣生活在2000年以前的犹太国，由童贞女马利亚所生，后来被罗马人钉死在十字架上，三天后从死里复活。有关耶稣的生平和传说对西方文化的发展产生了很大影响。圣诞节是庆祝耶稣诞生的节日，复活节是纪念耶稣死而复生的节日。——译者注

[3]《旧约·传道书》第1章第2节。——译者注

[4]《旧约·传道书》第1章第8节。——译者注

[5]《旧约·传道书》第115章第5节。——译者注

[6]受造之物，基督教教义用语。指上帝以外的任何其他事物。基督教认为这些皆非自生自有，而系创世主所造，故皆为“受造之物”。

[7]《新约·哥林多前书》第10章第13节。——译者注

[8]《新约·路加福音》第17章第21节。——译者注

[9]《新约·约翰福音》第14章第23节。——译者注

[10]《旧约·以赛亚书》第57章第21节。——译者注

[11]《新约·哥林多后书》第10章第18节。——译者注

[12]《彼得前书》第1章第24节。

[13]《新约·马太福音》第16章第24节。——译者注

[14]《新约·马太福音》第25章第41节。——译者注

[15]引文来自《圣经·新约·罗马书》第8章第18节。

[16]《新约·使徒行传》第9章第16节。——译者注

[17]《新约·路加福音》第9章第23节。——译者注

[18]《新约·使徒行传》第14章第22节。——译者注

[19]《旧约·出埃及记》第20章第19节。——译者注

[20]圣经记载，撒母耳（Samuel）是以色列最后的一位士师，也是以色列民立国后的第一位先知。他不但是一个先知，也是祭司；更是一位伟大的军事家、政治家、宗教家。是圣经中极少的没有记载任何罪行的人之一。

[21]《新约·以赛亚书》第23章第4节。——译者注

[22]《旧约·诗篇》第37章第4节。——译者注

[23]《新约·约翰福音》第14章第27节。——译者注

[24]《新约·马太福音》第6章第34节。——译者注

[25]《新约·约翰福音》第15章第9节。——译者注

[26]《旧约·诗篇》第55章第6节。——译者注

[27]参见《新约·约翰福音》第11章。——译者注

[28]圣保罗，基督教圣徒，是神所拣选的外邦人的使徒，也被历史学家公认是对于早期教会发展贡献最大的使徒。他一生中至少进行了三次漫长的宣教之旅，足迹遍至小亚细亚、希腊、意大利各地，在外邦人中建立了许多教会，影响深远。

[29]摩西是公元前13世纪时犹太人的民族领袖。史学界认为他是犹太教（Judaism）的创始者。在犹太教、基督教、伊斯兰教和巴哈伊信仰等宗教里都被认为是极为重要的先知。

[30]会幕指“上帝居住其中”的规定的神圣建筑。在《出埃及记》中，耶和华指示摩西：“他们当为我造圣所，使我可以住在他们中间。制造帐幕和其中的一切器具，都要照我所指示你的样式。”

[31]参见《旧约·约书亚记》第9章。——译者注

[32]《新约·马太福音》第26章第41节。——译者注

[33]《旧约·诗篇》第8章第4节。——译者注

[34]《新约·罗马书》第8章第18节。——译者注

BOOK ONE
Counsels on the Spiritual Life

CHAPTER 1
On the Imitation of Christ

'He who follows Me shall not walk in darkness,' says Our Lord.

In these words Christ counsels us to follow His life and way if we desire true enlightenment and freedom from all blindness of heart. Let the life of Jesus Christ, then, be our first consideration.

The teaching of Jesus far transcends all the teachings of the Saints, and whosoever has His spirit will discover concealed in it heavenly manna. But many people, although they often hear the Gospel, feel little desire to follow it, because they lack the spirit of Christ. Whoever desires to understand and take delight in the words of Christ must strive to conform his whole life to Him.

Of what use is it to discourse learnedly on the Trinity, if you lack humility and therefore displease the Trinity? Lofty words do not make a man just or holy; but a good life makes him dear to God. I would far rather feel contrition than be able to define it. If you knew the whole Bible by heart, and all the teachings of the philosophers, how would this help you without the grace and love of God? 'Vanity of vanities, and all is vanity,' except to love God and serve Him alone. And this is supreme wisdom - to despise the world, and draw daily nearer the kingdom of heaven.

It is vanity to solicit honours, or to raise oneself to high station. It is vanity to be a slave to bodily desires, and to crave for things which bring certain retribution. It is vanity to wish for long life, if you care little for a good life. It is vanity to give thought only to this present life, and to care nothing for the life to come. It is vanity to love things that so swiftly pass away, and not to hasten onwards to that place where everlasting joy abides.

Keep constantly in mind the saying, 'The eye is not satisfied with seeing, nor the ear filled with hearing.' Strive to withdraw your heart from the love of visible things, and direct your affections to things invisible. For those who follow only their natural inclinations defile their conscience, and lose the grace of God.

CHAPTER 2
On Personal Humility

Everyone naturally desires knowledge, but of what use is knowledge itself without the fear of God? A humble countryman who serves God is more pleasing to Him than a conceited intellectual who knows the course of the stars, but neglects his own soul. A man who truly knows himself realizes his own worthlessness, and takes no pleasure in the praises of men. Did I possess all knowledge in the world, but had no love, how would this help me before God, who will judge me by my deeds?

Restrain an inordinate desire for knowledge, in which is found much anxiety and deception. Learned men always wish to appear so, and desire recognition of their wisdom. But there are many matters, knowledge of which brings little or no advantage to the soul. Indeed, a man is unwise if he occupies himself with any things save those that further his salvation. A spate of words does nothing to satisfy the soul, but a good life refreshes the mind, and a clean conscience brings great confidence in God.

The more complete and excellent your knowledge, the more severe will be God's judgement on you, unless your life be the more holy. Therefore, do not be conceited of any skill or knowledge you may possess, but respect the knowledge that is entrusted to you. If it seems to you that you know a great deal and have wide experience in many fields, yet remember that there are many matters of which you are ignorant. So do not be conceited, but confess your ignorance. Why do you wish to esteem yourself above others, when there are many who are wiser and more perfect in the Law of God? If you desire to know or learn anything to your advantage, then take delight in being unknown and unregarded.

A true understanding and humble estimate of oneself is the highest and most valuable of all lessons. To take no account of oneself, but always to think well and highly of others is the highest wisdom and perfection. Should you see another person openly doing evil, or carrying out a wicked purpose, do not on that account consider yourself better than him, for you cannot tell how long you will remain in a state of grace. We are all frail; consider none more frail than yourself.

CHAPTER 3
On the Teaching of Truth

Happy the man who is instructed by Truth itself, not by signs and passing words, but as It is in itself. Our own conjectures and observations often mislead us, and we discover little. Of what value are lengthy controversies on deep and obscure matters, when it is not by our knowledge of such things that we shall at length be judged? It is supreme folly to neglect things that are useful and vital, and deliberately turn to curious and harmful things. Truly, 'we have eyes and see not': for what concern to us are such things as genera and species?

Those to whom the Eternal Word speaks are delivered from uncertainty. From one Word proceed all things, and all things tell of Him; it is He, the Author of all things, who speaks to us. Without Him no one can understand or judge aright. But the man to whom all things are one, who refers everything to One, and who sees everything as in One, is enabled to remain steadfast in heart, and abide at peace with God.

O God, living Truth, unite me to Yourself in everlasting love! Often I am wearied by all I read and hear. In You alone is all that I desire and long for. Therefore let all teachers keep silence, and let all creation be still before you; do You, Lord, speak alone.

The more closely a man is united to You in pure simplicity, the more varied and profound the matters which he understands without effort, for he receives light and understanding from heaven. A pure, simple, and stable man, however busy and occupied, does not become distracted thereby, for he does all things to the glory of God, and strives to preserve himself free from all self-seeking. And what harms and hinders you more than the undisciplined passions of your own heart? A good and devout man firstly sets in order in his mind whatever tasks he has in hand, and never allows them to lead him into occasions of sin, but humbly subjects them to the dictates of a sound judgement. Who has a fiercer struggle than he who strives to conquer himself? Yet this must be our chief concern - to conquer self, and by daily growing stronger than self, to advance in holiness.

All perfection in this life is accompanied by a measure of imperfection, and all our knowledge contains an element of obscurity. A humble knowledge of oneself is a surer road to God than a deep searching of the sciences. Yet learning itself is not to be blamed, nor is the simple knowledge of anything whatsoever to be despised, for true learning is good in itself and ordained by God; but a good conscience and a holy life are always to be preferred. But because many are more eager to acquire much learning than to live well, they often go astray and bear little or no fruit. If only such people were as diligent in the uprooting of vices and the planting of virtues as they are in the debating of problems, there would not be so many evils and scandals among the people, nor such laxity in communities. At the Day of Judgement, we shall not be asked what we have read, but what we have done; not how eloquently we have spoken, but how holily we have lived. Tell me, where are now all those Masters and Doctors whom you knew so well in their lifetime in the full flower of their learning? Other men now sit in their seats, and they are hardly ever called to mind. In their lifetime they seemed of great account, but now no one speaks of them.

Oh, how swiftly the glory of the world passes away! If only the lives of these men had been as admirable as their learning, their study and reading would have been to good purpose! But how many in this world care little for the service of God, and perish in their vain learning. Because they choose to be great rather than humble, they perish in their own conceit. He is truly great, who is great in the love of God. He is truly great, who is humble in mind, and regards earths highest honours as nothing. He is truly wise who counts all earthly things as dung, in order that he may win Christ. And he is truly learned, who renounces his own will for the will of God.

CHAPTER 4
On Prudence in Action

We should not believe every word and suggestion, but should carefully and unhurriedly consider all things in accordance with the will of God. For such is the weakness of human nature, alas, that evil is often more readily believed and spoken of another than good. But perfect men do not easily believe every tale that is told them, for they know that man's nature is prone to evil, and his words to deception.

It is wise not to be over hasty in action, nor to cling stubbornly to our own opinions. It is wise also not to believe all that we hear, nor to hasten to report to others what we hear or believe. Take counsel of a wise and conscientious man, and seek to be guided by one who is better than yourself, rather than to follow your own opinions. A good life makes a man wise towards God, and gives him experience in many things. The more humble and obedient to God a man is, the more wise and at peace he will be in all that he does.

CHAPTER 5
On Reading the Holy Scriptures

In the holy Scriptures, truth is to be looked for rather than fair phrases. All sacred scriptures should be read in the spirit in which they were written. In them, therefore, we should seek food for our souls rather than subtleties of speech, and we should as readily read simple and devout books as those that are lofty and profound. Do not be influenced by the importance of the writer, and whether his learning be great or small, but let the love of pure truth draw you to read. Do not inquire, 'Who said this?' but pay attention to what is said.

Men pass away, but the word of the Lord endures for ever.

God speaks to us in different ways, and is no respecter of persons. But curiosity often hinders us in the reading of the Scriptures, for we try to examine and dispute over matters that we should pass over and accept in simplicity. If you desire to profit, read with humility, simplicity, and faith, and have no concern to appear learned. Ask questions freely, and listen in silence to the words of the Saints; hear with patience the parables of the fathers, for they are not told without good cause.

CHAPTER 6
On Control of the Desires

Whenever a man desires anything inordinately, at once he becomes restless. A proud and avaricious man is never at rest; but a poor and humble man enjoys the riches of peace. A man who is not yet perfectly dead to self is easily tempted, and is overcome even in small and trifling things. And he who is weak in spirit, and still a prey to the senses and bodily passions, can only with great difficulty free himself from worldly lusts. Therefore he is sad when he does so withdraw himself, and is quickly angered when anyone opposes him. Yet, if he obtains what he desires, his conscience is at once stricken by remorse, because he has yielded to his passion, which in no way helps him in his search for peace. True peace of heart can be found only by resisting the passions, not by yielding to them. There is no peace in the heart of a worldly man, who is entirely given to outward affairs; but only in a fervent, spiritual man.

CHAPTER 7
On Avoiding Vain Hope and Conceit

Whoever puts his confidence in men or in any creature is very foolish. Do not be ashamed to be the servant of others for love of Jesus Christ, and to appear poor in this world. Do not trust in yourself, but put your whole confidence in God. Do what you are able, and God will bless your good intention. Do not trust in your own knowledge, nor in the cleverness of any man living, but rather in the grace of God, who aids the humble, and humbles the proud.

Do not boast of your possessions, if you have any, nor of the influence of your friends; but glory in God, who gives all things and desires above all things to give you Himself. Do not be vain about your beauty or strength of body, which a little sickness can mar and disfigure. Take no pleasure in your own ability and cleverness, lest you offend God, who has Himself bestowed on you all your natural gifts.

Do not esteem yourself better than others, lest you appear worse in the eyes of God, who alone knows the heart of man. Do not be proud of your good deeds, for God does not judge as men; and what delights men often displeases God. If you have any good qualities, remember that others have more; and so remain humble. It does you no harm when you esteem all others better than yourself, but it does you great harm when you esteem yourself above others. True peace dwells only in the heart of the humble: but the heart of the proud is ever full of pride and jealousy.

[…]

CHAPTER 10
On Avoiding Talkativeness

Avoid public gatherings as much as possible, for the discussion of worldly affairs becomes a great hindrance, even though it be with the best of intentions, for we are quickly corrupted and ensnared by vanity. Often I wish I had remained silent, and had not been among men. But why is it that we are so ready to chatter and gossip with each other, when we so seldom return to silence without some injury to our conscience? The reason why we are so fond of talking with each other is that we think to find consolation in this manner, and to refresh a heart wearied with many cares. And we prefer to speak and think of those things which we like and desire, or of those which we dislike. Alas, however, all this is often to no purpose, for this outward consolation is no small obstacle to inner and divine consolation.

We must watch and pray, that our time may not be spent fruitlessly. When it is right and proper to speak, speak to edify. Evil habits and neglect of spiritual progress are the main cause of our failure to guard the tongue. But devout conversation on spiritual matters greatly furthers our spiritual progress, especially with those who are heart and soul with us in the service of God.

CHAPTER 11
On Peace, and Spiritual Progress

We could enjoy much peace if we did not busy ourselves with what other people say and do, for this is no concern of ours. How can anyone remain long at peace who meddles in other people's affairs; who seeks occasion to gad about, and who makes little or no attempt at recollection? Blessed are the single-hearted, for they shall enjoy much peace.

How were some of the Saints so perfect and contemplative? It is because they strove with all their might to mortify in themselves all worldly desires, and could thus cling to God in their inmost heart, and offer themselves freely and wholly to Him. But we are held too firmly by our passions, and are too much concerned with the passing affairs of the world. We seldom completely master a single fault, and have little zeal for our daffy progress; therefore we remain spiritually cold or tepid.

If only we were completely dead to self, and free from inner conflict, we could savour spiritual things, and win experience of heavenly contemplation. But the greatest, and indeed the whole obstacle to our advance is that we are not free from passions and lusts, nor do we strive to follow the perfect way of the Saints. But when we encounter even a little trouble, we are quickly discouraged, and turn to human comfort.

If we strove to stand firm in the struggle like men of valour, we should not fail to experience the help of our Lord from heaven. For He is ever ready to help all who fight, trusting in His grace; He also affords us occasions to fight that we may conquer. If we rely only on the outward observances of religion, our devotion will rapidly wane. But let us lay the axe to the root, that, being cleansed from our passions, we may possess our souls in peace.

If each year we would root out one fault, we should soon become perfect. But, alas, the opposite is often the case, that we were better and purer in the beginning of our conversion than after many years of our profession. Our zeal and virtue should grow daily; but it is now held to be a fine thing if a man retains even a little of his first fervour. If only we would do a little violence to ourselves at first, we would later be enabled to do everything easily and gladly.

It is hard to give up old habits, and harder still to conquer our own wills. But if you cannot overcome in small and easy things, how will you succeed in greater? Resist your evil inclinations in the beginning, and break off evil habits, lest they gradually involve you in greater difficulties. Oh, if you could only know how great a peace for yourself and how great a joy for your fellows your good endeavour would win, you would have greater care for your spiritual progress.

CHAPTER 12
On the Uses of Adversity

It is good for us to encounter troubles and adversities from time to time, for trouble often compels a man to search his own heart. It reminds him that he is an exile here, and that he can put his trust in nothing in this world. It is good, too, that we sometimes suffer opposition, and that men think ill of us and misjudge us, even when we do and mean well. Such things are an aid to humility, and preserve us from pride and vainglory. For we more readily turn to God as our inward witness, when men despise us and think no good of us.

A man should therefore place such complete trust in God, that he has no need of comfort from men. When a good man is troubled, tempted, or vexed by evil thoughts, he comes more clearly than ever to realize his need of God, without whom he can do nothing good. Then, as he grieves and laments his lot, he turns to prayer amid his misfortunes. He is weary of life, and longs for death to release him, that he may be dissolved, and be with Christ. It is then that he knows with certainty that there can be no complete security nor perfect peace in his life.

CHAPTER 13
On Resisting Temptations

So long as we live in this world, we cannot remain without trial and temptation: as Job says, 'Man's life on earth is a warfare.' We must therefore be on guard against temptations, and watchful in prayer, that the Devil find no means of deceiving us; for he never rests, but prowls around seeking whom he may devour. No one is so perfect and holy that he is never tempted, and we can never be secure from temptation.

Although temptations are so troublesome and grievous, yet they are often profitable to us, for by them we are humbled, cleansed, and instructed. All the Saints endured many trials and temptations, and profited by them; but those who could not resist temptations became reprobate, and fell away. There is no Order so holy, nor place so secluded, where there are no troubles and temptations.

No man can be entirely free from temptation so long as he lives; for the source of temptation lies within our own nature, since we are born with an inclination towards evil. When one temptation or trial draws to a close, another takes its place; and we shall always have something to fight, for man has lost the blessing of original happiness. Many try to escape temptations, only to encounter them more fiercely, for no one can win victory by flight alone; it is only by patience and true humility that we can grow stronger than all our foes.

The man who only avoids the outward occasions of evil, but fails to uproot it in himself, will gain little advantage. Indeed, temptations will return upon him the sooner, and he will find himself in a worse state than before. Little by little and by patient endurance you will overcome them by God's help, better than by your own violence and importunity. Seek regular advice in temptation, and never deal harshly with those who are tempted, but give them such encouragement as you would value yourself.

The beginning of all evil temptation is an unstable mind and lack of trust in God. Just as a ship without a helm is driven to and fro by the waves, so a careless man, who abandons his proper course, is tempted in countless ways. Fire tempers steel, and temptation the just man. We often do not know what we can bear, but temptation reveals our true nature. We need especially to be on our guard at the very onset of temptation, for then the Enemy may be more easily overcome, if he is not allowed to enter the gates of the mind: he must be repulsed at the threshold, as soon as he knocks. Thus the poet Ovid writes, 'Resist at the beginning; the remedy may come too late.' For first there comes into the mind an evil thought: next, a vivid picture: then delight, and urge to evil, and finally consent. In this way the Enemy gradually gains complete mastery, when he is not resisted at first. And the longer a slothful man delays resistance, the weaker he becomes, and the stronger his enemy grows against him.

Some people undergo their heaviest temptations at the beginning of their conversion; some towards the end of their course; others are greatly troubled all their lives; while there are some whose temptations are but light. This is in accordance with the wisdom and justice of God's ordinance, who weighs the condition and merits of every man, and disposes all things for the salvation of those whom He chooses.

We must not despair, therefore, when we are tempted, but earnestly pray God to grant us his help in every need. For, as Saint Paul says, 'With the temptation, God will provide a way to overcome it, that we may be able to bear it.' So, let us humble ourselves under the hand of God in every trial and trouble, for He will save and raise up the humble in spirit. In all these trials, our progress is tested; in them great merit may be secured, and our virtue become evident. It is no great matter if we are devout and fervent when we have no troubles; but if we show patience in adversity, we can make great progress in virtue. Some are spared severe temptations, but are overcome in the lesser ones of every day, in order that they may be humble, and learn not to trust in themselves, but to recognize their frailty.

CHAPTER 14
On Avoiding Rash Judgements

Judge yourself, and beware of passing judgement on others. In judging others, we expend our energy to no purpose; we are often mistaken, and easily sin. But if we judge ourselves, our labour is always to our profit. Our judgement is frequently influenced by our personal feelings, and it is very easy to fail in right judgement when we are inspired by private motives. Were God Himself the sole and constant object of our desire, we should not be so easily distressed when our opinions are contra dicted.

Very often some inner impulse or outward circum stance draws us to follow it, while many people are always acting in their own interest, although they are not conscious of it. Such appear to enjoy complete tranquillity of mind so long as events accord with their wishes, but at once become distressed and disconsolate when things fall out otherwise. Similarly, differences of opinions and beliefs only too often give rise to quarrels among friends and neighbours, and even between religious and devout people.

Old habits are hard to break, and no one is easily weaned from his own opinions; but if you rely on your own reasoning and ability rather than on the virtue of submission to Jesus Christ, you will but seldom and slowly attain wisdom. For God wills that we become perfectly obedient to Himself, and that we transcend mere reason on the wings of a burning love for Him.

CHAPTER 15
On Deeds Inspired by Love

No motive, even that of affection for anyone, can justify the doing of evil. But to help someone in need, a good work may sometimes be left, or a better undertaken in its place. For in so doing, the good work is not lost, but changed for what is better. Without love, the outward work is of no value; but whatever is done out of love, be it never so little, is wholly fruitful. For God regards the greatness of the love that prompts a man, rather than the greatness of his achievement.

Whoever loves much, does much. Whoever does a thing well, does much. And he does well, who serves the community before his own interests. Often an apparently loving action really springs from worldly motives; for natural inclination, self-will, hope of reward, and our own self-interest will seldom be entirely absent.

Whoever is moved by true and perfect love is never self-seeking, but desires only that God's glory may be served in all things. He envies none, for he seeks no pleasure for himself, nor does he act for self-gratification, but desires above all good things to merit the blessing of God. All good he ascribes not to men, but to God, from whom all things proceed as from their source, and in whom all the Saints enjoy perfection and peace. Oh, if only a man had a spark of true love in his heart, he would know for certain that all earthly things are full of vanity.

CHAPTER 16
On Bearing with the Faults of Others

Whatever a man is unable to correct in himself or in others, he should bear patiently until God ordains otherwise. Consider, it is perhaps better thus, for the testing of our patience, without which our merits are of little worth. Whenever such obstacles confront you, pray to God that He may grant you His help, and give you grace to endure them in good heart.

If anyone who has been once or twice warned remains obdurate, do not argue with him, but commit all things to God, that His will may be done, and His Name hallowed in all His servants; for He knows well how to bring good out of evil. Strive to be patient; bear with the faults and frailties of others, for you, too, have many faults which others have to bear. If you cannot mould yourself as you would wish, how can you expect other people to be entirely to your liking? For we require other people to be perfect, but do not correct our own faults.

We wish to see others severely reprimanded; yet we are unwilling to be corrected ourselves. We wish to restrict the liberty of others, but are not willing to be denied anything ourselves. We wish others to be bound by rules, yet we will not let ourselves be bound. It is amply evident, therefore, that we seldom consider our neighbour in the same light as ourselves. Yet, if all men were perfect, what should we have to bear with in others for Christ's sake?

Now, God has thus ordered things that we may learn to bear one another's burdens; for there is no man without his faults, none without his burden. None is sufficient in himself; none is wise in himself; therefore we must support one another, comfort, help, teach, and advise one another. Times of trouble best discover the true worth of a man; they do not weaken him, but show his true nature.

[…]

CHAPTER 23
A Meditation on Death

Very soon the end of your life will be at hand: consider, therefore, the state of your soul. Today a man is here; tomorrow he is gone. And when he is out of sight, he is soon out of mind. Oh, how dull and hard is the heart of man, which thinks only of the present, and does not provide against the future! You should order your every deed and thought, as though today were the day of your death. Had you a good conscience, death would hold no terrors for you; even so, it were better to avoid sin than to escape death. If you are not ready to die today, will tomorrow find you better prepared? Tomorrow is uncertain; and how can you be sure of tomorrow?

Of what use is a long life, if we amend so little? Alas, a long life often adds to our sins rather than to our virtue!

Would to God that we might spend a single day really well! Many recount the years since their conversion, but their lives show little sign of improvement. If it is dreadful to die, it is perhaps more dangerous to live long. Blessed is the man who keeps the hour of his death always in mind, and daily prepares himself to die. If you have ever seen anyone die, remember that you, too, must travel the same road.

Each morning remember that you may not live until evening; and in the evening, do not presume to promise yourself another day. Be ready at all times, and so live that death may never find you unprepared. Many die suddenly and unexpectedly; for at an hour that we do not know the Son of Man will come. When your last hour strikes, you will begin to think very differently of your past life, and grieve deeply that you have been so careless and remiss.

Happy and wise is he who endeavours to be during his life as he wishes to be found at his death. For these things will afford us sure hope of a happy death; perfect contempt of the world; fervent desire to grow in holiness; love of discipline; the practice of penance; ready obedience; self-denial; the bearing of every trial for the love of Christ. While you enjoy health, you can do much good; but when sickness comes, little can be done. Few are made better by sickness, and those who make frequent pilgrimages seldom acquire holiness by so doing.

Do not rely on friends and neighbours, and do not delay the salvation of your soul to some future date, for men will forget you sooner than you think. It is better to make timely provision and to acquire merit in this life, than to depend on the help of others. And if you have no care for your own soul, who will have care for you in time to come? The present time is most precious; now is the accepted time, now is the day of salvation. It is sad that you do not employ your time better, when you may win eternal life hereafter. The time will come when you will long for one day or one hour in which to amend; and who knows whether it will be granted?

Dear soul, from what peril and fear you could free yourself, if you lived in holy fear, mindful of your death. Apply yourself so to live now, that at the hour of death, you may be glad and unafraid. Learn now to die to the world, that you may begin to live with Christ. Learn now to despise all earthly things, that you may go freely to Christ. Discipline your body now by penance, that you may enjoy a sure hope of salvation.

Foolish man, how can you promise yourself a long life, when you are not certain of a single day? How many have deceived themselves in this way, and been snatched unexpectedly from life! You have often heard how this man was slain by the sword; another drowned; how another fell from a high place and broke his neck; how another died at table; how another met his end in play. One perishes by fire, another by the sword, another from disease, another at the hands of robbers. Death is the end of all men; and the life of man passes away suddenly as a shadow.

Who will remember you when you are dead? Who will pray for you? Act now, dear soul; do all you can; for you know neither the hour of your death, nor your state after death. While you have time, gather the riches of everlasting life. Think only of your salvation, and care only for the things of God. Make friends now, by honouring the Saints of God and by following their example, that when this life is over, they may welcome you to your eternal home.

Keep yourself a stranger and pilgrim upon earth, to whom the affairs of this world are of no concern. Keep your heart free and lifted up to God, for here you have no abiding city. Daily direct your prayers and longings to Heaven, that at your death your soul may merit to pass joyfully into the presence of God.

[…]

BOOK TWO
Counsels on the Inner Life

CHAPTER 1
On the Inner Life

'The Kingdom of God is within you,' says Our Lord. Turn to the Lord with all your heart, forsake this sorry world, and your soul shall find rest. Learn to turn from worldly things, and give yourself to spiritual things, and you will see the Kingdom of God come within you. For the Kingdom is peace and joy in the Holy Spirit; these are not granted to the wicked. Christ will come to you, and impart his consolations to you, if you prepare a worthy dwelling for Him in your heart. All true glory and beauty is within, and there He delights to dwell. He often visits the spiritual man, and holds sweet discourse with him, granting him refreshing grace, great peace, and friendship exceeding all expectation.

Come then, faithful soul; prepare your heart for your Divine Spouse, that He may deign to come to you and dwell with you. For He says, 'If any man love Me, he will keep My word; and We will come and make our abode with him.' Therefore welcome Christ, and deny entrance to all others. When you possess Christ, you are amply rich, and He will satisfy you. He will dispose and provide for you faithfully in everything, so that you need not rely on man. For men soon change and fail you; but Christ abides for ever, and stands firmly by you to the end.

Never place your whole trust and reliance in weak and mortal man, however helpful and dear to you he may be; nor should you grieve overmuch if sometimes he opposes and contradicts you. Those who take your part today may tomorrow oppose you; for men are as changeable as the weather. Put your whole trust in God; direct your worship and love to Him alone. He will defend you, and will dispose all things for the best. Here you have no abiding city, and wherever you may be, you are a stranger and pilgrim; you will never enjoy peace until you become inwardly united to Christ.

What do you seek here, since this world is not your resting place? Your true home is in Heaven; therefore remember that all the things of this world are transitory. All things are passing, and yourself with them. See that you do not cling to them, lest you become entangled and perish with them. Let all your thoughts be with the Most High, and direct your humble prayers unceasingly to Christ. If you cannot contemplate high and heavenly things, take refuge in the Passion of Christ, and love to dwell within His Sacred Wounds. For if you devoutly seek the Wounds of Jesus and the precious marks of His Passion, you will find great strength in all troubles. And if men despise you, you will care little, having small regard for the words of your detractors.

Christ Himself was despised by men, and in His direst need was abandoned by his friends and acquaintances to the insults of His enemies. Christ was willing to suffer and to be despised; and do you presume to complain? Christ had enemies and slanderers; and do you expect all men to be your friends and benefactors? How will your patience be crowned, if you are not willing to endure hardship? Suffer with Christ, and for Christ, if you wish to reign with Christ.

Had you but once entered perfectly into the Heart of Jesus, and tasted something of His burning love, you would care nothing for your own gain or loss; for the love of Jesus causes a man to regard himself very humbly. The true, inward lover of Jesus and the Truth, who is free from inordinate desires, can turn freely to God, rise above self, and joyfully rest in God.

He who knows all things at their true worth, and not as they are said or reputed to be, is truly wise, for his knowledge comes from God, and not from man. He who walks by an inner light, and is not unduly influenced by outward things, needs no special time or place for his prayers. For the man of inner life easily recollects himself, since he is never wholly immersed in outward affairs. Therefore his outward occupations and needful tasks do not distract him, and he adjusts himself to things as they come. The man whose inner life is well-ordered and disposed is not troubled by the strange and perverse ways of others; for a man is hindered and distracted by such things only so far as he allows himself to be concerned by them.

If your inner life were rightly ordered and your heart pure, all things would turn to your good and advantage. As it is, you are often displeased and disturbed, because you are not yet completely dead to self, nor detached from all worldly things. Nothing defiles and ensnares the heart of man more than a selfish love of creatures. If you renounce all outward consolation, you will be able to contemplate heavenly things, and often experience great joy of heart.

CHAPTER 2
On Humble Submission to God

Do not be concerned overmuch who is with you or against you, but work and plan that God may be with you in all that you do. Keep a clean conscience, and God will mightily defend you; for whoever enjoys the protection of God cannot be harmed by the malice of man. If you learn to suffer in silence, you may be sure of receiving God's help. He knows the time and the way to deliver you; so trust yourself entirely to His care. God is strong to help you, and to free you from all confusion. It is often good for us that others know and expose our faults, for so may we be kept humble.

When a man humbly admits his faults, he soon appeases his fellows, and is reconciled to those whom he had offended. God protects and delivers a humble man; He loves and comforts him. To the humble He leans down and bestows great success, raising him from abasement to honour. To him He reveals His secrets, and lovingly calls and draws him to Himself. Even in the midst of trouble, the humble man remains wholly at peace, for he trusts in God, and not in the world. Do not consider yourself to have made any spiritual progress, unless you account yourself the least of all men.

CHAPTER 3
On the Good and Peaceful Man

Firstly, be peaceful yourself, and you will be able to bring peace to others. A man of peace does more good than a very learned man. A passionate man turns even good into evil, and readily listens to evil; but a good and peaceable man turns all things to good. He who is truly at peace thinks evil of no one; but he who is discontented and restless is tormented by suspicions beyond number. He has no peace in himself, nor will he allow others any peace. He often says what he ought not to say, and leaves undone what he should have done. He takes note how other people carry out their duties, but neglects his own. Therefore, before all else, attend diligently to your own affairs; then you may properly be concerned for your neighbour also.

You readily excuse and explain your own doings, but you will not accept the explanations of others. It would be more just to accuse yourself, and to excuse your fellows. If you wish others to bear with you, you must bear with them. See how far you still are from true charity and humility, which feels no anger nor indignation towards any save itself. It is no great matter to associate with the good and gentle, for this is naturally pleasant to everyone. All men are glad to live at peace, and prefer those who are of their own way of thinking. But to be able to live at peace among hard, obstinate, and undisciplined people and those who oppose us, is a great grace, and a most commendable and manly achievement.

There are some who remain at peace with themselves and also with others. And some neither have peace in themselves nor allow others to have peace. Such people are a trouble to others, and an even greater trouble to themselves. And there are some who are at peace with themselves, and who try to guide others into peace. But all our peace in this present life should depend on humble forbearance rather than on absence of adversity. He who knows the secret of endurance will enjoy the greatest peace. Such a one is conqueror of self, master of the world, a friend of Christ, and an heir of Heaven.

CHAPTER 4
On Purity of Mind and Simplicity of Purpose

There are two wings that raise a man above earthly things - simplicity and purity. Simplicity must inspire his purpose, and purity his affection. Simplicity reaches out after God; purity discovers and enjoys Him. No good deed will prove an obstacle to you if you are inwardly free from uncontrolled desires. And if you are free from uncontrolled desires, and seek nothing but the Will of God and the good of your neighbour, you will enjoy this inner freedom. If your heart be right, then every created thing will become for you a mirror of life and a book of holy teaching. For there is nothing created so small and mean that it does not reflect the goodness of God.

Were you inwardly good and pure, you would see and understand all things clearly and without difficulty. A pure heart penetrates both heaven and hell. As each man is in himself, so does he judge outward things. If there is any joy to be had in this world, the pure in heart most surely possess it; and if there is trouble and distress anywhere, the evil conscience most readily experiences it. Just as iron, when plunged into fire, loses its rust and becomes bright and glowing, so the man who turns himself wholly to God loses his sloth and becomes transformed into a new creature.

When a man begins to grow dull and lukewarm in spirit, even the smallest labour distresses him, and he eagerly welcomes any worldly comfort. But when he begins to overcome self and advance manfully in Gods way, then he regards as nothing those labours which he previously found so burdensome.

CHAPTER 5
On Knowing Ourselves

We may not trust overmuch in ourselves, for we often lack grace and understanding. There is little light in us, and even this we easily lose through carelessness. Moreover, we often do not realize how blind we are. We often do evil, and we do worse in excusing ourselves. Sometimes we are moved by passion, and mistake it for Zeal. We rebuke small faults in others, but overlook greater faults in ourselves. We are too quick to resent and feel what we suffer from others, but fail to consider how much others suffer from us. Whoever considers his own defects fully and honestly will find no reason to judge others harshly.

The spiritual man puts the care of his soul before all else; and whoever diligently attends to his own affairs is ready to keep silence about others. You will never become interior and devout unless you refrain from criticism of others, and pay attention to yourself. If you are wholly intent on God and yourself, you will be little affected by anything outside this. Where are you when you fail to attend to yourself? And when you have occupied yourself in countless affairs, what have you gained, if you have neglected your soul? If you really desire true peace and union with God, attend to yourself, and set aside all else.

Keep yourself free from all worldly entanglement, and you will make good progress; but if you set great value on any worldly things, it will prove a great obstacle. Let nothing be great, pleasant or desirable to you save God alone, and whatever comes of God. Regard as empty comfort all things that derive from creatures. The soul that loves God regards as worthless all things other than God. God alone is eternal and immeasurable, filling all things; He alone is the true comfort of the soul and joy of the heart.

CHAPTER 6
On the Joys of a Good Conscience

The glory of a good man is the witness of a good conscience. Preserve a quiet conscience, and you will always have joy. A quiet conscience can endure much, and remains joyful in all trouble, but an evil conscience is always fearful and uneasy. You may rest easy if your heart does not reproach you, and you are happy only when you have done right. The wicked never know true happiness, nor do they enjoy inward peace, for 'There is no peace for the wicked,' says the Lord. And although they say, 'We are at peace; no evil happens to us, and no one will dare to harm us,' yet God's anger will rise suddenly, all their works will be brought to nothing, and their plans perish.

To glory in suffering is not hard for one who truly loves God, for so to glory is to glory in the Cross of our Lord. Short-lived is the glory that is granted and received by men, and sorrow is ever its companion. The glory of good men is in their own conscience, not in the tongues of men. For the joy of the Saints is from God and in God, and their joy is in the truth. Whoever desires true and lasting glory cares nothing for worldly glory. And whoever craves worldly glory, or who does not at heart despise it, shows himself to have little love for the glory of heaven. Great tranquillity of heart is his who cares for neither praise nor blame.

The man who has a clean conscience rests easily content, and is at peace. You are none the holier for being praised, and none the worse for being blamed. You remain what you are, nor can you be accounted greater than you are in the sight of God. If you take heed to what you are inwardly, you will not mind what men say of you; for while man looks on outward appearance, God looks into your heart. Man sees your actions, but God your motives. The sign of a humble soul is always to be doing good, and to think little of oneself. To desire no comfort from creatures is a sign of great purity and inward faith.

When a man seeks no other witness but himself, he shows that he puts his whole trust in God. For, as Saint Paul says, 'Not he who commends himself is approved, but he whom God commends.' To live inwardly to God, and not to be bound by worldly affections, is the proper state of a spiritual man.

CHAPTER 7
On Loving Jesus above all Things

Blessed is he who understands what it is to love Jesus, and to despise himself for Jesus' sake. You must surrender all other love for His love, for Jesus desires to be loved alone, and above all things. The love of creatures is deceptive and unstable; the love of Jesus is faithful and enduring. Whoever clings to any creature will fall with its falling; but he who holds to Jesus shall stand firm for ever. Love Him, therefore, and keep Him as your friend; for when all others desert you, He will not abandon you, nor allow you to perish at the last. Whether you wish it or not, you must in the end be parted from them all.

Hold fast to Jesus, both in life and death, and trust yourself to His faithfulness, for He alone can aid you when all others fail. Your Beloved is of such a nature that He will not share your love with another; He desires your heart for Himself alone, and to reign there as a King on His throne. If you could empty your heart of all creatures, Jesus would delight to dwell with you. Whatever trust you place in men rather than in Jesus is almost wholly wasted. Do not trust or lean on a wind blown reed, for 'all flesh is as grass, and its glory will fall like the flower of the grass.'

If you look only to men's outward appearance, you will soon be deceived; for if you seek comfort or gain from others, you will often meet with loss. If you seek Jesus in all things, you will surely find Jesus. And if you seek yourself, you will surely find yourself, but only to your ruin. For a man who does not seek Jesus does himself greater hurt than the whole world and all his enemies could ever do him.

[…]

CHAPTER 12
On the Royal Road of the Holy Cross

'Deny yourself, take up your cross, and follow Me.' To many this saying of Jesus seems hard. But how much harder will it be to hear that word of doom, 'Depart from Me, you cursed, into everlasting fire'. For those who now cheerfully hear and obey the word of the Cross will not tremble to hear the sentence of eternal damnation. The sign of the Cross will appear in the heavens, when Our Lord comes as Judge. Then will all the servants of the Cross, who in their lives conformed themselves to the Crucified, stand with confidence before Christ their Judge.

Why, then, do you fear to take up the Cross, which is the road to the Kingdom? In the Cross is salvation; in the Cross is life; in the Cross is protection against our enemies; in the Cross is infusion of heavenly sweetness; in the Cross is strength of mind; in the Cross is joy of spirit; in the Cross is excellence of virtue; in the Cross is perfection of holiness. There is no salvation of soul, nor hope of eternal life, save in the Cross. Take up the Cross, therefore, and follow Jesus, and go forward into eternal life. Christ has gone before you, bearing His Cross; He died for you on the Cross, that you also may bear your cross, and desire to die on the cross with Him. For if you die with Him, you will also live with Him. And if you share His sufferings, you will also share His glory.

See how in the Cross all things consist, and in dying on it all things depend. There is no other way to life and to true inner peace, than the way of the Cross, and of daily self-denial. Go where you will, seek what you will; you will find no higher way above nor safer way below than the road of the Holy Cross. Arrange and order all things to your own ideas and wishes, yet you will still find suffering to endure, whether you will or not; so you will always find the Cross. For you will either endure bodily pain, or suffer anguish of mind and spirit.

At times, God will withdraw from you; at times you will be troubled by your neighbour, and, what is more, you will often be a burden to yourself. Neither can any remedy or comfort bring you relief, but you must bear it as long as God wills. For God desires that you learn to bear trials without comfort, that you may yield yourself wholly to Him, and grow more humble through tribulation. No man feels so deeply in his heart the Passion of Christ as he who has to suffer in like manner. The Cross always stands ready, and everywhere awaits you. You cannot escape it, wherever you flee; for wherever you go, you bear yourself, and always find yourself. Look up or down, without you or within, and everywhere you will find the Cross. And everywhere you must have patience, if you wish to attain inner peace, and win an eternal crown.

If you bear the cross willingly, it will bear you and lead you to your desired goal, where pain shall be no more; but it will not be in this life. If you bear the cross unwillingly, you make it a burden, and load yourself more heavily; but you must needs bear it. If you cast away one cross, you will certainly find another, and perhaps a heavier.

Do you think to escape what no mortal man has been able to escape? Which of the Saints lived without cross or trial? Even our Lord Jesus Christ was never without sorrow and pain, as long as He lived. 'Christ must needs suffer,' said He, 'and rise again from the dead, and so enter into His glory.' Why, then, do you seek any other road than this royal road of the Holy Cross? The whole life of Christ was a cross and martyrdom; and do you look for rest and selfish pleasure?

You are greatly mistaken if you look for anything save to endure trials, for all this mortal life is full of troubles, and everywhere marked with crosses. The further a man advances in the spiritual life, the heavier and more numerous he finds the crosses, for his ever-deepening love of God makes more bitter the sorrows of his earthly exile.

Yet a man who is afflicted in many ways is not without solace and comfort, for he perceives the great benefit to be reaped from the bearing of his cross. For while he bears it with a good will, the whole burden is changed into hope of God's comfort. And the more the body is subdued by affliction, the more is the spirit strengthened by grace within. Sometimes he is so greatly comforted by the desire to suffer adversity for love of conforming to the Cross of Christ, that he would not wish to be without grief and pain; for he knows that the more he can suffer for His sake, the more pleasing he will be to God. This desire does not spring from man's own strength, but from the grace of Christ, which can and does effect such great things in the frail frame of man; so that which nature fears and avoids, he boldly meets and loves through ardour of spirit.

Man is not by nature inclined to carry the cross, to love the cross, to chasten the body, and bring it into subjection; to refuse honours, to submit to insults with goodwill, to despise himself and welcome disparagement; to bear all adversity and loss, and to desire no kind of prosperity in this world. And if you trust in your own strength, you will be unable to achieve any of these things. But if you trust in the Lord, you will be given strength from Heaven, and the world and the flesh will become subject to your will. Neither will you fear your enemy the Devil, if you are armed with faith and signed with the Cross of Christ.

Resolve, then, as a good and faithful servant of Christ, manfully to bear the cross of your Lord, who was crucified for love of you. Prepare yourself to endure many trials and obstacles in this vale of tears; for such will be your lot wherever you are, and you will encounter them wherever you conceal yourself. It must needs be so; nor is there any remedy or means of escape from ills and griefs; you must endure them. Drink lovingly the cup of your Lord, if you wish to be His friend, and to share all with Him. Leave consolations to God, to dispose as He wills. But set yourself to endure trials, regarding them as the greatest of all comforts, 'for the sufferings of this present time are not worthy to be compared with the glory to come', even though you alone were to endure them all.

When you have arrived at that state when trouble seems sweet and acceptable to you for Christ's sake, then all is well with you, for you have found paradise upon earth. But so long as suffering is grievous to you and you seek to escape it, so long will it go ill with you, for the trouble you try to escape will pursue you everywhere.

If you steel yourself - as you must - to suffer and to die, all will go better with you, and you will find peace. For although, like Saint Paul, you were 'caught up into the third heaven', you would not on this account be secured against suffering further adversity. For Jesus says, 'I will show him how great things he must suffer for My Name.' Therefore, be prepared to suffer, if you wish to love Jesus and serve Him for ever.

Oh, if only you were worthy to suffer for the Name of Jesus! How great and enduring a glory would be yours! How great would be the joy of the Saints of God! How edified your friends would be! For all men commend patience, although few are willing to suffer. It is right that you should suffer a little for the sake of Christ, since many suffer greater things for worldly motives.

Be assured of this, that you must live a dying life. And the more completely a man dies to self, the more he begins to live to God. No man is fit to understand heavenly things, unless he is resigned to bear hardships for Christ's sake. Nothing is more acceptable to God, and nothing more salutary for yourself, than to suffer gladly for Christ's sake. And if it lies in your choice, you should choose rather to suffer hardships for Christ's sake, than to be refreshed by many consolations; for thus you will more closely resemble Christ and all His Saints. For our merit and spiritual progress does not consist in enjoying such sweetness and consolation, but rather in the bearing of great burdens and troubles.

Had there been a better way, more profitable to the salvation of mankind than suffering, then Christ would have revealed it in His word and life. But He clearly urges both His own disciples and all who wish to follow Him to carry the cross, saying, 'If any will come after Me, let him deny himself, and take up his cross and follow Me.' Therefore, when we have read and studied all things, let this be our final resolve: 'that through much tribulation we must enter the Kingdom of God.'

BOOK THREE
On Inward Consolation

CHAPTER 1
How Christ Speaks Inwardly to the Soul

'I will hear what the Lord God speaks within me.' Blessed is the soul that hears the Lord speaking within it, and receives comfort from His Word. Blessed are the ears that hear the still, small voice of God, and disregard the whispers of the world. Blessed are the ears that listen to Truth teaching inwardly, and not to the voices of the world. Blessed are the eyes that are closed to outward things, but are open to inward things. Blessed are those who enter deeply into inner things, and daily prepare themselves to receive the secrets of heaven. Blessed are those who strive to devote themselves wholly to God, and free themselves from all the entanglements of the world. Consider these things, O my soul, and shut fast the doors against the desires of the senses, that you may hear what the Lord your God speaks within you.

Your Beloved says: 'I am your Salvation, your Peace, and your Life; keep close to Me, and you shall find peace.' Set aside the things of time, and seek those of eternity; for what are the things of time but deceits? And how can any creature help you, if your Creator abandon you? Set aside, therefore, all else, and make yourself acceptable to your Creator, and be faithful to Him, that you may lay hold on true blessedness.

CHAPTER 2
How Truth Instructs us in Silence

the disciple. 'Speak, Lord, for Your servant listens.' 'I am Your servant; grant me understanding, that I may know Your testimonies.' 'Incline my heart to the words of Your mouth; let Your speech descend on me like the dew.' The people of Israel of old time said to Moses, 'Speak with us, and we will hear: let not God speak with us, lest we die.' But I do not pray thus, O Lord; but with the Prophet Samuel, I humbly and earnestly beg, 'Speak, Lord, for your servant listens.' Let not Moses or any of the Prophets speak to me, but rather do You speak, O Lord God, who inspire and enlighten the Prophets. You alone can perfectly instruct me without their aid, but without You they can do nothing.

The Prophets can preach the word, but they cannot bestow the Spirit. They speak most eloquently, but if You are silent, they cannot fire the heart. They instruct in the letter, but You open the understanding. They set forth the mysteries, but You reveal the meaning of all secrets. They teach your commandments, but You help us to observe them. They point the way, but You grant us strength to follow it. Their action is external; You instruct and enlighten the heart. They water the seed; You make it fruitful. They proclaim the words, but You impart understanding to the mind.

Therefore, let not Moses speak to me, but You, O Lord my God, the Everlasting Truth, lest I die and bear no fruit if I am but warned in word, and not kindled at heart; lest it turn to my condemnation, if I hear Your word, but do not obey it; know it, but do not love it; believe it, but do not keep it. Therefore, speak, Lord, for Your servant is listening. 'You have the words of eternal life.' Speak to me, Lord, and comfort my soul: order my life to Your praise, glory, and eternal honour.

CHAPTER 3
On Humble Attention to God's Word

christ. My son, hear My words. They are of surpassing sweetness, and excel all the learning of the philosophers and wise men of this world. My words are spirit and life, not to be weighed by man's understanding. They are not to be quoted for vain pleasure, but are to be heard in silence, and received with all humility and love.

the disciple. Blessed is the man whom you instruct, O Lord, and teach him out of Your Law. You refresh him in evil days, and he will not be desolate on the earth.

christ. I have taught the Prophets from the beginning of the world, and I do not cease to speak to all men today; but many are hardened, and deaf to My voice. Many listen more willingly to the world than to God, and would rather follow the desires of the body than the good pleasure of God. The world promises passing rewards of little worth, and is served with great eagerness; I promise eternal and rich rewards, yet the hearts of men are indifferent to them. Who is there who serves and obeys Me with as great devotion as he serves the world and its rulers? 'Be ashamed, O Sidon,' cries the sea; and if you ask the reason, hear why.

For a small reward a man will hurry away on a long journey, while for eternal life many will hardly take a single step. Men seek petty gains; they will quarrel shamefully over a single coin; for a mere trifle or vague promise they will toil day and night. Oh, the shame of it! For an imperishable good, for a reward beyond all reckoning, for the highest honour and for glory without end, they are unwilling to endure a little toil. O unwilling and complaining servant, shame on you that worldly men are more ready for damnation than you for salvation; for they are more wholehearted in vanity than you in the Truth. They are often deceived in their hopes, but no one is ever deceived in My promises, and I never send away empty any who trusts in Me. What I promise, I give; what I have said, I will perform, provided you remain faithful in My lord to the end. I am the rewarder of all good men, and the mighty vindicator of all the faithful.

Write My words in your heart, and meditate on them earnestly; they will aid you in temptation. What ever you do not understand when you read, you shall know in the day of My coming. I visit My chosen in two ways; with trial and with consolation. Day by day, I teach them two lessons, one in which I correct their faults, and the other in which I encourage them to progress in virtue. 'He who hears My words and despises them has One who will judge him on the Last Day.'

A Prayer for the Grace of Devotion

the disciple. O Lord my God, You are my all and every good. And what am I, that I should presume to address You? I am the poorest of Your servants and a wretched worm, far more poor and worthless than I can ever realize or express. Yet, Lord, remember that I am nothing: I have nothing, and can do nothing. You alone are good, just and holy; You can do all things, fill all things, bestow all things, leaving only the wicked empty-handed. Remember Your mercies, Lord, and fill my heart with Your grace, since it is Your will that none of Your works should be worthless. How can I endure this life of sorrows, unless You strengthen me with Your mercy and grace? Do not turn Your face from me; do not delay Your coming, nor withdraw Your consolation from me, lest my soul become like a waterless desert. Teach me, O Lord, to do Your will; teach me to live worthily and humbly in Your sight; for You are my Wisdom, who know me truly, and who knew me before the world was made, and before I had my being.

CHAPTER 4
On Truth and Humility

christ. My son, walk before Me in truth, and constantly seek Me in simplicity of heart. He who walks before Me in truth shall be protected against the assaults of evil; truth shall deliver him from his deceivers and from the slanders of the wicked. If truth set you free, you are truly free, and need care nothing for the vain words of men.

the disciple. Lord, this is true; let it be as you have said. Let Your truth be my teacher and my guard, and lead me to salvation in the end. Let it free me from every evil affection and lawless love, and I will walk before You in complete freedom of heart.

christ. I will teach you, says the Truth, what is pleasing to Me. Remember your sins with deep sorrow and displeasure, and never think yourself to be anything because of your good deeds. Remember that you are a sinner, entangled and enchained by many passions. Of yourself, you always tend to nothing; you quickly fail, and are overcome; you are soon disturbed and overthrown. You have nothing of which to boast, but many things of which to be ashamed, for you are much weaker than you realize.

Let nothing that you have achieved seem of great importance. Let nothing seem great, precious or admirable to you; nothing worthy of regard, nothing high, praiseworthy or desirable, save that which is everlasting. Let the eternal Truth be your sole and supreme joy, and let your own deep unworthiness always distress you. Nothing should be more feared, condemned, and shunned than your own sins and vices; these should cause you more distress than the loss of everything. Some do not live sincerely in My sight, but, moved by curiosity and conceit, wish to know My secrets and to fathom the high mysteries of God, while neglecting the salvation of their own souls. When I refuse them, such men often fall into great temptations and sins through pride and curiosity.

Stand in awe of God's judgement, and fear the anger of Almighty God. Do not presume to investigate the ways of the Most High, but rather examine yourself, see how greatly you have sinned, and how much good you have left undone. Some carry their devotion only in books, pictures, and other visible signs and representations. Some have Me on their lips, but seldom in their hearts. There are others who are enlightened in mind and pure in affection, who long always for the things of heaven. These listen with reluctance to worldly matters, and grudge even to serve their bodily needs. They fully understand what the Spirit of Truth speaks within them. For He teaches them to despise earthly things and to love heavenly; to forsake this world, and to long for Heaven.

CHAPTER 5
On the Wonderful Effect of Divine Love

the disciple. O Heavenly Father, Father of my Lord Jesus Christ, blessed be Your Name for ever, for You have deigned to consider me, the poorest of Your servants. Father of mercies and God of all comfort, I thank You that, unworthy as I am, You sometimes refresh me with Your consolation. Blessing and glory to You, with Your sole-begotten Son and with the Holy Spirit the Comforter, now and through endless ages. You are my glory, and the joy of my heart; for You are my hope, and my refuge in time of trouble.

As yet my love is weak, and my virtue imperfect, and I have great need of Your strength and comfort. Therefore, visit me often, I pray, and instruct me in Your holy laws. Set me free from evil passions, and heal my heart from all disorderly affections; that, healed and cleansed in spirit, I may grow able to love, strong to endure, and steadfast to persevere.

Love is a mighty power, a great and complete good; Love alone lightens every burden, and makes the rough places smooth. It bears every hardship as though it were nothing, and renders all bitterness sweet and acceptable. The love of Jesus is noble, and inspires us to great deeds; it moves us always to desire perfection. Love aspires to high things, and is held back by nothing base. Love longs to be free, a stranger to every worldly desire, lest its inner vision become dimmed, and lest worldly self-interest hinder it or ill-fortune cast it down. Nothing is sweeter than love, nothing stronger, nothing higher, nothing wider, nothing more pleasant, nothing fuller or better in heaven or earth; for love is born of God, and can rest only in God, above all created things.

Love flies, runs, and leaps for joy; it is free and unrestrained. Love gives all for all, resting in One who is highest above all things, from whom every good flows and proceeds. Love does not regard the gifts, but turns to the Giver of all good gifts. Love knows no limits, but ardently transcends all bounds. Love feels no burden, takes no account of toil, attempts things beyond its strength; love sees nothing as impossible, for it feels able to achieve all things. Love therefore does great things; it is strange and effective; while he who lacks love faints and fails.

Love is watchful, and while resting, never sleeps; weary, it is never exhausted; imprisoned, it is never in bonds; alarmed, it is never afraid; like a living flame and a burning torch, it surges upward and surely surmounts every obstacle. Whoever loves God knows well the sound of His voice. A loud cry in the ears of God is that burning love of the soul which exclaims, 'My God and my love, You are all mine, and I am Yours.'

A Prayer

Deepen Your love in me, O Lord, that I may learn in my inmost heart how sweet it is to love, to be dissolved, and to plunge myself into Your love. Let Your love possess and raise me above myself, with a fervour and wonder beyond imagination. Let me sing the song of love. Let me follow You, my Beloved, into the heights. Let my soul spend itself in Your praise, rejoicing for love. Let me love You more than myself, and myself only for Your own sake. Let me love all men who truly love You, as the law of love commands, which shines out from You.

Love is swift, pure, tender, joyful, and pleasant. Love is strong, patient, faithful, prudent, long-suffering, vigorous, and never self-seeking. For when a man is self seeking he abandons love. Love is watchful, humble, and upright; Love is not fickle and sentimental, nor is it intent on vanities. It is sober, pure, steadfast, quiet, and guarded in all the senses. Love is submissive and obedient to superiors, mean and contemptible in its own sight, devoted and thankful to God, trusting and hoping in Him even when not enjoying His sweetness; for none can live in love without suffering.

Whoever is not prepared to endure everything, and to stand firmly by the will of the Beloved, is not worthy to be called a lover. A lover must willingly accept every hardship and bitterness for the sake of his Beloved, and must never desert Him because of adversity.

CHAPTER 6
On the Proof of a True Lover

christ. My son, you are not yet a brave and wise lover.

the disciple. Why, Lord?

christ. Because as soon as you encounter a little trouble, you abandon what you have begun, and eagerly seek for comfort. A brave lover stands firm in temptation, and pays no heed to the crafty arguments of the Devil. He is as true to Me in trouble as in prosperity.

A wise lover values not so much the gift of the lover, as the love of the giver. He esteems the affection above the gift, and values every gift far below the Beloved. A noble lover is not content with a gift, but desires Myself above all gifts. All is not lost, therefore, if sometimes you do not feel that devotion to Me and My Saints that you desire. The good and pleasant affection which you sometimes enjoy is the effect of My grace in you, and is a foretaste of your heavenly home; but do not rely on it too much, for it comes and goes. To fight against evil thoughts as they occur, and to reject with scorn the suggestions of the Devil, is a noteworthy sign of virtue and merit.

Let no strange fancies disturb you, from whatever source they spring. Hold to your purpose bravely, and keep an upright intent towards God. It is no illusion if you are sometimes rapt out of yourself, yet swiftly return to the usual trivial thoughts of men. For these are involuntary rather than deliberate, and as long as they do not please you, can be turned to your gain and not your loss.

You may be sure that the old Enemy is working by every means to frustrate your desire for good, and to entice you away from every spiritual exercise of devotion; from veneration of the Saints, from devout meditation on My Passion, from profitable examination of your sins, from the guard of your heart, and from the firm resolve to grow in holiness. He suggests many evil thoughts to discourage you, and to draw you away from holy reading and prayer. Humble Confession is hateful to him, and if he could, he would make you give up Communion. Do not listen to him or believe him, however often he tries to entrap you. Charge him with it, when he suggests evil and unholy things. Say to him, 'Away, unclean spirit! Blush for shame, wretch! You are foul indeed to speak of these things! Off with you, most evil of liars! You shall have no part in me. Jesus will be with me like a mighty warrior, and you will stand confounded. I would rather die and suffer any torture than consent to you. Be silent, and shut your mouth! I will listen to you no longer, however often you pester me.' 'The Lord is my light and my salvation: whom shall I fear?' 'Though a host should encamp against me, my heart shall not be afraid.' 'The Lord is my helper and redeemer.'

Give battle, like a good soldier, and if through weakness you sometimes fall, take greater strength than before and put your trust in My more abundant grace. Be also on your guard against vain complacency and conceit, for this leads many into error, and causes almost incurable blindness of heart. Let the overthrow of the proud, who presumed in their own strength, be a warning to you and keep you always humble.

CHAPTER 7
On Concealing Grace under Humility

christ. My son, it is safer and better for you to conceal the grace of devotion; do not boast of it, do not speak much of it, and do not dwell much on it. It is better to think the more humbly of yourself, and to fear that this grace has been granted to one who is unworthy of it. Never depend too much on these feelings, for they may be rapidly changed to the opposite. When you enjoy such grace, consider how sad and needy you are without it. Progress in the spiritual life consists not so much in enjoying the grace of consolation, as in beating its withdrawal with humility, resignation and patience, neither growing weary in prayer nor neglecting your other acts of devotion. Do willingly, and to the best of your ability and understanding, whatever lies in your power, and do not neglect your spiritual life because of any dryness or anxiety of mind.

There are many who grow impatient or indolent when all does not go according to their wishes. But man's life is not always in his control; it belongs to God alone to give and to comfort when He wills, as much as He wills, and whom He wills, just as He pleases and no more. Some people, lacking discretion, have brought ruin on themselves through the grace of devotion, attempting more than lay in their power, ignoring the measure of their own littleness, and following the promptings of the heart rather than the dictates of reason. And because they presumed to greater things than pleased God, they soon lost His grace. These souls, who aspired to build their nest in Heaven, became needy and wretched outcasts, in order that, through humiliation and poverty, they might learn not to fly with their own wings, but to trust themselves under My wings. For those who are still new and untried in the Way of the Lord can easily be deceived and lost, unless they are guided by wise counsel.

If they follow their own notions rather than trust others of proved experience, their end will be perilous unless they are willing to be drawn away from their own conceit. Those who are wise in their own conceit seldom humbly accept guidance from others. A little knowledge and understanding tempered by humility is better than a great store of learning coupled with vain complacency. It is better to have few talents than many of which you might be conceited. Whoever yields himself to joy, forgetful of his former poverty, is very unwise, for he forgets also that pure reverence for the Lord which fears to lose grace already given. Nor is he wise who, in trouble and adversity, yields to despair, and fails to put his trust in Me.

The man who feels secure in time of peace, will often in time of war be found discouraged and afraid. If you were careful to remain always humble and modest in your own esteem, and to direct and control your mind rightly, you would not fall so readily into danger and disgrace. It is good advice, that when the spirit of devotion is aflame in your heart, you should consider how you will fare when the light leaves you. When this happens, remember that this light will one day return, which I have now for a while withdrawn as a warning to you and for My glory.

Such a trial is often more profitable than if all went agreeably with you, and in accordance with your wishes. For a man's merit is not to be reckoned by the visions and comforts he may enjoy, nor by his learning in the Scriptures, nor by his being raised to high dignity. Rather is it by his being grounded in humility and filled with divine love; by his pure, constant, and sincere seeking of God's glory; by his low esteem and honest depreciation of himself; and by his preference for humiliation and despite rather than honours at the hands of men.

[…]

CHAPTER 9
How God Alone is our True End

christ. My son, I must be your supreme and final End, if you desire true happiness. Fixed on Myself, your affection which too often is wrongly inclined to yourself and creatures, will be cleansed. For whenever you seek yourself, at once you become discouraged and desolate. Therefore, refer all things to Me, for it is I who have given all to you. Consider everything as springing from the supreme Good, since to Myself, as their Source, must all things return.

From Myself, as from a living fountain, both small and great, rich and poor alike draw the water of life; and they who freely and willingly serve Me, shall receive grace upon grace. But whoever desires to glory in anything outside Me, or to delight in some personal good thing, will not be established in true joy, nor uplifted in heart, but will be hindered and frustrated in countless ways. Therefore, ascribe no good to yourself, nor to any man, but ascribe all to God, without whom man has nothing. I have given all, and it is My will that all return to Me again; I shall require a grateful and exact account.

This, then, is the troth, by which vainglory is put to flight. And if heavenly grace and tree charity enter in, there will be no envy or meanness of heart, nor will self-love retain possession. Divine charity overcomes everything, enlarging every power of the soul. If you are truly wise, you will rejoice and hope in Me alone; for none is good but God alone, who is to be praised above all, and to be blessed in all.

CHAPTER 10
On the Joy of Gods Service

the disciple. Lord, I will speak once more; I cannot remain silent. I will say to my God, my Lord and my King, who dwells on high, 'Oh, how great and manifold are Your joys, kept in secret for those who fear You.' But what are You to those who love You? What to those who serve You with their whole heart? The contemplation of Yourself is the ineffable sweetness that You grant to those who love You. And this is the supreme manifestation of Your love, that when I had no being, You created me; when I went astray, You led me back to Your service, and taught me to love You.

O Fount of eternal love, what may I say of You? How can I forget You, who have deigned to remember me, even after I was corrupted and lost? You have showed mercy on Your servant beyond all my hope; You have given grace and friendship beyond all my deserts. What return can I make to You for this grace? For it is not granted to all men to forsake everything, to renounce the world, and to enter the life of religion. And is it a great thing that I should serve You, whom all creation is bound to serve? It should not seem much to me that I should serve you; rather is it great and wonderful to me that You should see fit to receive into Your service one so poor and unworthy, and count him among Your beloved servants.

All that I have is Yours, and myself with it. Yet it is really You who serve me, rather than I You. Heaven and earth, which You created for the use of man, await Your pleasure, and obey Your laws day by day. And even this is little, for You have appointed the very Angels to minister to men. But what surpasses all these, is that You Yourself stoop to serve man, and have promised him the gift of Yourself.

What return can I make for all these countless favours? If only I could serve You faithfully all the days of my life! If only I could render You worthy service, even for a single day! For You alone are worthy of all service, honour, and eternal praise. You are truly my God, and I Your poor servant, who am bound to serve with all my powers, nor should I ever weary in Your praise. This is my wish and desire; whatever is lacking in me, I pray You to supply.

It is a great honour and glory to serve you, and to despise all else for Your sake; for great grace will be given to those who have willingly entered Your most holy service. They will discover the sweetest consolations of the Holy Spirit, who for Your love have renounced all the delights of the flesh. They will win true freedom of mind, who for Your Name's sake have entered on the narrow way, and set aside all worldly interests.

O gracious and joyful service of God, in which man is made truly free and holy! O sacred state of religious service, which makes man the equal of Angels, pleasing to God, terrible to devils, and an example to all the faithful! O most lovely and desirable service, in which we receive the reward of the supreme Good, and obtain the joy that abides for ever!

CHAPTER 11
On Control of the Heart

christ. My son, you have still many things to learn.

the disciple. What are these, Lord?

christ. How you must frame your desires in accordance with My good pleasure, and be not a lover of self, but an earnest follower of My will. Desires often inflame you and drive you violently onwards; but consider whether it be My honour or self-interest that moves you most. If I Myself be the cause, you will be content with whatever I shall determine; but if self-interest is your hidden motive, this will be a hindrance and burden to you.

Take care, therefore, not to rely overmuch on any preconceived desire without asking My counsel, lest you regret or become displeased at what first pleased you, and for which you were eager. For not every feeling that seems good is at once to be acted upon, nor is every feeling that runs contrary to your inclinations to be immediately rejected. It is sometimes necessary to restrain even your good intentions and endeavours, lest by over-eagerness your mind becomes distracted; lest by lack of discipline you cause offence to others; or lest you suddenly become confused and upset by the opposition of others.

You must bravely and forcibly resist your sensual appetite, taking no account of what the body likes or dislikes, and struggle to subdue the unwilling flesh to the spirit. For it must be corrected and brought under control, until it is obedient in everything. It must learn to be content with little, to take pleasure in simple things, and not to complain at any hardship.

CHAPTER 12
On Learning Patience

the disciple. O Lord God, I know that I need patience above all else, for in this life there are many trials. For however earnestly I seek peace, I cannot escape struggle and sorrow.

christ. This is true, My son. But My will is that you do not try to find a place free from temptations and troubles. Rather, seek a peace that endures even when you are beset by various temptations and tried by much adversity. If you say that you cannot endure much, how will you endure the fires of Purgatory? Of two evils, always choose the lesser. Endeavour patiently to endure for God's sake all the ills of this life, that you may escape eternal punishment. Do you imagine that worldly men suffer little or nothing? Ask the most wealthy, and you will not find it so.

But, you may say, they enjoy many pleasures, and follow their own desires; in this way they make light of any troubles. Yet, even if they enjoy whatever they desire, how long will this last? The rich of this world will vanish like smoke, and no memory of their past pleasures will remain. But even in their lifetime they do not enjoy them without bitterness, weariness and fear, for the very things whence they derive their pleasures often carry with them the seeds of sorrow. And this is but just; for having sought and followed pleasures to excess, they may not enjoy them without shame and bitterness. Ah, how short-lived and false, how disorderly and base are all these pleasures! Yet so besotted and blind are such persons that, like dumb beasts, they bring death to their souls for the trivial enjoyments of this corruptible life! My son, do not follow your lusts, and do not be self-willed. Delight in the Lord, and he will grant your heart's desire.

If you would taste true pleasure and receive the fullness of My consolation, know this: that in the despising of worldly things and in the shunning of base delights shall be your blessing, and you shall win abundant consolation. The more you withdraw yourself from the comfort of creatures, the sweeter and more potent will be the consolations that you will find in Me. But you will not find these at once, or without sorrow, toil and effort. Old habits will stand in your way, but by better they will be overcome. The body will complain, but by fervour of the spirit it can be disciplined. The Old Serpent will goad and disturb you, but by prayer he will be put to flight; and by profitable labour you will bar the wide path by which he comes to attack you.

CHAPTER 13
On Obedience, after the Example of Christ

christ. My son, whoever strives to withdraw from obedience, withdraws from grace. And he who seeks personal privileges, loses those that are common to all. When a man is unwilling to submit freely and willingly to his superior, it is a sign that his lower nature is not yet under his control, but frequently rebels and complains. Therefore learn to obey your superior promptly if you wish to subdue your lower nature, for the Enemy without is sooner overcome if our inner fortress remains intact. There is no enemy more wicked or troublesome to the soul than yourself, when you are not in harmony with the Spirit, and you must have a very real scorn for self, if you are to prevail against flesh and Blood. It is because you are unwilling to yield your will to that of others, that you are still full of self-love.

Is it so hard for you, who are dust and nothingness, to subject yourself to man for God's sake, when I, the Almighty and most high, who created all things from nothing, humbly subjected Myself to man for your sake? I became the humblest and least of all men, that you might overcome your pride through My humility. Learn to obey, you who are but dust; learn to humble yourself, earth and clay, and to bow yourself beneath the feet of all. Learn to curb your desires, and yield yourself to complete obedience.

Direct your anger against yourself, and let no swelling pride remain in you. Show yourself so submissive and so humble that all men may trample over you and tread on you like the mud of the streets. Vain man, what right have you to complain? What can you, an unclean sinner, answer to any who reproach you, when you have so often offended God, and so many times deserved Hell? But I have spared you, for your soul was precious to Me, that you might know My love, and be ever grateful for My favour: also, that you might give yourself constantly to true obedience and humility, enduring patiently any contempt laid on you.

[…]

CHAPTER 17
How we must put our Whole Trust in God

christ. My son, let My will be your guide. I know what is best for you. Your mind is but human, and your judgement often influenced by personal considerations.

the disciple. Lord, this is true, and Your providence will order my life better than I can myself: most insecure is the man who does not put all his trust in You. Lord, keep my will steadfast and true to You, and do with me whatever is Your pleasure; for all is good that comes to me by Your will. If You will that darkness be my lot, blessed be Your Name; if it be light, again blessed be Your Name. If You stoop to comfort me, blessed be Your Name; and if You wish to try me, ever blessed be Your Name.

christ. My son, let this be your disposition if you wish to walk with Me. Be as ready to suffer as to be glad; be as willing to be needy and poor as to enjoy wealth and plenty.

the disciple. Lord, for Your sake I will gladly bear whatever You shall send to me. From Your hand I will accept gladly both good and ill, sweet and bitter, joy and sorrow; and for all that may befall me, I will thank You. Only keep me, O Lord, from all sin, and I shall fear neither Death nor Hell. Do not, I pray, reject me for ever, nor blot out my name from the book of life; then, whatever trials beset me can do me no harm.

CHAPTER 18
How Sorrows are to be Borne Patiently

christ. My son, I came down from Heaven for your salvation. I took upon Myself your sorrows, not because I must, but out of pure love, that you might learn patience, and bear without complaint all the troubles of this world. From the hour of My Birth until My Death on the Cross, I had always to endure sorrow. I suffered great lack of worldly goods; many accusations were levelled against Me. I bore all disgrace and insults with meekness. In return for blessings I received ingratitude; for miracles, blasphemies; for My teaching, reproofs.

the disciple. Lord, because You were patient in Your life, in this respect especially fulfilling the command of Your Father, it is fitting that I, a wretched sinner, should bear myself patiently in accordance with Your will, and that, for the salvation of my soul, I should bear the burden of this corruptible life so long as You shall will. For though this present life is hard, yet by Your grace it is made full of merit; and by Your example and the lives of Your Saints it is rendered easier and happier for the weak. Its consolations are richer than under the old Law, when the gates of Heaven were shut, and the way thither dark, so that few cared to enter the Kingdom of Heaven. And even those who in former days were righteous and to be saved could not enter the Kingdom of Heaven until Your Passion and the Atonement of Your sacred Death.

What boundless gratitude is Your due, for revealing to me and to all faithful people the true and holy way to Your eternal Kingdom! Your life is Our Way, and by holy patience we will journey onwards to You, who are our crown and consummation. If You, Lord, had not gone before us and showed the way, who could follow? How many would have stayed behind and far distant had they not Your glorious example for their guide? Even now we are cold and careless, although we have heard Your teaching and mighty acts; what would happen to us had we not Your light as our guide?

CHAPTER 19
On Enduring Injuries, and the Proof of Patience

christ. My son, what are you saying? Consider My sufferings and those of My Saints, and cease to complain. You have not yet shed your blood in resistance; your troubles are but small in comparison with those who have suffered so much, whose temptations were so strong, whose trials so severe, and who were proved and tested in so many ways. Remember the heavier sufferings of others, that you may more easily bear your own small troubles. If they do not seem small to you, beware lest your impatience be the cause; and whether they be small or great, try to bear them all patiently.

The better you prepare yourself to meet suffering, the more wisely will you act, and the greater will be your merit. You will bear all more easily if your heart and mind is diligently prepared. Do not say, 'I cannot endure such things from this person,' or, 'I will not tolerate these things: he has done me great injury, and accused me of things I never considered; from another person I might bear it, and regard it as something that must be endured.' Such thoughts are foolish, for you ignore the merit of patience and Him who rewards it, and think only of the person who has injured you and the wrong you endure.

You are not truly patient if you will only endure what you think fit, and only from those whom you like. A truly patient man does not consider by whom he is tried, whether by his superior, his equal, or his inferior; whether by a good and holy man, or by a perverse and wicked person. But however great or frequent the trial that besets him, and by whatever agency it comes, he accepts it gladly as from the hand of God, and counts it all gain.

Always be ready for battle if you wish for victory; you cannot win the crown of patience without a struggle; if you refuse to suffer, you refuse the crown. Therefore, if you desire the crown, fight manfully and endure patiently. Without labour, no rest is won; without battle, there can be no victory.

the disciple. Lord, make possible for me by grace what is impossible to me by nature. You know how little I can bear, and how quickly I become discouraged by a little adversity. I pray You, make every trial lovely and desirable to me for Your Name's sake, since suffering and affliction for Your sake is so profitable to the health of my soul.

CHAPTER 20
On our own Weakness, and the Trials of This Life

the disciple. Lord, I confess my sinfulness, and acknowledge my weakness. Often it is but a small matter that defeats and troubles me. I resolve to act boldly, but when I am assailed even by a small temptation, I am in sore straits. From a trifling thing sometimes arises a strong temptation; and when I think I am secure, I am almost overwhelmed by a mere breath.

Consider my lowness and weakness, O Lord, for You know all things. Have mercy on me, and raise me from the mire, that I may not stick fast in it, nor remain prostrate. It is this that often defeats and confounds me in Your eyes - that I am so prone to fall and so weak in resisting my passions. And although I do not yield to them entirely, yet their assaults trouble and distress me, so that I am weary of living constantly at conflict. My weakness is apparent to me, for evil fancies rush in on me more readily than they depart.

Most mighty God of Israel, zealous lover of souls, I pray You remember the toil and grief of Your servant, and support him in all his undertakings. Strengthen me with heavenly courage, lest my old and wicked enemy the flesh, not yet wholly subject to the spirit, prevail and gain the upper hand. For against this I must fight while breath remains in this troublous life. Alas, what a life is this, where trials and sorrows never cease, and where all things are full of snares and foes! For when one trial or temptation departs, another takes its place; and even while the conflict rages, other troubles arise, innumerable and unexpected.

How can we love life, when it holds so much bitterness, and is subject to so many sorrows and calamities? How, indeed, can that be called life, which breeds death and pain in such full measure? Yet it is loved, and many find great delight in it. The world is often blamed for its falseness and vanity, but it is not readily abandoned: the desires of the body exercise too strong a hold. Some things cause us to love the world, others to hate it. The desires of the body, the desires of the eyes, and the pride of life all draw us to love the world; but the pains and sorrows that justly ensue cause us to hate and weary of it.

Alas, a perverted pleasure overcomes the mind that surrenders to the world, and counts it a delight to lie among the brambles, for it has neither seen nor tasted the sweetness of God and the inner joy of holiness. But they who perfectly despise the world and study to live under God's holy rule know something of that heavenly sweetness promised to all who sincerely forsake the world. They see most clearly how sadly the world goes astray, and how grievously it is deceived.

CHAPTER 21
How we must Rest in God Alone above all Things

the disciple. Above all things and in all things rest always in the Lord, O my soul, for He is the everlasting rest of the Saints.

A Prayer

Grant me, most dear and loving Jesus, to rest in You above created things; above health and beauty, above all glory and honour; above all power and dignity above all knowledge and skill; above all fame and praise, above all sweetness and consolation; above all hope and promise, above all merit and desire; above all gifts and favours that You can bestow and shower upon us; above all joy and jubilation that the mind can conceive and know; above Angels and Archangels and all the hosts of Heaven; above all things visible and invisible; and above everything that is not Yourself, O my God.

O Lord my God, You transcend all things; You alone are most high, most mighty, most sufficient and complete, most sweet and comforting. You alone are most full of beauty and glory, in Whom all good things in their perfection exist, both now and ever have been, and ever will be. All, therefore, is too small and unsatisfying that You can give me beside Yourself, or that You can reveal and promise me of Yourself unless I can see and fully possess You. For my heart cannot rest nor be wholly content until it rests in You, rising above all Your gifts and creatures.

O Lord Jesus Christ, spouse of the soul, lover of purity, and Lord of creation, who will give me wings of perfect liberty, that I may fly to You, and be at rest? When shall I be set free, and taste Your sweetness, O Lord my God? When shall I become recollected in You, that for love of You I may no longer be conscious of myself, but of You alone in a manner not known to all men, and above all perception and measure? But now I mourn and bear my unhappy lot with grief, for many evils happen in this vale of sorrows, which often disturb, sadden and darken my path. They often hinder and distract, entice, and entangle me, so that I cannot approach You freely, nor yet enjoy the sweet embrace which You prepare for the souls of the blessed.

O Jesus, Brightness of eternal glory and comfort of the pilgrim soul, hear my cry, and regard my utter desolation. Words fail me in Your presence; let my silence speak for me. How long will my Lord delay His coming? Come to me, Lord, poor and little as I am, and bring me joy. Stretch out Your hand, and deliver me from all my misery and pain. Come, Lord, come, for without You no day or hour is happy; without You my table is without its guest, for You alone are my joy. Sadness is my lot, and I am like a man imprisoned and loaded with chains, until You refresh me with the light of Your presence, and show me Your face as my friend. Let others seek whom they will besides You, but nothing ever can or will give me joy but Yourself alone, my God, my Hope, and my eternal Salvation. I will not keep silent, nor cease from urgent prayer till Your grace returns and my heart leaps at the sound of Your voice.

christ. See, I am here. I have come at your cry. Your tears and your souls longing, your humiliation and contrition of heart have moved Me to come to you.

the disciple. Lord, I have called You and longed for You. I am ready to renounce everything for Your sake, who first moved me to seek You. Blessed be Your Name, O Lord, for Your goodness to Your servant, according to the richness of Your mercies. What more can Your servant say, Lord? He can only humble himself entirely in Your presence, ever mindful of his own wickedness and unworthiness. For none can compare with You, among all the wonders of heaven and earth. All Your works are good, Your judgements are true, and by Your providence are all things ruled. Praise and glory to You, O Wisdom of the Father! Let my soul, my lips, and all creation join in Your blessing and Your praise!

[…]

CHAPTER 23
On Four Things that Bring Peace

christ. My son, I will now teach you the way of peace and true freedom.

the disciple. Lord, instruct me, I pray. I am eager to learn.

christ. My son, resolve to do the will of others rather than your own.

Always choose to possess less rather than more.

Always take the lowest place, and regard yourself as less than others.

Desire and pray always that Gods will may be perfectly fulfilled in you.

A man who observes these rules shall come to enjoy peace and tranquillity of soul.

the disciple. Lord, in these few words of Yours lie the whole secret of perfection. If I could only faithfully observe them, no trouble could distress me. For whenever I am anxious and weary, I find that it is because I have strayed from Your teaching. All things are in Your power, and You always long to bring souls to perfection. Give me Your grace ever more richly; help me to keep Your word and advance my salvation.

A Prayer against Evil Thoughts

My Lord and God, do not abandon me; remember my need, for many evil thoughts and horrid fears trouble my mind and terrify my soul. How shall I pass through them unhurt? How shall I break their power over me? You have said, 'I will go before you, and will humble the proud upon earth. I will open the gates of the prison, and reveal to you the hidden treasures and secrets of the ages.' Do, O Lord, as You have said, and let Your coming put to flight all wicked thoughts. It is my hope and comfort that I can turn to You in all my troubles, put my trust in You, call upon You in my heart, and wait Your comfort in patience.

A Prayer for Mental Light

O merciful Jesus, send the brightness of Your light into my mind, and banish all darkness from the sanctuary of my heart. Restrain my many wayward thoughts, and destroy the temptations that beset me with such violence. Let Your great strength be with me in the fight, and overcome the seducing desires of the flesh, that rage in me like evil beasts. By Your power establish peace, and let Your praises be sung in the temple of a pure heart. Command the winds and storm; subdue the fury of the seas and the blast of the north wind, and there shall be a great calm. Send out Your light and Your truth to shine over the world; for until Your light illuminates my soul, I am dull earth, formless and empty. Pour forth Your grace from above, and bathe my heart in the dew of Heaven. Supply fresh streams of devotion to water the face of the earth, and produce good and perfect fruit. Inspire my mind, now burdened by my sins, and fix my whole desire on heavenly things, so that, having once tasted the sweetness of eternal joys, I may turn with distaste from all the passing pleasures of this world. Release me, and free my heart from all dependence on the passing consolation of wicked things, since none of these things can yield true satisfaction or appease my longings. Unite me to Yourself by the unbreakable bonds of love. You alone can satisfy the soul that loves You, and without You the world is worthless.

CHAPTER 24
On the Evils of Curiosity

christ. Beware of vain curiosity, My son, and do not busy yourself in profitless matters; what are they to you? Follow Me. What concern is it of yours whether a man is good or evil, or what he says and does? You will not be called on to answer for others, but you will certainly have to give a full account of your own life. Why, then, must you meddle where you have no need? I know the hearts of all men, and nothing under the sun is hid from My knowledge. I know the life of every man - his thoughts, his desires and his intentions. Therefore trust yourself entirely to My care, and let your heart be at peace. Let the meddlesome man trouble himself as he will; his words and deeds will recoil on his own head, for he cannot deceive Me.

Do not court the favour of powerful patrons, nor popular favour, not even the particular affection of friends. All these things are distractions, and fill the heart with uncertainty. If you will but await My coming, and throw open the door of your heart, I Myself will speak to you, and reveal to you My secrets.

Be ready; watch and pray. Above all, be humble.

CHAPTER 25
On Lasting Peace and True Progress

christ. I have said, 'Peace I leave with you; My own peace I give you. Not as the world gives do I give you.' All men want peace, but all do not seek those things that bring true peace. My peace is with the humble and gentle of heart, and depends on great patience. If you listen to Me, and follow My words, you shall find true peace.

the disciple. What must I do, Lord?

christ. Keep guard over your whole life, your actions and words. Direct all your efforts to the single purpose of pleasing Me: seek and desire Myself alone. Never make rash judgements on the behaviour of others, and do not interfere when your opinion is not sought. If you do as I say, you will seldom be troubled in mind. But do not imagine that you can avoid anxiety in this life, or that you may never experience sorrow of heart or pain of body, for true peace is only to be found in the state of eternal rest. So do not think that you have found true peace when you happen to experience no trouble, and do not think that all is well when no one opposes you. Nor should you imagine that everything is perfect when everything happens in accordance with your wishes. Do not hold an exaggerated opinion of yourself, or believe that you are a favourite of God when you enjoy the grace of great devotion and sweetness; for it is not by these things that the true lover of holiness is known, or is a man's spiritual progress dependent on such things.

the disciple. Lord, on what then does it depend?

christ. On complete surrender of your heart to the will of God, not seeking to have your own way either in great matters or small, in time or in eternity. If you will make this surrender, you will thank God with equal gladness both in good times and in bad, and will accept everything, as from His hand, with an untroubled mind. Be courageous and of such unshakeable faith that, when spiritual comfort is withdrawn, you may prepare your heart for even greater trials. Do not think it unjust that you should suffer so much, but confess that I am just in all My dealings, and praise My holy Name. In so doing, you will walk in the true and noble way of peace, and I will surely come to you again and give you great joy. Only think humbly of yourself, and I promise you as great peace as man may enjoy in this life.

CHAPTER 26
On the Excellence of a Free Mind

the disciple. Lord, one who desires perfection must make it his first task to keep his mind at all times set on heavenly things. By so doing, he can pass carefree through many troubles, not as one who has not the wit to realize the dangers that beset him, but in the strength of a free mind, unfettered by undue attachment to worldly things.

Most loving God, I beg You so to preserve me that I am not overborne by the cares of this life. Keep me, also, from becoming the servant of my body's many needs, that I may not become absorbed in its pleasures. Save me from all the pitfalls that beset my soul, that they may not overwhelm and crush me. I do not ask to be preserved from those things that vain and worldly men pursue with such ardour, but rather from those miseries that so heavily burden and impede the soul of Your servant, who lies under the curse common to all mortal men. It is these miseries that prevent my soul from entering into the true liberty of the spirit whenever I would. My Lord God, my Delight above all delights, make bitter to me all worldly pleasure that draws me away from the love of eternal joys, and wickedly seduces me by promising me all the joys of the present. Let me not be overcome by flesh and blood, I entreat You. Let not the world and its brief glory deceive me, nor the Devil and his cunning overthrow me. Give me strength to resist, patience to endure, and constancy to persevere. Give me the rich graces of Your spirit rather than all the pleasures of the world and supplant all worldly love by the love of Your Name. A man of fervent spirit grudges much attention to food, drink, clothing and other bodily needs. Grant me to use these things with moderation, and not to be over-concerned about them. It is not right to ignore them, for nature bids us supply their needs; but the law of holiness forbids us to crave for needless luxuries, since the body then revolts against the spirit. In all things, I pray You, let Your hand guide and govern me, that moderation may be my rule at all times.

[…]

CHAPTER 28
Against Slander

christ. My son, do not take it to heart if others think ill of you, and say unpleasant things about you. Consider yourself to be even worse than they imagine, and regard yourself as the weakest of men. If your inner life is strong, you will not pay much heed to passing words. A wise man remains silent when beset by evil; he turns to Me in his heart, and is untroubled by man's judgements.

Do not let your peace depend on what people say of you, for whether they speak good or ill of you makes no difference to what you are. True peace and joy is to be found in Me alone. He who is neither anxious to please nor afraid to displease men enjoys true peace. All unrest of heart and distraction of mind spring from disorderly affections and groundless fears.

CHAPTER 29
How we should Bless God in all Trouble

the disciple. Blessed be Your holy Name for ever, O Lord. I know that it is by Your will that temptation and trouble come upon me. I cannot escape it, but must needs come to You for help, that it may be turned to my good. Lord, I am tormented and uneasy in mind, and my present troubles weigh heavy on me.

Most loving Father, what may I say? I am in dire straits. Save me from this hour. Yet it is for Your glory that I have been brought to this hour, and that I may learn that You alone can deliver me from the depths of my humiliation. Of Your goodness, deliver me, O Lord. For what can I do, helpless as I am; and where can I go without Your aid? Give me patience, Lord, even in this trial. Grant me help, and I shall fear nothing, however hard pressed I may be.

And now, in this trouble, this shall be my prayer, 'Your will be done.' I have fully deserved this trouble, and must bear it. Let me bear it patiently, until the storm is past and better days return. I know that Your almighty power can remove even this trial from me and lessen its violence, so that I am not completely crushed by it. Often in times past, my God and my Mercy, You have done this for me. And the harder it is for me, the easier it is for You to change my way, O God most high.

CHAPTER 30
On Asking God's Help, and the Certainty of His Grace

christ. My son, I am the Lord, who gives strength in time of trouble. Come to Me when the struggle goes hard with you. Your slowness in turning to prayer is the greatest obstacle to receiving My heavenly comfort. For, when you should earnestly seek Me, you first turn to many other comforts, and hope to restore yourself by worldly means. It is only when all these things have failed that you remember that I am the Saviour of all who put their trust in Me; and that, apart from Me, there can be no effective help, no sound counsel, and no lasting remedy. But now, with spirit renewed after the tempest, gather fresh strength and light in My mercies. For I am near, and will restore all things, not only completely, but generously and in full measure.

Is anything too hard for Me? Shall I be like one who does not fulfil his promise? Where is your faith? Stand firm, and persevere. Be courageous and patient, and help will come to you in due time. Wait patiently for Me, and I Myself will come and heal you. Temptation is your testing - there is no cause for alarm or fear. Sorrow upon sorrow can be the only result if you worry about the future. Sufficient to the day is the evil in it. It is quite vain and useless to be either anxious or pleased about the future, for what you anticipate may never happen.

The mind of man is prone to delusions, but to be deceived by the suggestions of the Devil is a sign of spiritual weakness. Satan does not care whether it be by truth or falsehood that he mocks and deceives you; or whether he obtains your downfall through love of the present or fear of the future. Therefore, let not your heart be troubled, neither let it be afraid. Trust in Me, and put your whole confidence in My mercy. When you think I am far away, then often I am nearest to you. And when you think the battle almost lost, then the reward of all your toil is often near. All is not lost when anything turns out contrary to your plans. Therefore do not allow your feelings of the moment to obscure your judgement, nor yield to depression as though all hope of recovery were lost.

Do not imagine yourself utterly forsaken if for a while I have allowed some trial to harass you, or withdrawn the comfort that you desire; for this is the way to the Kingdom of Heaven. Be assured that it is better for you, and for all My servants, to struggle against difficulties than to have everything as you wish. I know your secret thoughts, and it is necessary for your salvation that you should sometimes be deprived of spiritual joys, lest you become conceited in your happy state, and complacently imagine yourself better than you are. What I have granted, I can take away, and restore it when I choose.

When I grant comfort, it remains Mine; and when I withdraw it, I am not taking anything that is yours, for every good gift and every perfect gift is Mine alone. If I send you trouble and affliction, do not be indignant or downhearted; for I can swiftly help you, and turn all your sorrow into joy. Notwithstanding, I keep My own counsel, and in all My dealings with you, give Me due praise.

If you are wise and have right judgement, you will never despair or be discouraged. On the contrary, if I scourge you with trouble and do not spare you, be glad and grateful, and regard it as cause for joy. For, 'as My Father has loved Me, so do I love you,' were My words to my well loved disciples, whom I did not send out to enjoy the pleasures of the world, but to fight hard battles; not to win honours, but contempt; not to be idle, but industrious; not to rest, but to bring forth much fruit with patience.

CHAPTER 31
On Forsaking Creatures to Find the Creator

the disciple. Lord, I am greatly in need of yet more abundant grace if I am to reach that state where no creature can impede my progress. For as long as anything holds me back, I cannot come freely to You. One who desired to fly freely to You said, 'Who will give me wings like a dove? I will fly, and be at rest.' And who is more perfectly at rest than the man of single purpose? Who more free than he who desires nothing upon earth? Rapt in spirit, a man must rise above all created things, and perfectly forsaking himself, see clearly that nothing in creation can compare with the Creator. But unless a man is freed from dependence on creatures, he cannot turn freely to the things of God. This is the reason why there are so few contemplatives, for there are few who can free themselves entirely from transitory things.

A soul needs much grace to be raised up and carried beyond itself. Yet, unless a man's soul is raised, set free from all attachment to earthly things, and wholly united to God, neither his knowledge nor his possessions are of any value. So long as he esteems as precious anything outside the One, Infinite, and Eternal Good, he will remain mean and earthbound in spirit. For whatever is not God is nothing, and is to be accounted nothing. There is a great difference between the wisdom of a devout man enlightened by God, and the knowledge of a learned and studious scholar. More noble by far is the learning infused from above by divine grace, than that painfully acquired by the industry of man.

Many desire the grace of contemplation, but few take the trouble to practise what is essential to it. It is a great obstacle if we rely on external signs and the experience of the senses, and pay small regard to the perfecting of serf-discipline. I hardly know what motives can inspire us, or what our purpose may be, when we who wish to be considered spiritual take so much trouble and are so concerned with trivial, daily affairs, and so seldom give our full and earnest attention to our interior life.

Alas, after a short meditation we break of, and do not make a strict examination of our lives. We do not consider where our affections really lie, nor are we grieved at the sinfulness of our whole life. Yet it was because of the wickedness of men that the Flood came upon the earth. When our inner inclinations are corrupted, the actions that spring from them are also corrupted. And this is a sign of our lack of inner strength; for from a pure heart alone springs the fruit of a holy life.

A man's achievements are often discussed, but seldom the principles by which he lives. We inquire whether he is brave, handsome, rich, clever, a good writer, a fine singer, or a hard worker: but whether he is humble-minded, patient and gentle, devout and spiritual is seldom mentioned. Nature regards the outward characteristics of a man: Grace considers his inner disposition. And while Nature is often misled, Grace trusts in God and cannot be deceived.

CHAPTER 32
On Self-Denial, and Renunciation of our Desires

christ. My son, complete self-denial is the only road to perfect liberty. Those who are obsessed by self-interest and self-love are slaves of their own desires; they are greedy, inquisitive, and discontented. They spend themselves in pleasures, but never in the service of Jesus Christ, their whole interest being in passing affairs. But all that is not of God shall perish utterly.

Observe this simple counsel of perfection: Forsake all, and you shall find all. Renounce desire, and you shall find peace. Give this due thought, and when you have put it into practice, you will understand all things.

the disciple. Lord, this is not the work of a single day, and no easy matter. These few words contain the whole way of spiritual perfection.

christ. My son, do not be discouraged or diverted from your purpose at hearing of this way of perfection. Rather let it spur you to higher things, and, at least, to set your heart on them. If only you would do this, and attain that state where you cease to be a lover of self, and stand ready to do My will and His whom I have appointed as your Father, you would greatly please Me, and your whole life would be filled with joy and peace. You have still many things to renounce, and unless you surrender them to Me without reserve, you cannot obtain what you ask of Me. I counsel you to buy from Me gold, reined in the ire, that you may be rich in that heavenly wisdom that rejects all worthless things. Despise the wisdom of the world, and every temptation to please others or yourself.

I have said, exchange what men consider desirable and honourable for that which they hold in low esteem. For true heavenly wisdom, having no exalted opinion of itself, seeks no recognition from the world, is almost disregarded by men, and seems to them useless and of no importance. Many pay it lip-service, but it plays no part in their lives. Yet this is the precious pearl, that remains hidden from many.

CHAPTER 33
On Inconstancy of Heart

christ. My son, do not trust your affections, for they are changeable and inconstant. All your life you are subject to change, even against your inclination. At one time you are cheerful, at another sad; now peaceful, now troubled; now full of devotion, now wholly lacking it; now zealous, now slothful; now grave, now gay. But the wise man, who is well versed in spiritual matters, stands above these changing emotions. He pays small regard to his momentary feelings and whims, but directs all the powers of his mind towards the right and true end. Thus, having fixed his gaze and kept his intention constantly on Me, he can remain single in purpose, and unshaken under all circumstances.

The more single his purpose, the more steadily will a man pass through all the storms of life. But in many, this single purpose becomes obscured; for men pay ready attention to any pleasant thing that comes their way, and it is a rare thing to find anyone wholly free from the sin of self-interest. Thus the Jews once came out to Bethany to Martha and Mary, not for Jesus' sake only, but to see Lazarus. Therefore make your intention pure, single, and upright, that it may be directed to Me alone without hindrance.

[…]

CHAPTER 36
Against the Vain Judgements of Men

christ. My son, trust in God with all your heart. If your conscience bears witness to your devotion and innocence, you need not fear the judgements of men. It is a good and holy thing to suffer in this way, and it will not be a burden to the humble heart that trusts in God rather than itself. Many people talk too much, and little attention should be paid them. Moreover, it is quite impossible to please everyone. Although Saint Paul endeavoured to be pleasing to all men in the Lord, and became all things to all men, yet he cared very little what they thought of himself. He did whatever lay in his power to bring instruction and salvation to others, but even he could not escape being misjudged and despised by others. Accordingly he trusted himself wholly to God, who knows all things, and opposed the shield of patience and humility to the unjust accusations, empty lies and vain boasts of his detractors. Notwithstanding, sometimes he replied to them, lest his silence should give scandal to the weak.

Why should you fear mortal man? Today he is here; tomorrow he is gone for ever. Fear God, and you need never fear man. What real harm can the words or actions of any man do you? He injures himself rather than you, and he cannot escape the judgement of God, whoever he be. Keep God always before you, and do not engage in bitter controversies. Even if for the present you seem to suffer defeat and undeserved disgrace, do not complain nor lessen your due reward through impatience. Instead, raise your eyes to Me in Heaven, for I have power to deliver you from all shame and wrong, and to reward every man according to his merits.

CHAPTER 37
How Surrender of Self Brings Freedom of Heart

christ. My son, renounce self, and you shall find Me. Retain no private choice or personal interest, and you will always be the gainer. As soon as you yield yourself unreservedly into My hands, I will grant you even richer graces.

the disciple. How often shall I yield myself, and in what way forsake myself, Lord?

christ. Always, and at all times, in small things as well as in great. I make no exceptions, for I desire to have you wholly divested of self: otherwise, unless you are wholly stripped of self-will, how can you be Mine, mine or yours? The sooner you do this, the better it will be with you, and the more completely and sincerely you do it, the better you will please Me, and the greater will be your gain.

Some resign themselves, but with some reservation; these do not put their whole trust in God, and are therefore concerned to provide for themselves. Others at first offer everything, but later are overcome by temptation, and return to their former state. These make very little progress in virtue, and will never obtain the true freedom of heart, nor enjoy the favour of My friendship, unless they first make a complete surrender and daily offering of themselves to Me. Without this, no fruitful union with Me can exist or endure.

I have often said to you, and I now say once more: Renounce yourself, surrender yourself, and you shall enjoy great inner peace. Give all for all, look for nothing, ask nothing in return: rest purely and trustingly in Me, and you shall possess Me. Then you will be free in heart, and no darkness will oppress your soul. Strive for this, pray for this, desire this one thing - that you may be stripped clean of all selfishness, and follow Jesus in complete self-abandonment, dying to self that you may live to Me for ever. Then will all vain fantasies be put to light, and all evil disorders and groundless fears vanish. Then will all fear and dread depart, and all disordered love die in you.

CHAPTER 38
On the Right Ordering of our Affairs

christ. My son, take great care to ensure that in every place, action, and outward occupation you remain inwardly free and your own master. Control circum stances, and do not allow them to control you. Only so can you be master and ruler of your actions, not their servant or slave; a free man and a true Christian, enjoying the freedom and high destiny of the children of God. These stand above the things of time, and view those of eternity, seeing in their true light both earthly and heavenly things. The things of this world have no hold over the children of God; on the contrary, they draw them into their service, and employ them in the ways ordained by God and established by the Heavenly Architect, who has let nothing in His creation without its due place.

Stand firm in all circumstances. Do not judge by outward appearances or reports as men do, but in each instance enter like Moses into the Tabernacle, to ask guidance of the Lord. Sometimes you will receive God's answer, and return instructed on many matters, both present and future. For Moses always had recourse to the Tabernacle to obtain an answer to his doubts and questions, and he took refuge in prayer to support him amidst the dangers and wickednesses of men. Similarly must you take refuge in the depths of your heart, and pray most earnestly for God's help. We read that Joshua and the children of Israel were deceived by the men of Gibeon because they had not first asked counsel of God. Therefore, in giving credit to their statements, they were misled by their pretended piety.

CHAPTER 39
How we should not be Over Anxious

christ. My son, always commit your cause to Me, and I will bring it to a good issue in due time. Wait until I order it, and you will find it to your advantage.

the disciple. Lord, I readily commit everything into your hands, for my own judgement is of small value. I wish I were less concerned about the future, and could unreservedly submit myself to Your good pleasure.

christ. My son, a man often labours incessantly to obtain his desire; but when he has obtained it, he begins to change his mind. For man's affections do not remain constant, but tend to move from one object to another. It is therefore no small advantage, if a man can renounce self even in small things. Man's true spiritual progress depends on the denial of self, and he who renounces self is completely free and secure. But the Old Enemy, the Adversary of all good never ceases to tempt man. Day and night he lies in ambush, hoping to trap the unwary into the snares of his deceit. 'Watch and pray lest you enter into temptation.'

CHAPTER 40
How Man has no Personal Goodness of which to Boast

the disciple. 'Lord, what is man that You are mindful of him, or the son of man, that You visit him?' What has man done to deserve Your grace? Lord, I have no cause to complain if You abandon me; and if You Will is contrary to my desires, I have no right to plead against it. But this I may rightly think and say, 'Lord, I am nothing and I can do nothing. I have no good of Myself, but am imperfect in every respect, and always tend to nothing. Unless You guide my soul and grant me strength, I become weak and completely helpless.'

You, O Lord, remain ever Yourself, abiding in eternity, good, just, and holy, ordering all things in goodness, justice, and holiness, and disposing them in wisdom. But I, who am always more ready to slip back than go forward, never remain the same, for seven times have passed over me. Yet, when You deign to stretch out Your hand to help me, my state is quickly changed for the better; for You alone, and without human aid, can help and strengthen me, so that I may no longer be unstable, but turn my heart to You alone, and be at peace. No mortal man can comfort me, and if only I could wholly renounce all human comfort - whether to increase my devotion, or because my needs compel me to seek You - then I could rightly trust entirely to Your grace, and rejoice in the gift of Your renewed comfort.

Whenever things go well with me, I offer thanks to You, from whom all proceeds. Before You, I am empty nothingness, a weak and unstable man. I have nothing of which to boast, nothing for which I merit any consideration. Can nothing boast of its nothingness? This would be the height of vanity! Empty conceit is like an evil disease, and the most monstrous of vanities, for it leads a man away from true glory, and robs him of heavenly grace. For so long as a man is filled with complacency, he displeases You; and while he hankers after popularity and praise, he is deprived of true virtue. True glory and holy joy are to be found in giving glory not to self, but to You; rejoicing not in one's own strength, but in Your Name; taking no pleasure in creatures, unless it be for Your sake. Praised be Your holy Name, not mine. I will praise your Name, but not my own; I will esteem Your doings, not my own: I will bless Your holy Name. I desire no share in the praises of men. You alone are my glory. You alone are the joy of my heart. I will offer You praise and glory every hour of the day; but for myself, I will glory in nothing, unless it be in my own weakness. Let the Jews seek such glory as men give to one another; I will seek the glory that God alone can give. For all human glory, all this world's honours, all earthly titles, compared with Your eternal glory, are mere vanity and foolishness. O blessed Trinity, my God, my Truth, my Mercy, to You alone let all things ascribe all praise, honour, power, and glory throughout endless ages.

CHAPTER 41
On Contempt for Worldly Honours

christ. My son, do not be discouraged if you see others given honours and advancement, while you are overlooked and humiliated. Lit up your heart to Me in Heaven, and the contempt of men will not trouble you.

the disciple. Lord, we are blind, and are easily deceived through vanity. If I carefully examine my life, I find that no creature has ever done me wrong, and I have no right to complain. But because I have so often and grievously sinned against You, every creature is rightly in aims against me. Shame and contempt are my just due; but to You, O Lord, be praise, honour, and glory. Unless I am ready, willing, and glad to be despised and abandoned by all creatures, and to be regarded as of no consequence, I cannot obtain inward peace and stability, nor can I become spiritually enlightened and fully united to You.

CHAPTER 42
That our Peace cannot Depend on Man

christ. My son, if your peace depends on anyone, by reason of your affection or friendship with him, you will always be unsettled, and dependent on him. But if you turn to the living and eternal Truth, the departure or death of your friend will not distress you. Your love for a friend must rest in Me, and those who are dear to you in this life must be loved only for My sake. No good and lasting friendship can exist without Me, and unless I bless and unite all love it cannot be pure and true. You should be so mortified in your affection towards loved ones that, for your part, you would forego all human companionship. Man draws the nearer to God as he withdraws further from the consolations of this world. And the deeper he descends into himself and the lower he regards himself, the higher he ascends towards God.

He who attributes any goodness to himself, obstructs the coming of God's grace, for the grace of the Holy Spirit always seeks a humble heart. If you would perfectly overcome self and set yourself free from love of creatures, I would come to you with all My grace. But while your interest is in creatures, the vision of the Creator is hidden from you. Learn, then, for love of the Creator, to overcome self in everything, and you shall come to the knowledge of God. But so long as anything, however small, occupies too much of your love and regard, it injures the soul and holds you back from attaining the highest Good.

CHAPTER 43
A Warning against Vain and Worldly Learning

christ. My son, do not allow fair phrases and subtle sayings to beguile you; for the Kingdom of God comes not by words, but by My power. Pay attention to My words, for they fire the heart and lighten the understanding, foster contrition and bring all comfort. Never study in order to appear more wise and learned; study rather to overcome your besetting sins, for this will profit you more than will the grasp of intricate problems.

When you have read and mastered many subjects, always return to this fundamental truth: that I am He who teaches man knowledge, and who grants My children a dearer understanding than man can impart. He whom I teach will swiftly gain wisdom and advance far in the life of the spirit. But those who seek curious knowledge from men, and care nothing for My service, will discover only sorrow. In due time Christ will come, the Teacher of teachers and Lord of Angels. He will hear the lessons of all; that is, He will examine each man's conscience. He will search Jerusalem with lamps; the hidden things of darkness will be brought to light, and the tongues of controversy silenced.

I am God, who enable the humble-minded to understand more of the ways of the everlasting Truth in a single moment than ten years of study in the Schools. I teach in silence, without the clamour of controversy, without ambition for honours, without confusion of argument. I teach men to despise earthly things, to find this present life burdensome, to seek eternal things, to shun honours, to endure injuries, to place all trust in Me, to desire nothing but Myself, and to love Me ardently above all things.

There was once a man who loved Me very dearly, who learned My divine secrets, and spoke eloquently of Me. He profited more by renouncing everything than by studying subtleties. For to some I speak on everyday affairs; to others on particular matters; to some I graciously reveal Myself in signs and symbols, while to those who are enlightened I reveal My mysteries.

A book has but a single voice, but is not equally profitable to all who read it. I alone am the Teacher of truth, the Searcher of man's heart, the Discerner of his doings, and I give to each man as I judge right.

CHAPTER 44
On Avoiding Distractions

christ. My son, you must needs be ignorant of many things: so consider yourself as dead, and crucified to the whole world. Furthermore, you must turn a deaf ear to many things, and consider only such as bring peace. It is better to turn away from controversial matters, and leave everyone to hold their own opinions, than to belabour them with quarrelsome arguments. So long as you remain in God's grace, and carry His Will in your heart, you will more easily endure apparent discomfiture.

the disciple. Lord, to what a pass have we come? We grieve over a worldly loss; we labour and hustle to gain some small profit, forgetting the harm to our souls, and seldom recalling it. We attend to matters of little or no value, and neglect those of the greatest importance. For when a man devotes all his energies to material affairs, he rapidly becomes immersed in them, unless he quickly recovers his senses.

CHAPTER 45
How we should not Believe all we Hear

the disciple. Lord, help me in my trouble, for vain is the help of man. How often have I found no loyalty where I expected to find it! And how often have I found it where I least expected! It is useless to place our hope in man; salvation is to be found in You alone, O God. In all that befalls us, we bless You, O Lord our God.

We are weak and unstable, changeable and easily deceived. None of us can guard himself so carefully and completely that he is never deceived nor in doubt. But whoever trusts in You, Lord, and seeks You with a pure heart, does not easily fall. And if he encounters any trouble, however great it be, You will swiftly deliver or comfort him; for You never abandon those who trust in You to the end. Rare indeed is a faithful friend, who stands by his friend in all trouble. And You, Lord, are the most faithful of all friends, and there is none like You.

How wise was the holy soul (Saint Agatha) who said, 'My mind is firmly established and grounded in Christ.' Were this true of myself, I should never fear any man, and no bitter words could disturb me. We cannot foresee the future or provide against evils to come; and if things that we expect often harm us, how can unexpected events do otherwise than seriously harm us? Why have I not made better provision for my unfortunate self, and why have I trusted so readily in others? For we are but mortal men, and nothing if not weak, even if many people imagine and say that we are angels. There is none in whom I can trust, Lord, save Yourself, who are the Truth, and who neither deceives nor can be deceived. But every man is deceitful, weak, unstable and fallible, especially in what he says, so that we should not at once believe even what at first appears to be true.

Your wisdom warns us to beware of man, since a man's enemies are those of his own household, and we may not believe any who says, 'He is here, or 'He is there'. I have learned this to my cost, and I only hope that it may make me more careful and correct my foolishness. 'Be discreet,' says one: 'Be discreet, and keep what I tell you to yourself.' And while I remain silent about it, imagining it to be a secret, he cannot himself keep the silence which he enjoined on me, but at once betrays both himself and me, and goes on his way. From such tales and from such indiscreet folk, protect me, O Lord! Do not let me fall into their power, nor behave in the same way myself. Make my conversation truthful and trustworthy, far removed from slyness. For what I do not tolerate in others, I must myself avoid at all costs.

To remain silent about others makes for peace and goodwill, neither believing all that is said, nor repeating what one has heard. There are few to whom we should open our hearts, but we should always seek You, who see into all hearts. We may not allow ourselves to be carried to and fro by the windy blast of words, but rather pray that all our life, both public and private, may be ordered in conformity to Your Will.

A sure way of retaining the grace of heaven is to disregard outward appearances, and diligently to cultivate such things as foster amendment of life and fervour of soul, rather than to cultivate those qualities that seem most popular.

Very many people have been harmed by publicity and by lightly-bestowed praise of their virtues. But grace is most powerful when preserved in silence in this transitory life, which consists wholly of temptation and warfare.

[…]

CHAPTER 51
How when we Lack Strength for Higher Work we should Undertake Humble Tasks

christ. My son, you cannot always bum with zeal for virtue, nor remain constantly in high contemplation; the weakness of sinful human nature will at times compel you to descend to lesser things, and bear with sorrow the burdens of this present life. So long as you wear this mortal body, you will be subject to weariness and sadness of heart. Therefore, in this life, you will often lament the burden of the body, which hinders your giving yourself wholly to the life of the spirit and to divine contemplation.

When this happens, you will be wise to resort to humble, exterior tasks, and to restore yourself by good works. Await My coming with unshakeable trust, and bear your exile and desolation of spirit with patience until I come again and set you free from all anxiety. Then you will forget all your former toil, and will enjoy inward peace. I will unfold he fore you the fair fields of the Scriptures, and you shall advance in the way of My commandments with heart at liberty. Then you shall say, 'The sufferings of this present time are not worthy to be compared with the glory that shall be revealed in us. '

[…]

CHAPTER 53
How God's Grace is not Granted to the Worldly-Minded

christ. My son, My grace is precious, and may not be mingled with worldly concerns and pleasures. Therefore, if you wish to receive it, you must remove every obstacle to grace. Seek out a place apart, and love the solitary life. Do not engage in conversation with men, but instead pour forth devout prayer to God, that you may preserve a humble mind and a clean conscience. Count the whole world as nothing, and place attendance on God before all outward things. For you cannot attend on Me, and at the same time take pleasure in worldly things. Remain detached from acquaintances and friends and independent of this world's consolations. It is for this reason that the blessed Apostle Peter begs all the faithful in Christ to keep themselves as strangers and pilgrims in this world.

With what confidence will a man meet death, to whom no worldly affection clings! But a weak soul cannot bear to be thus detached from all things, nor can a worldly-minded man understand the freedom of the spiritual man. Nevertheless, when a man sincerely desires to be spiritual, he must renounce all, both friend and stranger, and must beware of none more than himself. If you can win complete mastery over self, you will easily master all else. To triumph over self is the perfect victory. For whoever so controls himself that his passions are subject to his reason, and his reason wholly subject to Me, is master both of himself and of the world.

If you aspire to reach this height of perfection, you must make a brave beginning. Lay the axe to the roots, to cut out and destroy all inordinate and secret love of self, and of any personal and material advantage. From this vice of inordinate self-love spring nearly all those other failings that have to be completely overcome. But as soon as this evil is mastered and subdued, great peace and lasting tranquillity will follow. But few endeavour to die completely to self, and to rise wholly above it; consequently, they remain absorbed in themselves, and quite unable to rise in spirit above self. He who desires to walk with Me in true freedom must mortify all irregular and undisciplined desires, and have no selfish longing for any creature.

CHAPTER 54
On the Contrary Workings of Nature and Grace

christ. My son, carefully observe the impulses of nature and grace, for these are opposed one to another, and work in so subtle a manner that even a spiritual, holy and enlightened man can hardly distinguish them. All men do in fact desire what is good, and in what they say and do pretend to some kind of goodness, so that many are deceived by their appearance of virtue.

Nature is crafty, and seduces many, snaring and deceiving them, and always works for her own ends. But Grace moves in simplicity, avoiding every appearance of evil. She makes no attempt to deceive, and does all things purely for love of God, in whom she rests as her final goal.

Nature is unwilling to be mortified, checked or overcome, obedient or willingly subject. Grace mortifies herself, resists sensuality, submits to control, seeks to be overcome. She does not aim at enjoying her own liberty, but loves to be under discipline; and does not wish to lord it over anyone. Rather does she desire to live, abide and exist always under God's rule, and for His sake she is ever ready to submit it to all men.

Nature works for her own interest, and estimates what profit she may derive from others. Grace does not consider what may be useful or convenient to herself, but only what may be to the good of many. Nature is eager to receive honour and reward: Grace faithfully ascribes all honour and glory to God. Nature fears shame and contempt: Grace is glad to suffer reproach for the Name of Jesus. Nature loves ease and rest for the body; Grace cannot be idle, but welcomes work cheerfully.

Nature loves to enjoy rare and beautiful things, and hates the cheap and clumsy. Grace takes pleasure in simple and humble things, neither despising the rough, nor refusing to wear the old and ragged. Nature pays regard to temporal affairs, takes pleasure in this world's wealth, grieves at any loss, and is angered by a slighting remark. But Grace pays attention to things eternal, and is not attached to the temporal. The loss of goods fails to move her, or hard words to anger her, for she lays up her treasure and joy in Heaven where none of it can be lost.

Nature is greedy, and grasps more readily than she gives, loving to retain things for her personal use. But Grace is kind and generous, shuns private interest, is contented with little, and esteems it more blest to give than to receive. Nature inclines a man towards creatures - to the body, to vanities, to restlessness. But Grace draws a man towards God and virtue. Renouncing creatures, she flees the world, loathes the lusts of the flesh, limits her wanderings, and shuns public appearances. Nature is eager to enjoy any outward comfort that will gratify the senses. Grace seeks comfort in God alone, and delights in the Sovereign Good above all visible things.

Nature does everything for her own gain and interest; she does nothing without fee, hoping either to obtain some equal or greater return for her services, or else praise and favour. But Grace seeks no worldly return, and asks for no reward, but God alone. She desires no more of the necessaries of life than will serve her to obtain the things of eternity.

Nature takes pleasure in a host of friends and relations; she boasts of noble rank and high birth; makes herself agreeable to the powerful, flatters the rich, and acclaims those who are like herself. But Grace loves even her enemies, takes no pride in the number of her friends, and thinks little of high birth unless it be allied to the greater virtue. She favours the poor rather than the rich, and has more in common with the honourable than with the powerful. She takes pleasure in an honest man, not in a deceiver; she constantly encourages good men to labour earnestly for the better gifts, and by means of these virtues to become like the Son of God.

Nature is quick to complain of want and hardship; but Grace bears poverty with courage. Nature, struggling and striving on her own behalf, turns everything to her own interest: but Grace refers all things to God, from whom they come. She attributes no good to herself; she is not arrogant and presumptuous. She does not argue and exalt her own opinions before others, but submits all her powers of mind and perception to the eternal wisdom and judgement of God. Nature is curious to know secrets and to hear news; she loves to be seen in public, and to enjoy sensations. She desires recognition, and to do such things as win praise and admiration. But Grace does not care for news or novelties, because all these things spring from the age-old corruption of man, for there is nothing new or lasting in this world.

Grace therefore teaches us how the senses are to be disciplined and vain complacency avoided; how anything likely to excite praise and admiration should be humbly concealed; and how in all things and in all knowledge some useful fruit should be sought, together with the praise and honour of God. She wants no praise for herself or her doings, but desires that God may be blessed in His gifts, who out of pure love bestows all things.

Grace is a supernatural light, and the especial gift of God, the seal of His chosen and the pledge of salvation, which raises man from earthly things to love the heavenly, and from worldly makes him spiritual. The more, therefore, that Nature is controlled and overcome, the richer is the grace bestowed, while man is daily renewed by fresh visitations after the likeness of God.

CHAPTER 55
On the Corruption of Nature, and the Power of Grace

the disciple. O Lord my God, You have created me in Your own image and likeness. Grant me this great grace, so necessary to my salvation, that I may conquer the base elements of my nature, that drag me down into sin and perdition. Within my being I can feel the power of sin contending against the rule of my mind, leading me away an obedient slave to all kinds of sensuality. I cannot resist its onslaughts, unless Your most holy grace is poured glowing into my heart to help me.

I need Your grace in fullest measure, to subdue that nature which always inclines to evil from my youth up. For it fell through Adam the first of men, and was tainted by sin, the penalty of that fault descending upon all mankind. Thus the nature which You created good and upright has now become the very symbol of corruption and weakness, for when let to itself, it leans always towards evil and base things. The little strength that remains is only like a small spark, buried beneath ashes. Yet this same natural reason, though hidden in profound darkness, still retains the power to know good and evil, and to discern truth and falsehood. But it is powerless to do what it knows to be good, neither does it enjoy the full light of truth, nor its former healthy affections.

Thus, O Lord my God, it comes about that, while I inwardly delight in Your law, and know Your commands to be good, just, and holy, both for the condemnation of all evil and the avoiding of sin, yet in my body I serve the law of sin, and obey my senses before my reason. Hence, while I indeed possess the will to good, I find myself powerless to follow it. In this way, I make many good resolutions, but, through lack of grace to support my weakness, any small obstacle causes discouragement and failure. Thus, too, I know the way of perfection, and see clearly enough what I ought to do; but I am borne down by the burden of my own corruption, and advance no nearer to perfection.

Lord, how urgently I need Your grace if I am to undertake, carry out and perfect any good work! Without it, I can achieve nothing; but in You and by the power of Your grace, all things are possible. O true and heavenly grace, without which our own merits are nothing, and our natural gifts of no account! Neither arts nor riches, beauty nor strength, genius nor eloquence have any value in Your eyes, Lord, unless allied to grace. For the gifts of nature are common to good men and bad alike, but grace or love are Your especial gift to those whom You choose, and those who are sealed with this are counted worthy of life everlasting. So excellent is this grace that neither the gift of prophecy, nor the working of miracles, nor any speculation, however sublime, is of any value without it. Indeed, not even faith, or hope, or any other virtue is acceptable to You without love and grace.

O most blessed grace, that makes the poor in spirit rich in virtues, and the richly blessed humble in heart! Come, descend on me! Fill me with your comfort, lest my soul faint from weariness and dryness of mind. I pray, Lord, that I may find favour in Your sight, for Your grace is sufficient for me, even if I obtain none of those things that nature desires. However often I am tempted and troubled, I will fear no evil so long as Your grace remains with me.

Your grace is my strength, my counsel, and my help. It is more powerful than all my enemies, and wiser than all the wise. It is the teacher of truth, the instructor of doctrine, the light of the heart, the consoler of affliction. It banishes sorrow, drives away fear, fosters devotion, and moves to contrition. With out grace, I am nothing but a dry tree, a barren stock fit only for destruction. Therefore, O Lord, let Your grace always lead and follow me, and keep me ever intent on good works, through Your Son Jesus Christ. Amen.

[…]

CHAPTER 57
That we should never Despair

christ. My son, patience and humility in adversity are more pleasing to Me than great devotion and comfort in times of ease. Why are you so distressed when you are criticized in some small matter? Had it been a far more serious matter, that is no reason for your being disturbed. Let it pass. It is not your first mistake, or anything new; nor, if you live long, will it be your last. You are brave enough when you meet no opposition. You can give good advice and encouragement to others, but when trouble knocks unexpectedly at your own door, your strength and judgement fail you. Remember the great weakness you often experience in small troubles; yet these things happen for your own good.

Banish discouragement from your heart as best you can, and if trouble comes, never let it depress or hinder you for long. At the least, bear it bravely if you cannot bear it cheerfully. Even if you are reluctant to bear it, and feel indignant, yet control yourself, and let no rash words escape you that may harm Christ's little ones. The violence of your feelings will soon subside, and grace return to heal your inner pain. 'I live,' says the Lord, 'ready to help and comfort you more than ever, if you will trust Me and call on Me with devotion.'

Be of good heart, and steel yourself to endure greater trials. All is not lost, however often you feel tempted or sorely troubled. You are a man, not God; you are human, not an angel. How can you expect to remain always in a constant state of virtue, when this was not possible even for an angel of Heaven, nor for the first man in the Garden? I am He who grants healing and comfort to those in distress, and I raise up to My Divinity those who acknowledge their weakness.

the disciple. Lord, blessed are Your words! They are sweeter to my mouth than honey and the honeycomb. What would I do in such trials and troubles as mine, if You did not uphold me with Your holy words? So long as I come at last to the haven of salvation, what matters the kind or magnitude of my sufferings? Grant me a holy end, and a joyful passing out of this world. Remember me, O my God, and lead me in the right way to Your Kingdom.

天使

天使（angel）一词，在希腊语中是信使之意。波斯人有佩里斯[1]、希伯来人有马拉克姆（Malakim），希腊人则有代莫诺伊（Daimonoi）。知晓了这些人物，我们对天使就有了非常深刻的认识。

然而，我们却发现一个非常有趣的事实，极具启发性，那就是人的思想在潜意识中，总想在神与人之间安排一些中间角色。于是，早在远古时期，就创造了魔鬼与魔仆。人间的帝王国君也通过信使发布诏令，当然上帝也指派了自己的使者，比如墨丘利（Mercury）和艾里斯（Iris），他们都是使者，都是上帝的信使。

而希伯来人，作为唯一接受过上帝亲自引导的人类子民，起初并未给神赐的天使们命名，而是在被囚禁于巴比伦之时，借用迦勒底人（Chaldeans）给的名字。米迦勒（Michael）和加百列（Gabriel）两位天使最先由但以理（Daniel）命名，彼时他还是一名被困于巴比伦的犹太人奴隶。而居住在尼尼微（Nineveh）的犹太人托比特（Tobit），在与儿子一同去向犹太人加倍尔（Gabael）收账的路途中结识了天使拉斐尔（Raphael）。

然而，贵为犹太人教规的《利未记》和《申命记》却丝毫未曾提及过天使的存在，遑论尊崇。更有甚者，撒都该人（Sadducees），即古代犹太人，根本就不相信天使。

可是，犹太人在他们的历史故事中又对天使之事讨论颇多。他们认为天使是有形的，背生双翼，与异教徒所伪称的墨丘利脚踝处生有双翼如出一辙。有时，天使们能将双翼隐匿于衣裳之内，他们能吃能喝，并能在营救罗德（Loth）之时，吸引索多玛（Sodom）人对其欲行淫辱之事，所以怎能说天使们没有肉身呢？

据迈蒙尼德（Maimonides）所言，古代犹太人传统上认为天使有十级天阶之分：1.纯粹圣洁的圣天使（chaios acodesh）；2.敏捷迅速的座天使（ofanim）；3.强壮有力的力天使（oralim）；4.神之火焰的焰天使（chasmalim）；5.生命之火的炽天使（seraphim）；6.上帝信使及副手玛拉基（malachim）；7.神之判官埃洛伊（eloim）；8.神之子（ben eloim）；9.神之像（cherubim）；10.神之肉身（ychim）。

《摩西五经》并未记载有关天使堕落的故事，最先声称此事的是先知以赛亚（Isaiah），他在向巴比伦国王惊叹之时，说道：“称颂者到底怎么了？对于他的堕落，松柏之类的正直之人都拍手称快？从天堂坠落，你到底怎么样了？哦，赫勒（Hellel），晨之明星？”这里的赫勒译为拉丁文时变成了路西法（Lucifer），随后路西法这个名字，饱含寓意，给予了在天堂中参加过战斗的天使长。最终，这个本意为晨星与黎明的名字，成了魔鬼的代名词。

基督教的信仰是以天使的堕落为基础的。那些反叛的天使，被驱逐出久居的天界，驱赶至地球中心的地狱，最终变成了魔鬼。而化身为蛇的魔鬼引诱了夏娃，让人类受到诅咒。耶稣前来救赎人类，最终战胜了恶魔，但是恶魔现在仍然还在引诱我们。然而，这一圣传仅见于旁经《以诺书》，并且与公认的圣传也存在巨大差异。

圣·奥古斯丁（Saint Augustine）在他的第109封信中，毫不犹豫地赋予了善、恶两类天使苗条敏捷的身形。不同于犹太人认为的天使有10个等级，教皇格列高利二世将天使等级浓缩至9个，分别是：炽天使（seraphim）、智天使（cherubim）、座天使（thrones）、主天使（dominations）、德天使（virtues）、力天使（powers）、天使长（archangels），以及给予其他8级天使名字的天使。

在犹太人的神殿中，有两位智天使，均是牛鹰二首六翼。现在我们在绘画中，将他们描绘成一个飞翔着、耳下生有一对微型翅膀的脑袋。而天使和天使长在绘画中的形象则是背生双翼的婴孩。至于座天使和主天使，还没有人考虑过去描绘他们的形象。

圣·托马斯（Saint Tomas），在《诫命108》（Question 108）中的第二章中说到，与炽天使一样，座天使和智天使都与上帝很亲近，因为他们都是上帝的座驾。斯科茨（Scotus）曾统计过天使的数量，总共约有10万名。东方、希腊和罗马古典神话中都存在善恶天使，这说明了每个人都有善恶天使之分，从生至死，一个助人，一个害人。但我们现在仍不清楚这些善恶天使是否能从一端不断转移到另一端，是否得到了救赎。关于这个问题，可以参见圣·托马斯的神学总论。

至于天使住在哪儿，是住在天空中，在虚空里，抑或是行星上，我们都不得而知。当然上帝也不希望我们知道。

动物

动物如同机器，是被剥夺了认知与感觉的死物，它们日复一日，重复着相同的动作，学习不了，进步不得，如此云云，而持有此等看法的人实在是太粗鄙无知了！

确实如此！一只鸟儿倚墙筑巢时造半圆巢，倚角筑巢时造四分之一圆巢，倚树筑巢时便造圆形巢，这只鸟儿做所有事不都是这样吗？一只你已经训练了3个月的猎狗，难道经过训练后，它还没有之前懂得更多吗？金丝雀能立即重复你所教的曲调吗？你不是要花很长时间教它吗？你没见过它犯错误，然后更正自己吗？

你判断我有感觉、有记忆、有思想，是因为我向你提过这些吗？不！我没有提过。你见我回到家中，神情忧虑，动作急切地要寻找报纸，我记得将报纸放在了抽屉里，于是我拉开抽屉，找到了报纸，随后开心地开始看报。你判断我有过忧虑、有过快乐，也判断我有记忆、有认知。

那就以同样的方式来看待一只找不见主人的狗。它在每条过道上来回寻觅，叫声悲戚，躁动不安，在楼梯间上上下下，逐个屋子寻找主人的踪影。最终，它在书房找到了亲爱的主人，通过轻声叫唤，上下跳跃，来回蹭抚来表现它万分欣喜的心情。

然而，野蛮人却抓住了这只远比人类更看重友谊的狗。他们将它固定在桌子上，活生生地解剖了它，向人展示它的肠膜系静脉。你会发现它具备所有你拥有的感觉器官。机械论者，回答我，自然让这动物具备所有的感觉器官，难道只是为了让它无法感知吗？它能无动于衷吗？不要假想自然会制造这种荒谬的矛盾。

可是，这一学派的领袖们却在探问动物的灵魂。我不懂这个问题：一棵树能借助纤维吸收在树体内循环的树液，也能发芽、长叶和结果，你会问我什么是树的灵魂吗？它已经获得了那些馈赠；动物有感觉，有记忆，还有些想法。那是谁给予了这些馈赠？是谁赋予了它们这样的能力？就是那能让土地上的草木生长，能让地球被太阳吸引之人。

亚里士多德说：“动物的灵魂是以实体形式存在着的。”持此相同看法的在后世相继有阿拉伯学派、天使学派和索邦神学，此后就后继无人了。

另外一些哲学家们则认为：“动物的灵魂是物质的。”其实相较其他人，此种观点也未取得多大进步。当被问到什么是物质性灵魂时，这些哲学家们也答不上来。于是，他们不得不承认物质性灵魂其实就只是个感觉问题而已。然而，究竟是什么给予了这种感觉呢？答案就是实质性灵魂，换言之，是一个实质性灵魂给予另一个实质性灵魂感觉。这种循环，他们不能打破。

让我们来听听其他动物们对动物的解读吧。他们声称灵魂是一个灵性的存在体，肉体死亡时，灵魂也随之消散，但是又有什么证据来证明这种灵魂的存在呢？你又是如何看待这种灵性的存在体的呢？这些存在体在现实生活中有感觉、有记忆、有想法、懂适应，却永不知道一个6岁的小孩懂得什么？你又是依据什么来想象这种不是肉体的存在体会随着肉体的死亡而消亡呢？最愚蠢的人莫过于那些声称灵魂既非肉体又非灵体的人。您看这有一个绝佳的理论！说到灵体，我们知道是非肉身的、但未可知的东西，仅此而已。于是，这些绅士们的理论逻辑就是这样的：动物的灵魂是个实体，但这个实体既非肉身，也非不是肉身的东西。

话说回来，引起如此多矛盾性错误的原因到底是什么呢？原因就在于人类那在弄清楚事物是否存在之前，先弄清楚这个事物究竟是什么的长久习惯。移动的榫舌、风箱的阀门，就被称作是风箱的灵魂。那什么是灵魂呢？在我看来，灵魂就是那阀门，当我鼓动风箱时，它下降、引入空气、扩张自己、再将空气挤压进入管道。

在这里，我们没有异于机器的灵魂。但究竟是什么鼓动了动物的“风箱”呢？我已经告诉了你，操控之人就是那操控天地星辰之人。那位说着“Deus est anima brutorum”（上帝是动物们的灵魂）的哲人无疑是正确的，可惜他本可以走得更远。

反三位一体论者

非基督徒的异教徒们虽然认同耶稣是救世主，是人神的中间人，但是他们却绝不认同基督徒们所普遍接受的一条教义，即：位格三位一体，三种位格同时存在于同一神圣本体中，第二位格（圣子）由第一位格（圣父）所生，第三位格（圣灵）由其他两位位格所出。异教徒们认为此条教义最有悖于逻辑。

这条难以理解的教义并未出现在《圣经》之中。

没有经文能赋予它权威，也没有文章能让它在不偏离《圣经》文本本意的情况下，获得更清晰、更自然、与真理和常识更一致的蕴意。

相信在同一神圣本体中存在几种不同的位格，那么圣父（耶和华）就不再是唯一的真神，圣子和圣灵也加入了真神的行列。而这种观念，是基督教犯下的最愚笨无知、最危险万分的错误，因为这根本就是在提倡多神论，做法与基督教的反对者们如出一辙。

声称只有唯一的真神，同时也声称唯一的真神拥有三种位格，并且每种位格都是真神。这两种说法本就相互矛盾。

一个本体和三种位格的区分在《圣经》中从未出现。

这明显是个错误，因为本体不可能少于位格，位格也不可能少于本体。

三位一体中的三种位格，或者说是三种不同的实体，或者说是神圣本体的外性，又或者说是那本就无差别的同一本体。

第一种情况，创造了三个神。

第二种情况，神由诸多外性组成，人信奉外性，并将外性变异成位格。

第三种情况，一个不可分割的主体被毫无用处、毫无根据地分割开来，在主体内部并未进行区分的东西被区分为三种。

如果说，这三种个性既不是神圣本体中的不同实体，也不是神圣本体中的外性，那么人们就很难说服自己这三种个性到底是什么。

当然，也不可相信最顽固、最坚定的三位一体论者，对于这三种位格，在不分割实体，从而不增多数量的情况下，是以何种方式存在于神体内的这个问题，会有何种见解。

连圣·奥古斯丁在此问题上历经了千次论证推理之后，仍觉错误和晦涩，他也不得不承认三位一体说不清、道不明。

后来，三位一体论者引述了这位神父的话（这做法实际上非常异常）：“当被问到这三者到底是什么时，人类的语言已不足以去表达，也没有特定术语去描述这三者。而说到存在三种位格，其实我们不是为了表达些什么，而是因为我们必须要说些什么，不能保持沉默。（Dictum est tres personae, non ut aliquid diceretur, sed ne taceretur.）”（《论三位一体》V.ix）

现代神学家对此问题也没有更好的阐述。

当被问到如何理解“位格”一词时，他们只是解释说，这是一种特定的、难以言说的划分方式，让人们在唯一的神圣本体中去区分圣父、圣子和圣灵。

对这些术语的解释，他们的回答难以让人满意。因为依他们所言，这些术语表明，三位一体中的三种位格存在着令人难以理解的关系。

据上所述，我们可以概括出，现代神学家与正统基督教信奉者之间的基本争论就在于此问题上，即上帝是否有三者之分（这三者我们毫无概念），以及这三者之间是否存在特定的联系（这种联系我们也丝毫不知）。

基于上述所言，现代神学家们作出结论，认为相信使徒们的权威，遵从他们的做法将会明智许多。使徒们从不讨论三位一体，在宗教活动里也从不使用《圣经》中未出现过的术语，比如三位一体、位格、本体、本质、本质的、身合、道成肉身、创世、圣灵的发出等诸如此类的术语。这些术语毫无实际意义，不指代自然界中的任何真实存在的东西，只能在理解上引发错误、模糊、晦涩且不完善的想法。

“地上三者做见证，生命之液、水、血液，此三者为一体。天上三者做见证，圣父、圣言和圣灵，此三者为一体。”此段文字选自《约翰福音》中的使徒书信，《约翰福音》由福音传道者约翰撰写。大师卡尔梅（dom Calmet）在其论文中针对此段文字做过一些评述。他承认这两段文字从未出现在任何古《圣经》之中。他认为如果圣·约翰在一封书信中提到了三位一体，却在他自己撰写的福音书中只字不提，这做法未免太过奇怪。另外在福音书权威版中也找不到与此教条相关的任何痕迹，在《新约》外典中也是如此。所有这些原因，也许就能解释为什么反三位一体论者成功地让历届宗教会议没有正式确认三位一体论。但是，异教徒们对宗教会议常常不以为意，因此我们也不知道应当如何去说服他们。就让我们单纯地相信反三位一体，并希望他们也能如此。

启示录

殉道者贾斯廷（Justin Martyr）记录了公元170年的历史，他首次提到了《启示录》，并认为该书的作者是耶稣门徒、福音传道者圣·约翰。在与犹太人泰福（Trypho）的对话中，当他被问到是否相信耶路撒冷终有一天会复原如初时，贾斯廷给予了肯定回答，就像其他所有拥有正统思想的基督徒那样。他说道：“我们之中有位名叫约翰的人，是耶稣十二门徒之一，约翰预言说，耶路撒冷的信徒前后将延续1000年之久。”

统治1000年这个观念长久地扎根在基督徒的思想里，这段时期是绅士贵族们的最爱。埃及人的灵魂在千年之末可修复肉身。而在同样的时空里，维吉尔（Virgil）笔下的灵魂正在炼狱中接受审判。1000年后的新耶路撒冷将有十二道门，来纪念十二门徒，门的形状为正方形，长宽高均为12000视距尺（stadia）[2]，即500里格（league）[3]，也就是说门的高度也有500里格之高，住在顶层想必会极不舒适。然而，这就是《启示录》第21章中的预言。

坚信圣·约翰是《启示录》作者的人，贾斯廷是第一位。然而也有人反对他的说法，因为贾斯廷在与犹太人泰福的对话中还说过，根据门徒们的描述，耶稣基督在进入约旦之时，约旦河河水翻滚沸腾，漫天火焰。然而，并无门徒有此类记载。

贾斯廷还非常自信地引用了西比尔巫语。更有甚者，他还声称在埃及法洛斯岛灯塔（Pharos）处看到了疯人院遗迹，该院在希律王（Herod）时期曾关押了72位释道者。有人很不幸地见过这些疯人院，那人的证词似乎暗示着贾斯廷也曾被关押在那儿。

稍晚时期出现，并也坚信千禧年的圣·艾雷尼厄斯（Saint Irenaeus）说过，他从一位老人那儿得知圣·约翰撰写了《启示录》一书。然而，圣·艾雷尼厄斯自己也饱受责难，因为他认为世上只有4册福音书，原因在于世界只有4部分、只有4种主要风向以及以西结（Ezekiel）只看到了4种动物。他将这种逻辑推理过程称之为论证。我们必须承认，艾雷尼厄斯所做的论证推理，与贾斯廷的所见所闻，同样精彩绝伦。

亚历山大的克莱门特（Clement of Alexandria）在他的《雷克塔》（Electa）中提到说，圣·约翰仅仅只撰写了一项启示录，但此项非常重要。德尔图良（Tertullian）是一名伟大而虔诚的教徒，坚信千禧年，他不仅断言圣·约翰预言了耶路撒冷的复兴，以及信徒将统治耶路撒冷1000年之久，还声称新的耶路撒冷已经开始形成。巴勒斯坦的所有基督教徒，甚至异教徒，在夜之末尾已经连续40天看到了新的耶路撒冷，但不幸的是，这座城市白天一旦来临便消失无踪。

在圣·约翰福音书的前言中，以及奥利金（Origen）的《圣经讲道》（Homilies）里都引用了《启示录》中的神谕，但是他也引用了西比尔巫语。圣徒亚历山大的丹尼斯（Saint Denis of Alexandria），他记录了截至三世纪中期的历史，在他的分章之一（此分章由尤西比乌斯保存）中提到，几乎所有的有识之士都认为《启示录》成书必有渊源。也提到说此书的作者并不是圣·约翰，而是一名叫作克林妥（Cerinthus）的人，此人借用了约翰这个伟大的名字，以便让他的思想得以传播。

于公元360年举行的老底嘉（Laodicea）宗教会议并未将《启示录》纳入正典书卷。奇怪的是老底嘉宗教会议作为宣扬《启示录》的目标场所，竟然拒绝了这本是它命中注定的财富。此外，参与该会议的以弗所（Ephesus）的主教们，竟然也拒绝承认《启示录》的作者就是安葬在以弗所的圣·约翰。

由此可见，圣·约翰就算身处坟墓，仍然极具影响力，能够不间断地将这世间捣鼓得上上下下。相信圣·约翰并未真正死亡的人，也认定《启示录》并非他所作。但是，千禧年的信奉者仍对此坚信不疑。苏尔比基乌斯·塞维鲁（Sulpicius Severus）在其《宗教史》第九卷中说到，那些不承认、不接受《启示录》的人是无情且不恭的。后经历诸多犹疑，历经教会万般责难，苏尔比基乌斯·塞维鲁的观点最终获胜。此事经过阐释，教会最终认定《启示录》由圣·约翰所作，无可争辩，此后再无上诉。

基督教各教派团体都结合自身情况，对《启示录》中的预言加以运用。英国人受此预言启发，发动了英国大革命，路德教派给德国造成了不小的麻烦，法国革命者推翻了查理九世的统治，以及凯瑟琳·德·梅迪茜（Catherine de Medicis）的摄政。这些都是秉持正义，行大道的行动。博胥埃（Bossuet）和牛顿都为《启示录》撰写了评论。然而，总体来说，博胥埃和牛顿之所以声名远播，更多的是因为激昂演说与伟大发现，而非他们对《启示录》所作的评论。

无神论者和无神论

I

在以前的时代，每一位拥有秘密技能的人都有被当成巫师的风险；每一种新生的教派都会被谴责说在秘密宗教仪式中屠杀孩童；每一位不屑于僵化教条的思想家都会饱受愚蠢之人的谴责，被狂热分子、无赖流氓指责为无神论者。

勇敢的阿那克萨哥拉（Anaxagoras）坚持认为双轮战车上的阿波罗并不是太阳神，他就被世人称作是无神论者，从而不得不开始逃亡。

亚里士多德也曾被一名教士谴责持有无神论，亚里士多德非但没能成功地惩罚这位谴责者，反而是自己隐退到了卡尔基斯（Chalcas）。然而，希腊历史上最可憎的事件就是苏格拉底之死。阿里斯托芬尼（Aristophanes）（评论家们多倾慕此人，因为他是希腊人，但评论家们似乎忘记了苏格拉底也是希腊人）是第一个让希腊人相信苏格拉底是无神论者的人。

而我们现在的社会，是不会容忍阿里斯托芬这种既不喜剧也不诗人的喜剧诗人颠倒黑白，将圣·劳伦特（Saint-Laurent）的光明正义塑造成滑稽丑剧的。在我看来，阿里斯托芬此人比普鲁塔克笔下所描绘的更加低贱不堪，卑鄙无耻。充满智慧的普鲁塔克这样评价这个骗子，“阿里斯托芬的语言泄露了他卑鄙的品行：他的语言完全是由最低下，最恶心的嘲弄言语组成，人们不会觉得有趣，有识之士与谦谦君子也会发现他人品不佳，他的傲慢，让人难以忍受，体面人着实厌恶他的恶毒。”

紧接着上场的就是滑稽剧中的小丑塔伯里（Tabarin）。顺便提一句，达希耶夫人（Mme Dacier），苏格拉底的崇拜者，竟然也对塔伯里十分仰慕。塔伯里准备了毒药，毒药被那臭名昭著的法官使用，毒死了希腊史上道德最崇高的人。

雅典城里的制革工人、补鞋匠和裁缝们都为一个滑稽剧拍手喝彩，在这剧中，苏格拉底被人用篮子吊在半空中，公然宣告世上没有上帝，并吹嘘说他在教授哲学之时还偷了一件外套。整整一个民族，他们的政府允许的自由竟然如此伤风败俗，实在是应当好好享受发生在他们身上的报应，即先成为罗马人的奴隶，如今又受到土耳其人的奴役。

我们先忽略罗马共和国与我们的时代相距的这一整段时期。罗马人要比希腊人明智得多，他们从不因为哲学家的观点而去迫害他们，所以并不能认为罗马帝国的继承者是野蛮人。神圣罗马帝国皇帝腓德烈二世一与教皇闹掰，就被教皇谴责说是无神论者，指责他与他的总理大臣德·维内斯（de Vineis）共同撰写了《三个骗子》（Three Impostors】）这本书。

当伟大的总理大臣洛比达（de L' Hospital）宣称要反对迫害时，他立刻被谴责信仰无神论。一个耶稣会士的身份不及阿里斯托芬尼，正如阿里斯托芬尼的身份比不上荷马一样。然而在宗教狂热者眼中，荷马这可怜人的名字也会变得荒谬无比。总之，在耶稣会士格拉斯（Garasse）眼中，他会发现到处都有无神论者，他谎称西奥多·德·贝茨（Théodore de Bèze）是个无神论者，也引导大众误解瓦尼尼（Vanini）。

瓦尼尼悲惨的结局并未像苏格拉底的死那样让我们满怀遗憾和愤慨，因为他只是一个毫无功绩的外邦空谈家。但是，瓦尼尼毕竟不是一个所谓的无神论者。恰好相反，他是一个贫穷的那不勒斯教士，职业的传道士和神学者，他探究事物的本质，宇宙的共性，他的内心里没有一丝无神论的思想。他对上帝的理解在神学上是最彻底、最正确的。在他看来：上帝是众生之父、无需任何人；是脱离时间限制的永恒存在，无处不在却又从不现身；上帝没有过去，没有未来，他超越、统治和拥有所有事物；他亘古不变，无穷无尽，却又永不分离，他的力量就是他的意愿，等等。

柏拉图认为上帝创造万物，从最微小至最宏大，形成一条生命链，而这一生命链的顶端则系于上帝那永恒的王座之上。瓦尼尼深信此点，以复兴柏拉图的美好理想为己任，并深以为傲，还得到了阿威罗伊（Averroes）的支持。实际上，这种想法比真理更崇高，而这种想法离无神论如此之远，就如同生命之远离虚空。

瓦尼尼四处游历以寻找财富，却不断陷入争论。而这些争论很不幸地让他远离了财富。他树立死敌的数量等同于与之理论的学者和学究们的数量。瓦尼尼的不幸并无他因，只因他在争论中所表现出的狂热与野蛮招致了很多神学家的憎恶。他与一个叫弗兰科（Francon）或称弗兰科尼（Franconi）的人发生过争执，而这个弗兰科又是他敌人们的朋友，理所当然，弗兰科指责他是传播无神论的无神论者。

这位弗兰科（或弗兰科尼），凭借少数几名证人，在审判瓦尼尼期间，泯灭人性地坚持自己的说辞。交叉询问时，瓦尼尼被问及对上帝存在的看法，他回答说，就像教会那样，信仰唯一的、三位一体的上帝。捡起一根稻草，他说道：“这小小的东西就足以证明造物主的存在。”然后，他就植物和运动发表了一番不错的演说，当他谈到上帝存在的必要性时，他说没有上帝，就没有植物的运动与生长。

当时，身处图卢兹的首席法官格拉蒙（Grammont）在其《法国的历史》一书中记载了这次演说。然而，格拉蒙却因为偏见，断言瓦尼尼的说辞“不是源于内心的信念，而是出于恐惧或功利之心”。

那首席法官格拉蒙这一武断而狠毒的判决是基于什么原因呢？显而易见，瓦尼尼的回答本可以让他免受无神论的指控。然而，到底发生了什么事？原来这个不幸的外国传教士还是个药物行家。他们在瓦尼尼的家中发现了一只活生生的大蟾蜍，这只蟾蜍就在一个盛满水的器皿里，因此他们指控瓦尼尼是巫师。他们还声称，这只蟾蜍就是瓦尼尼信奉的神，他书中的几段内容还被指控说含有不虔诚的意义。这种事做起来轻而易举，通常就是把否认当成回答，再恶意曲解一些有歧义的短语，让本是干净清白的词句变得污秽不堪。最终，这些刻意打压瓦尼尼的小集团成功地让法官作出判决，将这不幸之人处死。

显而易见，想要为瓦尼尼的死亡辩护，就需要谴责那些卑鄙之人所做的可怕之事。默森里（Mersenne）心胸狭窄，疯狂过度，竟诬陷瓦尼尼“和他的12个旨在劝慰所有国家皈依无神论的使徒离开了那不勒斯”。真是愚笨呀！一个穷困潦倒的教士怎能有钱供养12个人？他是怎么说服那12个那不勒斯人，甘愿花费巨资，冒着生命危险，与他一同游历，去各地传播这令人憎恶且反动的教义呢？一个国王是否足够强大富有去供养12个无神论传道士？默森里神父制造如此可恶的谬论，真是前无古人，但后有来者，报纸、历史词典都受到他的传染，这热爱喧嚣轰鸣的世界也毫无怀疑，坚信这极具传奇色彩的谬论。

贝耳（Bayle）在《多样的思想》（Pensées Diverses）一书中也把瓦尼尼说成是一位无神论者。他用此例去证明“一个无神论者的社会是能够存在的”这样一个悖论。他信誓旦旦地保证说，瓦尼尼道德崇高，是自己哲学观点的殉道者。然而，贝耳在这两个方面都犯了错误。瓦尼尼曾模仿伊拉斯谟写过《对话》，在此文中，他自白说自己有位情妇，名叫伊莎贝拉。瓦尼尼就如自己所描述的那般行事大胆，但无论如何，他绝不是无神论者。

瓦尼尼死后一个世纪，学者拉·克劳兹（La Croze）和一位笔名为菲内特（Philète）的人试图为他正名。然而，人们对于一个忧伤的那不勒斯人的回忆，一个写作糟糕的人，实在无法提起兴趣，他们所写的辩护词，鲜有人问津。

比格拉斯更博学多才的耶稣会士阿杜恩（Hardouin）在《无神论探讨》（Athei Detecti）一书中曾谴责笛卡尔、阿诺（Arnauld）、帕斯卡（Pascal）、尼科尔（Nicole）和梅尔布朗斯（Malebranche）信仰无神论，所幸的是这些人并未重蹈瓦尼尼悲惨命运的覆辙。

结合上文罗列出的事实，我们继续来讨论贝耳所关注的道德伦理问题，即“一个无神论者的社会能否存续”的问题。首先让我们来观察一下，人们在这个问题上发生争论时，自相矛盾的程度究竟有多大：贝耳观点最激烈的反对者，以及以最侮辱人的话语否定无神论者社会存在可能性的人，都毫无畏惧，坚持认为无神论是一种由中国主导的宗教。

毫无疑问，他们对中国政府的看法都是错误的。只要阅读一下这个广袤国度所颁布的诏书，他们就会发现这些诏书的内容都是布道，所宣扬的全是神灵、天子、因果报应。

与此同时，他们在“无神论者社会存在的可能性”这一问题上也没少犯错误，我不懂贝耳先生怎能忘记那样一个绝好的实例，本来完全可以支撑他的论点。

一个无神论者的社会为什么看似无法存在呢？原因有三：一是不受上帝约束而成长的人类应该无法适应群居生活；二是法律对于隐蔽性犯罪基本无用；三是人类需要一个报复心重的上帝去惩罚此世或来世逃脱了人间法律制裁的恶人。

摩西律法没有涉及来世，没有提到死后惩罚，也没有告诉第一代犹太人灵魂是永恒不朽的，这是事实，但是犹太人非但没有成为逃避神圣复仇的无神论者，反而成了人类中最虔诚的信徒。他们不仅相信上帝是永恒存在着的，而且还认定上帝就出现在他们中间，无处不在，他们害怕上帝会惩罚自己，会降罪子女，会阻断家庭的幸福，甚至会为第四代子孙担心害怕，上帝的这种督查考验着实威力无穷。

然而，异教徒中一些宗派是不存在上帝督查考验的，比如怀疑论者质疑世间万物；柏拉图信奉者保留对所有事物的看法；享乐主义者坚信上帝不能干涉人间之事，在内心深处并不相信上帝的存在。他们认为灵魂不是实体，而是与肉体同生共死的虚幻意志，所以他们不受上帝的束缚，而受道德与荣誉的影响。罗马元老院中的元老和骑士们是真正的无神论者，因为对于从不害怕上帝、对上帝也毫无所求的人来说，上帝是不存在的。所以，恺撒和西塞罗时代的罗马元老院才是真正的无神论者大本营。

伟大演说家西塞罗在名为“为克鲁恩修斯”[4]的演说中，他对集会中的元老们说：“死亡能给他造成什么伤害？我们拒绝所有有关地狱的愚笨而不实的寓言。死亡能带走他什么东西呢？什么也带不走，只能带走疼痛的感觉。”

处死罪犯，死并不是对罪犯的惩罚；死亡并不代表什么；死亡只是我们苦难的结束；死亡是快乐而非痛苦的时刻。对于这些观点，恺撒难道有发表反对意见？西塞罗和整个元老院难道不接受这些看法吗？就算恺撒是卡塔琳娜（Catalina）的朋友，并且还想从西塞罗手下挽救自己朋友的性命。因此，这些举世闻名的世界征服者和立法者们对上帝都无敬畏之心，他们是彻头彻尾的无神论者。

随后，贝耳探究了偶像崇拜是否比信仰无神论更加危险。不信神明与对于神明浅薄无知，此二者相比较，前者是否是更大的罪过？关于此点，贝耳与普鲁塔克的看法一致。普鲁塔克认为相较于拥有错误观点来说，还不如没有观点来得好。然而，依据普鲁塔克的看法，显而易见，希腊人敬畏谷物女神刻瑞斯、海神尼普顿和主神朱庇特要比无所畏惧要好太多。与此同时，维护誓言的神圣地位也是必须，我们所信赖的人应当是那些相信错误誓言会招致惩罚的人，而不是那些认为胡乱发誓也不会受到惩戒的人。毋庸置疑，在一个文明城市里，存在一种宗教，就算不太完善，但较于全无宗教来说，还是要有用很多。

所以说贝耳应当去探讨宗教狂热与无神论，这两者之间哪一种更危险。毫无疑问，相较于无神论来说，宗教狂热所带来的危险当然要强出千百倍。因为无神论并不嗜血，但宗教狂热却热衷于此；无神论并不赞成犯罪，但宗教狂热却热衷犯罪。跟随《高卢事物注疏》（Commentarium Rerum Gallicarum）一书的作者，让我们一起来假设一下总理大臣洛比达是名无神论者。他颁布的法令可行亲民，推行的政策仁爱和睦，可是宗教狂热者们却杀害了圣·巴多罗买（Saint Bartholomew）。霍布斯（Hobbes）也被视作无神论者，然而他生活平静而简单，可在他所处的时代，宗教狂热者们在英格兰、苏格兰和爱尔兰泛滥成灾，流血事件时有发生。斯宾诺莎不仅是名无神论者，同时还宣扬无神论。当然他并未参与对巴纳菲尔德（Barneveldt）的司法暗杀，也不是他将德·维特（de Witt）兄弟扯成碎片，折磨致死。

大部分无神论者都是性情莽撞、又受到误导的学者。他们逻辑推理不严密、不懂创世、不知恶魔起源，也不知道其他许多难解的事物，因为无法解释，所以就转向事物永恒性与必然性的假说。

雄心勃勃、骄奢淫逸的人几乎不会花时间去论证，去接纳一个不完备的理论。他们与其做其他事也不会去比较卢克莱修（Lucretius）[5]和苏格拉底之间的区别，这就是当下的行事之风。

而罗马元老院的情况却不是如此。元老院上下几乎全由理论和实践上皆是无神论者组成，也就是说，他们既不信天意，也不信来世。这个元老院是哲学家、酒色之徒和野心勃勃之人的大本营，他们都很危险，是他们毁了共和国。享乐主义在罗马帝国皇帝统治下大行其道。元老院中的无神论者在苏拉（Sulla）和恺撒时代曾经是煽动反叛的人，而在奥古斯都（Augustus）和提比略（Tiberius）时代又成了无神论者的奴隶。

我不想与一个信仰无神论的王子有任何瓜葛，他会认为将我塞进炮筒会非常有用，我也确信我会被塞进去；如果我是一个君主，我不想有信奉无神论的朝臣，因为他们的兴趣就是要将我毒死，那样每天我都需要随身携带解毒剂。由此看来，帝王国君和各类民众都绝对有必要将神灵、上帝、统治者和因果报应的概念深深地植入脑海。

贝耳在《关于彗星的思考》（Pensées Sur Les Comètes）一书中提到说存在信奉无神论的人。卡菲尔人、霍屯督人、图皮南布人，以及其他许多小型部族都没有上帝。也许是这样，但这也并不意味着他们否认上帝的存在。他们既不否认，也不认同上帝，因为他们从未听说。告诉他们上帝的存在，他们就会相信。告诉他们所有事情都是自然而然发生的，他们也会相信。称他们为无神论者或反笛卡尔主义者（anti-Cartesians）都是适当的，因为他们既不认同，也不反对笛卡尔。他们就是真正的孩童，既不是无神论者也不是有神论者，他们是白纸一张。

那我们从中可以得出什么结论呢？结论就是：无神论对统治阶级、对学者们来说都是莫大的邪恶，就算是对于生活简单的学者来说，也是如此，因为学者们可利用所学知识去影响统治者。然而，无神论的危害就算没有宗教狂热来得那么强烈，但对于品德来说，也是致命伤。总而言之，自从哲学家们认识到了没有种子就没有蔬菜，没有筹备就没有种子，同时依靠腐烂不可以生产粮食之后，现在比起过去而言，无神论者已经少了很多。

非哲学的数学家们拒绝接受终极因，但是真正的哲学家们是接受的。正如一位著名作家所言：传道士告诉孩子们上帝的存在，而牛顿向明智之人演示上帝的存在。

II

灵魂里的暴君因为唯利是图，欺诈行骗招致我们的反感，这灵魂暴君还强迫一些虚弱的心灵去否定被恶魔侮辱着的上帝。如果此事的责任不在于无神论者，那谁才是责任人呢？榨取民脂民膏的吸血鬼迫使无力的民众去背叛国王的频率有多高呢？

依靠吸食我们血肉而壮大的人向我们大声吼道：“确信一头母驴会说话；相信一条鱼在吞食一个人3天之后会将其安全无损地抛回海边；全能的上帝命令一个犹太先知（即以西结）去吃粪便，命令另一个先知（即何西阿书）去购买两个妓女并与她们生下子嗣，不要对此抱有怀疑。这字字都是真理、纯洁之上帝所说的话语。要么相信显而易见令人厌恶的东西，要么相信数学上完全不可能之事。否则，仁慈的上帝将会用地狱中的烈火将你烧成灰烬。这不仅限于成千上万个世纪的时间，而是贯穿了永恒，不管你有无肉体。”

这些难以置信的愚蠢之事不仅引起个性软弱、鲁莽之人的反感，也招致心性坚定、明智之人的不耻。他们说：“我们的宗教领袖们将上帝描述成所有物种中最愚蠢、最野蛮的事物，所以上帝是不存在的。”但是他们应该说：“我们的宗教领袖们将他们自己的愚蠢与狂怒强加给上帝，所以上帝恰恰是他们所宣称那样的反面，上帝明智仁善，程度等同于所被宣称的疯狂邪恶的程度。”这就是有识之士的结论。但是这些倘若被一个宗教狂热分子听到，那他会将他们告发至执法官和教士处，然后这个执法官会将他们置于慢火中活活烧死，并坚信自己是在模仿神圣的上帝来惩治这些不敬之人。

洗礼

洗礼在希腊语中意为浸礼。通常以感官为导向的人类，很容易联想到在洗涤肉体的同时也是在净化灵魂。而此事，在很大程度上，都要归功于那些在埃及神殿穹顶下洗礼的发起人和首次进行实践的祭司。自远古时期以来，印度人就以恒河之水净化自身，至今这一仪式仍然十分盛行。后来这仪式传给了希伯来人，他们为所有皈依犹太教的外邦人举行洗礼，这仪式的重要性丝毫不逊色于割礼。除埃塞俄比亚外，所有的女人都不要求实行割礼，但需要举行洗礼。因为洗礼代表一种重生，人能被赋予全新的灵魂，正如埃及的传统那样。关于这点，参见伊皮法纽[6]，迈蒙尼德[7]和《革马拉》[8]。

约翰在约旦举行过洗礼，他甚至还为耶稣举行了洗礼。而耶稣，这个从未为别人举行过洗礼的人，却让这个古老仪式变得圣洁、神圣。其实，每条教义本身都无意义，只是上帝将他的祝福融入了他所选择的教义之中。很快，洗礼就成了基督教的首要宗教仪式和信徒的主要标志。耶路撒冷的首批15名大主教虽然都受过割礼，但是是否都行过洗礼却无法确定。

可是，这一神圣仪式在基督教的头一个世纪里遭到了滥用。死亡之时等待接受洗礼成了最稀松平常之事，其中的典型事例就是康斯坦丁大帝。以下是他对洗礼的看法：洗礼可以洗净世间任何东西，所以我可以杀尽妻儿亲人，之后只要受洗，照样可以进入天堂。实际上他也如此做了。但这是一个很极端的例子，其实接受神圣洗礼之前等死的习俗已经渐渐消亡了。

希腊人总将洗礼等同于浸礼。8世纪末期，拉丁人在将他们的宗教传入高卢和德国后发现，在气候严寒的国家实行浸礼会冻死孩童，于是用简单的淋水取代了浸礼。他们还因为此事经常受到希腊教会的谴责。

迦太基大主教圣·塞浦路斯（Saint Cyprian）曾被问到那些全身只受过微量水洗的人是否真的受洗了。他在第76封信中回答道：有几个教会不相信这些轻微受洗过的人是基督徒，但是就他自己而言，他觉得他们是基督徒，只不过相较于那些根据习俗受过3次浸礼的人，毫无疑问得到的祝福要少得多。

就基督徒来说，一个人一旦受洗，那么他就被教会正式接纳为信徒了。在受洗之前，他就只是一个初学者。想要被教会接受，就需要有保证人、监护人，这些人会被授予一个类似于教父一样的名字，只有这样，教会才能确认这新的基督教徒能始终保持信仰，而不会沉溺于其他秘密宗教。这就是为什么在头几个世纪里，关于基督教的秘密宗教仪式，连同伊希斯[9]和依洛西斯[10]的秘密宗教仪式，基督徒都没有受到正确的指引。

亚历山大的区利罗[11]在他反对朱利安大帝的小册子中这样说道：“我会谈论洗礼，就算我的言语会传到非基督徒的耳中，我也不怕。”

早在2世纪时，他们就已经开始为儿童举行洗礼。基督徒们期望他们的孩子受到洗礼，这是人之常情，因为不受洗就会受到诅咒。最终将洗礼的举行时间定在孩子出生一周后，因为这时间也是犹太教为孩子举行割礼的时间。尽管人在死亡时接受洗礼盛行于3世纪，但是这一习俗至今仍是希腊教会的传统。

根据教会中最严格的教父的说法，婴儿出生后一周内死亡是受到了诅咒。但是在5世纪时，皮特·克索罗格斯[12]发明了地狱边境一说。地狱边境就是一种轻量级地狱，更确切地说，是地狱的边境部分，是地狱的郊区，是未受洗礼的儿童和在耶稣降生之前已去世的正直的人死后的栖身之所。从此以后，人们认为耶稣死后进入的是地狱的边境而非地狱。

降生在阿拉伯的沙漠之中的基督徒能否用沙子进行洗礼一事也引起过各方争论，最后的答案是不可以。又问玫瑰香水是否可以用来进行洗礼，答案是纯净水是必要的，但是浑浊水也可以使用。显而易见，所有的规则主要取决于首次创立该规则牧师的谨慎程度。

……

洗礼：补充

受到洗浴盆的启发而认为一壶水能洗净所有的罪恶，是个多么奇怪的观点呀！之所以所有的孩子都接受洗礼，是因为再没有比这更荒谬的观点能假定所有的孩子都是罪犯，假定他们都被拯救了，直到他们长大到懂事的年龄并能开始犯罪为止。所以尽可能快地屠戮他们以求让他们相信天堂。这个结论是如此逻辑严密，以至于存在一个虔诚的教派，致力于毒杀所有刚受洗的婴儿。这些信徒的辩解是如此的理所当然，他们说：“对于这些纯洁无瑕的小东西，我们给予最大的善意，我们这是在防止他们变得邪恶，不让他们品尝生活的艰辛，我们是在赋予他们永生。”

食人族

我讨论过爱。从讨论人类相亲相爱到讨论人类互相啃食，实现这个转换很是艰难。但是食人族又千真万确地存在着。在美洲已经发现过一些。然而在远古时代，偶尔会吃人血肉的，并不只有独眼巨人[13]，可能其他一些人也会如此。尤维纳利斯（Juvenal）就曾描述说古埃及人，一个如此明智博学，以其律法完善、人民虔诚、崇拜鳄鱼与洋葱而著称的民族，他们中的丹德拉人（Denderites）竟然也吃掉了一个落入他们之手的敌人。尤维纳利斯讲述的这个故事并非异端邪说，这宗罪恶几乎就在他眼皮底下发生，当时他就在埃及，离丹德拉（Dendera）不远。他在连接日记的文件夹里还引证了以前吃同胞血肉的加斯科涅人（Gascons）和桑加提人（Sagantines）。

1725年，4个野蛮人被人从密西西比带到枫丹白露，我有幸能有机会和他们对话。我问其中一个女人是否吃过人，她很无辜地回答说，她吃过。我震惊了。她解释说吃掉敌人的尸体好过敌人被野兽吞食，胜利者有这个特权。在对阵战或者野战中，我们杀死邻居，为乌鸦和蠕虫只留下最少量的食物。只要有惨状，就会有犯罪。当一个人被杀死了，死后尸体是被士兵吃掉还是被乌鸦或者狗吃掉，这又有什么关系呢？

我们尊敬死者甚于尊敬生者。两者都应当受到我们的尊敬。国家之所以文明在于我们不会将屈服的敌人置于烤肉叉上。因为一旦允许吃掉敌人，那很快我们也会吃掉自己的同胞，这对社会公德来说将会是一种双重的诅咒。但是文明国度并非总是文明的，因为所有人在很长时间里都曾是野蛮人。在这世界所经历的无数次革命中，人类种群的数量有时巨大，有时稀少。如今大象、狮子和老虎数量锐减的现象，也曾发生在人类身上。所以，当人类聚居在一个狭小区域，又无诸多技艺，他们就都是猎人，以杀死的猎物为食的习惯就很容易导致他们对待敌人就像对待他们的猎物野鹿和野猪一样。以人献祭是迷信，但以人为食是必需。

有两种罪，一种是为了向神表达敬意，将幼小的祭品用束带装饰好，然后在虔诚的集会中，将刀插入祭品心脏；另一种则是吃掉一个为了自卫而杀死的恶棍。这两种罪，哪一种更严重呢？

然而，男孩被当作祭品献祭的事例要比被当作食物吃掉的事例多得多。其中，犹太人就献祭。这种仪式被称为咒逐，这是真正意义上的献祭。《利未记》第27章明确要求不要放过那些已经致力于服侍上帝的生魂，但是没有规定说他们应该被吃掉，他们只是受到这种命运的威胁。我们也已经知道摩西对犹太人说，如果他们不观看这些仪式，那么不只是他们会有这种渴望，就连母亲也会吃掉自己的孩子。在以西结时代，犹太人一定有吃人的习惯，因为在第39章他向犹太人预言说，上帝不只会让他们敌人的战马成为他们的食物，甚至骑马者和其他的战士也会成为他们的食物。这千真万确。但是为什么犹太人实际上又没有成为食人族呢？这本应是唯一一件事能使这些上帝选民成为世上最令人厌恶的人。

在一些有关克伦威尔时期英格兰历史的书上，我曾经读到过一件奇闻轶事：都柏林有一个油脂蜡烛商贩售卖用英格兰人的油脂制作的、质量上乘的蜡烛。一段时间后，她的一个顾客向她抱怨说蜡烛质量没那么好了。她说：“哎，这是因为这个月英格兰人缺货。”我想问谁才是罪人？是那些杀死英格兰人的刽子手？还是这个将他们的脂肪做成蜡烛的女人呢？

确信与确信度

“你的朋友克里斯托弗多大年龄？”

“28岁。我俩打小就认识，我见过他的结婚证，知道他什么时候接受洗礼的。他28岁，这一点毫无疑问，我很确定。”

此人如此确信，其他20多人也证明了此事，然而我刚听完回答，就发现克里斯托弗出于某种不为人知的原因，利用一些小手段将实际举行洗礼的日期提前了。那些回答我问题的人到现在都还没意识到这个错误。他们犯了错，却不自知地坚持错误。

哥白尼出现之前，如果你问“今天太阳会升起吗？会降落吗？”那么所有人可能都会这样回答你：“当然，我们万分肯定。”他们都万分肯定，确信无疑，然而他们都错了。

曾经在很长的岁月里，符咒、占卜和神魔附身在世人眼中都是确信无疑的事情。那个时候，认同并对这些神奇之物确信无疑的人何其多也！如今，这种确信度在一定程度上有所变弱。

曾经有一名学习几何学的年轻人来拜访过我。他不理解三角形的定义。我就问他说：“一个三角形的三个角等于两个直角，你不觉得确定无疑吗？”他回答说，他对这个命题连一个清楚的认识都没有，根本谈不上确定无疑。于是，我向他演示了这道命题，然后他就对此确信无疑了，并且终生都会如此。

数学上的这种确定性不同于其他类别的确定性，它是亘古不变的，然而其他类别的确定性仅仅只是可能性，一旦加以验证，就会变成错误。

我存在、我思考、我感受苦痛！所有这类问题是否也与几何真理一样确定呢？答案是肯定的，为什么呢？原因在于此类真理都可以由同一条原则加以证明，此原则就是一个事物不可能同时存在又不存在。我不可能同时存在又不存在，感知又不感知。一个三角形不可能同时有又没有180度，而这180度恰好是两个直角的总和。

所以，对于我的存在和感知的物理确定性与数学上的确定性，尽管种类不同，但是他们具有同等的价值。

但这并不适用于那些基于表象或者由众口一词而得来的确定性。

“真的吗？”你告诉我“北京真是存在吗？我们没有从北京得来的纺织品吗？国度不同，见解不同的人，虽会对彼此口诛笔伐，但是对于北京的存在却都确信无疑。他们没有向你保证说这座城市是真实存在的吗？”我回答说，对于我而言，北京存在着只是一件很可能的事情，我不会赌上我的性命说这座城市是存在的，但是，在任何时候，我都会赌上我的性命说一个三角形的三个角等于两个直角。

《大百科辞典》中的有些内容真的非常可笑。比如，里面有篇文章写道：如果整个巴黎都说德·萨克斯元帅[14]复活了，那么人们就该对此确信无疑，正如人们都相信巴黎人所说的德·萨克斯元帅取得了丰特努瓦之战胜利一样。那我请您考虑一下，想想这个逻辑是多么的令人钦佩：当所有的巴黎人告诉我一些在原则上可能发生的事情时，我相信他们；所以当他们告诉我一些在原则上、在生理上不可能发生的事情时，我仍旧必须相信他们。

显而易见，这篇文章的作者就是想博人一笑。而另一名作者在文章末尾还陷入狂乱状态，写作自相矛盾，估计这也是想逗人一笑吧。而对于我这么一个试图从这本辞典中挑出问题的人来说，所谓的确信离我太远。

性格

“性格”一词源于希腊语，是印记、雕刻之意。性格是大自然铭刻于我们人类体内之物。我们可以抹除性格吗？这是个高深的问题。如果我有一个鹰钩鼻，两只猫儿眼，那我可以将它们隐藏在面具之下。那对于自然赋予我的性格，我可以让它变得更好吗？一个生性狂暴、暴躁易怒的人，去法国国王弗朗索瓦一世面前抱怨说他受到了不公正待遇。但王子的面容、朝臣的敬意以及他正身处的这个地方，都会给他留下深刻的印象：不知不觉中，他会垂下眼睑，放柔声音，来表现他的谦恭。人们会觉得他个性自然温顺，身处朝臣们中间时，甚至会有些惊慌失措。但是，如果弗朗索瓦一世精于观察面相，那么从他那低垂却隐藏火焰的眼睛里，从那紧绷的面部肌肉里，从那紧紧闭合的嘴唇上，国王就能很轻易地发现，此人并不像他所表现出来的那样谦卑恭顺。此人跟随国王一起去帕维亚，一起被俘，一道被关押在马德里的监狱里。此时，弗朗索瓦一世国王的形象在此人心中就起了变化，此人对他曾经顶礼膜拜的国王已经相当熟悉。有一天，当他为国王脱骑马靴时，手法不对，国王又想起自己的不幸，一下子就暴怒起来。于是乎，这人就把国王送给了魔鬼，将国王的靴子扔出了窗外。

西斯都五世本性急躁、顽固倔强、傲慢自大、鲁莽冲动、报复心重、嚣张骄纵。他在见习修士期间进行过苦修，他的本性看似有所柔化。然而，当他声名鹊起、大权加身之时，一名侍者侍奉不周，让他暴怒，他就用自己的拳头将这侍者击倒在地。西斯都五世在威尼斯任审问者一职时，行事傲慢无礼，在成为红衣主教之后，他想成为教皇的野心肆意膨胀。这种野心膨胀侵蚀了他的本性，他将自己的人性与性格隐匿于黑暗之中，他假装谦逊，身体虚弱，直到被选为教皇。一当选，他就恢复了所有强行压制着的本性。他是最傲慢自大、最暴怒专制的最高统治者。

Naturam expellas furca, tamen ipsa redibit.

（就算用干草叉将本性暂时驱逐，但它总会回归。）

Chassez le naturel, il revient au galop.

宗教和道德只能束缚但不能摧毁本性。修道院里的嗜酒者，就算将喝酒量减至每餐只喝一杯苹果酒，不会再喝醉，但他永远还是爱酒。

年岁的增加会让性格有所弱化。但是一棵树结出的果子，有些尽管较次，总归是同一种类。树会起疙瘩、长苔藓，会被虫蛀，但是它总还是一颗橡树或者梨树。如果我们可以改变自己的性格，那么也许我们会给自己创造一种性格，我们会成为自然的主宰。我们可以给予自己什么东西呢？难道我们所拥有的还不够吗？尝试着在充满惰性的群众里连绵不断地发起活动、尝试着用冷漠去给滚烫冲动的灵魂降温、也尝试着激发那些无品位、无悟性的人群生出对音乐、对诗歌的热爱与品位。如果你能为生而眼盲的人带去光明，那么再没有什么能比这更加成功的了。我们可以去完善、调节或者隐藏自然赋予我们的东西，但是我们不能肆意为自己创造东西。

一个农民曾被告知说：“你这鱼塘里鱼太多了，它们无法茁壮成长；你农田里动物太多了，食草不够，它们会减重。”听从这劝告之后，梭鱼吃了这人一半的鲤鱼，狼群吃了一半的绵羊，剩下的就长肥了。农民会为这种管理方式而欢呼雀跃吗？这农民其实就是你自己，你自身的一种热情吞噬了其他热情，你还以为自己战胜了自己。有位90高龄的老将军偶然遇见一些年轻的军官正与镇上的女人们调情，他怒气冲冲地说道：“绅士们，这就是我给你们树立的榜样吗？”难道我们自己不都与这位90岁的老将军大同小异吗？

宗教会议

毫无疑问，所有的宗教会议阐述教义绝无谬误，因为会议的成员都是有智慧的人。在他们的集会中，感情用事、阴谋诡计、喜辩好战、仇恨嫉妒、偏见傲慢都不可能占主导地位。

但是为什么如此多的宗教会议又会彼此冲突呢？这是个会被问到的问题。这就要检验我们的信仰了，每一个会议就其本身而言都是正确的。

罗马天主教只相信梵蒂冈认可的宗教会议；希腊天主教则只信任君士坦丁堡认可的宗教会议。而新教徒对此两者都加以嘲弄。所以说每个人都想着自己应该被满足。

在这里，我只提及影响大的会议，规模小的略去不提。

第一个就是尼西亚（Nicaea）会议。该会议于公元325年召开，召开原因主要是康斯坦丁大帝吩咐奥蒂斯（Ozius）给迷惑的亚历山大教士写了一封重要的信，信中说道：“你是在为一些无关紧要的事情争论，这些细微之处在理性之人看来毫无价值。”这里提到的事主要就是：耶稣是上帝创造的，还是自存的。此事与道德无关，这点是核心。耶稣是受到时间限制还是凌驾于时间之上，这怎么说均是不妥。在历经众多解读之后，会议最终决定圣子与圣父同龄同质。这个解读虽然我们难以理解，然而正是由于这个缘故，圣子变得更加庄严崇高。但是，却有17名主教反对这项教令，据亚历山大所著的编年史记载（此编年史保存在牛津），还有2000名教士也持反对意见。然而，高级教士对贫穷困苦的底层教士的意见通常是不屑一顾的。尽管出现这种情况，第一次宗教会议对于三位一体还是不存在争议的。教条这样写道：“我们相信耶稣与圣父同质同体，是神之神，是光之光，是上帝所生而非创造。我们也相信圣灵。”在这里我们必须承认圣灵遭受了比较随意的对待。

尼西亚会议的附录中还记载到：由于分不清辨不明哪些是《旧约》和《新约》的真经，哪些是伪经，迷惑的神父们将所有经书混杂无序地置于祭坛之上，不被认可的经书就会掉到地上。如此优雅讲究的仪式竟然没有被继承流传下来，真是可惜呀！

第一次尼西亚会议成员由317位在阐述教义方面绝不会出错的主教们组成，此次会议之后，另一会议在里米尼[15]召开，与会成员多达400名主教，这还不包括塞琉西亚的一大队人马，将近200人。这600名主教，在历经四个月的争论之后，一致同意剥夺耶稣与圣父同质的特性。之后，除了索齐尼派教徒（Socinians），会议又恢复了耶稣与圣父同质的特性。所以说，怎样做都是可以的。

公元431年举行的以弗所会议也是最重要的会议之一。君士坦丁堡大主教、异教徒伟大的迫害者聂斯脱利（Nestorius）认为耶稣实际上就是上帝，但是耶稣的母亲绝对不是上帝的母亲，只是耶稣的母亲，因为这一看法他遭到了圣·赛瑞利（Saint Cyril）的谴责。然而，之后在这同一会议上，聂斯脱利的支持者们废黜了圣·赛瑞利。这些事情使得圣灵的处境非常难堪。

亲爱的读者们，在这里请仔细注意，福音书对于同实体性这一词尚未发表任何意见，对于圣母玛利亚是否是上帝之母，以及那些引发主教们集会的争执点也未发表任何意见。

欧迪奇（Eutyches）是名修道士，他极力反对聂斯脱利，认为聂斯脱利所宣扬的“耶稣其实是两个人”是异端邪说，是可怕断言。为了更好地否定对手的观点，他还断言说耶稣只有一种本性。一位名为弗拉维亚（Flavian）的君士坦丁堡主教不同意他的观点，认为耶稣具有二重本性是绝对必需的。449年，无数的宗教会议在以弗所举行。这次会议的参会人数是以往人数的四分之一，与355年举行的小型锡尔塔（Cirta）会议以及一个在迦太基举行的会议规模相当。会上弗拉维亚饱受攻击、遍体鳞伤，然而耶稣还是被赋予了二重本性。但是，卡尔西登（Chalcedon）会议又将耶稣的本性减少到一种。

我跳过那些讨论细枝末节的会议，直达第六次君士坦丁堡大型宗教会议，会议旨在确认只拥有一种本性的耶稣，是否有过两种欲念。为了讨好上帝，你会意识到此点的重要性。

正如此前诸多会议都由国王们召集一样，此次会议由康斯坦丁二世（绰号“大胡子”）召集。罗马主教的使者们坐于左侧，君士坦丁堡和安提俄克（Antioch）的主教们则坐在右侧。我不知道罗马的谄媚者们是否视左方座位为上座，但是无论如何，耶稣在此事上就有两种欲念。

摩西律法禁止将耶稣图像化，因此，画家和雕塑家在犹太人中从不吃香。除了路加（Luke）画的圣母玛利亚，耶稣图像从未出现过。无论怎样，犹太人从不崇拜耶稣基督的图像。然而，基督徒们直到4世纪末都还在崇拜着耶稣的图像，他们对于这种精湛的美术技艺已经相当熟悉。这种错误的做法严重泛滥，以至于到了8世纪，康斯坦丁五世科普罗尼穆斯（Constantine V Copronymus）召集了320名主教在君士坦丁堡举行宗教会议，强烈谴责图像崇拜，并为其打下了偶像崇拜的烙印。

还有那位后来挖了她儿子眼睛的伊琳娜女皇于787年召开了尼西亚第二次会议，该会议恢复了图像崇拜。如今要为此次会议正名，理由通常是：这种对图像的崇拜是二等崇拜的一种（对圣徒的尊崇），而非最高崇拜（专对上帝之崇拜）。

然而，到底是二等崇拜还是最高崇拜，794年，查理曼大帝在法兰克福召集了另一场会议，该会议指责第二次尼西亚会议，认为它是盲目的偶像崇拜。教皇哈德良四世派遣了两名使者参加此会议，但并不召集人。

第一次由教皇召集而举行的大型宗教会议是1139年举行的第一次拉特兰（Lateran）会议。约有1000名主教参加，然而，此次会议除了诅咒那些抱怨教会太富有的人之外，没有取得任何成果。

1179年，教皇亚历山大三世召集举行了另一场拉特兰会议，此次会议只讨论了教规问题，但是红衣主教的地位在此次会议上第一次超过了主教。

另一场重要的会议是1215年举行的拉特兰会议。此次会上，教皇英诺森三世将图卢兹伯爵逐出教会，剥夺了他所有的财产。在这次会议上，首次出现了与变质论相关的问题。

1245年，还是当时皇城的里昂举行了大型宗教会议，在此期间，教皇英诺森四世将皇帝腓特烈二世逐出教会，进而废黜，永世放逐。也就是在这次会议上，红衣主教们被授予红帽，用来提醒他们自己必须沐浴在皇帝支持者们的鲜血之中。此次会议摧毁了斯瓦比亚家族（House of Swabia），使得意大利和德国30年里都处于无政府状态。

1311年，在维也纳举行的大会上，圣殿骑士团（the Order of the Templars）被废除，骑士团的主要成员们，基于许多毫无事实根据的指控，饱受谴责与最严酷恐怖的刑讯逼供。

1414年，举行了康斯坦茨（Constance）大会，该大会废黜了教皇约翰二十三世，指控他罪行1000种。此会议还以顽固不化的罪名烧死了约翰·胡斯（John Huss）和布拉格的哲罗姆（Jerome of Prague）。因为在当时，相对于谋杀、强奸、买卖圣职和鸡奸，顽固不化是项更严重的犯罪。

1431年的巴塞尔（Basle）大会不被罗马教会承认，原因在于此次会议未经罗马教会同意就废黜了教皇尤金四世。

罗马人将1512年举行的第五次拉特兰宗教会议也视为一次大会，此次会议由教皇尤里乌斯二世（Julius II）召集，但遭到法国皇帝路易十二世的反对。然而，随着尤里乌斯二世这样一位战士式的教皇离世，此次会议也化为乌有。

最后就是特伦托（Trent）大会，此会议在教规问题上在法国并无权威。但是，它的教规却是无可挑剔的，因为根据弟兄[16]保罗·萨比（Fra Paolo Sarpi）的说法，圣灵每周都会借助信使之身从罗马来到特伦托。但是弟兄保罗·萨比的说辞总有一丝异端邪说的感觉。

狂热

狂热，这一希腊词语意为内脏的骚乱，内心的激动。希腊人创造这一词语，是否旨在描述一种感觉，那就是当人被深深感动时，神经受到震动，内脏膨胀紧绷，心脏强烈收缩，暴乱的情绪横冲直撞，从内脏直灌大脑？

或者说，创造狂热这一词语的目的，不是用来描述内脏的骚动，而是首先用来描述女祭司皮提亚（Pythia）在德尔斐（Delphi）的三脚祭坛上，借助特制的道具，来接受阿波罗神谕时的激动心情呢？

我们如何理解狂热？在我们的情绪之中又有何细微差别？赞赏、敏感、情绪、悲痛、震惊、酷爱、狂暴、疯癫、激怒、愤怒：这些都是一个悲惨的灵魂可能经历的情绪状态。

一位几何学家观看一场感人肺腑的悲剧：他只看到该局的结构精巧。他身旁的年轻人深受感动却未有任何发现。一位女子掩面而泣，另一年轻人深受感染，以至于决定自己也去书写一个悲剧，他很不幸地被狂热这种疾病传染了。

百人队长或军团将校将战争视为一种有利可图的贸易，他们踏入战场就如一个盖屋匠爬上屋顶一样。恺撒见到亚历山大大帝的雕像时还会哭泣。

奥维德（Ovid）觉得爱情有趣好笑，萨福（Sappho）则对爱情狂热不已，如果说真的是这种狂热侵蚀了萨福的生命，那么也是因为狂热在萨福这里早已变成了癫狂。

党派之分极大地助推了这种狂热之情，任何团体都有其忠实狂热的追随者。

狂热，说到底，就是误入歧途的虔诚之心。有那年轻的苦行僧，盯着鼻尖，反复祈祷，直到自己坚信倘若身负50磅重的枷锁，那么神会由衷地感激他。脑海中充斥着对梵天的无尽想象，他陷入沉睡，在睡梦中他也无可避免地看到了自己的身影。有时，在沉睡与清醒之间，他的眼睛还会闪烁着星光点点：他看到梵天闪闪发光，为此他陷入狂喜之境，而这种狂喜之疾再也无法治愈。

理智与狂热并存是世上最稀有之事。理智在于看事物总看到本质。醉酒之人视物出现重影之时，他已经丧失理智。而狂热恰恰就像是烈酒：它能使血管骚动、神经震颤、彻底地摧毁理智；它也能只引发些许震动，促使大脑稍稍活动。此时就是雄辩之能大爆发，绝妙诗歌横空出世之时，这种有理智指导的狂热使他们的技艺才能变得完美。在过去时代，当人们提到从未被其他艺术家们提及之物时，通常会认为这是受到了神的启发。

理智怎么能控制狂热呢？原因在于诗人首先会在画布上勾画出结构，此时理智主导了画笔。然而，当他继续着笔，赋予人物灵动与生气时，想象力迸发，狂热取得主导地位：这就是一匹赛马，在合理铺设的赛道上，猛力向前奔跑。

平等

狗与狗之间，马与马之间，存在欠债关系吗？当然不存在，同类动物之间，从不依赖彼此。但是对于接受了神之光，拥有理智的人类来说，结果又是怎样的呢？结果是奴隶制盛行于世界各地。

世界理应如此运行，那就是：倘若人们发现这个世界舒适惬意、物质充足、气候适宜，那么显而易见，人奴役人的现象将不可能发生。就让这个世界遍布健康的果实、让维系生命的空气不再带给我们疾病和死亡、让人们不再拥有比鹿儿更多的贪念，那么成吉思汗和帖木儿，除了他们自己的子嗣，就不会再有其他的仆人，因为子嗣已经足够照顾他们养老了。

所有四足动物、鸟类和爬行类动物都享受着这种自然的状态，人类也应和它们一样快乐，这时控制奴役就会成为一种虚妄，一种所有人都不会接受的荒谬，原因就是既然不需要服侍，又为何要去渴求、要去占有仆人呢？

如果一些内心残暴，但力量充沛的个人想要征服较弱的邻居，那么也不会成功，因为，在他们这种压迫者采取行动之前，被压迫者就会结盟，一同抗争。

由此看来，若无欲望，人人都会平等。但是我们人类这个物种，拥有的低劣品性使得人与人之间形成隶属关系。不平等其实并不是真正的罪恶，依赖才是。世上有人被称为殿下，有人被称为圣座，这些称号无关紧要，但是要去服侍他们则是艰难万分。

一个富裕的大家族所耕种的土地土壤肥沃，两个临近的小家族土地贫瘠。很明显，这两个贫穷的家族要么服侍、要么杀死这个豪族。其中一个贫穷家族献出劳动，获取面包；另外一个发动攻击、惨遭毒打。前者成为仆人和劳工，后者则成为奴隶。

在我们这个不幸的世界里，人类居住的社会都被分成两个阶级，即统治者和被统治者。而这两个阶级又细分成一千个阶层，这一千个阶层也继续往下细分。

并不是所有的被压迫者都会感到不幸。他们大多数都出生在那样的环境里，不断地劳动能阻止他们对自己现状的关注。但是，一旦他们察觉，就会发生战争，比如像发生在罗马人民党与元老院之间的对抗，也如发生在德国、英格兰和法国的农民起义。所有的这些战争早晚都是以奴役弱者而结束，强大一方资金雄厚，而资金在很多情况下都是万能的。我只说在很多情况下，因为并不是说在每个国家都是如此。一些善用刀剑武器的国家通常能征服那些富裕但缺乏勇气的国家。

每个人生来都有强大的欲望，渴求征服、财富和享乐，对于闲适的渴望也十分强烈。于是，每个人都想将别人的钱财、妻子或女人据为己有，成为他们的主人，征服他们来满足自己善变的喜好、或者放置不管、又或者只做一些令人愉悦的事情。显而易见，好处如此多多，人与人之间实现平等着实不太可能，正如两位传道士或者两位神学教授之间不可能不嫉妒彼此一样。

除非大批无产却有用处的阶级存在，否则人类无以为继。因为一个富有的人当然不会放弃自己肥沃的土地，转而耕种你那贫瘠的土地。如果你需要一双鞋子，法官是无法帮你做一双的。于是，平等就成为最理所当然却也是最虚妄不实的东西。

但是，人类通常喜欢尽可能地在每件事上走极端，所以这种不平等也被夸大了。有些国家规定公民无权离开自己的国家，尽管他们降生在这国家纯粹是偶然。显而易见，这法律的意思就是：这个国家治理得很差，差到需要我们严禁个人逃脱，因为我们害怕人人都会逃走。那就做得好一点，让你所有的臣民都心甘情愿地留在家中，并吸引外来者的到来。

每个人都有相信自己的权利，在人的内心深处，人人生而平等。当然这并不是说要红衣主教的厨子命令其主人来准备饭菜，只是说厨子可以这样说：“我和主人都是人，我和他一样出生在泪水之中，他和我一样要遭受同样的苦难，历经同样的葬礼而消逝。我们都是动物，拥有同样的功能。如果土耳其人俘获了罗马人，那么我就会是红衣主教，我的主人就会是厨子，他会是我的仆人。”这些话公正合理，但是就算是伟大的土耳其征服了罗马，那这厨子照样得坚守自己的岗位，否则每个人类社会都会腐化堕落。

对于一个既不是红衣主教的厨子，也没有任何公职的人来说，如果他为人温和谦恭，却为那充满了施舍和蔑视味道的周遭环境而恼怒，明显地发现有些身居高位者，相较于自己而言，学识、智慧、道德品性都无法相比，也发现自己在他们的候客室里等待，疲乏不已，那他应该如何？当然应该离开。

祖国

祖国就是几个家族的合成体。当我们没有利益冲突时，出于自爱，通常都会坚定地支持自己的家族，所以出于同样的自爱，我们都会支持自己的乡村和城镇，这些地方就被叫作祖国。祖国疆域越大，我们对它的爱就越淡，因为被分割的爱是被弱化了的爱，要我们温柔体贴地去爱一个过于庞大，成员甚至素不相识的家实在太难。

一个满怀雄心抱负，想要成为行政官、护民官、裁判官、执政官、独裁者的人叫嚣着他热爱自己的国家，但是实际上他只爱自己。人人都想护财保命，都想确保自己能安稳地睡在家中，权利不被他人霸占，不需挪地休息。于是，所有人都有着同样的愿望，最终私人利益演变成公共利益，当我们传达着自己的希望时，我们也在传达公众的利益。

世上国家治理之初，都以共和制度开始，因为这是符合人类本性的正常道路。少许几个家族首先聚集起来对付熊和狼，只拥有粮食的家族与只拥有木头的家族互补有无。

发现美洲大陆之时，我们也发现陆上的所有部落都实行共和体制，在这整片大陆上只有两个王国。1000个国家中只发现两个国家被征服。

古代时期也是如此。在伊特鲁利亚（Etruria）和罗马的小国国王之前，欧洲实行的都是共和制。这种制度，在如今的非洲仍在实行。的黎波里、突尼斯、阿尔及利亚和往北地区仍然居住着这样一群人，他们以世界开始之初的生活方式生活着，自由而平等，他们之间，没有主人和臣民之分，没有金钱也没有欲求。所养的羊羔哺育他们，羊羔的皮毛温暖他们，泥土和树木所建的小屋就是他们的避难所。他们臭气熏天，却从未察觉，相较于我们而言，他们的生存和死亡都来得更加平静。

在我们欧洲，没有君主的共和国有8个，分别是：威尼斯、荷兰、瑞士、热那亚、卢卡、拉古萨、日内瓦和圣马里诺。波兰、瑞典和英格兰可以视作是拥有国王的共和国，但是只有波兰才是真正的符合。

如今，国家实行君主制或者共和制，哪一个更好？这个问题已经被争论了4000年。拿这个问题去向富人征求解决方式，他们倾向于贵族制；去问民众，他们则倾向于民主制。只有国王们想要君主制，那么为什么几乎世界上所有的国家都被君主统治着呢？去问那些建议在猫脖子上悬挂铃铛的老鼠们吧。但是真正的原因是，我以前说过的，人无法管理自身。

据说，一个好的爱国者常常是其余人类的敌人。好公民老加图（the elder Cato）在元老院发表演说时，常说：“这是我的观点，让迦太基毁灭吧。”想做一个好的爱国者，就是希望自己的城市通过商贸变得富有，通过武器变得强大。显而易见，一个国家得必有另一个国家失，而征服一个国家也不可能一帆风顺。

所以这就是人类的情况，渴望自己的祖国变得强大必然以邻为沟壑。而世界公民就是那些不求自己国家强大或弱小，不在乎自身富有或贫穷的人。

洪水

是否有段时间洪水吞没了整个地球呢？这从自然规律上来说绝无可能。

海洋逐步覆盖地球各个部分尚有可能，但是这个进程缓慢，将持续无数个世纪。艾格·莫尔特（Aigues-Mortes）、弗雷瑞斯（Fréjus）和拉文纳（Ravenna）都曾是良港，用了500年的时间海水才从这些地方撤退，留下了两块干燥的陆地。但照这样的速度，显而易见，海洋要绕过整个地球将需要250万年的时间。值得注意的是，这段时间与地轴向右运转并与赤道重合所花费的时间非常相近。此运转极有可能发生，人们对此已经猜测了50年，而要完成这一运转，需要超过230万年的时间。

在各个岩层以及因海水撤退而形成的几块陆地上发现的河床和贝壳层，都是无可争议的证据，证明海洋生物一点一滴地沉淀在那曾是海岸的陆地上。但是，与此同时，那淹没全球的洪水从自然科学上来说，完全是荒谬而虚妄的。重力定律、流体运动定律以及水量的不足都证明此事绝无可能。我无意质疑摩西五经中记载的世纪大洪水的真实性，相反，此洪水是一个奇迹，是一个人们必须相信的奇迹。正因为是一个奇迹，所以它并不受自然法则的约束。

在这洪水的故事里，所有的事物都是奇迹。40天连续降雨淹没了整个陆地，水平面比最高的山峰还要高出15腕尺，这是奇迹；天空中有大瀑布，有门，有出口是奇迹；所有动物能从世界各个角落集聚而来进入方舟是奇迹；诺亚能找到足够的食物喂养它们10个月之久是奇迹；所有动物能在方舟之中找到他们各自的房间是奇迹；它们中的大多数能存活下来是奇迹；它们离开方舟后能找到食物是奇迹；而勒·佩尔蒂埃（Le Pelletier）认为他已经清楚地解释了动物是如何适应方舟生活并喂养自己的，这也是一个奇迹，另一种类型的奇迹。

洪水的故事是我们所听到的所有故事里最具奇迹色彩的，若要去解释它，那会显得非常愚蠢。这故事是我们信念中所坚信的神秘事物之一，信念就是相信逻辑推理不相信的东西，这本身也是一个奇迹。

所以，大洪水的故事与巴别塔、巴兰的母驴、耶利哥（Jericho）在号角声中陨落、水变成鲜血、红海之路以及所有因上帝为帮助其选民而屈尊所产生的神迹一样，如出一辙。这些都是超越人类认知的深奥之事。

伟大的存在之链

一想到事物存在着层次，上有最至高无上的神，下有最轻简的原子，这一无限之阶梯，使世人难免惊讶万分。但是，若仔细观测，这一伟大的空想就会幻灭，正如所有的鬼怪都会在鸡鸣之时逃遁一样。

这一幻想首先无声地从无生命物质过渡到有细胞组织的物质、从纯植物到植虫、从植虫到动物、从动物到人类、再由人类到精神，而这些精神拥有轻巧的无形之体后，就成了非物质的实体，最后，这些实体，经过上千个不同的等级排名，从美到完美最终上升到上帝本身。这一等级必须得到权贵之人的青睐，他们将此等级比作教皇、红衣主教、大主教、主教、教区长、教区牧师、一般神父、主祭、副主祭，然后是修道士，这一列队最终以托钵僧结束。

其实，上帝与最完美的物种之间的距离要远远大于圣父与神学院院长之间的距离。院长可以成为教皇，但是上帝所创造的最完美的灵魂却不可能成为上帝，因为上帝与他之间存在永恒的沟壑。

这一链条，这一声称植物与动物之间存在层次之分的链条也已经被摧毁。骨螺已经灭绝。犹太人被禁止吃狮鹫和伊克西翁（ixion）。但不管博加特（Bochart）会说什么，这两个物种已经从世界上消失。那链条到底在哪里呢？

尽管有些物种我们没有失去，但是，显而易见，它们是可以被摧毁消灭的。狮子和犀牛的数量正变得越来越稀少。

有些人种已经灭绝，这极有可能。但是我真心地希望他们存活下来了，就像白人、黑人和卡菲尔人一样，自然给予了他们能遮盖肚腹到大腿部分的腰裙；也像萨莫耶德人（Samoyedes）那样，他们的妻子拥有一个漂亮的黑色乳房。

猴子与人之间难道不存在明显的差异吗？想象一下这样一种动物：拥有两条腿，没有羽毛，拥有智慧，没有能力说话，没有人类外形，却能被我们驯服，能懂得回应人类的指示，服务人类，这样的想象不容易吧？而在这种新物种与人类之间，难道我们不能设想其他的物种吗？

神圣的柏拉图啊，你在天堂里放置了一系列超越人类的神圣实体。但是，就我们而言，我们只相信其中的很小一部分，因为信念使然。但是，你又有什么理由去相信他们呢？看来你并没有和苏格拉底的恶魔谈话，大好人老厄尔（old Er）特意复活来告诉你另一世界的秘密，看来对于这些神圣实体，他也没教授你任何东西。

所谓的存在之链在这物理世界中也没少被打断。

请问，在行星们之间又存在怎样的层次之分呢？我们的地球大小是月球的40倍。当你跨越空间，从月球来到金星时，你会发现金星与地球一般大小。继续前进来到水星，水星以不同于金星圆形轨道的椭圆形轨道运转。它比地球小27倍，太阳则比地球大100万倍，地球是火星的5倍大小。火星运转周期为2年，它的邻居木星12年，土星30年，尽管这作为行星中最远的土星也不与木星一般大小。那这所谓的层次之分到底在哪里呢？

所以，你如何能期待存在这样一种链条，能将这浩瀚无垠的空间里的所有物种都联系在一起呢？如果有一种这样的链条，那毫无疑问也会是牛顿发现的：就是它能使世界上的所有行星能在这巨大的虚空之中相互吸引。

哦，柏拉图，享有如此多尊崇的柏拉图，恐怕你除了寓言之外，没有教会我们任何东西，除了诡辩，没有说出任何有价值的话语。

哦，柏拉图，你比你自己认为的还要作恶多端。我会被问到你是如何作恶的，但我不会回答。

地狱

人只要生活在这个社会里，一定会注意到有些罪人逃脱了法律的惩处。他们能惩罚公开犯罪，但是对于秘密犯罪则有必要建立一个检查机制，而只有宗教才可担此重任。波斯人、迦勒底人、埃及人和希腊人创立了死后惩罚措施，而我们已知的所有古代人中只有犹太人赞同现世惩罚。基于几段晦涩难懂的文字，我们相信或者假装去相信地狱的存在是荒谬无比的，因为地狱虽然得到了犹太人古代律法、《利未记》和摩西十诫的认可，但是这些律法的作者却从未提及任何含有来世惩罚意味的字眼。人们就有权对摩西五经的汇编者这样说：“你是一个不负责任的人，既不诚实也不理性，实在担当不起你所霸占的立法者的名号。你明知地狱这样的教义对于人们来说是多么的沉重压抑，多么的急需迫切，你竟然却不言明？另外，尽管地狱这一教义已经被你周边的国家认可接受，但是你却任由这条教义被一些评论者们肆意猜测揣度。这些人来自于你死后的4000多年，他们会考究、歪曲你的话语，从中发现一些不是你本意的东西。或者你是个无知之人，完全没有意识到这一信念在埃及、迦勒底和波斯广为流传，或者你是明知这条教义，却听从了不良建议，未将其作为你们宗教的基础。”

犹太律法的立法者们至多这样回答：“我们承认自己非常无知：我们很晚才学会写字；我们的人民是未开化之人，正如所展现的那样，我们是一个在不适合人类居住的沙漠中游荡了半个世纪之久的野蛮部落；最终，通过史无前例的残酷而可恨的掠夺侵占了一个小国家。我们与文明国家毫无交往：你如何能指望我们这种最世俗的人去创造一个纯粹的精神体系呢？

“我们只就生命意义上使用‘精神’这一词语，意为灵魂。我们认为上帝、教长和天使都是有肉体的实质存在：灵魂和肉体之分，以及来世的概念都只能是长久冥思及微妙哲学的结果。霍屯督人（Hottentots）和黑人所居住的国家是我们国家的100倍大，问问他们是否知道来世。上帝对作恶之人的惩罚会延续四代人，惩罚手段或是麻风病，或是暴毙，又或是剥夺他们有可能得到的一丁点财物。我们极力劝服人们相信这一点，此事我们已经做得足够。”

有人会这样回复这一辩解：“你创造了这样一个体系，它的荒谬之处不证自明，因为身体康健、家族繁荣的作恶者必定会对你嗤之以鼻。”然后，犹太律法的辩护者会这样回答：“你错了，因为许多罪犯根本不讲道理，也因为每个人都有清晰思维。一个犯了罪的人，自己和儿子未遭受惩罚，却害怕孙子遭受牵连。另外，如果此人在今日尚无发臭的溃疡，那么在几年之内他也会感染，因为我们都容易患上这类疾病。每个家庭都有不幸之事，而这些不幸都来自于上帝之手，来自于那秘密犯罪的惩处复仇之手，而让人们相信这点，给人们灌输这样一种信念其实非常容易。”

回应这样的回答着实容易，可以如此说：“你的辩解毫无意义，因为正经体面之人失去健康和财富的事情每天都在发生，倘若没有一个家庭能逃脱代表上帝惩罚的不幸之事，那么你所有的家庭成员必然都曾是下贱卑鄙之流。”

犹太教教士可以做进一步的反驳。他会说人之本性会附带一些不幸之事，另外的不幸之事则是上帝特别赐予的。但是，人们会让这个反驳者意识到，认为而今只是自然作用的热病和冰雹是神圣的惩罚，这样的想法何其荒谬。

最终，犹太教中的法利赛派（the Pharisees）和艾赛尼派（the Essenes）信徒以自己的方式接受了地狱这一概念。这一教条已经从希腊人传播到了罗马人那里，最终被基督教徒接受。

一些教堂的神父并不相信永恒的惩罚，因为在他们看来，让一个偷了一只羊的可怜人永久地遭受火刑的惩罚是非常可笑的。维吉尔在《埃涅阿斯纪》（Aeneid）第六卷中吟到：

……Sedet aeternumque sedebit

Infelix Theseus.

（可怜的提修斯坐着，永久地坐着。）

他暗示提修斯永久地坐在一把椅子上，而这一姿势对他来说就是折磨，但这种暗示徒然无效。其他人则认为，提修斯并未在地狱中就座，而是身处极乐世界。

不久之前，一个心善而正派的新教徒牧师在布道中写道，终有一天，受诅咒之人能得到原谅，惩罚的力度要与所犯罪行相当，一时的错误不应当接受永恒的惩罚。他的同行牧师们对他这一放纵性言论不屑一顾。有个人对他说：“亲爱的朋友，我同你一样也不相信地狱是永恒的，但是，对于你的女仆、裁缝，甚至你的律师来说，相信地狱着实是件好事。”

偶像，偶像崇拜者，偶像崇拜

“偶像”（Idol）一词源自希腊语εδoς，是形式之意；εϊδωλον，形式的展现；λατεύειν，侍候、敬畏和崇拜。“崇拜”（adore）一词是拉丁文，也拥有其他很多不同的意思，它意味着将一只手靠近嘴，满怀敬意地诉说、鞠躬、下跪、致敬，向神表达最真挚的崇拜。这些意思除了模糊还是模糊。

这里值得注意的是，《特雷乌词典》（Dictionnaire de Trévoux）在开篇就说到所有的异教徒都是偶像崇拜者，印度人仍然崇拜偶像。首先，在狄奥多西二世之前，没有人被称作异教徒，此词是用来称呼那些居住在意大利城中、固守自己古老宗教的人；其次，印度斯坦人信奉穆罕默德，而穆罕默德是偶像和偶像崇拜的坚决反对者；再次，很多印度人都信奉帕西人（Parsees）的古老宗教，所以不应当称他们为偶像崇拜者，如同不应当实行根本没有偶像的种姓制度一样。

探寻是否存在过崇拜偶像的政府

看来世上没有人想被称作偶像崇拜者，这词是一种挑衅，一种辱骂，就像gavaches（懦夫）和maranes（摩尔人）一样，前者西班牙人用来侮辱法国人，而后者法国人用来招呼西班牙人。“你是偶像崇拜者吗？”如果有人就此问题询问过罗马元老院、希腊最高法院和波斯王国法庭的人，那么他们几乎听不懂这个问题。没有人会回答说：“我们崇拜偶像。”“偶像崇拜者”和“偶像崇拜”这些词汇，在荷马、赫西奥德（Hesiod）、希罗多德（Herodotus），以及基督教徒作者们的作品中遍寻不到。也从来没有任何法令和教条命令人们去崇拜偶像，像服侍神一样去服侍他们，视他们为神。

当罗马和迦太基的领袖们缔结条约之时，他们召唤出了所有的神祇，说道：“诸神见证，我们誓保和平。”此时此刻，数量众多的诸神像并不在将军们的帐篷里，因为他们认为诸神在人类的行动中充当的是见证者和裁判官。毫无疑问，虚幻的影像是无法代替神的。

那对于神殿中虚假的神祇造像，他们持怎样的看法呢？若我说，就与我们看待自身崇拜对象的造像的态度是一样的。崇拜一块木头或大理石并无错误，错的是去崇拜这木头或大理石所代表的虚假之神。他们与我们之间的区别，并不在于他们有偶像而我们没有，而是在于他们的偶像表现了他们宗教中神奇的存在，希腊人他们有赫拉克勒斯（Hercules）像，而我们有圣·克里斯托弗（Saint Christopher）像；他们有埃斯科拉庇俄斯（Aesculapius）与他的羊，我们则有圣·罗克（Saint Roch）与他的狗；他们有雷电武装的朱庇特，我们则有帕多瓦的圣·安东尼（Saint Anthony of Padua）以及卡帕斯特拉的圣·詹姆斯（Saint James of Compostella）。

执政官普林尼（Pliny）在图拉真（Trajan）的颂词里，向不朽的神灵们祈祷之时，他并未面向具体的神像，因为这样的神像并非永恒不朽。

异教的最后时光和远古时期都不存在能够让我们断定存在偶像崇拜的事实。荷马只提及居住在奥林匹斯山的诸神。尽管帕拉斯雅典娜的神像从天堂坠落人间，但那只是帕拉斯提供保护的一个神圣保证，人们尊敬的还是雕像代表的雅典娜。

然而，罗马人和希腊人在神像前下跪，给它们戴上王冠、焚香献花、在公众场合游行展示，庆祝胜利。我们将这些风俗习惯神圣化，但我们并不是偶像崇拜者。

在干旱时期，禁食的女人手捧诸神的造像，头发蓬乱，赤脚而行，立刻迎来倾盆大雨。正如佩特罗尼乌斯（Petronius）所言，“马上下起雨来（et statim urceatim pluebat）”。难道我们没有神圣化这一仪式吗？相同的仪式，异教徒举行起来就是非法，而我们举行则是正当合法。还有多少个村庄，是不存在人们赤着脚、手捧着圣徒的圣骨匣，祈祷通过圣徒的说情而得到上天的眷顾这样的现象呢？倘若一个土耳其人或受过教育的中国人看到了这样的仪式，在不熟悉的情况下，他首先会责怪我们轻信于神的图像，携带着图像列队行进。但是只要说句话就能使之明了。

各个时期，由于罗马和希腊的偶像崇拜而产生的反对言论，其数量巨大无比，人们会对此惊讶不已。但是，如果人们发现罗马人和希腊人根本就不是偶像崇拜者，就会感到更加惊讶了。

相较于其他神庙而言，有些神庙地位较高。以弗所的狄安娜大神庙比一座村野狄安娜神庙享有更高的声誉。埃皮达鲁斯（Epidaurus）在埃斯科拉庇俄斯（Aesculapius）神庙中创造的神迹数量远比他位于其他地方的神庙多。奥林匹亚的朱庇特神像所吸引的供奉也多于帕弗拉戈尼亚（Paphlagonian）的朱庇特神像。然而，既然我们总是将正统宗教和虚假宗教的习俗加以比较，难道在好几个世纪的时间里，我们就没有向某些特定的祭坛献出更多的供奉？难道我们就没有将更多的供奉送往拉瑞多圣母院（Notre Dame of Loretto）而不是雪中圣母院（Notre Dame of the snows）？我们自己决定这些事是否应该被人抓住当成借口，从而用来指控我们进行偶像崇拜。

人们心中只有一个狄安娜，一个阿波罗和一个埃斯科拉庇俄斯，数量并不及他们所拥有的神庙数量多。仅就历史这一点来说，这就可以证明古代人并不相信神像就是神，人对神的崇拜也不能转移到神像，即偶像身上。因而，古代人根本就不是偶像崇拜者。

一个下等人，他醉心于迷信，缺乏理性思维，不懂如何去质疑、否认和相信事物；他来到神庙只是由于无所事事，或是觉得在神庙里能贵贱平等；他携带供品只是出于习惯；他也可以喋喋不休地谈论神迹，可是自己却从未做过相关调查；他是一个不比祭祀牺牲品高贵多少的下等人。我要再一次重复，这个下等人，他一看见伟大的狄安娜和雷神朱庇特，也会被那种宗教性的神圣恐怖给吓蒙，从而在不知不觉中崇拜了神像本身。这种情况有时也会发生在前来我们神庙祭拜的粗野农夫身上，然后他们就被教导说：不是木像和石像，而是蒙上帝赐福者在替人祷告，这些永生之人已获准进入天堂。

希腊人和罗马人通过崇拜和赞美增加了他们神的数量。希腊人崇拜征服者们，比如巴克斯（Bacchus）、赫拉克勒斯和珀尔修斯（Perseus），罗马人为他们的皇帝建造了祭坛。而我们的崇拜则是另一种形式，我们崇拜圣徒，而不是像他们那样崇拜半神和二类神，高位和征服都不是我们崇拜的对象。我们多半会为一些籍籍无名、没有位列仙班、仅仅只是正直善良有道德的人建立神庙。奉承和谄媚可以赢得古人的崇拜，但善良与正直才能赢得我们的尊敬。

西塞罗在他的哲学作品中经常表露这样的怀疑，他认为神的造像会被人误解，会与神本尊相互混淆。他的对话者们严词谴责当时的宗教，但是没有一个人能让西塞罗产生想法去控诉罗马人，控诉他们视大理石和黄铜为神。卢克莱修（Lucretius）申斥各种迷信之事，但他也没有因为这种愚蠢之事去责备任何人。所以，再一次证明，偶像崇拜这种观点当时是不存在的，完全没有这种概念，根本就没有偶像崇拜者。

贺拉斯（Horace）为普里阿波斯（Priapus）造了一尊像：“我曾是一颗无花果树的树干。一个木匠犹豫着是要把我当成神还是做成一把椅子，最终还是决定把我当成神，等等。”从这个笑话里我们能得出什么结论呢？普里阿波斯，作为下级神祇中的一员，饱受嘲弄。而这一笑话本身，就强有力地证明了普里阿波斯那竖立在果菜园中、用来吓退鸟类的形象并未得到人们的崇拜。

达西耶采用一种评论者的态度，说到“造像只依工匠之所愿”，说出这句话时，就表明达西耶成功地指出了巴录（Baruch）早已预测到了这一事件。然而关于所有造像之事，他能说的都已说尽。那是否可以认为，巴录对贺拉斯的讽刺诗也有自己的看法呢？

将大理石打磨成洗脸盆，和将其雕刻成亚历山大、朱庇特或者更受尊敬事物的雕像，其难度其实一样。雕刻至圣所里的智天使们所用的材料，同样可以用来制作生活器具，满足生活基本需要。难道王座和祭坛所享受到的崇高会因为工匠们可以将其制作成餐桌而降低吗？

由此，达西耶应该得出结论说罗马人是在取乐，而不是得出罗马人崇拜普里阿波斯像、巴录也预测到了此事这样的结论。翻阅所有提及神像的作者的作品，你会发现没有人谈论过偶像崇拜，恰恰相反，在马提雅尔（Martial）的作品中，你会发现：

Qui finxit sacros auro vel marmore vultus，

Non facit ille deos；……

（用金或大理石制作的神像并不能成为神。）

奥维德：

Colitur pro Jove forma Jovis.

（通过朱庇特像，朱庇特受崇拜。）

斯塔提乌斯（Statius）：

Nulla autem effigies, nulli commissa metallo

Forma del; mentes habitare ac numina gaudet.

（造像和金属不能固上帝之形，

上帝选择活在我们的脑海与心间。）

卢坎（Lucan）：

Estne del sedes, nisi terra et pontus et aer?

（上帝的家，如果不是陆地，海洋，天空，那会是什么呢？）

所有证明图像仅仅只是图像而已的段落，多得可以集结成册。

能让人产生神像体内有神存在的想法的只有那些内含神像显灵、发布神谕的例子。然而，盛行的观点肯定是认为神选择了特定的祭坛与影像，神偶尔居住在里面倾听人类的诉说并加以回复。

在荷马的作品，以及古希腊悲剧的颂词中，我们只发现向阿波罗祷告的祈祷文，阿波罗在群山中、在这座神庙里、在那个城市发布了神谕。古物中也发现很多遗迹表明祈祷者朝着造像祷告。

那些相信或假装相信巫术是科学并使用巫术的人声称他们懂得如何让神进入造像，这种神并非伟大的神，而是次等神，是魔仆。这就是墨丘利·特里斯梅季塔斯（Mercury Trismegistus）所谓的“创神”，就是圣·奥古斯丁在其《上帝之城》中所驳斥的东西。然而，既然需要巫师去激活，那么这本身也清楚地显示了造像之内并无真神存在。在我看来，巫术给予造像灵魂，让其开口说话，着实不太可能。

总之，神之像并非真神。猛掷惊雷的是朱庇特，而非其神像；翻卷大海的不是尼普顿之像；赋予我们光的也不是阿波罗之像。希腊人和罗马人是异教徒、是多神论者，但不是偶像崇拜者。

波斯人、赛伯伊人、埃及人、鞑靼人和土耳其人是否是偶像崇拜者，被称为偶像的仿像起源有多古老，以及他们崇拜的历史

将崇拜太阳和星星的人描述为偶像崇拜者着实是个极大的错误。很久以来，这些国家既无仿像也无神庙。如果他们错了，那就错在他们应当崇拜星星的创造者，而非星星本身。无论如何，收集在《伤之伤》（Sadder）一书中，琐罗亚斯德（Zoroaster）或称泽达斯特（Zerdust）的教义颂扬一个赏善罚恶、至高无上的存在，这绝非偶像崇拜。中国政府没有过任何偶像，只保留了对天之主天帝的崇拜。鞑靼人中，成吉思汗不是偶像崇拜者，也没有任何仿像。充斥在希腊、小亚细亚、叙利亚、波斯、印度和非洲的穆斯林将基督教徒视作偶像崇拜者、异教徒，因为他们坚信基督教徒崇拜神像。他们还砸毁了好几座位于君士坦丁堡圣索菲亚大教堂（Santa Sophia）、圣徒教堂和其他一些已改建为清真寺教堂的造像。表面现象对他们的误导与对人类的误导如出一辙，基督教徒为曾是凡人的圣徒建造神庙，他们的形像享受着众人下跪朝拜的尊崇，神庙中实行的神迹，所有这些都让人们相信、都证明基督教徒实行绝对的偶像崇拜，这点毋庸置疑。然而事实并非如此，实际上，基督教徒只信奉一位神，崇拜蒙神赐福的人只是崇拜上帝赋予在他们身上的特质。同样反对教会、谴责偶像崇拜的反偶像崇拜者和新教徒也已给出了相同的答案。

由于人类对于偶像崇拜者这一名称几乎没有准确概念，更未曾用明确、毫不含糊的话语表达自己的看法，所以我们将此名称扣在异教徒，尤其是多神论者头上。我们为此还书写了大量的文献，来探究他们崇拜有可见形态的一神或多神的起源，与此相关的各种观点，说法不一，交杂转述。但是，浩如烟海的书籍与观点只印证了我们的无知。

谁发明了衣服鞋袜，我们不知道，但是我们想知道是谁首先创造了偶像。桑渠尼阿通（Sanchuniathon）所说的一段话很要紧吗？此人生活在特洛伊战争之前，他说是上帝依据自己的原则，用一口气在混沌天地之间创造了原始人类，同时让天空明亮；他说是风神考尔普（Colp）和他的妻子博乌（Bau）生下了伊恩（Eon），伊恩生下了吉诺斯（Genos），他们的后裔柯罗诺斯（Chronos）在脑袋前后都有两只眼睛，在他成神之后，就将埃及赐给了他的儿子萨伍特（Thaut），我们从中能得到什么启示呢？这可是古代最令人敬佩的不朽之作之一。

俄耳甫斯（Orpheus）生活时代早于桑渠尼阿通。大马士革乌斯（Damascius）帮我们留存了他的作品《诸神之谱》（Theogony），但是此书也未带给我们更多的启示。俄耳甫斯所呈现的世界取形于一只双头龙，一为牛首，一为狮头，中间有一张被他称为“上帝之面”的脸，肩部拥有镀金的翅膀。

然而，我们从这些光怪陆地的想法中可以得出两个伟大的真理：一是明显可见的图形和象形符号起源于最远古的时代；二是所有的古代哲学家们都认同第一性原则。

至于多神论，良好的判断力会让你知道，人类是一种体弱的动物，拥有理智却也能行愚蠢之事，屈从于每一次事故、疾病和死亡。这些人类已经体会到了自己的虚弱和依赖性。于是，他们很快地就认识到存在一些事物比人类来得更强大。从供给人类食物的土地里、从时常带给他们毁灭性打击的天空中、从耗尽的火焰、浸入的水中，人类都感觉到了一种力量。还有什么比无知人类想象有一个特殊的存在统治着这些元素来得更自然的呢？还有什么比崇拜那能使太阳和繁星在我们眼中闪耀的无形力量来得更自然的呢？人类一旦形成观念，认为这些力量更加崇高，那他们以有形之物来代表这些力量不就最自然不过了吗？否则他们究竟能做什么呢？比我们基督教更早并由上帝亲自赐福的犹太教里充斥了以下这样一些代表上帝的图像：上帝身处灌木丛中屈尊讲着人类语言；上帝在一座高山中现身；所有经上帝派遣而来的神之灵魂均以人形现身；甚至充斥在至圣所里的小天使们都拥有人类身体，外加翅膀和动物脑袋。这就使得普鲁塔克、塔西佗（Tacitus）、亚庇（Appian），以及如此之多的人错误地责备了犹太人，谴责他们崇拜一头驴的头颅。上帝禁止人类为他画像或制作雕塑，然而尽管如此，他还是调整自身，屈尊为人形，而人形柔弱，需要借助形象去实现沟通。

《以赛亚书》第六章中，以赛亚看见上帝端坐在王座之上，长袍的裙裾遍及神庙。据这位先知所书的第一章中所言，上帝伸出手，触摸到了耶利米（Jeremiah）的嘴。《以西结书》第三章，以西结看见一座蓝宝石的王座，上帝以人形之态端坐在王座之上。这些图像并未腐蚀犹太教的纯洁性，他们从来不使用图像、造像和偶像来代表世人眼中的上帝。

受过教育的中国人、帕西人和古代埃及人都没有偶像，然而伊西斯（Isis）和奥西里斯（Osiris）的图像很快出现，天地之神贝尔（Bel）的巨像也出现在了巴比伦。在印度群岛，梵天是一个怪物。尤其是希腊人，他们为神命名、制作雕像、建造神庙，数量巨大，但是他们总将至高无上的力量归因于宙斯（Zeus），即拉丁语中的朱庇特，人类之神，神中之主。罗马人效仿了希腊人的做法。这些人总将所有的神都置于天空之内，但却不知天空之意。

罗马人有12主神，6男6女，将其命名为：朱庇特、尼普顿、阿波罗、伏尔甘、玛尔斯、墨丘利、朱诺、维斯塔、密涅瓦、刻瑞斯、维纳斯、狄安娜。布鲁托当时被忘记了，维斯塔替代了他的位置。

其次就是次级神，包括：当地神灵；英雄人物，比如巴克斯、赫拉克勒斯和埃斯科拉庇俄斯（Aesculapius）；地狱之神，布鲁托、普洛塞尔皮娜（Proserpine）；海之神，比如西蒂斯（Thetis）、安菲特律特（Amphitrite）、涅瑞伊得斯（Nereids）和格劳克斯（Glaucus）；护树女神德律阿得斯（Dryads）和水泽女神那伊阿得（Naiads）；还有园艺、畜牧之神。每一个行业、每一种活动、孩童、待嫁少女、已婚妇女和分娩女子都有神照管。他们还有放屁之神。最终，他们尊皇帝为神明。然而，实际上，无论是这些帝王、放屁之神、性爱享乐女神普特腾达（Pertunda）、男性生殖神普里阿普斯（Priapus），还是乳房女神鲁米莉亚（Rumilia）、厕所之神斯特库蒂乌斯（Stercutius），他们都不是天地之主。人间帝王有时还有庙宇，主管日常生活的次级神则没有；但是他们全部都有自己的形象和偶像。这些偶像们其实就是小型造像，男人用它们来装饰书房，老妇和孩子们用它们来娱乐消遣，并未享受到公众崇拜。每个个体的迷信思想都太过骄纵放任了。这样的小偶像如今还能在古代城市的废墟中找到。

尽管无人知晓人类何时开始制造偶像，但是我们知道他们必定始于最古老的时期。亚伯拉罕的父亲他拉（Terah）在迦勒底的乌尔（Ur）制作偶像；拉结（Rachel）从继父拉班（Laban）处偷走偶像。除此之外，无法再追溯更早的时期了。

然而，古人对这些仿像到底拥有怎样确切的看法呢？赋予了它们怎样的品德和力量？人们是相信诸神屈尊从天堂下来，隐匿于这些造像之中，还是相信诸神将一部分的神魂让渡给了造像，或是认为诸神并未让渡任何东西给造像？这些问题也曾是很多无用之作的探讨主题。显而易见，每个人都是依据自身的理性、盲从和狂热程度作出判断。很显然，神职人员会赋予造像尽可能多的神性，用来吸引更多的供奉。我们知道，哲人斥责这些为迷信、勇士们采取取笑态度、执法官对此表示容忍，而总是荒谬可笑的普通人则不知到底为何物。简而言之，这就是所有尚不知神的国家的历史。

从埃及人崇拜公牛，一些城市的人崇拜狗、猴子、猫和洋葱的事例中，人们可以得出一个相同的看法。那就是，这些事物起先都只是徽章符号，然后某一头牛成了神牛埃皮斯（Apis），某一只狗成了墓穴神安努毕斯（Anubis），从而受到人们的崇拜。人们仍旧吃牛排和洋葱，但是很难想象古埃及女人是如何看待神圣的洋葱和公牛。

偶像们经常开口说话。将自然女神西布莉（Cybele）的造像从阿塔罗斯（Attalus）国王宫殿移走之时，神像所说的优雅言辞，在罗马还成为庆祝该女神节日时的纪念。

Ipsa peri volui; ne sit mora, mitte volentem：

Dignus Roma locus quo deus omnis eat.

（我想被搬走，赶紧把我搬走，

罗马值得成为每个神的家园。）

命运之神（Fortune）的造像也说过话、显过灵。西庇阿斯（Scipios）、西塞罗和恺撒大帝不信此事是真的，但是接受恩可比乌斯（Encolpius）用王冠换鹅的老妇人以及众神可能会相信。

偶像们也发布神谕，但是，是由教士们藏在中空的造像内，以神的名义开口说话。

众神林立，神谱众多，外加一些个体教派，神的数量巨大而繁杂，然而为何在所谓的偶像崇拜者之间从未发生过任何宗教战争呢？这种和平是邪恶和错误自身的优秀产物。因为每一个国家自己都承认几个次等神，那么理所当然周边邻里国家也应该有他们自己神。除了杀死神牛埃皮斯而饱受斥责的冈比西斯（Cambyses），我们在世俗世界的历史上，没有发现任何征服者去凌辱被征服者的神明。异教徒们没有信奉唯一真神的宗教，所以教士们只能去增加供奉和祭品的数量。

祭品最初只是水果。不久之后，教士们的桌子需要动物了，他们自己动手，宰杀动物，他们成了屠夫，冷血而残忍。最终，他们引进了人祭那恐怖的仪式，祭品最好是孩童和处女。中国人、帕西人和印度人都未曾实施过这种令人憎恶的仪式，但是据波尔菲里（Porphyry）所言，人祭在埃及希拉波利斯（Hieropolis）实行过。

在陶里斯（Tauris），外邦人会成为祭品。幸运的是，陶里斯的教士们并未实施很多。早期希腊人、塞浦路斯人、腓尼基人、提尔人和迦太基人都信奉这种可憎的迷信。罗马人自己也陷入了这种宗教犯罪中，据普鲁塔克报告，他们生祭了2名希腊人、2名高卢人，来为3名处女的情爱之事赎罪。与法兰克人国王西奥多贝特（Theodobert）同时代的普罗科匹厄斯（Procopius）告诉我们，法兰克人与这位国君进入意大利之时将人献祭。高卢人和日耳曼人经常实行这种恐怖的人祭。阅读历史时，想要不读到人类所制造的恐怖之事，这几乎是不可能的。

犹太人中，杰弗瑟（Jephtah）将其女儿献祭、扫罗（Saul）打算牺牲其儿子，这是事实。献身于上帝却被上帝诅咒之人，不能像动物回归那样回归教门，而是应当永久消逝，这也是事实。犹太教教士撒母耳（Samuel）用一把神圣的短柄小斧将国王亚甲（Agag）砍成碎片。亚甲是一名战俘，已得到扫罗的原谅，但是扫罗却因遵守国家律法、原谅这位国王得受到谴责。然而，上帝，作为人之主，乐意之时便可夺走他们的生命，如何乐意，以及借谁之手都依上帝之意。人类无法将自身放置于主人的生死之地上，也无法篡夺上帝的权利。

为了就这种恐怖奇观、这些虔诚却悖理逆天的行为去安慰人类，我们一定要知道，几乎在所有被称为偶像崇拜者的国度里，都存在神圣神学和普遍错误，存在秘密祭礼和公开仪式，也存在智者之宗教与粗鄙之宗教。在秘密宗教仪式中，新入教徒被教导说只有唯一的真神，对此人们只需瞟一眼赞美诗就可得知。此诗被认为是俄耳甫斯所作，在刻瑞斯厄琉希诺斯（Ceres Eleusinus）的秘密宗教仪式上吟唱，在欧亚两洲闻名遐迩：“凝视神圣本性，照亮你的灵魂，支配你的内心，走上正义之路。愿天地之神与你常伴。上帝，独特唯一，单独自存，所有生灵均起源于他，受他供养。他从未在凡人面前露面，但他无所不知。”

也看看以下这段摘自马道拉斯的马克西姆斯（Maximus of Madaurus）写给圣·奥古斯丁的信件中的一段话：“存在这样一位神，他至高无上、亘古不变、无穷无尽，他是所有生灵之父、却未创造过任何类似于自己的东西。也不在什么样的人粗鄙、愚蠢到去怀疑此点。”

上千文献可以证明智者哲人不仅痛恨偶像崇拜，也憎恶多神论。

埃皮克提图（Epictetus）是苦难忍受与耐性之典范，他是如此伟大以至于就算是在极端恶劣的情况下，都只谈上帝，不论其他。以下是他的格言之一：“上帝创造了我，他就在我体内，处处与我相伴。难道我要用淫秽之思、不公之行与可耻的欲望将他玷污吗？我的责任就是去感谢他，赞美他，祝福他，只有死亡能让我停止。”埃皮克提图的所有思想都围绕这一原则，那么他是偶像崇拜者吗？

在罗马皇帝中的伟大程度不亚于埃皮克提图在奴隶制中地位的马可·奥里利乌斯（Marcus Aurelius）常说，无论众神是遵从公认语言、还是求助于介于上帝与人之间的中间存在，这两者都是真实的。然而，有多少处地方都未表露他只承认一位亘古不变、无穷无尽的神！他说：“我们的灵魂是神性溢出之物。我的孩子、肉体和智慧都来自于上帝。”

斯多葛学派和柏拉图学派都承认存在一种神圣自然理法。伊壁鸠鲁派对此表示反对。罗马教宗在秘密宗教仪式上也只提到一名真神。那哪里存在偶像崇拜者呢？我们所有的词汇贩子都宣称存在偶像崇拜，就像小狗听见大狗狂吠之时也会学样。

至于其他，《莫雷里词典》（Moréri's Dictionary）声称，在狄奥多西（Theodosius）时代，偶像崇拜只在遥远的亚洲和非洲国家存在。此等说法是该词典所犯的重大错误之一。甚至在7世纪之时，意大利仍有许多异教徒。查理曼大帝时代，德意志北部地区，威悉河（Weser）以北也不信奉基督教。波兰以及所有北部地区，在查理曼大帝之后很长一段时间都被认为实行偶像崇拜。半个非洲、所有恒河彼岸王国、日本、中国普通民众，以及鞑靼人上百个部落都保持着自己的传统祭祀仪式。而欧洲只有少量的拉普兰人（Laplanders）、萨莫耶德人和鞑靼人保留了他们的祖传宗教。

总之，我要提醒一下，中世纪时代，我们将信奉穆罕穆德的国家称之为异教国。我们自己完全符合偶像崇拜者的条件，是一群对偶像充满畏惧的人。我们必须再一次承认，当土耳其人看见我们的祭坛挂满了图像、摆满了雕塑之时，他们将我们视为偶像崇拜者着实更加情有可原。

约瑟夫

《约瑟夫的故事》被视为新奇之作和文学著作，是古时期留给我们的最宝贵的遗产。《约瑟夫的故事》是所有东方作家作品中的典范之作，比荷马的《奥德赛》更感人，因为一个宽恕的英雄比一个雪耻复仇的英雄更能触动人心。

人们一贯认为阿拉伯人第一个写就了那些绝妙精巧，被译作多国文字的故事。然而，我却无法从中找到一个冒险故事能与约瑟夫的故事媲美。在约瑟夫的故事里，几乎所有的事物都不可思议，故事的结局动人心弦。故事里有一个16岁的少年，因遭到兄弟的嫉妒被卖给一个以实玛利（Ishmaelite）商队，随后他被带往埃及，卖给一个服侍国王的阉人做奴隶。此阉人有一个妻子，这一点也不奇怪。科斯拉瑞卡（Kislaraga）是一个彻头彻尾的阉人，他那东西被切得彻彻底底，然而他在如今的君士坦丁堡却有一群妻妾，他失了眼，丢了手，却没有丧失内心源自天性的权利。而另外一些只切掉了两个生殖器伴随物的阉人却仍旧频繁地使用生殖器官，其中一个阉人很有可能是波提乏（Potiphar），也就是约瑟夫的买主。

波提乏的妻子爱上了年轻的约瑟夫，而约瑟夫出于对主人，同时也是恩人的忠诚之心，而拒绝了这女人的求爱。约瑟夫的拒绝触怒了这女人，于是她控告约瑟夫，诬陷他试图引诱自己。这故事就相当于希波吕托斯（Hippolytus）与菲德拉（Phaedra）、柏勒罗丰（Bellerophon）与斯忒涅玻亚（Stheneboea），海布罗斯（Hebrus）与达玛斯帕（Damasippa）、坦尼斯（Tanis）与佩雷比（Peribea）、马提尔（Myrtil）与希波达弥亚（Hippodamia），以及珀琉斯（Peleus）与德梅内特（Demenette）之间的故事。

这么多故事里，我们很难分辨出谁才是鼻祖。然而，在古阿拉伯作家的作品里，约瑟夫与波提乏妻子之间的冒险故事还是具有浓厚的原创色彩的。这位作家想象着：波提乏在妻子和约瑟夫之间举棋不定，他并不认为那被妻子自己扯开的束腰外衣是证明约瑟夫实行侵犯行为的证据。当时这女人的房间里还有一个坐在摇篮里的孩子。约瑟夫说是她自己扯开了衣服，脱掉了束腰外衣，当时这孩子也在。波提乏询问了这孩子，这孩子在这年纪已经十分聪慧，他对波提乏说道：“看看这束腰外衣到底是从前面脱掉的还是从后面脱掉的，如果是前者，那么这就证明约瑟夫试图侵犯她，而她自卫反抗；如果是后者，那么这就证明你妻子正在追求约瑟夫。”多亏这孩子机智，波提乏认定他的奴隶是清白的。这就是这位古阿拉伯作者在《古兰经》中所详述的约瑟夫的冒险经历。这孩子智力非凡、判断明智，可作者并不考虑告诉我们这个孩子到底是谁的。如果这孩子是波提乏妻子的儿子，那么约瑟夫就不是这女人追求的第一个人了。

尽管如此，据《创世纪》记载，约瑟夫被投入监狱，与埃及国王的酒侍和面包师关在一起。这两个犯人晚上做梦了，约瑟夫为他们解梦，并预测说三天之内，酒侍会重新受宠，而面包师会被吊死，后来事情果真如此。

两年之后，埃及国王也做梦了。他的酒侍告诉他说，在监狱里有个年轻的犹太人，是世界上最懂得解梦的人。国王召来这位年轻人，他预测了7年丰收与7年饥荒。

稍微打断一下这故事的发展线索，让我们来看看古代解梦的奇妙之处。雅各（Jacob）曾在梦中见到那神秘的、通往上帝所在的阶梯。他在梦中学到了一种繁殖羊群的方法，这种方法唯有他能成功使用。他也在梦中得知终有一天他会统治他所有的兄弟。很久以前，亚比米勒（Abimelech）曾在梦中被警告说萨拉是亚伯拉罕的妻子。

回到约瑟夫的故事。约瑟夫一解读出法老的梦境，就立刻被任命为总理大臣。我们可能会怀疑，如今就算是在亚洲，是否能够找到这样一个国王，仅仅因为解梦，就将如此重要的政府职位授予他人。法老让约瑟夫娶了波提乏的一个女儿为妻。据说波提乏是赫利奥波利斯（Heliopolis）的大祭司，所以这个波提乏并不是约瑟夫的第一个阉人主人，如果是，那么除了大祭司这一称呼外，波提乏肯定还有其他称谓，他的妻子也生过不止一个孩子。

与此同时，正如约瑟夫所预测的那样，饥荒如期到来。而约瑟夫完全对得起国王的厚爱，他迫使人们将自己的土地卖与法老，整个国家的子民为了换取粮食均沦为奴隶。显而易见，这就是专制权力的开端。但是必须承认，从没有一个国王做交易能做得如此漂亮，然而人民却无法由衷地祝福这位总理大臣。

后来，饥荒席卷了整个大地，约瑟夫的父亲和兄弟们也需要粮食。在这里，完全没有必要描述约瑟夫是如何接受、原谅并带领他的兄弟们发家致富的。所有组成一部有趣史诗的素材在这故事中都能找到：引子、困苦、赞誉、变迁和奇迹。东方天才的标记在这里彰显得无比显著。

约瑟夫的父亲雅各回答法老的话语，一定给所有能读能写之人都留下了深刻的印象。“你的生命能持续多少日，多少年？”国王问到。“我的朝圣之行持续了130年，而在这短暂的朝圣之旅中我从未有过快乐的一天。”

朱迪亚

感谢上帝，我从未去过朱迪亚（Judea），以后也决不会去。从那里回来的各个国家的人我都见过，他们告诉我说耶路撒冷这地方可怕极了，周边都是山石林立，山体裸露，闻名遐迩的约旦河也只有45英尺宽，这国家唯一环境较好的省份就是耶利哥。简而言之，他们都认同圣哲罗姆的看法。圣哲罗姆长久以来都居住在耶稣降生之地伯利恒（Bethlehem），他将这块地方描述为被自然抛弃之地，这里夏天的时候甚至都没有饮用水，然而，这地方对于刚从沙漠穿越而来的犹太人而言还是一块宝地。可怜的人们离开荒沙之地朗德省（Landes），定居到蓝珀尔丹（Lampourdan）（大约在巴约纳附近）的群山里，他们会赞美自己的新家。倘若他们曾经想要继续前进，来到朗格多克（Languedoc）的富饶地区，那么他们会震惊不已，认为这就是应许之地。

这恰恰就是犹太人的历史。耶利哥和耶路撒冷就是图卢兹和蒙彼利埃，西奈沙漠就是横在波尔多和巴约纳之间的国度。然而，如果引导犹太人的上帝想赐予他们肥沃的土地，如果这些不幸之事在埃及实际存在，那么上帝为什么不把犹太人留在那里？关于此问题，仅有的解答就是一些神学术语。据说朱迪亚就是应许之地。上帝对亚伯拉罕说：“自埃及河流起至幼发拉底河之间的土地，我都将赐予你们。”

哎！我的朋友，你从未见识过幼发拉底河和尼罗河那些肥沃的河岸，他们欺骗了你。尼罗河和幼发拉底河的主人们轮流充当你们的主人，你们几乎总是奴隶。承诺和实践完全是两回事，可怜的犹太人。你们曾有一个老拉比阅读着那预告你们奶与蜜之地的明智预言之时，大声呼喊说在你们得到的许诺中黄油多于面包。你们意识到了吗？现在如果大土耳其（Grand Turk）授予我耶路撒冷统治者的地位，我会对此不屑一顾。

看着这个令人嫌恶的国家，腓特烈二世曾公开说，摩西带领那些别人唯恐避之不及的同伴们来到这里真是糊涂，“为什么他不去那不勒斯呢？”腓特烈二世说道。再见了，我亲爱的犹太人。我很抱歉那应许之地竟然是荒原之地。

享乐

人们在诗词和散文里慷慨陈词了2000年，一再反对享乐，却又沉迷其中。

最早期的罗马人，是毁坏、掠夺邻居收成，摧毁沃尔西人（Volscians）和萨谟奈人（Samnites）的贫困村庄，只求缓解己方困难的强盗，关于他们，还有什么未被提及呢？那就是他们曾是公正无私、善良正直之人！那时他们都还没能力去偷窃金银宝石，因为受他们洗劫的所有地方没有这些东西。他们的树林和沼泽既不产鹧鸪，也不生野鸡，他们的温和节制受到了赞扬！

他们一点点地掠夺干净，偷光了亚得里亚海远端至幼发拉底河之间的所有财富，同时也有了足够的意识要去享受这累积了七八百年之久的掠夺之物。于是，他们发展各式的艺术，体验各种享乐，甚至也让被征服者们品尝一番。当他们做这些事时，有人说这些罗马人不再明智，不再正直。

所有的这些雄辩之词就是为了证明：一个小偷决不能吃他自己偷来的食物，穿他自己盗来的衣服，也不能用抢来的戒指装饰自己。据说，小偷们如果想做一个正直的人，那么所有的这些财物都应弃入江河。这还不如说人们不应该偷窃。强盗们掠夺之时要谴责他们，但是当他们在享乐自己夺来之物时，就不要辱骂他们是疯子了。老实说，很多英国水手通过掠夺本地治里（Pondicherry）和哈瓦那（Havana）大发横财，后来回到伦敦，尽情享乐，以犒劳自己在亚洲、非洲的危险情况下所遭受的苦痛，这难道错了吗？

难道空谈家是想埋葬那些通过战争、农业、贸易和工业而累积起来的财富吗？他们举了斯巴达的实例。那他们为什么不引用圣马里诺共和国的例子呢？斯巴达对希腊到底作出了怎样的贡献？他们有德摩斯梯尼（Demosthenes）、索福克勒斯（Sophocles）、阿佩利斯（Apelles）和菲狄亚斯（Phidias）吗？享乐的雅典各行各业里都涌现出了伟大的人物。斯巴达却只有少数的几个船长，其数量甚至比其他的一些城邦还要少。但是，就让它这样吧！就让斯巴达这样的小共和国持续它的贫困吧。穷困潦倒和惬意享乐都会迎来死亡。加拿大的野蛮人，与拥有5万基尼收入的英格兰公民，一样都活着，一样都会变老。但是谁又会去拿易洛魁人（Iroquois）的国家与英格兰相比呢？

就让拉古沙共和城邦（republic of Ragusa）和楚格州（canton of Zug）制定禁止享乐的律法吧。他们做得对，的确有必要让穷人避免入不敷出。但是我又在某个地方读到了这样的一段话：

Sachez surtout que le luxe enrichit

Un grand état, s'il en perd un petit.

（享乐成就大国，毁灭小国。）

如果你眼中的享乐是过度之意，那么其实每个人都知道，凡事过度都是有害无益，正如暴饮暴食要节制，慷慨挥霍要节约。我不知道我所居住的村庄是怎么回事，这里土地贫瘠、赋税沉重，所收获的小麦严禁出口。然而，所有农夫都能穿上上等布料制作的衣服鞋袜，衣食无忧。如果这农夫身穿白色亚麻华服、头顶卷曲且经过精心修饰的发式，那么这肯定就是极致的奢侈，非常不合时宜。但是如果一个巴黎或伦敦的资本家打扮成农夫的模样进入剧院，那么这资本家就是最无礼，最荒谬的吝啬鬼。

Est modus in rebus, sunt certi denique fines，

Quos ultra citraque nequit consistere rectum.

（所有的事情都有一个固定的衡量标准，

既不可逾越也不可不及。）

剪刀肯定不是最伟大的古代遗产。发明剪刀之初，关于第一个使用它来修甲理发的人，还有什么是没被提到的呢？那时，毫无疑问，剪刀是代表名利与地位的工具，花花公子和浪荡子们高价购买，这是对造物主作品的糟蹋。我们的指尖末端是上帝让其生长的小角，剪短它们这是多大的罪过！这是对神的冒犯，这比发明衬衫、袜子更加恶劣。这下我们知道了那些从未穿过它们的老派议员，向那些已向这些致命奢侈品投降的年轻执法官叫嚷之时，是多么的愤怒。

殉道

对于所有有关殉道者的谎言，我们只能捧腹大笑。这样的人包括提图斯（Titus）、图拉真和马可·奥里利乌斯，他们本是道德的典范，却被描述成残忍的野兽。洛克迪（Loc-Dieu）修道院院长弗勒里（Fleury）的神职生涯因为一些故事，一些凡是明白事理的女人都不会告诉小孩子的故事而蒙羞。

罗马人惩罚70人中的7位处女，要求每一位处女都必须让安卡拉城邦内所有的年轻男子享用一次，同样也是罗马人，他们会因为一点小小的情爱之事就判处处女死刑，这样的事情真的会再次重现吗？创作这一故事的人，是一个叫作狄奥多士（Theodotus）、信奉基督教的酒馆老板，他向上帝祈祷说与其让这7个处女丧失童贞，还不如处死她们。如果这样说，显然这会使酒馆老板们心情愉悦。上帝倾听了这一过分正经的酒店老板的祈祷，于是地方总督将这7名少女溺毙在湖中。这些少女一溺亡，就找到狄奥多士，抱怨他在她们身上使用诡计，但诚心恳求他帮忙，让她们的尸身免受湖中鱼虾吞食的命运。于是狄奥多士带上他酒馆中的3个酒徒，由神之火炬和神之骑士领路，一同前往那湖边，将这7人的尸身打捞上来，加以埋葬，最后狄奥多士自己却因此被绞死。

戴克里先（Diocletian）曾遇到一个叫圣·罗马，说话结巴的小男孩，他想烧死这孩子，因为这孩子是一个基督教徒。此时恰好有3个犹太人也在场，他们开始大笑，因为耶稣基督竟然允许一个皈依他的小男孩被人烧死。他们大声说道，他们的宗教要优于基督教，因为上帝将沙得拉（Shadrach）、米煞（Meshach）和亚伯尼歌（Abednego）投入了炙热的火炉。此时正包围着小罗马的火焰并未伤及他，而是立刻分散开来，将这3个犹太人烧死。皇帝戴克里先震惊了，说他不想与上帝有争执，但有一个不太认真负责的乡村法官判处这小结巴割舌的刑罚。皇帝的首席医生还亲自动手，堂而皇之地实施了这一手术。小罗马的舌头一被割掉，立刻就能流利地与人谈话，令在场的人无不感到钦佩。

这样的故事在殉教史中能找到成百上千个，他们想要让古罗马人显得可憎，却让自己变得荒谬。你想要实施完美、证据充分的暴行；想要真实性经过严格验证的大屠杀；想要看到血海真的横流；想要父亲、母亲、男人、女人和孩子们胸口受创，尸体成堆？热衷迫害的野兽们，只能去你们的编年史里寻找这些真相：你会在针对阿尔比派（Albigensians）的十字军战争中，会在梅兰多勒（Mérindol）和卡布里埃（Cabrières）大屠杀中，会在圣·巴多罗买（Saint Bartholomew）的可怖一天中，也会在爱尔兰大屠杀和瓦勒度派（Waldenses）的山谷中找到的。是你这野蛮人将惨无人道的残暴行径归咎于最伟大的皇帝；是你让欧洲洪水泛滥，尸横遍野，要证明在顷刻之间可以到达成千上万个不同的地方，证明教皇可以兜售赎罪券！不要再诽谤中伤罗马人了，是他们让你制定了自己的律法，也是他们为不受你们先祖喜爱的人事向上帝祈求原谅。

你说，不是磨难造就了殉道者，而是原因。我承认你们的牺牲者不应该被冠以殉道者之名，殉道者意为见证者。但是，应该怎样称呼你们这些刽子手呢？法拉里斯（Phalaris）和布西里斯（Busiris），相较于你而言，是最绅士的名字。你那仍旧存在的宗教法庭难道不会让理性、人性和宗教战栗不已吗？伟大的上帝！如果这可憎的法庭归于尘土，那么你那有仇必报的凝视目光会不高兴吗？

奇迹

奇迹（miracle），就其完全意义来说，是个极妙的事物。从这层意义上说，所有事物都是不可思议的。自然界的奇妙秩序、一亿个球体围绕100万个太阳运转、光的运动，以及动物的生活都是永恒的奇迹。

通常，我们所说的奇迹，打破了这些神圣而永恒的定律。如果在月圆之时出现日食，如果一个死人手提脑袋，但还能双脚行走，那么我们把这些叫作奇迹。

几位自然哲学家认为，从这层意义上说，奇迹不可能存在，以下是他们的论证。

奇迹，是对神圣、不变且永恒的数学定律的违反。若依据此定义，那么奇迹，毫不含糊地说，就是一个矛盾体。一条定律不可能在保持不变的同时又被打破。然而，有人问他们，上帝可不可以让自己创造的定律暂时失效呢？他们底气十足地回答说毫无可能，拥有无限智慧的神不可能为了打破定律而去创造定律。他们说，上帝可以中断机器运转，但只是为了改进功能。如今，显而易见，这巨大无比的机器与上帝本身一样优秀。而他，作为上帝，能够创造这机器。如果发现物质的自然性导致缺陷出现，上帝就会从头再来，所以机器里的任何东西，上帝从不改变。

另外，上帝做事，事必有因，那是什么原因能让他去暂时损毁自己的作品呢？他们会被告知说那是为了人类的利益。他们则回复说，那就一定是为了全人类的利益，因为神性不为整个人类种族，而只为少数个人服务，这样的事情是不可想象的。但是无论怎样，人类种族其实也没有很多，这浩瀚无垠的空间内存在所有人类数量要远远小于一个小型蚁山中蚂蚁的数量。神，出于维护生存在这小泥堆上的三四百只蚂蚁的利益，选择去改变那维持整个宇宙运转的巨型引擎的永恒运转模式。现在设想一下这样的事情，难道不是愚蠢荒谬至极的吗？

然而，我们假设一下，上帝想偏爱某一小部分人：那么他需要对自己创造的永恒且无处不在的东西作出改变吗？他完全没有一丝必要去做这种改变，用这种反复无常去讨好他自己创造的生物。上帝的偏爱体现在那独特的戒律中，他为他们预测并安排所有事情，而这些人也都义无反顾地臣服于他的力量，受这种力量的影响深入骨髓。

那为什么上帝要行奇迹呢？是给少数一些人完成一个既定的计划吗？那么上帝会说：“通过创造宇宙，颁布神圣法令，制定永恒定律，我仍有一个计划没能完成。所以我将改变一些永恒不变的观念和定律，而去实施一些我不能借助它们来完成的事情。”这不是上帝力量的展示，而是软弱的告白，是他自身最不可思议的矛盾之处。所以，将奇迹归因于上帝其实是对上帝的侮辱（如果人类可以侮辱上帝的话），因为这等于对他说：“你是一个软弱无能，反复无常的存在。”因而，相信神迹，实在荒诞可笑，因为那是对神的羞辱。

这些窘迫的自然哲学家被告知说：“你们欢庆神的不变性，神之定律的永恒性，以及神之世界的规律性注定是徒劳无功的。我们这些小小的泥土堆已经见证了大量的奇迹发生，历史上神迹发生的频率并不亚于自然事件。大祭司安纽斯的女儿们，把她们拣选的所有东西都变成了大麦、葡萄酒和油；墨丘利的女儿艾萨丽达（Athalida）复活了好几次；埃斯科拉庇俄斯（Aesculapius）也让希波吕托斯（Hippolytus）复活了；赫拉克勒斯将阿尔刻提斯（Alcestis）从死亡线上拉回来；赫勒斯（Heres）在地狱中度过两星期后回到世界；罗穆卢斯（Romulus）和雷穆斯（Remus）的父母一个是神，一个是纯洁的处女；帕拉斯雅典娜的神像在特洛伊城从天堂落下；贝雷尼丝（Berenice）的毛发变成群星；鲍西丝（Baucis）和费莱蒙（Philemon）的破旧小屋变成了一座辉煌的神庙；俄耳甫斯的头颅死后还可宣读神谕；底比斯（Thebes）的城墙在希腊人的见证下，仅在一阵笛声中就拔地而起；埃斯科拉庇俄斯神殿中成功治愈的病人不计其数，我们还有记录，记载着埃斯科拉庇俄斯创造神迹时的见证人名单。

还有哪些人群没有行过难以置信的奇迹吗，特别是在很多人都不会读写的时代？请告诉我。

自由思想家，对于这些异议的回答，只有大声地嘲笑和不屑地耸肩。然而基督教哲学家则说：“我们相信自己神圣宗教里出现的奇迹，相信奇迹凭借的是信念而非理智，我们尽全力不去理会理智的声音，因为众所周知，信念说话时理智靠边站。发生在耶稣基督和他使徒们身上的神迹，我们坚定并且全心全意地相信，但是你必须允许我们对有些奇异之事保持一点点的怀疑态度。比如，有一个故事，其阐述者是一个享有伟大之名的普通人，他声称有一个小修道士非常善于行奇迹，以至于修道院院长最终禁止他运用自己这项才能。这小修道士遵照了指示。但是，当他看到一个可怜的砖瓦匠从房顶上跌落下来时，他在救人与神圣服从之间犹豫不决，于是他将这砖瓦匠停留在空中，他自己跑去问修道院院长该如何行事。这院长认定他未经允许就行奇迹，一开始就是罪过，但考虑到他中止实施并未再犯，就允许他将其完成。对于这样的故事，请允许我们持保留态度。我们同意自由思想家的看法，认为这个故事可信度不高。”

但是，他们会被问到，你怎敢否认圣·格瓦斯（Saint Gervase）和圣·普罗泰西乌斯（Saint Protasius）出现在圣·安布罗斯（Saint Ambrose）的梦中，并告诉他哪里能找到他们的遗骸呢？怎敢否认圣·安布罗斯将他们挖掘出来，否认他们治好了一个盲人呢？当时，圣·奥古斯丁正在米兰，正是他报告了这一奇迹。“无数人充当了见证”（Immensopopulo teste），他在《上帝之城》第22章写道。这是证据充分，可信度最高的奇迹之一。但是，自由思想家说他们一个字都不信，他们认为格瓦斯和普罗泰西乌斯并未出现在任何人面前，人类知不知道他们的尸骸到底在哪里一点都不重要，他们也不相信这个盲人，正如不相信维斯帕先（Vespasian）一样，认为这是个毫无用处的奇迹，但上帝从不做无用之事，也表明他们会坚定地坚持自己的原则。我对圣·格瓦斯和圣·普罗泰西乌斯的尊敬，不允许我与这些自由思想家持相同观点，我只是表述他们的怀疑。卢西安（Lucian）的很多文章都提起过他们，在其《异邦人之死》（Death of Peregrinus）中说道：“当一个玩杂耍的高手变成基督徒之时，他一定会找到自己的路。”但是，由于卢西安是一个世俗作家，那他对于我们而言，就无权威性可言。

这些自由思想家无法让自己相信发生在2世纪的奇迹。那么目击证人记载以下这些东西就是徒然无功的，士麦那（Smyrna）主教圣·波利卡（Saint Polycarp）被判处火刑，扔进火焰时，他们听到一个来自天堂的声音大声喊道：“勇气，波利卡！坚强，像个男人一样。”柴堆上的火焰脱离了波利卡的身体，在头的上方形成了一道火幕，一只鸽子从火堆之间飞出。最终，他们不得不砍掉了波利卡的头颅。“这个奇迹有什么好？”怀疑者问道。“为什么火焰失去了它的特性，为什么不是刽子手的斧头着火？为什么殉道者能从滚烫的油锅中安然无恙地存活下来却死于剑刃之下？”他们回答说，这是神的旨意。但是自由思想家们还是偏向于自己亲眼所见后再相信。

那些依靠知识增强论据力度的人会告诉你说，教堂里的神父们自己都经常承认说，在他们的时代奇迹也久不曾出现。圣·克里索斯托（Saint Chrysostom）明确地说：“神之所以将非凡的能力赋予平庸，是因为当时教会需要神迹；而现在他们之所以连非凡的人都不再赋予这种能力，则是因为教会已经没有需要。”随后，他还承认说，再没有人能使死人复活，甚至连救助伤病也已无可能。

虽然有格瓦斯和普罗泰西乌斯的神迹，圣·奥古斯丁在他的《上帝之城》也说道：“曾经出现过的奇迹为什么现在不出现了呢？”他给出了相同的原因：“Cur, inquiunt, nunc illa miracula quae praedicatis facta esse non fiunt?Possem quidem dicere necessaria prius fuisse quam crederet mundus, ad hoc ut crederet mundus.”（他们问：“为什么那些你吹噓曾出现过的奇迹现在不出现了？”我会说，在这个世界还未相信之前，奇迹是有必要的，这样世界才会相信。）

除了以上的这个坦白之言，自由思想家们却不赞同圣·奥古斯丁提到的希波（Hippo）补鞋匠的故事。这鞋匠丢了衣服，随后到一个二十殉道者小型教堂做祈祷。回去后，他在一条鱼的体内发现了一枚金戒指，做鱼的厨师告诉补鞋匠：“这就是那20个殉道者给你的礼物。”

对于这个故事，自由思想家们的回答是，这个故事与自然定律一点都不矛盾，一条鱼吞了一只金戒指丝毫不违背自然定律，厨师将这金戒指给补鞋匠也不是神迹。

倘若提醒一下这些自由思想家们，依据圣·哲罗姆在《隐士保罗的生活》（Life of the Hermit Paul）中所言，这位隐士与森林之神萨梯（satyrs）和农牧之神范恩（fauns）还有过几次对话，乌鸦每天都给他叼来半条面包作为饭食，圣·安东尼（Saint Anthony）造访之日还叼来一整条面包，这前后持续了整整30年。他们又会回答说，所有的这些事物并不会绝对地违反自然定律，萨梯和范恩也许存在过。这个故事尽管幼稚，但是无论如何，它与救世主和他的使徒们那样纯粹的奇迹是完全不同的。一些虔诚的基督徒已经不相信狄奥多勒（Theodoret）所讲的关于坐柱者圣·西蒙（Saint Simon Stylites）的故事。很多在希腊被认为是可信的奇迹已经受到几个拉丁教会的质疑，同样的，一些拉丁的奇迹也引起了希腊教会的怀疑。紧接而来就是新教徒们，他们对两种教会的奇迹都不太相信。

一个在东印度群岛布道良久、知识渊博的耶稣会士抱怨说，他与同事们从来都不能行奇迹。泽维尔（Xavier）在他的几封信中悲叹道自己没有语言能力，他说身处日本人中间，除了是一尊哑巴雕像外，什么都不是。尽管如此，耶稣会士们也写到他使8个死人复活了，8个人着实很多，但是我们要考虑这8个人是他从距离此地5000格之远的地方复活成功的。从此以后，有人声称在法国废除耶稣会，相较于废除泽维尔和伊格内修斯（Ignatius）而言是个更大的神迹，这些人因为发表此言论而为人所知。

话虽如此，所有的基督徒仍相信耶稣基督和使徒们的神迹是千真万确的，但是我们也有权利运用我们的力量去质疑一些近当代发生的，还未经权威验证的奇迹。

因为一个真实完美的奇迹，人们会希望它能在巴黎科学院、伦敦皇家学会和医学院的见证下，能在卫兵军团派遣支队，防止拥挤人群的轻率行为妨碍神迹创造的支持下加以实践。

总有一天，自由思想家会被问到，如果发现太阳停止运动，换而言之，就是地球不再围绕太阳这一天体运转；如果所有死人都能复活；如果连绵的群山变为海洋，所有这些都是去证明一些重要的真理，比如万能的上帝恩宠。“那么我会说什么呢？”自由思想者问到。“我会成为摩尼教徒，我会说存在一条原理能将其他原理破坏。”

彼得

彼得（Peter），在意大利语里，他的名字是皮埃罗（Piero）或皮埃特罗（Pietro），在西班牙语里，佩德罗（Pedro），拉丁语里，柏图斯（Petrus），希腊语里，彼特拉斯（Petros），而在希伯来语里，他则被称为刻法（Cepha）。

为什么彼得的继任者们在西方能有如此大的权力而在东方情况却并非如此？这就好像是在问为什么维尔茨堡（Wurzburg）和萨尔茨堡（Salzburg）的主教们在混乱时期可以拥有王权而希腊的主教们却永远只有是臣民。时间，时机，某些人的野心以及另一些人的软弱总可以成就这个世界上所有已经发生或是将要发生的事情。

在这个混乱的时期，某种意见却得到了普遍的认同，这种意见统治着人们的思想；事实上并不是说这些人有着自己明确的意见，但是总有声音代替他们表达。

福音书中提到，上帝对彼得说“我将赐予你天国的钥匙”。而在11世纪，罗马主教的支持者们仍然认为赐予的东西越是宏大，也就越渺小，也认为天国包裹着大地；倘若彼得拥有天国之匙，那他也一定拥有开启大地之匙。如果说天国指的是所有的恒星和行星，那么根据托马修斯（Thomasius）的说法，显而易见，给西蒙·巴-乔那（Simon Bar-Jona）也就是彼得的钥匙是一把万能钥匙。如果天国指的是云层，大气，或是行星自转所需要的空间，那么根据默尔修斯（Meursius）的说法，也就没有锁匠可以为这样的门打造钥匙了。

过去，巴勒斯坦的钥匙是用带子绑在一块的一堆木钉。耶稣对巴-乔那说：“凡是你在人世间所受的束缚，到了天国也同样会绑住你”。而服务于教皇的神学家们，从这一条解读出，教皇们拥有让人民忠于他们自己国王的权利，也有解除这一关系的权力；与此同时，教皇按自己的意愿管理所有的王国。这是一个绝妙的结论。1302年，在法国的三级会议上，法国民众在给国王的请愿书上写道：“波尼法斯八世（Boniface VIII）认为上帝在天国所约束和囚禁的也是他自己所约束的东西。”德国的路德教教徒（我记得是叫墨兰顿）觉得自己很难理解耶稣对西蒙·巴-乔那或称刻法所说的：“你是彼得（皮埃尔），在这块磐石（皮埃尔有石头之意）之上，我将筑造我的教堂，召集我的信徒。”他不相信上帝会在文字上做文章，会开如此特别的玩笑；更不相信教皇的权力原来只是基于一个语言的双关。

有人认为彼得是罗马的主教，但在当时以及之后的很长一段时间里，都没有人能够证实他在位。而基督教团体在公元2世纪末才成形。

彼得可能去过罗马，更有可能的是他被头朝下钉死在十字架上，虽然这在实际上不可行，也没有证据证明这点。我们有一封由他署名的信件，当中提到了他在巴比伦：明智的圣殿学者认为巴比伦即罗马。因此如果他有一封来自罗马的署有名字和日期的信件，我们就能得出信件是在巴比伦写的结论。很久之前就有过这样的推论，世界也一如既往地运行着。

曾经有一个虔诚的人在罗马花了大笔金钱买了一份圣职。这被称为圣职买卖行为。当时有人问他，相不相信西蒙·彼得在罗马。他回答说：“我不知道彼得，但是西蒙是在罗马的。”

对于彼得这个人，必须承认的一点是，保罗并不是唯一一个被他的行为所震惊的人。他和他继任者们常常在公开场合被人排斥。保罗严厉斥责他食用禁肉，比如猪肉、黑布丁、兔子、鳗鱼、伊克西翁和格里芬。彼得在为自己辩护时则说，他曾在约是正午之时见到天国之门打开，有4个人携一块大布从天而降，布上有好多鳗鱼、四足动物还有鸟类。有一个天使的声音大声喊道：“杀死它们，吃了吧！”渥拉斯顿（Wollaston）说，很明显，这个声音也对教皇们说：“杀死一切，侵吞人民的财产！”

卡索朋（Casaubon）不认同彼得对待好人亚拿尼亚（Ananias）和他的妻子萨菲拉（Sapphira）的方式。卡索朋问道，经过哪场战役之后可以让一个犹太人——罗马人的奴隶有权命令或是允许那些相信耶稣的信徒们变卖家产并把所得的收益摆在他的脚下。如果伦敦的某个再洗礼派（Anabaptist）让他的同胞们将自己的财产放在他脚下，难道他不会因为叛教而下狱，且毋庸置疑地因掠夺信徒财产而被送往泰伯恩（Tyburn）刑场？那么对亚拿尼亚处以死刑难道没有太过分吗？他只是私藏了他和他妻子变卖田产所得的一小部分，而对彼得谎称奉献了全部家产。他的妻子赶来时，亚拿尼亚才刚刚死去。彼得并没有仁慈地警告她，她的丈夫因私藏价银而死于中风，让她好好照顾自己，而是让她掉入了另一个陷阱。他问她，她的丈夫是不是将所得的所有价银交给了圣徒。这个可怜的女人说是，于是当场死去。这是多么残酷！

科尼利厄斯（Coringius）问彼得为什么处死那些捐献财产给他的人，却不处死那些对耶稣不止一次处以鞭刑，最后导致耶稣受难的神学家们。哦，彼得！你处死了两个捐献财物给你的基督徒，却允许那些迫害你主的人活着！

科尼利厄斯明显不是宗教法庭的人，所有才会问这些大胆的问题。伊拉斯谟注意到一件奇怪的事情，这件事与彼得有关：基督教的领袖在开始履行他们作为使徒的职责时，都不认主。犹太人的第一个主教开始履行职责时，打造了一个金牛犊，且对之敬如神明。

如果是这样，那么彼得只是一个盘问穷人的穷人而已。他就像那些秩序的创造者，自己为贫困所扰，而他的后继者们则成了有钱的贵族。

教皇作为彼得的继任者，不管是处于鼎盛时期还是没落时期，除去他们周边的教民，在这个世界上还是有5亿人需要遵守他的教规。

认同一个与自己相距三四百里格的主人；直到这个人开始考虑事情，你不能去想只能等着；只有等到这个外国人所指派的专员同意，你才敢对你的公民作出最后判决；不付给这个外国主人一大笔钱，你就不敢占用属于某个国王的土地或是葡萄园；如果你违反某个国家的法律，娶了自己的侄女，可以给这个外国主人一大笔钱使得这样的行为合法化；某天因为这个外国人要求纪念某个由他送入天堂的人，一个不认识的人，你就必须将田地里的农活放在一边——认同教皇，就必须认同这些，这是法国天主教堂所要求的。

而另外一些人则进一步提出他们的意见。比如，如今我们可以看到某个君主请求教皇准许他的皇家法庭判处某些僧侣叛逆的罪行，这样的请求并未得到准许，于是他也不能对这些僧侣进行判决。

众所周知，以前教皇的权力更大。他们的权力远远超过远古时期的神明，因为这些神明赋予了教皇管理各个帝国的权力，而教皇真的做到了这一点。

斯特毕勒斯（Sturbinus）说，那些质疑教皇的神圣性和权威性的人，如果是从这些方面来考虑，这是可以得到原谅的：

40个分裂教会亵渎了主教之位，而其中有27个教会让主教之位染满鲜血。

斯蒂芬七世（Stephen VII），一个神父之子，掘出了他的前任教皇福尔摩苏斯（Formosus）的尸体，并将之斩首。

塞尔吉乌斯三世（Sergius III），犯下谋杀罪，并让他的情妇马洛吉亚（Marozia）之子继承了教皇之位。

约翰十世，狄奥多拉（Theodora）的情人，被勒死在他的床上。

约翰十一世，也就是塞尔吉乌斯三世的儿子，就是一个浪荡子。

约翰十二世被杀死在情人的房间里。

本笃九世（Benedict IX）买下教皇之位之后又将其出售。

格列高利七世发起了历时500年的内战，这场战争由他的继任者延续。

最后，在这么多有野心的、残暴而又风流的教皇之中，还有一个亚历山大六世，他的名字与尼禄、卡利古拉（Caligula）并列。

据说，虽然历经了这么多的罪恶，教皇之位的神圣性依旧保持着。但若是这样的话，哈里发岂不是要作出更残忍的事情才可以更加神圣。这是德米尔斯（Dermius）的推论，但是耶稣会的信徒给了他答案。

哲人朱利安——罗马君主

对一个人作出公正评价有时需要很长一段时间。两三个要么唯利是图，要么狂热盲从的作者说到野蛮而阴柔的康斯坦丁时往往崇之为神，而谈到公正明智的朱利安（Julian）大帝时则称之为恶棍。而其他的作者们则复写了这样的言论，重复这同样的奉承和诽谤。这些几乎都变成了他们的信条。终于，公开评论的时代到来了，在1400年以后，文明开化的人们开始反思这些人之所以这样评论的原因。康斯坦丁被认为是一个野心勃勃，嘲笑上帝和人类的人。他傲慢无礼地假装上帝给了他指示而确保让他取得了胜利。他让整个家族浴血，而自己却懒惰地睡在床上；可他是一个基督徒，且被封为圣徒。

朱利安冷静、纯洁、无私、勇敢而仁慈；但他不是基督徒，且长期被视为可怕的怪物。

如今，在对比了事实、史料、朱利安以及他的对手的手稿之后，我们不得不承认，虽然他不喜欢基督教，但恨一个沾满自己家族鲜血的教派却是情有可原的；野蛮的君主康斯坦丁在位期间，朱利安被基督徒迫害、监禁、流放，面临着死亡的威胁。但他从未处决过基督徒，相反，他原谅了10个密谋杀害他的基督徒士兵。

我们读他的信，会由衷地佩服他。“基督徒们，”他说，“在我的前任君主在位时期遭受流放和监禁。他们称彼此为异教徒，最后屠杀彼此。我已召回那些被流放者，并释放了囚犯。我已将他们的财产判回给他们。我让他们过回安宁的生活。但这正是令加利利人（Galileans）愤怒之处，他们抱怨，因为他们不能再吞并彼此。”写得多好！多好的哲学家对迫害狂热者的宣言！

总之，每个对事实有了公正研究的人，都会承认朱利安拥有图拉真的所有品质，除了他对希腊人和罗马人的纵容；他有卡托（Cato）的所有优点，但没有他的固执和坏脾气；他有我们钦佩的尤利乌斯·恺撒的优秀品质，却没有他的罪恶；他和西庇阿（Scipio）一样纯洁。总之，他与马可·奥里利乌斯一样，是一个伟大的人。

现在，我们再也不会重复诬告者狄奥多勒对朱利安的诽谤，说朱利安在卡集（Carrhae）的一座神庙杀死了一个女人作为祭品以抚慰众神。我们不再反复提及，他在垂死时用手把血液洒向天堂的方向，对耶稣基督说：“你胜利了，基督徒！”仿佛他对波斯人的战争是他对战耶稣的一场战争；仿佛这个哲学家，死时无奈地认可了基督的存在。仿佛他相信基督就在空气中，而周围的空气即是天堂。这些教父们的不恰当言论如今已不被重复。

他们最后只能像安提俄克的无聊的市民们那样嘲笑他。他们指责他蓬乱的胡子和走路的方式。但拉贝特（La Bletterie）大人啊，你并未看到他走路的方式，但你读了他写的信件、制定的法律、写满他的美德的纪念碑。只要他的心胸坦荡，所做的事情彰显着他的美德，那么他的胡子肮脏，或是走得匆忙又何妨？

今天仍然值得研究的一个重要事实是，朱利安被指责想要通过重建耶路撒冷的圣殿篡改耶稣基督的预言。据说，有大火冒出了地面，阻止了重建工作。据说，这是一个神迹，而这个神迹并没有使朱利安改变信仰，也没有让重建工作的负责人阿里皮斯（Alypius），以及宫廷成员的信仰发生改变。而神父拉贝特对此事评论说：“他和他宫廷的哲学家们无疑是依赖于自然哲学知识，才能否定如此惊人的神迹。而自然一直是怀疑的避难所，但他与宗教的关系如此密切，应该至少被怀疑是共谋者。”

首先，福音书中说的犹太圣殿将不再重建这一点是不正确的。马太福音中关于不会有一块这座圣殿的石头留给土买人的希律王（Idumaean Herod）的预言确实写于自提图斯对耶路撒冷的破坏之后。但没有福音传道者说它从未重建。而在提图斯对破坏圣殿之后没有一块石头被留下来这一点也是不正确的。他保留了所有的地基、一整面城墙以及安东尼亚塔（Antonia tower）。

其次，在犹太人屠杀公牛和奶牛的地方建一座犹太圣殿、火药库或是一座清真寺，这对神而言又有什么关系？

第三，不知道出自某些被烧工人之口的所谓的大火，究竟是源自于被城墙包围的城市还是源自犹太圣殿。然而，我们很难理解为什么耶稣火烧朱利安大帝的工人，却放过那些很久以后在废墟上建立清真寺的哈里发·奥马尔（Caliph Omar）的信徒，以及那些之后重修了清真寺的萨拉丁王（Saladin）的工人。难道耶稣真的那么偏爱穆斯林的清真寺？

第四，耶稣预言没有一块石头将留给耶路撒冷的另一座圣殿，并未禁止圣殿被重建。

第五，耶稣预言的好几件事情并没有被上帝允许。他预言了世界末日的到来，届时他将驾云降临，在最后存活的人面前，显示其权力与威严。然而世界末日并未到来，并且这样的状态明显还将持续一段时间。

第六，如果朱利安描述了这一神迹，我只能说他被虚假而荒谬的报告所欺骗，我宁愿相信他的敌人，也就是基督徒不遗余力地反对他的计划，他们杀死了工人，还使人们相信那些工人是在神迹中被杀害。但朱利安对于此事并未发表言论，因为他忙于对波斯人的战争。他推迟了建筑圣殿的时间，而在这项工程开始之前，他已离世。

第七，报告这一神迹的是阿米安·马赛林纳斯（Ammianus Marcellinus），一个异教徒。那么这件事被基督徒篡改就是很有可能的了，他们因为这点被人指责已不止一次。

但在那个人们都谈论神迹与巫术的故事的时代，阿米安·马赛林纳斯所说的这个故事被某些人所轻信，这也是有可能的。因为从提图斯·李维斯（Titus Livius）直到那个时代所有的历史总会被打上神迹的烙印。

第八，根据当代作家们的说法，当时叙利亚发生大地震。大火燃及好几个地方，许多城镇被吞噬。因此并没有所谓的神迹。

第九，如果耶稣能行神迹，那他为什么不阻止让他自己献上祭品以及受割礼的圣殿重建呢？他为什么不行神迹让那些嘲笑基督教的国家信奉基督？或者让他的基督徒，从阿里乌斯（Arius）和亚他那修（Athanasius）到罗兰（Roland）和塞文山脉（Cévennes）的骑士，让这些手上沾满鲜血的食人者们更加温和且有人性？

从这些我得出的结论是，自然并不为基督教服务，正如拉贝特所言。但是拉贝特所说的却与老妇人的荒诞之见不谋而合，正如朱利安所说：麻烦事都在愚蠢的妇人身上（Quibus cum stolidis aniculis negotium erat）。

在为朱利安的某些美德正名之后，拉贝特在这段历史的结尾，将他的死亡写成“神之复仇”。如果是这样，那么所有英雄们的英年早逝，从亚历山大到古斯塔夫斯·阿道弗斯（Gustavus Adolphus），都是受到了神的惩罚。朱利安则是以最好的方式死去，他与敌人战斗取得多次胜利后战死沙场。朱庇特，他的继任者，统治时间比他更短，且政绩平平。我并未看到神的复仇，拉贝特在我看来不过是一个不诚实的大发豪言壮语之人。但谁敢讲真话呢？斯多葛派的利巴涅斯（Libanius）是其中一个。他用残杀帖撒罗尼迦人（Thessalonians）的狄奥多瑟斯（Theodosius）来赞扬勇敢仁慈的朱利安，而勒布（Le Beau）与拉贝特都不敢对忠诚的教民们赞扬他。

朱利安曾因性命受到威胁放弃基督教而遭人指责。这就相当于是责备一个人，在他被人所劫，被贼人用刀架在脖子上逼着参加他们的团伙时，逃离了这群强盗。康斯坦（Constant）皇帝比他那残忍的父亲康斯坦丁有过之无不及，他的双手沾满了朱利安家族的鲜血。他已经杀了这个伟人的兄弟。乌萨比（Eusabia）皇后为了让年轻的朱利安活下来，费尽周折。为了不被谋杀，这位不幸的王子削发为僧，保证并接受了所谓的四条法令。他模仿朱尼厄斯·布鲁图斯（Junius Brutus），装疯以骗过塔奎因（Tarquin），躲过他的愤怒。他生活毫无意义，直到他发现自己变成了高卢军队的长官，才真正地活着，并成为一个伟大的人。这就是理性的叛教者所谓的叛教，如果一定要给这个从未定义过的行为作出一个定义的话。

孟德斯鸠说：“悲哉，在敌营生存下来的王子总有一个坏声誉！”让我们想象一下，倘若朱利安战胜了波斯人，且在他漫长而宁静的晚年目睹了古老宗教的复兴，基督教的毁灭，法利赛人、撒都该人、利甲族人（Rechabites）、艾赛尼派（Essenians）、赛拉普特人（Therapeutes）教派的消失、对叙利亚女神的崇拜和其他无迹可追的大事，那么历史学家会给朱利安多少溢美之词啊！那么他的绰号绝不会是叛教者，而毫不夸张的会是重建者这一神圣称号。

看看这些不称职的罗马历史学家们，都臣服在康斯坦丁和狄奥多瑟斯的脚下，帮他们掩饰自己的罪过，多么的卑鄙！尼禄也没有做过比屠杀帖撒罗尼迦人更可怕的事。坎塔布连的狄奥多瑟斯（Cantabrian Teodosius）假装原谅帖撒罗尼迦人，而在6个月后，他邀请他们去了竞技场。竞技场至少有15000人的容量，当时一定座无虚席。人们对于这种大场面向来富有激情。父母带着几乎不能走路的孩子们来到这里。等到人们都已入场，基督教的皇帝派基督教的士兵屠杀男女老少，一个都没有留下。然而这个可怕的人在历史剽窃者的笔下却得到了颂扬。他们说，他忏悔了。上帝啊，什么忏悔！他一个欧宝[17]都没给死者的家庭，也没有去做弥撒。必须承认不做弥撒的人承受着巨大的痛苦，因为那是你该感激涕零的，那是上帝给你让你赎回所有罪行的机会。

劳伦·爱恰尔（Laurent Echard）的继承者，一个声名狼藉的国王，将狄奥多瑟斯下令的这场屠杀形容为一件快活事。

同样不幸的是有人乱写罗马史，用夸夸其谈的文风，充满文法错误的文字告诉你狄奥多瑟斯在与他的对手尤金战斗之前，看到圣·约翰和圣·菲利普穿着白色的衣服，他们向他保证他会取得胜利。让这等作家去给约翰和菲利普唱赞美诗吧，不要让他们写历史。

读者，问问你的良知。你钦佩爱戴亨利四世，但如果他在阿尔克（Arques）这场以一敌多的战争中失败，他的胜利只是因为历史学家们将他描述为一个英雄，你不会知道这个人：他只会是长胡子的游击队员，一个旧病复发的异端分子，一个异教徒。梅晏公爵（duc de Mayenne）则会是上帝派来的代表，教皇虽然染痘也会册封圣·菲利普为圣徒，圣·约翰会多次在他面前出现。而你，耶稣会士达尼埃尔，你将如何改写这段平淡无味的历史以取悦梅晏公爵？写成公爵如何“推着国王向前”，如何“彻底击败”这个大胡子？还是教会如何取得“胜利”的历史？

Careat successibus opto

Quisquis ab eventu facta notanda putaat.

（我恳求消灭那些以事情的结果论成败的人。）

偏见

偏见是非理性的观点。因此，在世界各地，孩子们被迫接受各种观点直至他们可以自己作出判断。

有些通用且必要的偏见本身便是美德。在任何一个国家，孩子们被教导承认有一位赏罚分明的神；敬爱他们的生身父母；视偷窃为罪行，视自私欺骗为恶习——直至他们可以认知何为善恶。

因此存在极善的偏见：当一个人能够理性思考时，其判断便会更正这些偏见使其成为美德。

感觉并非仅仅是偏见，而是更强大的东西。母亲爱她的儿子并非因为世俗要求她必须爱他：她幸福地爱着她的孩子更甚于自己。同理，你会去帮助一个即将掉入悬崖或被野兽吞噬的陌生孩子。

然而，你尊重一个衣着得体、举止庄重、言谈恰当的人却不属于上述情况。父母曾经告诉你需向此人鞠躬。甚至在了解此人是否值得尊重之前，你便尊重他。年龄和知识逐渐增长，你意识到这个人不过是一个毫无尊严、自私自利、阴险狡诈的小人。你鄙视你过往所尊敬的，此时偏见便服从于理性。由于偏见，你曾相信蛊惑你童年的寓言。寓言中讲到泰坦发起了诸神之战，维纳斯与阿多尼斯（Adonis）相恋。12岁的孩子信以为真，21岁的青年则把它们当作精妙的寓言。

让我们通过一些词汇审视不同类型的偏见，从而整理我们的思绪。或许我们会像约翰·劳体制[18]时代的人一样意识到原来他们一直以来指望的只是幻想中的财富。

感官偏见

我们的双眼常常欺骗我们，甚至是当我们看得很真切的时候——这难道不是一件奇特的事吗？但是反之，我们的双耳从不欺骗我们。如果你听力正常，听到有人说：“你真美，我爱你”时，显然你听到的不是：“我恨你，你真丑”。但是当你看到一面光滑的镜子时，你会发现你错了，其实镜面非常不平整。太阳的直径看起来比你的眼球宽两英尺，事实证明它比地球还要大几百万倍。

上帝似乎把真相注入你的耳朵而把谬误留给你的眼睛；但是研究光学你会发现，上帝并没有欺骗你，事物只能以现有的状态呈现给你。

物理偏见

日出月落，地球是静止的：物理世界里有许多自然偏见。因为煮熟后呈红色，所以小龙虾补血；因为鳗鱼机灵，所以会治愈瘫痪；因为从前在一次月缺时，一个病人的发烧加剧了，所以月球活动会影响疾病：数以千万计的类似观念只是古代愚者的错误，他们不假思索，妄加推断，以讹传讹。

历史偏见

很多历史故事未经证实便被轻信，这种轻信本身便是一种偏见。非比阿斯·皮科特（Fabius Pictor）告诉我们这样一个故事，在他之前的几个世纪，一个正要把水倒进水壶的艾尔巴城（Elba）处女被强暴了，然后她生下了罗穆卢斯和雷穆斯，被母狼抚养成人。罗马人相信了这个寓言。他们没有问那个时候拉丁姆（Latium）是否有处女，国王的女儿是否会带着她的水壶离开修道院，母狼是否会养育两个孩子而非把他们吃掉。偏见自成。

一个修道士写道，克劳维斯（Clovis）在托尔比亚克战役（battle of Tolbiac）中遭遇险境，此时他发誓，倘若能顺利渡过劫难，他将成为一名基督徒。然而，他在此时把自己托付于一个异教的神明是否合情合理呢？他生来就信仰的宗教不应该是最有力的么？在对抗土耳其人的战斗中，一个基督徒难道会向先知穆罕默德求救而非圣母玛利亚么？也有传言说，一只鸽子衔着圣油瓶给克劳维斯洗礼，举着旗帜的天使指引他的道路。偏见对诸如此类的逸闻都信以为真。熟知人类本性的人都知道，夺位者克劳维斯和夺位者罗隆（也叫罗尔）加入基督教只是想更好地控制基督徒，就像土耳其的夺位者加入伊斯兰教来更好地控制穆斯林一样。

宗教偏见

如果你的乳娘告诉你谷神星（Ceres）掌管粮食，或者毗瑟拏（Vishnu）和恰卡（Xaca）有时幻化成人形，或者萨摩诺克多姆（Sammonocodom）砍倒了一整座森林，或者欧丁神（Odin）在位于日德兰半岛的大厅等待着你，或者先知穆罕默德或其他什么人完成了去往天堂的旅程；如果你的导师之后给你灌输了一样的想法，那么你一生都会对此深信不疑。如果你的理性高于这些偏见，你那些智力高于妇女的邻居们便会高呼你信仰全无，并且对你施以恐吓。你的托钵僧害怕他的收入减少，一纸诉状把你告上法庭。法官想要操控愚者，相信他们更易管制，所以对你百般刁难。你会一直遭受窘境，直至你的街坊邻里、托钵僧人和下级法官开始意识到愚蠢毫无意义，迫害令人生厌。

邪恶

人说人性本恶，人类是恶魔之子，是邪恶的。这说法着实极不妥当。原因在于，老朋友，你布道说整个世界的人类生来就是堕落的，这倒提醒了我，你就是这样的出身，所以你就像狐狸和鳄鱼那样不可信任。你跟我说：“绝对不是！我精神上得到了重生，我既不是异教徒，也不是无信仰者，你可以信任我。”然而，其余的那些你口中的异教徒或无信仰之人就只是一群野兽。想必每次你与路德教信徒或土耳其人谈话时，一定确信他们会抢劫或谋杀你，因为他们是恶魔之子，生而邪恶，你们得到了重生，他们则腐朽堕落。也许这样告诉人类会显得更加理性而优雅：人性本善，想想玷污人类的纯洁是多么的可怕。我们对待人类的态度本应与对待每个个体的态度相同。如果一个修道士过着丑陋而可耻的生活，那我们对他说：“你真的会让修道士的尊严蒙羞吗？”一位律师有幸成为一名皇家议员，那他就应该以身作则。为了鼓舞一名士兵，人们告诉他：“牢记你属于香槟军团。”我们应该告诉每个个体：“记住你做人的尊严。”

但是实际上，无论如何阐释，我们总会回到最初。追寻你的内心，这一各国普遍使用的说法到底是什么意思？如果你生来就是恶魔之子，本源就是罪人，体内的血液都是低贱的液体组成，那“追寻你的内心”的短语意思就会是：请教并追寻你那恶魔的本性，成为一个骗子、小偷、杀人犯，这都是你父亲的行事之风。

人性本不恶，只有患病才能让人变得邪恶。医生们一同出现并说道：“你生来就病了。”那毫无疑问，如果病人的病是与生俱来，天性使然的，那么不管这些医生们说什么、做什么，此病都无法治愈。同时，拥有这样想法的人本身也是得了病的。

将全世界的孩子聚集起来，在他们身上，你只会发现天真、柔弱和恐惧。倘若他们生来就是残忍邪恶并且作恶多端的，那么他们就应该展现出这样的苗头，就像幼蛇试图撕咬、稚虎显露利爪。但是人之本性并不比鸽子、兔子拥有更具攻击性的武器，不可在天性上就将人类摧毁。

所以人生来并不是邪恶的。那为什么有人会被人性本恶这场瘟疫感染呢？那是因为他们那些已被此病感染的领袖们将此病传染给其他的人类，就如同一个女人，感染了哥伦布从美洲带回的疾病，然后将这毒害从欧洲的一头传播至另一头。第一位野心勃勃的人败坏了整个地球。

你会说是这个始作俑者将所有人类固有的傲慢、掠夺、欺骗、残暴激发了出来。我承认，一般说来，人类的大多数都会有这样的特点，但是难道每个人都会患有令人厌恶的热病、都会有石头和砂砾，只是因为人人都能接触到他们吗？

整个民族都不是邪恶之人的例子也是存在的，比如费城人和印度人就从没杀过人；中国人、越南人、老挝人、暹罗人，甚至日本人都已经有超过100年没有战争了。震惊人类的残酷犯罪，近10年来，很难在罗马、威尼斯、巴黎、伦敦和阿姆斯特丹发现，尽管在这些城市里作为万恶源头的贪婪之心依旧横行无忌。

如果人性本恶，人生来就是恶魔的奴隶，一不开心，就会受到恶魔的蛊惑，用暴怒与残酷来为自己的痛苦复仇，那么每天早晨，我们就会看到妻子谋杀丈夫、孩子谋杀父亲，就像在黎明时分发现鼬鼠紧紧地勒住鸡，吸食它们的血液一样。

倘若地球上有10亿人口，这数量很大，那么就会有5亿的女人缝衣纺纱、喂养孩子、打扫住房，以及议论邻里琐事。我就没发现这些天真的人类作出了什么伤天害理之事。考虑到全球居住者的数量，那么至少有2亿的孩童，他们既不杀人也不劫掠，以及同等数目的老弱之人，他们也无力如此。至多只有1亿的青壮年，精力充沛，可以犯罪。而这一亿人中间，9千万人经常被繁重的劳动束缚，努力工作，让土地生产，供养衣食。这些人很难再有时间去作恶。

而这10亿人口中余下的人还包括：只图享乐的游手好闲、群居寄生之人，忙于事业的有才之人，以及至少在表面上追求纯净生活的执法官和与神职人员。所以剩下的真正邪恶之人，只是少数的一些政客以及几千个出卖自己为这些阴谋者服务的流氓。政客们不管是世俗的还是宗教性的，他们总是麻烦制造者。实际上，这样残暴的野兽，不可能同时存在100万，这个数量还包括了拦路强盗。所以说，就算是在最动荡不安的年代，世界上也只有千分之一的人可以被称作是邪恶之人，况且他并不总是邪恶的。

因此，世界上的邪恶比所宣称的，所相信的要少得多。但是也还是太多了。可怕的不幸之事仍能看见，但是抱怨夸大邪恶的乐趣是如此之大，以至于最轻微的剐蹭也会被惊呼成血流成河。如果你被欺骗了，那所有人都是伪证者。一个遭遇过不公正待遇的忧郁之人会觉得世界上充满了该死之人，正如一个在观看歌剧后与女伴共饮的年轻酒色之徒无法想象世界上竟然还有不幸之事一样。

[1]佩里斯（Peris），波斯神话中一种美丽的仙女。下文中的Malakim, Daimonoi均是神之使者之意。——译者注

[2]视距尺，长度单位，1视距尺约合607英尺或185米。——译者注

[3]里格，长度单位，1里格约等于3英里。——译者注

[4]“为克鲁恩修斯”（For Cluentius）是古罗马著名演说家西塞罗为克鲁恩修斯（Cluentius）辩护所发表的演说，公元前66年，克鲁恩修斯被其母亲控告毒杀继父。——译者注

[5]卢克莱修（Lucretius，公元前99—前55），古罗马哲学家及诗人，具有唯物主义观点，反对神创论，著有哲学长诗《物性论》。——译者注

[6]伊皮法纽（Epiphanius，约310或320—403），萨拉米斯（Salamis）大主教，被东正教和基督教视为圣徒。著有《帕那里昂》（Panarion），详细反击了80种异端邪说。——译者注

[7]迈蒙尼德（Maimonides，1135—1204），出生于西班牙，被认为是中世纪最伟大的犹太哲学家、犹太教法学家、科学家、神学家和医学家。——译者注

[8]《革马拉》（Gemara），犹太教口传律法集《塔木德经》（Talmud）的后半部和释义部分，为《密西拿》的补编和说明。——译者注

[9]伊希斯（Isis），埃及宗教里司生育和繁殖的女神。——译者注

[10]依洛西斯（Eleusis），古希腊城市，依洛西斯秘密宗教仪式的发祥地。——译者注

[11]亚历山大的区利罗（Cyril of Alexandria，376—444），又译区利罗一世，412—444年间于罗马帝国统治下的埃及亚历山大城任亚历山大宗主教。区利罗著作甚多，积极参与当时关于耶稣基督的神性和人性的争论。——译者注

[12]皮特·克索罗格斯（Peter Chrysologos，约380—450），拉文那（Ravenna）大主教。——译者注

[13]独眼巨人，希腊神话中的人物，身体强壮、固执、感情冲动。——译者注

[14]德·萨克斯，全名莫里斯·德·萨克斯（Maurice de Saxe，1696—1750），法国元帅。军事才能突出，曾领导法国战胜英荷联军取得丰特努瓦战役的胜利。——译者注

[15]里米尼（Rimini），古称“阿里米努姆”。意大利北部城市。位于圣马力诺东北的马雷基亚河口，滨亚得里亚海。——译者注

[16]弟兄：Fra，用于意大利教士姓名前的称号。——译者注

[17]古代希腊的钱币。

[18]约翰·劳（John Law），苏格兰裔金融家和投机家，18世纪早期法国财政总监。其主导的“金融创新”和“体制改革”被称为劳体制（Law's system）。——译者注

Angel

Angel, in Greek, messenger; we shall hardly know more of them when we learn that the Persians had Peris, the Hebrews Malakim, the Greeks their Daimonoi.

But what we shall perhaps find more instructive is the fact that one of mankind's first notions has always been to place intermediary beings between divinity and us. It is these demons, these genii that antiquity invented. Princes were seen to intimate their orders through messengers, therefore divinity also sends its couriers: Mercury, Iris were couriers, messengers.

The Hebrews, the only people guided by divinity itself, at first gave no names to the angels god finally deigned to send them. They borrowed the names given to them by the Chaldeans when the Jewish nation was captive in Babylonia, Michael and Gabriel were first named by Daniel, a slave of that people. The Jew Tobit, who lived at Nineveh, knew the angel Raphael, who travelled with his son to help him collect some money which the Jew Gabael owed him.

In the laws of the Jews, that is, Leviticus and Deuteronomy, there is not the slightest reference to the existence of angels, let alone their worship. Moreover, the Sadducees did not believe in angels.

But they are talked about a great deal in the histories of the Jews. The angels were corporeal. They had wings on their backs, as the Gentiles pretended that Mercury had on his heels. Sometimes they hid their wings under their clothes. How could they have lacked bodies since they drank and ate, and the inhabitants of Sodom wanted to commit the sin of paederasty with the angels who visted Loth?

The ancient Jewish tradition, according to Maimonides, acknowledges ten degrees, ten orders of angels:1. The chaios acodesh, pure, saintly. 2. The ofamin, swift. 3. The oralim, the strong. 4. The chasmalim, the flames. 5. The seraphim, sparks. 6. The malachim, angels, messengers, deputies. 7. The eloim, the gods or judges. 8. The ben eloim, children of the gods. 9. cherubim, images, 10. ychim, the animated.

The story of the fall of the angels is not in the books of Moses; the first reported witness to it is that of the prophet Isaiah, who, apostrophizing the king of Babylon, exclaimed: 'What has become of the extorter of tribute? The pines and the cedars rejoice in his fall; how are you fallen from heaven, oh Hellel, star of the morning?' This Hellel has been translated by the Latin word Lucifer; then the name of Lucifer was given allegorically to the prince of the angels who battled in heaven; and finally this name, which means phosphorus and dawn, has become the name of the devil.

The Christian religion is based on the fall of the angels. Those who rebelled were thrown down from the spheres they inhabited into the hell at the centre of the earth, and became devils. A devil in the shape of a serpent tempted Eve, and damned mankind. Jesus came to redeem mankind and to triumph over the devil, who still tempts us. Nevertheless this fundamental tradition is found only in the apocryphal book of Enoch, and even there in a form quite different from the accepted tradition.

In his 109th letter saint Augustine does not hesitate to endow both good and evil angels with slender and agile bodies. Pope Gregory II reduced to nine choirs, nine hierarchies or orders, the ten choirs of angels recognized by the Jews: they are the seraphim, cherubim, thrones, dominations, virtues, powers, archangels and finally the angels who give that name to eight other hierarchies.

In their temple the Jews had two cherubim, each with two heads, one of an ox and the other of an eagle, with six wings. Today we paint them in the image of a flying head, with two little wings below the ears. We paint the angels and archangels in the image of youth, with two wings on their backs. As for the thrones and dominations, nobody has yet taken it into his head to paint them.

Saint Thomas, in the second article of question 108, says that the thrones are as close to god as the cherubim and seraphim because it is on them that god is seated. Scotus has counted a thousand million angels. The ancient mythology of the good and evil genii having passed from the east to Greece and to Rome we hallow this view in accepting that every man has a good and an evil angel, one of whom helps and the other harms him from his birth until his death; but we do not yet know whether these good and evil angels pass continuously from one post to another, or whether they are relieved by others. On this matter consult the Summa of saint Thomas.

It is not precisely known where the angels live, whether it is in the air, in the void, or the planets: god has not wished us to know it.

Animals

What a pitiful thing, what poor stuff it is to say that animals are machines deprived of knowledge and feeling, which always perform their operations in the same way, which learn nothing, which improve nothing, etc.!

What! this bird which makes its nest semi-circular when it is attached to a wall, which builds it in a quartercircle when it is in a corner, and makes it circular in a tree, this bird does everything in the same way? This gun dog you have trained for three months: does he not know more at the end of that time than he knew before your lessons? Does the canary immediately repeat the tune you are teaching him? Do you not spend much time in teaching him? Have you not seen that it makes mistakes and corrects itself?

Do you judge that I have feelings, memory, ideas because I speak to you? Well! I do not speak to you; you see me come home looking distressed, search anxiously for a paper, open the desk in which I remember having put it, find it, read it with joy. You judge that I have experienced the feeling of distress and that of pleasure, that I have memory and knowledge.

Judge in the same way this dog who has lost his master, who has searched for him with mournful cries in every path, who comes home agitated, restless, who runs up and down the stairs, who goes from room to room, who at last finds his beloved master in his study, and shows him his joy by the tenderness of his cries, by his leaps, by his caresses.

Barbarians seize this dog who so prodigiously surpasses man in friendship. They nail him to a table and dissect him alive to show you the mesenteric veins. You discover in him all the same organs of feeling that you possess. Answer me, mechanist, has nature arranged all the springs of feeling in this animal in order that he should not feel? Does he have nerves to be impassive? Do not assume that nature presents this impertinent contradiction.

But the leaders of this school inquire about the souls of animals. I do not understand this question: A tree has the faculty of receiving in its fibres the sap that circulates in it, of putting forth the buds of its leaves and of its fruit; will you ask me what is the soul of this tree? It has received these endowments; the animal has received those of feeling, of memory, of a certain number of ideas. Who has created all these endowments? Who has given all these faculties? He who has made the grass of the fields to grow, and who makes the earth gravitate towards the sun.

'The souls of animals are substantial forms,' said Aristotle; and after Aristotle the Arab school, and after the Arab school the angelic school, and after the angelic school the Sorbonne, and after the Sorbonne nobody at all.

'The souls of animals are material,' exclaim other philosophers. Those have had no greater success than the others. They were asked in vain what is a material soul; they had to agree that it is feeling matter: but what has given it this feeling? It is a material soul, that is, matter has given feeling to matter; they cannot break this circle.

Listen to other animals reasoning about animals. They allege that the soul is a spiritual being which dies with the body: but what proof have you of such a soul? What conception have you of this spiritual being which in reality has feeling, memory and its part of ideas and arrangements, but which will never know what a child of six knows? On what ground do you imagine that this being, which is not body, dies with the body? The greatest donkeys are those who have alleged that this soul is neither body nor spirit. There's a fine system! By spirit we can only understand something unknown which is not body: hence the system of these gentlemen comes down to this, that the soul of an animal is a substance which is neither body nor something which is not body.

What can be the cause of so many contradictory errors? It is the habit men have always had of examining what a thing is before knowing whether it exists. The mobile tongue, the valve of a bellows, is called the soul of the bellows. What is this soul? It is a name I have given to this valve which descends, lets the air in, raises itself, and pushes it through a tube when I agitate the bellows.

Here we have no soul distinct from the machine. But what operates the animals' bellows? I have already told you; he who operates the stars. The philosopher who said, 'Deus est anima brutorum' [God is the soul of animals], was right; but he should have gone further.

Anti-trinitarians

There are heretics who might not be regarded as Christians. Nevertheless they recognize Jesus to be saviour and mediator; but they dare to maintain that nothing is more contrary to strict reason than what is taught among Christians about the trinity of persons in a single divine essence, the second of which was begotten by the first, and the third of which proceeds from the two others.

That this unintelligible doctrine is nowhere found in scripture.

That no passage can be produced that authorizes it and to which, without in any way departing from the spirit of the text, a clearer, more natural meaning cannot be given, one more consistent with common sense and the basic and immutable truths.

That to maintain, as do their adversaries, that there are several distinct persons in the divine essence, and that it is not the eternal who is the only true god, but that the son and the holy ghost must be added to them, is to introduce the crudest and most dangerous error into the church of Jesus Christ, since it manifestly encourages polytheism.

That it implies a contradiction to say that there is only one god and that nevertheless there are three persons, each of which is truly god.

That this distinction, one essence and three persons, was never in scripture.

That it is obviously false, since it is certain that there are no fewer essences than persons, nor persons than essences.

That the three persons of the trinity are either three different substances, or accidents of the divine essence, or that same essence without distinction.

That in the first case three gods are created.

That in the second case god is composed of accidents and one worships accidents and metamorphoses accidents into persons.

That in the third case an indivisible subject is uselessly and groundlessly divided, and what is not distinguished in itself is distinguished into three.

That if it is said that the three personalities are neither different substances in the divine essence, nor accidents of that essence, one would have to be at some pains to convince oneself that they are anything.

That it must not be believed that the most rigid and the most convinced trinitarians themselves have any dear idea of the manner in which the three hypostases subsist in god without dividing his substance and consequently without multiplying it.

That saint Augustine himself, after he had advanced a thousand reasonings as false as they are obscure on this subject, was obliged to admit that nothing intelligible could be said about it.

Then they quote this father's words, which are in fact very singular: 'When it is asked', says he, 'what are the three, human language is found inadequate, and there are no terms to express them: yet it is said that there are three persons, not in order to say something, but because we must speak and not remain silent. Dictum est tres personae, non ut aliquid diceretur, sed ne taceretur' (De Trinitate V. ix).

That the modern theologians have not elucidated this matter any better.

That when they are asked what they understand by this word person, they explain it only by saying that it is a certain incomprehensible distinction that causes one to distinguish in a numerically single nature a father, a son and a holy ghost.

That the explanation they give of the terms to beget and to proceed is not more satisfactory since it comes down to saying that these terms indicate certain incomprehensible relationships between the three persons of the trinity.

That from all this we can gather that the basic argument between them and the orthodox turns on the question whether there are in god three distinctions of which we have no notion and between which there are certain relationships of which we do not have any notion either.

From all this they conclude that it would be wiser to abide by the authority of the apostles, who never spoke of the trinity, and to banish from religion for ever all terms which are not in the scriptures, such as trinity, person, essence, hypostasis, hypostatic and personal union, incarnation, generation, procession, and so many more like them, which, being absolutely meaningless, since they have no real representative being in nature, can provoke only false, vague, obscure and incomplete ideas in the understanding.

Let us add to this article what dom Calmet says in his dissertation on this passage from the epistle of John the evangelist: 'There are three who bear witness on earth, the spirit, and the water, and the blood: and the three agree in one. There are three who bear witness in heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Spirit; and these three are one.' Dom Calmet admits that these two passages are not in any ancient Bible; and it would indeed have been strange if saint John had spoken of the trinity in a letter, without saying a single word about it in his gospel. No trace of this dogma is to be found in the canonical gospels, nor in the apocryphal ones. All these reasons could excuse the anti-trinitarians had the councils not taken their decisions. But as heretics make light of councils, we are at a loss to know how to confound them. Let us simply believe and hope that they believe.

Apocalypse

Justin Martyr, who Wrote about the year 170 of our era, was the first who mentioned the Apocalypse [book of Revelation]; he attributed it to the apostle John the evangelist. In his dialogue with Trypho, this Jew asks Justin whether he does not believe that Jerusalem would be restored one day. Justin replies that like all rightthinking Christians he thinks it will. 'There was among us', he says, 'a certain personage named John, one of the twelve apostles of Jesus; he predicted that the faithful would pass a thousand years in Jerusalem.'

This reign of a thousand years was an opinion long held by Christians. It was a period much favoured among the gentiles. The souls of the Egyptians recovered their bodies at the end of a thousand years. In Virgil souls in purgatory were tried during the same space of time, et mille per annos [and for a thousand years]. The new Jerusalem of a thousand years was to have twelve doors in memory of the twelve apostles; its form was to be square; its length, width and height were to be 12,000 stadia, that is, 500 leagues, so that the houses were also to be 500 leagues high. It would have been rather disagreeable to live on the top floor; still, this is what the Apocalypse says in Chapter XXI.

Justin is the first who attributed the Apocalypse to saint John, but some people have challenged his testimony because in this same dialogue with the Jew Trypho he says that according to the narrative of the apostles when Jesus Christ went into the Jordan he made the waters of this river boil, and set them on fire, though this is not found in any of the apostles' writings.

The same saint Justin confidently cites the oracles of the sybils. What is more, he claims to have seen in the Egyptian Pharos the remains of the madhouses in which the seventy-two interpreters were confined in Herod's time. The testimony of a man who had the misfortune to see these madhouses seems to indicate that the author should have been locked up in them.

Saint Irenaeus, who came later, and who believed also in the millennium, says that he learned from an old man that saint John had written the Apocalypse. But saint Irenaeus has been reproached for having written that there must be only four gospels because there are only four parts of the world and four cardinal winds, and because Ezekiel saw only four animals. He calls this reasoning a demonstration. It must be admitted that Irenaeus certainly demonstrated as well as Justin saw.

In his Electa Clement of Alexandria mentions only an Apocalypse by saint Peter, to which great importance was attached. Tertullian, a great partisan of the millennium, not only asserts that saint John predicted this resurrection and this reign of a thousand years in the city of Jerusalem, but he also claims that this Jerusalem was already beginning to form in the air; all the Christians of Palestine, and even the pagans, had seen it for forty successive days at the end of the night; but unfortunately the city disappeared as soon as the day broke.

In this preface to the gospel of saint John and in his Homilies Origen cites the oracles of the Apocalypse; but he also cites the oracles of the sybils. Nevertheless saint Denis of Alexandria, who also wrote towards the middle of the third century, says in one of his fragments, conserved by Eusebius, that nearly all the doctors rejected the Apocalypse as a book devoid of reason; that this book had not been composed by saint John but by one Cerinthus, who borrowed a great name to give his dreams more weight.

The council of Laodicea, held in 360, did not include the Apocalypse among the canonical books. It was very singular that Laodicea, which was a church to which the Apocalypse was addressed, rejected a treasure destined for it, and that the bishop of Ephesus, who attended the council, also rejected this book by saint John, who was buried in Ephesus.

It was visible to all eyes that saint John still moved in his grave, and constantly made the earth rise and fall. Nevertheless the same people who were sure that saint John was not really dead were also sure that he had not written the Apocalypse. But those who believed in the millennium were unshakable in their opinion. Sulpicius Severus, in his Sacred history, book ix, calls insensate and impious those who did not accept the Apocalypse. Finally, after much hesitation, after opposition in council after council, the view of Sulpicius Severus prevailed. The matter having been elucidated, the church decided that the Apocalypse is incontestably by saint John: so there is no appeal.

Each Christian community has applied to itself the prophecies contained in this book; the English have found in it the revolutions of Great Britain; the Lutherans the troubles of Germany; the French protestants the reign of Charles IX and the regency of Catherine de Medicis. They are all equally right. Bossuet and Newton both wrote commentaries on the Apocalypse; but on the whole the eloquent declamations of the one and the sublime discoveries of the other have done them greater honour than their commentaries.

Atheist, atheism

I

In former times anybody who possessed a secret in one of the crafts ran the risk of being taken for a sorcerer; every new sect was accused of butchering children in its mysteries; and every philosopher who turned aside from the jargon of the schools was accused of atheism by fanatics and rascals, and condemned by fools.

Anaxagoras dared to maintain that the sun is not guided by Apollo riding in a quadriga: and he was called an atheist and obliged to flee.

Aristotle was accused by a priest of atheism; and, not succeeding in having his accuser punished, retired to Chalcas. But what is most odious in the history of Greece is the death of Socrates. Aristophanes (whom the commentators admire because he was a Greek, forgetting that Socrates also was a Greek) was the first who accustomed the Greeks to regard Socrates as an atheist.

This comic poet, who was neither comic nor a poet, would not have been allowed in our society to write farces for the fair of Saint-Laurent: he appears to me to be lower and more contemptible than Plutarch depicts him. This is what the wise Plutarch says of this humbug: 'The language of Aristophanes betrays his wretched character: it consists of the lowest and most disgusting quips; even the people do not find him amusing, and to men of judgement and honour he is insupportable; his arrogance is unbearable and decent people detest his malignity.'

This then is the Tabarin [buffoon] whom, by the way, mme Dacier, the admirer of Socrates, dared to admire: this is the man who from afar prepared the poison with which infamous judges put to death the most virtuous man in Greece.

The tanners, cobblers and dressmakers of Athens applauded a farce in which Socrates was shown hoisted in the air in a basket, announcing that there was no god, and boasting that he had stolen a coat while teaching philosophy. An entire people, whose bad government authorized such infamous liberties, well deserved what happened to it: to become slaves of the Romans and today of the Turks.

Let us pass over the whole period of time between the Roman republic and ourselves. The Romans, much wiser than the Greeks, never persecuted any philosopher for his opinions. This cannot be said of the barbarian peoples which succeeded the Roman empire. As soon as the emperor Frederick II quarrelled with the popes, he was accused of being an atheist and of being the author, with his chancellor de Vineis, of the book of the Three Impostors.

When our great chancellor de L'Hospital declared himself against the persecutions, he was at once accused of atheism, Homo doctus, sed verus atheos. A Jesuit, as inferior to Aristophanes as Aristophanes is inferior to Homer, a wretch whose name has become ridiculous even among the fanatics, in a word, the Jesuit Garasse, found atheists everywhere: this is what he called all those against whom he burst out. He called Théodore de Bèze an atheist. It was he who misled the public about Vanini.

Vanini's unhappy end does not move us with indignation and pity like that of Socrates because Vanini was only a foreign pedant without merit, but after all Vanini was not an atheist, as has been alleged; he was precisely the opposite. He was a poor Neapolitan priest, a preacher and theologian by trade, a merciless argufier about quidities and universals, et utrum chimera bombinans in vacuo possit comedere secundas intentiones. But for the rest, there was not a drop of atheism in him. His notion of god was theologically most sound and correct. 'God is his principle and his end, father of the one and the other, and needing neither the one nor the other; eternal without being in time, present everywhere without being anywhere. No past or future exists for him, he is everywhere and beyond everything, governing everything, and having everything, immutable, infinite without parts; his power is his will', etc.

Vanini prided himself on reviving Plato's fine conception, embraced by Averroes, that god had created a chain of beings, from the smallest to the greatest, whose last link is attached to his eternal throne: an idea, in truth, more sublime than true, but which is as far removed from atheism as being is from nothingness.

He travelled to make his fortune and to engage in disputations; but unfortunately disputation is the road that leads away from fortune; one makes as many irreconcilable enemies as one finds learned men or pedants with whom to argue. The misfortune of Vanini had no other cause; his heat and rudeness in dispute earned him the hatred of some theologians; and having had a quarrel with one Francon or Franconi, this Francon, the friend of his enemies, of course accused him of being an atheist who taught atheism.

This Francon or Franconi, aided by a few witnesses, had the barbarity to maintain during the trial what he had asserted. When cross-examined about what he thought of the existence of god, Vanini answered that, like the church, he worshipped one god in three persons. Picking up a straw he said: 'This trifle is enough to prove that there is a creator.' Then he pronounced a very fine discourse on vegetation and motion, and on the necessity for a supreme being without whom there would be neither motion nor vegetation.

Grammont, the presiding judge, then at Toulouse, reports this discourse in his History of France, today quite forgotten; and this same Grammont, because of an incredible prejudice, alleges that Vanini said all this from 'vanity, or from fear, rather than from an inner conviction'.

On what can the président Grammont's rash and atrocious judgement be based? It is obvious that Vanini's answer should have secured his acquittal on the charge of atheism. But what happened? This unhappy foreign priest also dabbled in medicine. They found a big live toad which he kept at home in a vessel full of water, and of course he was accused of being a sorcerer. They alleged that this toad was the god he worshipped. An impious meaning was given to several passages in his books, which is very easy and very commonly done, by taking objections for replies, by interpreting malignantly some ambiguous phrases, by poisoning an innocent expression. The faction that oppressed him finally extoned from the judges the sentence that condemned the unhappy man to death.

To justify this death it was clearly necessary to accuse the wretched man of the most frightful things. The Minim and very minimal Mersenne pushed lunacy so far as to print that Vanini 'left Naples with twelve of his apostles to convert all the nations to atheism'. How pitiful! How could a poor priest have had twelve men in his pay? How could he have persuaded twelve Neapolitans to travel at great expense, at the peril of their lives, to spread everywhere this abominable and revolting doctrine? Would a king be powerful enough to pay twelve preachers of atheism? Nobody before father Mersenne had put forward so enormous an absurdity. But it has been repeated after him, the newspapers, the historical dictionaries have been infected with it; and the world, which loves sensations, has believed this legend without question.

Bayle himself, in his Pensées diverses, speaks of Vanini as an atheist; he used this example to support his paradox 'that a society of atheists can exist'. He assures us that Vanini was a very moral man and that he was the martyr of his philosophic views. He is equally mistaken on both these points. The priest Vanini tells us in the Dialogue he wrote in imitation of Erasmus that he had had a mistress called Isabella. He was as bold in his writings as in his conduct, but he was not an atheist.

A century after his death the learned La Croze and the writer who took the name of Philète sought to justify him; but as nobody takes any interest in the memory of an unhappy Neapolitan, a very bad author, hardly anybody reads these apologies.

In his Athei detecti, the Jesuit Hardouin, more learned than Garasse, accuses Descartes, Arnauld, Pascal, Nicole, Malebranche of atheism: fortunately they did not suffer Vanini's fate.

From all these facts I pass on to the ethical problem debated by Bayle, that is, whether a society of atheists could exist. Let us first observe on this point the enormous extent to which men contradict themselves when disputing: those who have argued with the greatest vehemence against Bayle's opinion, those who have denied with the greatest insults the possibility of a society of atheists, have since maintained with the same dauntlessness that atheism is the religion by which China is governed.

They are certainly mistaken about the Chinese government; all they had to do was to read the edicts of the emperors of this vast country, they would have seen that these edicts are sermons, which everywhere speak of a supreme being, ruler, avenger and remunerator.

But at the same time they are no less mistaken about the impossibility of a society of atheists; and I do not know how M. Bayle could have forgotten a striking example which could have made his cause victorious.

In what respect does a society of atheists seem impossible? It is because men who are unchecked are supposed to be incapable of living together; because the law is helpless against secret crimes; because a vengeful god is needed to punish in this world or the next the wicked who have avoided human justice.

It is true that the laws of Moses did not teach a future life, threatened no punishments after death, did not teach the first Jews the immortality of the soul; but the Jews, far from being atheists, far from seeking to avoid divine vengeance, were the most religious of all men. Not only did they believe in the existence of an eternal god, but they believed that he was always present in their midst; they were terrified of being punished in themselves, in their children, in their posterity to the fourth generation, and this check was very powerful.

But among the gentiles several sects had no such check: the sceptics doubted everything; the Academics suspended their judgement on everything; the Epicureans were convinced that the divinity could not meddle in human affairs, and at bottom acknowledged no divinity. They were certain that the soul is not a substance but a faculty that is born and perishes with the body; therefore they bore no yoke but that of morality and honour. The Roman senators and knights were true atheists, for the gods did not exist for men who neither feared them nor hoped for anything from them. Thus in Caesar's and Cicero's time the Roman senate was really an assembly of atheists.

In his harangue for Cluentius the great orator said to the assembled senate: 'What harm does death do him? We reject all the inept fables about hell. What then has death taken from him? Nothing but the feeling of pain.'

Caesar, Catalina's friend, wishing to save his friend's life from this same Cicero, did he not object that to put a criminal to death is not to punish him, that death is nothing, that it is only the end of our sufferings, that it is a happy moment rather than a disastrous one? Did not Cicero and the entire senate yield to this reasoning? The conquerors and legislators of the known world were thus clearly a society of men who had no fear of the gods, who were true atheists.

Bayle next inquires whether idolatry is more dangerous than atheism, whether it is a greater crime not to believe in the divinity than to have unworthy opinions about it. In this he shares the views of Plutarch: he believes that it is better to have no opinion than a bad one. But with all due deference to Plutarch it is obvious that it was infinitely better for the Greeks to fear Ceres, Neptune and Jupiter than to fear nothing at all. It is obvious that the sanctity of oaths is necessary, and that we must have confidence rather in those who think that a false oath will be punished, than in those who think that they can take a false oath with impunity. It is indubitable that it is infinitely more useful in a civilized city to have even a bad religion than none at all.

It would thus appear that Bayle should rather have inquired which is the more dangerous, fanaticism or atheism. Fanaticism is certainly a thousand times more baneful, for atheism does not inspire bloody passions, but fanaticism does; atheism does not discountenance crime, but fanaticism causes crimes to be committed. Let us suppose, with the author of the Commentarium rerum Gallicarum, that the chancellor de L'Hospital was an atheist. He enacted only wise laws and counselled only moderation and concord: the fanatics com-mitted the massacres of saint Bartholomew. Hobbes was taken for an atheist. He led a calm and innocent life: the fanatics of his time deluged England, Scotland and Ireland with blood. Spinoza was not only an atheist, but he taught atheism: it was certainly not he who shared the judicial assassination of Barneveldt, it was not he who tore to pieces the two brothers de Witt and ate them on the grill.

For the most part atheists are bold and misguided scholars who reason badly and who, unable to understand the creation, the origin of evil, and other diffi-culties, have recourse to the hypothesis of the eternity of things and of necessity.

The ambitious, the voluptuous, hardly have the time to reason, and to adopt a bad system; they have other things to do than to compare Lucretius with Socrates. This is the way things are nowadays.

It was not so in the Roman senate, which was almost entirely composed of men who were atheists in both theory and practice, that is, who believed neither in providence nor in the future life. This senate was an assembly of philosophers, voluptuaries and ambitious men, all very dangerous, and who destroyed the republic. Epicureanism persisted under the emperors: the senate's atheists had been sedition-mongers in the times of Sulla and Caesar; under Augustus and Tiberius they were atheist slaves.

I should want no dealings with an atheist prince who thought it useful to have me pounded in a mortar: I am quite sure that I would be pounded. If I were a sovereign I should want no dealings with atheist courtiers whose interest it was to have me poisoned: I should have to take antidotes at random every day. It is thus absolutely necessary for princes and peoples to have deeply engraved in their minds the notion of a supreme being, creator, ruler, remunerator and avenger.

There are atheist peoples, says Bayle in his Pensées sur les comètes. The Kaffirs, the Hottentots, the Topinamboos, and many other small nations have no god. That may be so, but it does not mean that they deny god. They neither deny nor affirm him: they have never heard of him. Tell them that there is one, and they will readily believe it. Tell them that everything happens in the nature of things, they also believe you. To allege that they are atheists is as relevant as to say that they are anti-Cartesians: they are neither for nor against Descartes. They are real children; a child is neither atheist nor theist, he is nothing.

What conclusion can we draw from all this? That atheism is a monstrous evil in those who govern; and also in learned men even if their lives are innocent, because from their studies they can affect those who hold office; and that, even if not as baleful as fanaticism, it is nearly always fatal to virtue. Above all, let me add that there are fewer atheists today than there have ever been, since philosophers have perceived that there is no vegetative being without germ, no germ without design, etc., and that grain is not produced by putrefaction.

Unphilosophical mathematicians have rejected final causes, but true philosophers accept them; and as a well-known author has said, a catechist announces god to children, and Newton demonstrates him to wise men.

Ⅱ

If there are atheists, who is to be blamed if not the mercenary tyrants of souls who, in revolting us against their swindles, compel some feeble spirits to deny the god whom these monsters dishonour? How often have the people's leeches driven prostrated citizens to revolt against the king?

Men fattened on our substance cry out to us: 'Be sure that a she-ass spoke; believe that a fish swallowed up a man and threw him on the shore three days later safe and sound; don't doubt that the god of the universe ordered one Jewish prophet to eat shit (Ezekiel), and another prophet to buy two whores and to beget sons of whores on them (Hosea). These are the very words a god of truth and purity is made to pronounce. Believe a hundred things either obviously abominable or mathematically impossible: otherwise the god of mercy will burn you in the fires of hell, not only for millions of billions of centuries, but throughout all eternity, whether you have a body or whether you have no body.'

These inconceivable stupidities revolt feeble and reckless minds, as well as firm and wise minds. They say: 'Our masters depict god for us as the most senseless and the most barbarous of all kinds, therefore there is no god'; but they ought to say: 'Therefore our masters attribute to god their own absurdities and rages, therefore god is the opposite of what they proclaim, therefore god is as wise and as good as they allege him to be mad and wicked.' This is what wise men conclude. But if a fanatic hears them, he denounces them to a magistrate subservient to the priests; and this magistrate has them burnt on a slow fire, believing that he is avenging and imitating the divine majesty he violates.

Baptism

Baptism, Greek word meaning immersion. Men, who are always guided by their senses, easily imagined that what washes the body washes also the soul. There were great tanks for the priests and the initiates in the vaults under the Egyptian temples. From time immemorial the Indians have purified themselves in the water of the Ganges, and this ceremony is still in great vogue. It passed to the Hebrews: they baptized all the foreigners who embraced the Judaic law, and who would not submit to circumcision; above all the women, who were not made to undergo this operation except in Ethiopia, were baptized; it was a regeneration, which gave a new soul, as in Egypt. See, on this, Epiphanius, Maimonides and the Gemara.

John baptized in the Jordan, and he even baptized Jesus, who, however, never baptized anyone, but who deigned to hallow this ancient ceremony. Every symbol is meaningless in itself, and god attaches his grace to the symbol he is pleased to choose. Baptism soon became the chief rite and the seal of the Christian religion. Nevertheless the first fifteen bishops of Jerusalem were all circumcised; it is not certain that they were baptized.

This sacrament was misused in the first centuries of Christianity; nothing was so common as to await the final agony in order to receive baptism. The example of the emperor Constantine is pretty good proof of that. This is how he reasoned: baptism purifies everything; I can therefore kill my wife, my son and all my relations; after which I shall have myself baptized and I shall go to heaven; and in fact that is just what he did. This was a dangerous example; little by little disappeared the custom of waiting for death before taking the plunge into the sacred bath.

The Greeks always conserved baptism by immersion. The Latins, having extended their religion into Gaul and Germany towards the end of the eighth century, and seeing that immersion could kill children in cold countries, substituted simple aspersion, for which they were often anathemized by the Greek church.

Saint Cyprian, bishop of Carthage, was asked if those who had simply had their whole bodies sprinkled were really baptized. He answered in his seventy-sixth letter that 'several churches do not believe that these sprinkled people are Christians; that as for himself he thinks that they are Christians, but that they have infinite less grace than those who have been immersed three times according to custom'.

With the Christians a man was initiated as soon as he was immersed; before this was done he was merely a catechumen. To be initiated it was necessary to have guarantors, sureties, who were given a name corresponding to godfathers, so that the church could be sure that the new Christians would be faithful and would not divulge the mysteries. This is why in the first centuries the gentiles were usually as ill-instructed about the mysteries of the Christians as these were about the mysteries of Isis and Eleusis.

Cyril of Alexandria, in his tract against the emperor Julian, expresses himself thus: 'I would speak of baptism were I not afraid that my discourse might reach those who are not initiated.'

As early as the second century they began to baptize children; it was natural that the Christians should want their children to be provided with this sacrament, since they would have been damned without it. It was finally decided that it must be administered to them after a week because among the Jews this was the age at which they were circumcised. This is still the custom in the Greek church. Nevertheless in the third century the practice prevailed of being baptized only at death.

Those who died in the first week were damned, according to the strictest fathers of the church. But Peter Chrysologos, in the fifth century, invented limbo, a kind of mitigated hell, or, precisely, brink of hell, suburb of hell, where go little children who die without baptism, and where resided the patriarchs before the descent of Jesus Christ into hell; so that the view that Jesus Christ descended to limbo and not into hell has prevailed since then.

It has been debated whether a Christian born in the deserts of Arabia could be baptized with sand: the reply was he could not; whether it was permitted to baptize with rose water: and it was decided that pure water was necessary, but that muddy water could be used. It is obvious that all the regulations depended on the prudence of the first pastors who established them.

[…]

Baptism: An Addition

What a strange idea, inspired by the wash-pot, that a jug of water washes away all crimes! Now that all children are baptized because a no less absurd idea assumes them all to be criminals, they are all saved until they reach the age of reason and can become guilty. So butcher them as quickly as possible to assure them paradise. This conclusion is so logical that there existed a devout sect who went about poisoning or killing all newly baptized infants. These devotees reasoned perfectly. They said: 'We are doing these little innocents the greatest possible kindness; we are preventing them from being wicked and unhappy in this life, and we are giving them eternal life.'

Cannibals

I have spoken of love. It is hard to pass from people who embrace each other to people who eat each other. It is only too true that there have been cannibals. Some have been found in America. There may still be some, and the cyclops were not the only ones in antiquity who sometimes fed on human flesh. Juvenal reports that among the Egyptians, so wise a people, so famous for its laws, so pious a people, who worshipped crocodiles and onions, the Denderites ate one of their enemy who had fallen into their hands. He does not tell this story on hearsay: this crime was committed almost under his eyes; he was then in Egypt, not far from Dendera. In this connection he cites the Gascons and the Sagantines, who formerly fed on the flesh of their countrymen.

In 1725 four savages were brought from the Mississippi to Fontainebleau. I had the honour to converse with them. Among them was a lady of that country whom I asked whether she had eaten men. She replied very innocently that she had. I appeared a little scandalized. She excused herself by saying that it was better to eat one's dead enemy than to let him be devoured by beasts, and the victors deserved to have the preference. We kill our neighbours in pitched or unpitched battle, and for the meanest rewards prepare meals for the crows and the worms. There is the horror, there is the crime. When one has been killed what does it matter whether one is eaten by a soldier or by a crow or a dog?

We respect the dead more than the living. We ought to respect both. Nations called civilized are right not to put their vanquished enemies on the spit, for if we were permitted to eat our neighbours we would soon eat our fellow countrymen, which would be a mixed blessing for the social virtues. But the civilized nations have not always been civilized; all were for long savage; and in the infinite number of revolutions this globe has undergone, the human species has sometimes been numerous, sometimes very rare. What is happening today to elephants, lions, tigers, whose numbers have much decreased, once happened to mankind. In times when a region was little inhabited by men, they had few arts, they were hunters. The habit of feeding on what they had killed readily caused them to treat their enemies like their stags and their boars. It was superstition that caused human victims to be immolated, it was necessity that caused them to be eaten.

Which is the greater crime, piously to assemble to plunge a knife into the heart of a young girl adorned with fillets, in honour of the divinity, or to eat a villain who has been killed in self-defence?

Nevertheless we have many more examples of girls and boys who have been sacrificed than of girls and boys who have been eaten. The Jews immolated them. This was called the anathema. It was a real sacrifice, and it is commanded in the twenty-seventh chapter of Leviticus not to spare the living souls who had been devoted to god, but it is nowhere prescribed that they should be eaten, they are merely threatened with this fate. And Moses, as we have seen, said to the Jews that, if they did not observe these ceremonies, not only would they have the itch but mothers would eat their children. It is true that in Ezekiel's time the Jews must have been in the habit of eating human flesh, for in chapter xxxix he predicts to them that god would make them eat not only the horses of their enemies but also the horsemen and the other warriors. This is definite. And in fact why should the Jews not have been cannibals? It would have been the only thing the people of god lacked to be the most abominable on earth.

I have read in some anecdotes on the history of England in Cromwell's time that a tallow-chandler in Dublin sold excellent candles made of the fat of Englishmen. Some time after one of her customers complained that her candles were no longer so good. 'Alas,' she said, 'it's because we have been short of Englishmen this month.' I ask who were the guiltier, those who murdered Englishmen or this woman who made their grease into candles?

Certain, certainty

'How old is your friend Christopher?'

'Twenty-eight. I have seen his marriage contract and his baptismal certificate. I have known him since his childhood. He is twenty-eight; it is a certainty, I'm certain of it.'

Hardly had I heard the reply of this man, so sure of what he says, and of twenty others who confirmed the same thing, than I discovered that Christopher's baptismal certificate had been antedated by a strange trick for hidden reasons. Those to whom I spoke don't yet know about it. In the meanwhile they're still certain of something false.

If you had asked the entire world before the era of Copernicus: 'Did the sun rise today? did it set?' everybody would have answered you: 'We're absolutely certain of it.' They were certain, and they were mistaken.

Spells, divination, possession were for long the surest things in the world in the eyes of all peoples. What an innumerable crowd of people saw all these fine things and were certain of them! Today this certainty has somewhat diminished.

A young man who was beginning to study geometry called on me. He had not got beyond the definition of triangles. 'Aren't you certain,' I said, 'that the three angles of a triangle are equal to two right angles?' He replied that not only was he not at all certain of it, but that he did not even have a clear idea of this proposition. I demonstrated it to him; he then became very certain of it, and will be so all his life.

That certitude is very different from the others: they were no more than probabilities, and these probabilities, once examined, became errors; but mathematical certitude is immutable and eternal.

I exist, I think, I feel pain. Is all this as certain as a geometric truth? Yes. Why? It is because these truths are proved by the same principle that a thing cannot be and not be at the same time. I cannot at the same time exist and not exist, feel and not feel. A triangle cannot at the same time have and not have 180 degrees, which is the sum of two right angles.

The physical certainty of my existence and of my feelings, and mathematical certainty thus have the same value, although they are of a different kind.

This does not apply to the certainty based on appearances or to the unanimous reports made by men.

'But really!' you tell me, 'aren't you certain that Peking exists? Haven't we got fabrics from Peking? People from different countries, of different opinions, who wrote violently against each other while all preached the truth in Peking, haven't they assured you of the existence of this city?' I answered that it seems to me extremely probable that there was then a city of Peking; but I would not wish to bet my life that this city exists, and I would bet my life at any time that the three angles of a triangle are equal to two right angles.

Something very droll has been published in the Dictionnaire encyclopédique. It is maintained there that if all Paris told one that marshal de Saxe had been resurrected, one should be as sure, as certain of it as one would be if told by all Paris that marshal de Saxe had won the battle of Fontenoy. Consider, I beg, how admirable is this reasoning: 'I believe all Paris when they tell me something possible in principle; therefore I must believe all Paris when they tell me something impossible in principle and physically.'

Apparently the author of this article wanted to have a good laugh, and the other author, who goes into raptures at the end of this article and writes against himself, also wanted to have a good laugh. As for me, who have undertaken this little Dictionary in order to put questions, I am far from being certain.

Character

From the Greek word impression, engraving. It is what nature has engraved in us. Can we efface it? Vast question. If I have a hooked nose and two cat's eyes I can hide them with a mask. Can I do better with the character nature has given me? A man born violent, choleric, presented himself before François I, king of France, to complain of an injustice. The prince's countenance, the respectful conduct of the courtiers, the very place in which he found himself, made a powerful impression on this man; he unconsciously lowered his eyes, his rough voice softened, he presented his request humbly. One would believe him to be naturally as gentle as are (at least at this moment) the courtiers in whose midst he is even disconcerted; but if François I is good at reading faces he will easily realize in his eyes, lowered but alight with hidden fire, in the taut muscles of his face, in his lips pressed against each other, that this man is not so gentle as he is obliged to appear. This man followed him to Pavia, was captured with him, and taken to prison in Madrid with him; the majesty of François I no longer made the same impression on him; he became familiar with the object of his respect. One day, while pulling off the king's riding boots, and pulling them badly, the king, soured by his misfortune, became angry: my man sent the king to the devil, and threw his boots out of the window.

Sixtus V was by nature petulant, obstinate, haughty, impetuous, vindictive, arrogant: his character appears to have been softened by the ordeal of his novitiate. As he began to enjoy some reputation in his order, he lost his temper with an attendant and felled him with his fist. When inquisitor in Venice he exercised his office with insolence. Become cardinal he was possessed della rabbia papale [by the furious ambition to become pope]. This rage subdued his nature; he buried his person and his character in obscurity; he shammed humility and ill-health; he was elected pope: in this instant was restored all the elasticity so long restrained by policy; he was the proudest and most despotic of sovereigns.

Naturam expellas furca, tamen ipsa redibit.

[Nature will always return even if you expel her with a pitchfork]

Chassez le naturel, il revient au galop.

Religion, morality put a curb on the power of nature; they cannot destroy it. The drunkard in a cloister, reduced to one glass of cider with each meal, will no longer get drunk, but he will always love wine.

Age weakens the character; it is a tree that produces nothing but a few degenerate fruits, but they are still of the same kind; it gets to be covered with knots and moss, it becomes worm-eaten, but it is still an oak or a pear tree. If we could change our character we would give ourselves one, we would be the masters of nature. Can we give ourselves something? Do we not receive everything? Try to arouse continuous activity in an indolent mass, to freeze with apathy the boiling soul of the impetuous, to inspire a taste for music and poetry into one who lacks taste and an ear: you will no more succeed than if you undertook to give sight to one born blind. We perfect, we mitigate, we hide what nature has placed in us; but we place nothing in ourselves.

A farmer was told: 'You have too many fish in this pond, they will not thrive; there are too many animals in your fields, there is not enough grass, they will lose weight.' After this exhortation it so happened that pike ate half my man's carp, and wolves half of his sheep; the rest fattened. Will he congratulate himself on his management? This countryman is you yourself; one of your passions devours the others and you think you have triumphed over yourself. Do we not really all resemble the old general of ninety who, coming across some young officers who were causing a disturbance with some women of the town, said in a temper: 'Gentlemen, is this the example I give you?'

Councils

All councils are undoubtedly infallible: for they are composed of men. It is impossible for passions, intrigues, the lust for dispute, hatred, jealousy, prejudice, ignorance ever to reign in these assemblies.

But why, it will be asked, have so many councils contradicted each other? It is to try our faith. Each was in the right in its turn.

Roman Catholics now believe only in councils approved by the Vatican; and the Greek Catholics believe only in those approved in Constantinople. Protestants deride them both. Thus everybody should be satisfied.

I shall refer here only to the great councils; the small ones are not worth the trouble.

The first one was that of Nicaea. It was assembled in325 of the common era, after Constantine had written and sent by the hand of Ozius this noble letter to the rather confused clergy of Alexandria: 'You are quarrelling about something very trivial. These subtleties are unworthy of sensible people.' The thing was to determine whether Jesus was created or uncreated. This has nothing to do with morality, which is the essential point. Whether Jesus was in time or before time, we must none the less be good. After many altercations it was finally decided that the son was as old as the father, and consubstantial with the father. This decision is hardly comprehensible, but it is all the more sublime on that account. Seventeen bishops protested against the decree, and an ancient chronicle of Alexandria, preserved at Oxford, says that 2,000 priests also protested; but prelates pay little attention to simple priests, who are usually poor. Be that as it may, there was no question whatever of the trinity in this first council. The formula reads: 'We believe Jesus consubstantial with the father, god of god, light of light, begotten and not made; we also believe in the holy ghost.' The holy ghost, it must be admitted, was treated pretty off-handedly.

It is reported in the supplement of the council of Nicaea that the fathers, being very perplexed to know which were the cryphal or apocryphal books of the Old and New Testaments, put them all pell-mell on an altar, and the books to be rejected fell to the ground. It is a pity that this elegant procedure has not survived.

After the first council of Nicaea, composed of 317 infallible bishops, another was held at Rimini, and this time the number of infallibles was 400, not counting a big detachment of about zoo at Seleucia. These 600 bishops, after four months of quarrels, unanimously deprived Jesus of his consubstantiality. It has since been restored to him, except among the Socinians; so everything is fine.

One of the great councils was that of Ephesus in431. Nestorius, bishop of Constantinople, great persecutor of heretics, was himself condemned as a heretic for maintaining that in truth Jesus was really god, but that his mother was not absolutely the mother of god, but the mother of Jesus. It was saint Cyril who had Nestorius condemned; but then the partisans of Nestorius had saint Cyril deposed in the same council: which much embarrassed the holy ghost.

Note very carefully here, dear reader, that the gospel has never said a word about the consubstantiality of the word, nor about the honour Mary had had to be the mother of god, nor about the other disputes which have caused infallible councils to be assembled.

Eutyches was a monk who had much abused Nestorius, whose heresy did not fall short of alleging that Jesus was two persons: which is appalling. The better to contradict his adversary the monk asserted that Jesus had only one nature. A certain Flavian, bishop of Constantinople, maintained against him that it was absolutely necessary for Jesus to have had two natures. A numerous council was assembled at Ephesus in 449. This one was conducted with the quarter-staff, like the little council of Cirta in 355, and a certain conference at Carthage. Flavian's nature became black and blue, and two natures were assigned to Jesus. At the council of Chalcedon, in 451, Jesus was reduced to one nature.

I pass over councils held on account of minute details, and come to the sixth general council, of Constantinople, assembled to determine precisely whether Jesus, having only one nature, had two wills. It will be realized how important this is in order to please god.

This council was called by Constantine the bearded, just as all the others had been by the preceding emperors. The legates of the bishop of Rome sat on the left, the patriarchs of Constantinople and Antioch on the right. I do not know whether the Roman toadies claim the left to be the place of honour. Be this as it may, Jesus obtained two wills from this affair.

The Mosaic law had prohibited images. Painters and sculptors had never done very well among the Jews. It does not appear that Jesus ever possessed any pictures, except perhaps that of Mary painted by Luke. At any rate,Jesus Christ nowhere enjoins the worship of images. Nevertheless Christians worshipped them towards the end of the fourth century, when they had familiarized themselves with the fine arts. This error went so far in the eighth century that Constantine Copronymus assembled in Constantinople a council of320 bishops, which anathemized the worship of images and branded it as idolatry.

The empress Irene, the same who later had her son's eyes torn out, assembled the second council of Nicaea in 787. In this the worship of images was restored. Nowadays it is sought to justify this council by saying that this worship was one of dulia [veneration of the saints] and not of latria [veneration of god].

However, be it latria or dulia, in 794 Charlemagne called another council, at Frankfurt, which stigmatized the second of Nicaea as idolatrous. Pope Adrian IV sent two legates to it but did not convoke it.

The first great council called by a pope was the first Lateran, in 1139. About a thousand bishops were there, but almost nothing was accomplished in it, except that those who said that the church was too rich were anathemized.

There was another Lateran council in 1179, held by pope Alexander III, in which the cardinals for the first time took precedence over the bishops. Only matters of discipline were discussed.

Another great council was the Lateran of 1215. In it pope Innocent III stripped the count of Toulouse of all his possessions, by virtue of excommunication. This was the first council in which there was any question of transubstantiation.

In 1245 took place the general council of Lyon, then an imperial city, during which pope Innocent IV excommunicated the emperor Frederick II, and in consequence deposed him, and forbade him fire and water. It was in this council that the cardinals were given red hats to remind them that they must bathe in the blood of the emperor's supporters. This council brought about the destruction of the house of Swabia, and led to thirty years of anarchy in Italy and Germany.

In the general council of 1311 at Vienne, in Dauphiné was abolished the order of the Templars, whose leading members had been condemned to the most horrible tortures on the most unsubstantiated accusations.

In 1414 was held the great council of Constance, which contented itself with deposing pope John XXIII, convicted of a thousand crimes, and in which John Huss and Jerome of Prague were burned for being obstinate, since obstinacy is a much greater crime than murder, rape, simony and sodomy.

The great council of Basle in 1431 was not recognized in Rome because it deposed pope Eugene IV, who did not consent to be deposed.

The Romans reckon the fifth Lateran council of1512 as a general council. It was called by pope Julius II against Louis XII, king of France, but this warrior-pope died, and the council went up in smoke.

Finally we have the great council of Trent, which does not have authority in France in matters of discipline. However, its dogma is unquestionable, since the holy ghost came every week from Rome to Trent in the courier's trunk, according to fra Paolo Sarpi; but fra Paolo Sarpi smelled a little of heresy.

Enthusiasm

This Greek word means disturbance of the entrails, internal agitation. Did the Greeks invent this word to express the shocks felt by the nerves, the dilation and tightening of the bowels, the violent contractions of the heart, the precipitate rush of the fiery spirits that mount from the entrails to the brain when one is deeply moved?

Or was the word enthusiasm, from disturbance of the entrails, first given to the contractions of that Pythia who, on the tripod at Delphi, received the spirit of Apollo through a part which seems made only to receive bodies?

What do we understand by enthusiasm? What nuances in our sentiments! Approval, sensibility, emotion, distress, shock, passion, frenzy, madness, fury, rage: these are all the states a wretched human soul can pass through.

A geometrician watches a touching tragedy: he sees only that it is well constructed. A young man by his side is moved and sees nothing. A woman weeps. Another young man is so carried away that, unhappily for him, he also decides to write a tragedy: he has caught the disease of enthusiasm.

The centurion or military tribune who looked on war simply as a trade in which a little fortune could be made, went calmly into battle like a thatcher climbing a roof. Caesar wept when he saw the statue of Alexander.

Ovid always spoke amusingly about love. Sappho expressed the enthusiasm of this passion; and if it is true that it cost her her life it is because in her case enthusiasm became madness.

The spirit of party marvellously encourages enthusiasm: no faction is without its fanatics.

Enthusiasm is above all the lot of misguided piety. The young fakir who sees the tip of his nose when praying gradually works himself up until he believes that if he loads himself with chains weighing fifty pounds the supreme being will be much obliged to him. He goes to sleep with his imagination filled with Brahma, and inevitably sees him in his dreams. Sometimes sparks even shine from his eyes in the state between sleep and waking: he sees Brahma glittering with light, he has ecstasies, and this disease often becomes incurable.

It is the rarest of things to unite reason with enthusiasm. Reason consists of always seeing things as they are. The drunkard is deprived of his reason when he sees things double. Enthusiasm is precisely like wine: it can excite so much tumult in the blood vessels, and such violent vibrations in the nerves, that the reason is entirely destroyed. It can cause only slight jolts, which merely produce a little more activity in the brain. This is what happens in great outbursts of eloquence, and above all in sublime poetry. Rational enthusiasm is the attribute of great poets. This rational enthusiasm is the perfection of their art. In other times it led to the belief that they were inspired by the gods, a thing that has never been said of the other artists.

How can reason govern enthusiasm? This is because a poet first sketches the structure of his canvas: the reason then holds the brush. But when he proceeds to animate his personages and to endow them with passions, then the imagination kindles, enthusiasm takes over: it is a race horse carried away headlong, but its course has been properly laid out.

Equality

What does a dog owe to a dog, and a horse to a horse? Nothing, no animal depends on his like; but man having received the ray of divinity called reason, what is the result? Slavery throughout almost the whole world.

Were this world what it seems that it should be, that is, if man found everywhere on it easy and assured subsistence and a climate appropriate to his nature, it is clear that it would have been impossible for one man to subjugate another. Let this globe be covered with wholesome fruit; let the air which must contribute to our life no longer give us illness and death; let man require no other lodging and no other bed than those of the deer and the stag: then the Genghis Khans and the Tamerlanes would have no other servants than their children, who would be upright enough to help them in their old age.

In this natural state enjoyed by all quadrupeds, birds and reptiles, man would be as happy as they, domination would then be a chimera, an absurdity which would occur to nobody: for why seek for servitors when you need no service?

If some individual with a tyrannical head and vigorous arm got the idea of subjugating a neighbour less strong than he, the thing would be impossible: the oppressed would be 100 leagues away before the oppressor could take action.

Thus all men would necessarily be equal if they were without needs. The poverty characteristic of our species subordinates one man to another. It is not inequality that is the real evil, but dependence. It matters very little that some man is called his highness, and another his holiness; but it is hard to serve one or the other.

A numerous family has cultivated good land. Two small neighbouring families have barren and obstinate fields. It is obvious enough that the two poor families must serve the opulent family or murder it. One of the two indigent families offers its labour to the rich to get bread; the other attacks it and is beaten. The former family originated servants and labourers, the defeated family slaves.

It is impossible on our wretched globe for men living in society not to be divided into two classes, one of oppressors, the other of the oppressed; and these subdivide into a thousand, and the thousand have further gradations.

All the oppressed are not absolutely unhappy. Most of them are born in that state, and continual work prevents them from feeling their condition too keenly; but when they feel it, then we have wars like that in Rome of the popular party against that of the senate, and those of the peasants in Germany, in England, in France. All these wars end sooner or later by the enslavement of the people because the powerful have the money, and in a state money is the master of everything: I say in a state, because it is not so in every nation. The nation making the best use of the sword will always subjugate that having more gold and less courage.

Every man is born with a powerful enough desire for domination, wealth and pleasure, and with much taste for idleness. Consequently every man would like to have other people's money and wives or women, to be their master, to subjugate them to all his caprices, and to do nothing, or at least to do only very agreeable things. Obviously, having such amiable dispositions, it is as impossible for men to be equal as it is impossible for two preachers or two professors of theology not to be jealous of one another.

Mankind cannot subsist at all unless there is an infinite number of useful men who possess nothing at all. For a prosperous man will certainly not leave his land to cultivate yours; and if you need a pair of shoes it is not a judge who will make them for you. Equality is thus at once the most natural and the most chimerical of things.

As men are extreme in everything whenever possible, this inequality has been exaggerated. In some countries it has been claimed that a citizen is not entitled to leave the country in which he is born by chance. The meaning of this law is obviously: This country is so bad and so badly governed that we forbid every individual to leave it, for fear that everybody leave it. Do better: make all your subjects wish to remain at home and strangers to come to you.

Every man has the right to believe himself, at the bottom of his heart, entirely equal to all other men. It does not follow from this that a cardinal's cook should order his master to prepare his dinner; but the cook can say: 'I'm a man like my master, like him I am born in tears; like me he will die with the same sufferings and the same ceremonies. Both of us perform the same animal functions. If the Turks capture Rome, and I am then a cardinal and my master a cook, I will take him into my service.' All this speech is reasonable and just; but until the Grand Turk captures Rome the cook must do his duty, or every human society is perverted.

As for a man who is neither a cardinal's cook nor endowed with any other public office; as for a private person of modest views, but who is annoyed because he is received everywhere with an air of patronage or disdain, who sees clearly that several monsignors have no more knowledge, no more intelligence, no more virtue than he, and who is sometimes wearied to find himself in their waiting rooms, what should he do? He should leave.

Fatherland

A fatherland is a composite of several families; and as we usually stand by our family out of self-love when we have no conflicting interest, so because of the same selflove we support our town or village, which we call our fatherland. The bigger the fatherland the less we love it, because divided love is weaker. It is impossible to love tenderly too numerous a family which we hardly know.

He who burns with ambition to become aedile, tribune, praetor, consul, dictator, cries out that he loves his country, and he loves only himself. Every man wants to be sure that he can sleep at home without another man arrogating to himself the power to make him sleep elsewhere. Every man wants to be sure of his fortune and his life. Thus, all having the same wishes, it turns out that private interest becomes the general interest: when we express our hopes for ourselves we are expressing them for the republic.

There cannot be a state on earth which was not first governed as a republic: it is the normal course of human nature. A few families first assembled against the bears and the wolves. The family which had grain exchanged it with that which had only wood.

When we discovered America we found all the tribes divided into republics. There were only two kingdoms in all this part of the world. Only two out of1,000 nations were found to be subjugated.

So it was in the ancient world. All was republican in Europe before the petty kings of Etruria and Rome. Republics are still seen today in Africa. Tripoli, Tunis, Algeria, towards the north, still live as men are said to have lived in the first ages of the world, free, equal among themselves, without masters, without subjects, without money, and almost without needs. The flesh of their sheep feeds them, their skins clothe them, huts of wood and earth are their shelters. They stink worse than any other men, but do not know it. They live and die more calmly than we do.

Eight republics without monarchs remain in our Europe: Venice, Holland, Switzerland, Genoa, Lucca, Ragusa, Geneva and San Marino. Poland, Sweden, England can be regarded as republics under a king; but Poland is the only one that takes the name.

Is it better today for one's country to be a monarchical or a republican state? This question has been debated for 4,000 years. Apply for a solution to the rich, they all prefer an aristocracy. Question the people, they want democracy. Only kings prefer a monarchy. How then is it possible that nearly the whole world is governed by monarchs? Ask the rats who proposed to hang a bell round the cat's neck. But in truth the real reason is, as I have said, that men are very seldom worthy to govern themselves.

It is sad that, to be a good patriot, one is often the enemy of the rest of humanity. The elder Cato, that good citizen, when speaking in the senate, always said: 'Such are my views, and let Carthage be destroyed.' To be a good patriot is to want one's city to be enriched by commerce and powerful in arms. It is obvious that a country cannot gain unless another loses, and that it cannot vanquish without causing unhappiness.

So it is the human condition that to wish for the greatness of one's fatherland is to wish evil to one's neighbours. The citizen of the universe would be the man who wishes his country never to be either greater or smaller, richer or poorer.

Flood

Has there ever been a time when the globe was entirely flooded? This is physically impossible.

It may be that the sea covered all parts of the earth one after the other, but that could have happened only by slow stages in a prodigious multitude of centuries. In a period of 500 years the sea has withdrawn from Aigues-Mortes, from Fréjus, from Ravenna, which were great ports, and has left about two leagues of dry ground. At this rate it is evident that it would take the sea 2,500,000 years to move round our globe. What is very remarkable is that this period is very near that taken by the axis of the earth to right itself and coincide with the equator. This movement, which is very probable, has been suspected for fifty years, and can only be completed in a period of more than 2,300,000 years.

The beds, the layers of shells which have been discovered on all sides, at several leagues from the sea, are incontrovertible proof that it has deposited its maritime products little by little on land that once formed the ocean shore. But that water once covered the entire globe at the same time is a chimera absurd in natural science, demonstrated impossible by the laws of gravitation, by the laws of fluids, by the insufficient quantity of water. I do not claim to undermine in any way the great truth of the universal flood reported in the Pentateuch. On the contrary, it was a miracle, therefore it must be believed; it was a miracle, therefore it was not performed by physical laws.

Everything is miraculous in the story of the flood. It was a miracle that forty days of rain inundated the four quarters of the earth, and that the water should have risen fifteen cubits above all the highest mountains. It was a miracle that there were cataracts, doors, openings in the sky. It was a miracle that all the animals should have proceeded to the ark from every part of the world. It was a miracle that Noah found enough to feed them for ten months. It was a miracle that all the animals found room in the ark with their provisions. It was a miracle that most of them did not die in the ark. It was a miracle that they found food on leaving the ark. It was also a miracle, but of another kind, that a certain Le Pelletier thought that he had explained naturally how all the animals fitted into the ark and fed themselves.

Now the story of the flood being the most miraculous thing we have ever heard of, it would be senseless to explain it. It is one of the mysteries we believe by faith, and faith consists in believing what the reason does not believe, which is another miracle in itself.

Thus the story of the universal flood is like that of the tower of Babel, Balaam's she-ass, the fall of Jericho by the sound of trumpets, water changed into blood, the passage of the Red Sea, and all the prodigies god deigned to perform for the benefit of his people's elect. These are profundities beyond human comprehension.

Great chain of being

The gradation of beings which ascends from the lightest atom to the supreme being, this ladder of the infinite, strikes one with wonder. But when one looks at it attentively this great phantasm vanishes, as formerly all apparitions fled at the crowing of the cock.

At first the imagination is gratified by the imperceptible passage from brute matter to organized matter, from plants to zoophytes, from these zoophytes to animals, from these to man, from man to spirits, from these spirits, dressed in little aerial bodies, to immaterial substances, and finally a thousand different orders of these substances which ascend from beauty to perfection and finally to god himself. This hierarchy much pleases decent folk, who liken it to the pope and his cardinals followed by the archbishops and the bishops, after whom come rectors, vicars, simple priests, deacons, subdeacons; then appear the monks, and the march-past ends with the capuchins.

But there is a rather greater distance between god and his most perfect creatures than between the holy father and the dean of the sacred college. This dean can become pope, but the most perfect of the spirits created by the supreme being cannot become god: there is infinity between god and him.

Nor does this chain, this alleged gradation exist among the vegetables and the animals which have been destroyed. There are no longer any murex. The Jews were forbidden to eat the griffin and the ixion. These two species have disappeared from the world, whatever Bochart may say. Where then is the chain?

Even if we had not lost several species, it is obvious that they can be destroyed. The lions, the rhinoceros are getting quite rare.

It is very probable that there have been races of men which are no longer found. But I hope that they have all survived, like the whites, the blacks, the Kaffirs, to whom nature has given a skin apron hanging from the belly half way down the thigh, the Samoyedes, whose wives have one beautifully black breast, etc.

Is there not obviously a gap between monkey and man? Is it not easy to imagine an animal with two feet and no feathers, intelligent without having also the power of speech or our appearance, which we could tame, which would answer our signals and serve us? And between this new species and man, could we not imagine others?

Divine Plato, you place in heaven a succession of celestial substances beyond man. For our part, we believe in a few of these substances, because this is taught by our faith. But you, what reason have you for believing in them? It would seem that you have not spoken to Socrates's demon, and good old Er who resuscitated specially to reveal to you the secrets of the other world, taught you nothing about these substances.

The alleged chain is no less interrupted in the physical universe.

What gradation, if you please, between your planets? The moon is forty times smaller than our globe. When you have travelled from the moon through space you come to Venus: it is about as big as the earth. Thence you go to Mercury, which revolves in an ellipse very different from the circle traversed by Venus. It is twenty-seven times smaller than we are, the sun a million times bigger, Mars five times smaller. This last makes its revolution in two years, his neighbour Jupiter in twelve, Saturn in thirty, even though Saturn, the most distant of all, is not as big as Jupiter. Where is the alleged gradation?

And then how can you expect there to be a chain that links everything in the great empty spaces? If there is one it is certainly that which Newton discovered: this is what makes all the globes of the planetary world gravitate towards one another in this immense void.

O Plato, so much admired, I fear that you have told us nothing but fables, and that you have never uttered anything but sophisms!

O Plato! You have done much more evil than you think. I shall be asked how, but I shall not answer.

Hell

As soon as men lived in society they must have noticed that some guilty men eluded the severity of the laws. They punished public crimes. It was necessary to create a check on secret crimes: only religion could be this check. The Persians, the Chaldeans, the Egyptians, the Greeks invented punishments after life; and the Jews alone among all the ancient peoples known to us approved only temporal punishments. It is ridiculous to believe, or to pretend to believe, on the strength of a few very obscure passages, that hell was recognized by the ancient laws of the Jews, by their Leviticus, by their decalogue, when the author of these laws does not say a single word that could have the slightest bearing on punishments in the future life. One would be entitled to say to the compiler of the Pentateuch: 'You are an irresponsible man, without probity and reason, very unworthy of the name of legislator that you arrogate. What! you know a dogma so repressive, and so necessary to the people, as that of hell, and you do not explicitly proclaim it? And, though it is accepted by all the nations around you, you are content to allow this dogma to be guessed at by some commentators who are to come 4,000 years after you and will torture some of your words to find in them something you have not said. Either you are an ignoramus, who are not aware that this belief was universal in Egypt, in Chaldea, in Persia; or you are very ill-advised, knowing this dogma, not to have made it the basis of your religion.'

The authors of the Jewish laws might at best reply: 'We admit that we are exceedingly ignorant; that we learned to write very late; that our people was a savage and barbaric horde which, as we have shown, wandered for half a century in uninhabitable deserts; that it finally usurped a small country by the most odious rapine and the most detestable cruelties ever recorded in history. We had no intercourse with civilized nations: how can you expect us (the most earthly of men) to have invented a wholly spiritual system?

'We used the word meaning soul only in the sense of life. We knew our god and his ministers, his angels, only as corporeal beings: the distinction between soul and body, the notion of a life after death, can be the fruit only of long meditation and a very subtle philosophy. Ask the Hottentots and the Negroes, who inhabit a country a hundred times larger than ours, whether they know about a future life. We thought we had done enough in persuading our people that god punishes evil-doers to the fourth generation, whether by leprosy, sudden death, or the loss of what little property it was possible for them to possess.'

One would reply to this defence: 'You have invented a system the absurdity of which is self-evident; for the malefactor who was in good health and whose family prospered would necessarily laugh at you.'

The apologist of the Judaic law would then answer: 'You are mis-taken; for there were a hundred criminals who did not reason at all, for every one who thought clearly. The man who, having committed a crime, felt unpunished in himself and in his son, feared for his grandson. Besides, if he did not have some stinking ulcer today, he would get one in the course of a few years, for we were much subject to them. Every family has misfortunes, and it was easy for us to inoculate the belief that these misfortunes were sent by a divine hand, the avenger of secret offences.'

It would be easy to respond to this answer, and to say: 'Your excuse is worthless, for it happens every day that very decent folk lose their health and their goods; and if there is no family that has escaped misfortune, and if these misfortunes are god's punishments, all your families must have been families of rascals.'

The Jewish priest could retort further. He would say that there are misfortunes attached to human nature, and others sent expressly by god. But one would make this argufier see how ridiculous it is to think that fever and hail are now a divine punishment, and now a natural effect.

Finally the Pharisees and the Essenes, among the Jews, accepted a belief in a hell in their manner. This dogma had already passed from the Greeks to the Romans, and was adopted by the Christians.

Several church fathers did not believe in eternal punishment: it appeared to them absurd to burn a poor wretch throughout eternity because he had stolen a goat. Virgil can say in the sixth book of the Aeneid:

...Sedet aeternumque sedebit

Infelix Theseus.

[Wretched Theseus sits and shall for ever sit.]

He implies in vain that Theseus is seated forever on a chair, and that this position constitutes his torment. Others believed that Theseus is a hero who is not seated in hell, but that he is in the Elysian fields.

Not long ago a good and decent Protestant minister preached and wrote that the damned would one day be pardoned, that the suffering should be proportionate to the sin, and that the error of a moment cannot deserve infinite punishment. The priests, his colleagues, dismissed this indulgent judge. One said to him: 'My dear fellow, I don't believe any more than you do that hell is eternal; but it's a good thing for your maid, your tailor, and even your lawyer to believe it.'

Joseph

The story of Joseph, considered merely as a curiosity and as literature, is one of the most precious monuments of antiquity to have come down to us. It appears to be the model for all oriental writers. It is more affecting than Homer's Odyssey, for a hero who pardons is more touching than one who avenges himself.

We regard the Arabs as the first authors of those ingenious fictions that have passed into all languages; but I see in them no adventure comparable to Joseph's. Nearly everything in it is marvellous, and the end brings a lump to the throat. Here we have a young man of sixteen whose brothers are jealous. They sell him to a caravan of Ishmaelite merchants, he is taken to Egypt, and bought by one of the king's eunuchs. This eunuch had a wife, which is not at all surprising. The Kislar-aga, a complete eunuch, who has had everything cut off, has a harem today in Constantinople. He was left his eyes and his hands, and nature has not lost its rights in his heart. The other eunuchs, who have had cut off only the two accompaniments of the organ of generation, still use that organ frequently, and Potiphar, to whom Joseph was sold, may very well have been one of those eunuchs.

The wife of Potiphar fell in love with the young Joseph, who, faithful to his master and benefactor, rejected the woman's attentions. This irritated her, and she accused Joseph of trying to seduce her. It is the story of Hippolytus and Phaedra, Bellerophon and Stheneboea, Hebrus and Damasippa, Tanis and Peribea, Myrtil and Hippodamia, Peleus and Demenette.

It is difficult to know which of all these stories is the original. But in the ancient Arabic authors the adventure of Joseph and Potiplsar's wife contains a very ingenious touch. The author imagines that Potiphar, undecided between his wife and Joseph, did not consider Joseph's tunic, which his wife had torn, to be proof of the young man's attack. There was a child in a cradle in the woman's room. Joseph said that she had torn and removed his tunic in the child's presence. Potiphar consulted the child, whose intelligence was very developed for its age. The child said to Potiphar: 'See whether the tunic is torn in front or behind: if in front this is evidence that Joseph tried to violate your wife, who defended herself; if behind it is evidence that your wife was running after him.' Thanks to this child's genius, Potiphar recognized the innocence of his slave. This is how the adventure is recounted in the Koran after the ancient Arabic author. He is not concerned to tell us to whom belonged the child who judged with so much intelligence. If it was the son of Potiphar's wife, Joseph was not the first she had pursued.

Be that as it may, according to Genesis Joseph was imprisoned, and found himself in company with the Egyptian king's cup-bearer and baker. These two prisoners of state dreamed during the night. Joseph explained their dreams, predicting that in three days the cup-bearer would be restored to favour, and the baker hung: which is what came to pass.

Two years later the king of Egypt also dreamed. His cup-bearer told him that there was a young Jew in prison who understood dreams better than anyone else in the world. The king sent for the young man, who predicted seven years of plenty and seven years of want.

Let us here briefly interrupt the thread of the story to consider how prodigiously ancient is the interpretation of dreams. Jacob had seen in a dream the mysterious ladder that led to god himself. He learned in a dream a way to multiply his flocks, a way that succeeded only for him. Joseph himself had learned in a dream that he would one day dominate his brothers. Long before, Abimelech had been warned in a dream that Sarah was the wife of Abraham.

Let us return to Joseph. As soon as he had explained Pharaoh's dream, he became prime minister on the spot. We may doubt whether a king could be found nowadays, even in Asia, who would bestow such an office for the explanation of a dream. Pharaoh made Joseph marry one of Potiphar's daughters. It is said that this Potiphar was the high priest of Heliopolis. So this was not his first master the eunuch, or if it was he, he was certainly entitled to be called something else in addition to high priest, and his wife had been a mother more than once.

In the meanwhile famine came as Joseph had predicted, and Joseph, to deserve the marked favour of his king, obliged everybody to sell their land to Pharaoh, and the entire nation enslaved itself to get grain. This was apparently the origin of despotic power. It must be admitted that never had a king made a better bargain, but the people can hardly have blessed the prime minister.

Finally Joseph's father and brothers also needed grain, for 'the famine was sore in all the earth'. It is hardly necessary to relate here how Joseph received his brothers, how he forgave and enriched them. All that constitutes an interesting epic poem is found in this story: exposition, crux, recognition, vicissitudes and marvels. Nothing bears more clearly the hallmark of oriental genius.

What old Jacob, father of Joseph, replied to Pharaoh, must strongly impress anyone who can read. 'How many are the days of the years of thy life?' asked the king. 'The days of the years of my pilgrimage are 130 years, and I have not yet had one happy day in this short pilgrimage.'

Judea

I have not been to Judea, thank God, and will never go. I have met people of all nationalities who have come back from it. They have all told me that the site of Jerusalem is horrible, that all the surrounding country is stony, that the mountains are naked, that the famous river Jordan is only forty-five feet wide, that the only good province in this country is Jericho. In short, they all repeat saint Jerome, who lived for so long in Bethlehem, and who depicts this land as the scrap-heap of nature. He says that in the summer there is not even water to drink. Nevertheless this country must have appeared to the Jews a delightful spot in comparison with the deserts they had come from. Wretches who had left the Landes to live on the mountains of the Lampourdan[around Bayonne] would praise their new home, and if they hoped to penetrate into the good parts of the Languedoc these would strike them as the promised land.

This is precisely the history of the Jews. Jericho and Jerusalem are Toulouse and Montpellier, and the Sinai desert is the country between Bordeaux and Bayonne. But if the god who conducted the Jews wanted to give them good land, and if these unfortunates had in fact lived in Egypt, why did he not leave them there? The only answers given to this question are theological phrases. Judea, it is said, was the promised land. God said to Abraham: 'I will give you all this land from the river of Egypt unto the Euphrates.'

Alas! my friends, you have never seen these fertile banks of the Euphrates and the Nile. They fooled you. The masters of the Nile and the Euphrates were, each in his turn, your masters. You have nearly always been slaves. To promise and to perform are two things, my poor Jews. You had an old rabbi who, reading the wise prophecies that foretell for you a land of milk and honey, exclaimed that you had been promised more butter than bread. Do you realize that if the Grand Turk offered me today the lordship of Jerusalem I would spurn it?

On seeing this detestable country Frederick II said publicly that Moses was very ill-advised to lead his company of lepers to it: 'Why didn't he go to Naples?' said Frederick. Good-bye my dear Jews; I am sorry that the promised land should be waste land.

Luxury

For 2,000 years people have declaimed in verse and prose against luxury, and have always loved it.

What has not been said about the earliest Romans, these brigands who ravaged and pillaged the harvests of their neighbours, who destroyed the poor villages of the Volscians and the Samnites in order to aggrandize their own poor village? They were disinterested and virtuous men! They had not yet been able to steal either gold or silver or precious stones, because there was none in the places they sacked. Neither their woods nor their marshes produced partridges or pheasants, and their temperance is praised!

When little by little they had pillaged everything, stolen everything from the far end of the Adriatic to the Euphrates, and had had enough sense to enjoy the fruit of their rapines for seven or eight hundred years, when they cultivated all the arts, tasted every pleasure, and made even the vanquished taste them, then, it is said, they ceased to be wise and upright.

All these declamations come down to proving that a thief must never eat the dinner he has stolen nor wear the clothes he has purloined nor adorn himself with the ring he has taken. All this, it is said, should have been thrown into the river if the thieves wanted to live as honest men. Say rather that one should not steal. Condemn the brigands when they pillage, but do not call them lunatics when they enjoy what they have taken. Honestly, when a large number of English sailors enriched themselves on taking Pondicherry and Havana, were they wrong to enjoy themselves later in London in return for the pains they had taken at the extremities of Asia and Africa?

Do the windbags want the wealth amassed by the fortunes of war, agriculture, trade and industry to be buried? They instance Lacedaemon. Why do they not cite also the republic of San Marino? Of what benefit was Sparta to Greece? Did she ever have a Demosthenes, Sophocles, Apelles or Phidias? The luxury of Athens produced great men of every kind. Sparta had a few captains, and even those in smaller numbers than the other cities. But so be it! Let a little republic like Lacedaemon preserve its poverty. We attain death just as surely lacking everything as enjoying whatever makes life agreeable. The Canadian savage survives and reaches old age just like the English citizen who has an income of 50,000 guineas. But who will ever compare the country of the Iroquois with England?

Let the republic of Ragusa and the canton of Zug make sumptuary laws. They are right, it is necessary for the poor man not to spend beyond his means, but I have read somewhere:

Sachez surtout que le luxe enrichit

Un grand état, s'il en perd un petit.

[Know above all that luxury enriches a great state,

though it ruins a small one.]

If by luxury you mean excess, everybody knows that excess of every kind is pernicious, in abstinence as in gluttony, in economy as in liberality. I do not know how it has come about that in my villages, in which the land is barren, the taxes heavy, the prohibition against exporting the wheat we have sowed intolerable, there is nevertheless hardly a husbandman without clothes made of good cloth and who is not well shod and well fed. If this farmer cultivates the land in his fine clothes, white linen, curled and powdered hair, that would certainly be the greatest luxury, and the most impertinent. But if a bourgeois of Paris or London appeared in the theatre dressed like this peasant, that would be the crudest and most ridiculous niggardliness.

Est modus in rebus, sunt certi denique fines, Quos ultra citraque nequit consistere rectum.

[There is a measure in all things, fixed limits which virtue must neither overstep nor fail to attain.]

Scissors are certainly not of the greatest antiquity. When they were invented what was not said against the first who pared their nails and cut part of the hair that fell over their noses? They were no doubt called dandies and prodigals, who bought at a high price a tool of vanity to spoil the work of the creator. What an enormous sin to shorten the horn that god causes to grow at the ends of our fingers! It was an insult to divinity. It was much worse when shirts and socks were invented. We know how furiously the old councillors, who had never worn them, cried out against the young magistrates who yielded to this fatal luxury.

Martyr

We can only guffaw at all the humbug we are told about martyrs. Such men as Titus, Trajan, Marcus Aurelius, these models of virtue, are depicted as monsters of cruelty. Fleury, abbé of the Loc-Dieu, dishonoured his ecclesiastical history with stories a sensible woman would not tell to little children.

Can it be seriously repeated that the Romans condemned each of seven virgins of seventy to pass through the hands of all the young men of the city of Ancyra, the same Romans who punished vestals with death for the slightest love-affair? It was apparently to give pleasure to inn-keepers that the story was invented of a Christian inn-keeper called Theodotus, who prayed to god to kill these seven virgins rather than to expose them to the loss of the oldest virginities. God gave ear to the prudish inn-keeper, and the proconsul had the seven misses drowned in a lake. As soon as they were drowned they went to Theodotus to complain of the trick he had played on them, and begged him earnestly to prevent the fishes from eating them. Theodoms took with him three topers from his tavern, marched to the lake with them, preceded by a celestial torch and a celestial horseman, fished up the seven old ladies, buffed them, and finished by being hanged.

Diocletian met a little boy called saint Roman, who stuttered. He wanted to have him burnt because he was a Christian. Three Jews who happened to be there started to laugh because Jesus Christ allowed a little boy who belonged to him to be burnt. They exclaimed that their religion was superior to the Christian since god delivered Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego from the fiery furnace. The flames which enveloped the young Roman without hurting him at once divided and burned the three Jews. The emperor, very astonished, said that he wanted to have no quarrel with god, but a village judge, less scrupulous, condemned the little stutterer to have his tongue cut out. The emperor's chief physician had the decency to perform the operation himself. As soon as he had cut out the little Roman's tongue, the child started to chatter with a volubility that transported the whole assembly with admiration.

A hundred stories of this kind are to be found in the martyrologies. Thinking to make the ancient Romans odious they made themselves ridiculous. Do you want good, well-attested barbarities; good, well-authenticated massacres; rivers of blood that really ran; fathers, mothers, husbands, women, children at the breast really butchered and piled up on each other? Persecuting monsters, seek these truths only in your annals: you will find them in the crusades against the Albigensians, in the massacres of Mérindol and Cabrières, in the appalling day of saint Bartholomew, in the Irish massacres, in the valleys of the Waldenses. It well becomes you, barbarians that you are, to impute extravagant cruelties to the best of emperors, you who have inundated Europe with blood, and covered it with dying bodies, to prove that it is possible to be in a thousand places at once, and that the pope can sell indulgences! Stop slandering the Romans, who gave you your laws, and ask god's forgiveness for the abominations of your fathers.

It is not the suffering, you say, that makes the martyr; it is the cause. Well, I grant that your victims should not be given the name of martyr, which means witness. But what name shall we give your executioners? Phalaris and Busiris were the gentlest of men compared with you. Does not your inquisition, which still survives, make reason, nature, religion shudder? Good god! if this infernal tribunal were reduced to ashes, would your vengeful gaze be displeased?

Miracles

A miracle, in the full meaning of the word, is an admirable thing. In this sense everything is miraculous. The prodigious order of nature, the rotation of 100 million globes around a million suns, the activity of light, the life of animals are perpetual miracles.

By conventional usage we call miracle the violation of these divine and eternal laws. If there is an eclipse of the sun at full moon, if a dead man walks two leagues carrying his head in his arms, we call that a miracle.

Several natural philosophers maintain that in this sense there are no miracles; and here are their arguments.

A miracle is the violation of the divine, immutable, eternal laws of mathematics. By this very definition a miracle is a contradiction in terms. A law cannot be at once immutable and violated. But, they are asked, cannot god suspend a law established by himself? They have the hardihood to answer that it cannot, that it is impossible for a being infinitely wise to have made laws in order to violate them. He could disturb his machine, they say, only to make it function better. Now it is clear that this immense machine is as good as he; being god, he could make it: if he saw that there would be imperfection because of the nature of the material, he dealt with it from the beginning; therefore he will never change anything in it.

Besides, god cannot do anything without a reason; and what reason could lead him to disfigure his own work for a time? They will be told that it is for the benefit of mankind. They reply that it must then be for the benefit of all men, for it is impossible to conceive that the divine nature would work for a few individual men, and not for the entire human species. In any case, the human species is not up to much: it is much less than a small ant-hill in comparison with all the beings that fill immensity. Now is it not the most absurd of follies to imagine that the infinite being would invert the eternal play of the immense engines which move the entire universe for the sake of three or four hundred ants on this little heap of mud?

But let us suppose that god wanted to distinguish a small number of men by particular favours: would he have to change what he established for ever and for everywhere? He certainly has not the least need for such a change, for such inconstancy, to favour his creatures: his favours are in his very laws. He has foreseen everything, arranged everything for them: all obey irrevocably the power he has impressed for ever on nature.

Why should god perform a miracle? To accomplish a given plan for a few living beings? He would then be saying: 'I have been unable to accomplish a certain plan by the manufacture of the universe, by my divine decrees, my eternal laws. I am going to change my eternal ideas, my immutable laws to try to perform what I could not accomplish with them.' It would be a confession of his weakness, and not of his power. It would seem to be the most inconceivable contradiction in him. Hence it is really to insult him (if men can insult god) to dare to attribute miracles to him, it is to say to him: 'You are a weak and inconsistent being.' It is therefore absurd to believe in miracles, it is as it were to dishonour the divinity.

These philosophers are pressed, they are told: 'You exalt in vain the immutability of the supreme being, the eternity of his laws, the regularity of his infinite worlds. Our little mud heap has seen an abundance of miracles, history is as full of prodigies as of natural events. The daughters of the high priest Anius changed whatever they chose into wheat, wine or oil. Athalida, daughter of Mercury, resuscitated several times. Aesculapius resuscitated Hippolytus. Hercules dragged Alcestis back from death. Heres returned to the world after passing a fortnight in hell. The parents of Romulus and Remus were a god and a vestal virgin. The Palladium fell from heaven in the city of Troy. The hair of Berenice became a constellation. The hut of Baucis and Philemon was changed into a superb temple. The head of Orpheus rendered oracles after his death. The walls of Thebes were built by the sound of a flute alone, in the presence of the Greeks. The cures performed in the temple of Aesculapius were innummerable, and we still have monuments covered with the names of the eye-witnesses of the miracles of Aesculapius.'

Give me the name of one people among whom incredible prodigies were not performed, especially when few knew how to read and write.

Freethinkers answer these objections only by laughing and shrugging their shoulders. But Christian philosophers say: 'We believe in the miracles operated in our holy religion. We believe them by faith and not by reason, to which we take great care not to listen, for it is well known that the reason must not utter a single word when faith speaks. We have a firm and entire belief in the miracles of Jesus Christ and the apostles, but you must permit us to doubt a little about some others. Permit us, for instance, to suspend our judgement about the story told by a simple man to whom the name of great has been given. He asserts that a little monk was so much accustomed to perform miracles that the prior finally forbade him to exercise his talent. The little monk obeyed; but, having seen a poor tiler falling from the top of a roof, he hesitated between the wish to save his life and holy obedience. He simply ordered the tiler to remain in the air until further notice, and ran to tell his prior how things stood. The prior gave him absolution of the sin he had committed in beginning a miracle without permission, and allowed him to finish it, provided that he stopped there and did not do it again. We agree with freethinkers that this story must be distrusted a little.'

But how do you dare to deny, they will be asked, that saint Gervase and saint Protasius appeared in a dream to saint Ambrose, and told him where their relics were to be found? that saint Ambrose unearthed them, and that they cured a blind man? Saint Augustine was then in Milan. It is he who reports this miracle. Immenso populo teste, says he in the City of God, Chapter XXII. This is one of the best attested miracles. Freethinkers say that they do not believe a word of it, that Gervase and Protasius appeared to nobody, that it matters very little to mankind whether the whereabouts of the remnants of their carcasses be known or not, that they have no more faith in this blind man than in Vespasian's, that it is a useless miracle, that god does nothing useless; and they hold firmly to their principles. My respect for saint Gervase and saint Protasius does not permit me to share the opinion of these freethinkers. I merely report their incredulity. They make much of the passages in Lucian, in his Death of Peregrinus: 'When a deft juggler becomes a Christian he is bound to make his way.' But as Lucian is a profane author he should have no authority for us.

These freethinkers cannot bring themselves to believe the miracles operated in the second century. It is in vain that eye-witnesses write that saint Polycarp, bishop of Smyrna, having been condemned to be burned and thrown into the flames, they heard a heavenly voice crying out: 'Courage, Polycarp! be strong, show yourself a man'; that the flames of the pyre then parted from the body and formed a tent of fire above his head, and a dove came out of the midst of the pyre. At last they had to cut off Polycarp's head. 'What was the good of this miracle?' ask the incredulous. 'Why did the flames lose their nature, and not the executioner's axe? Why is it that so many martyrs have emerged safe and sound from boiling oil, and could not resist the edge of the sword?' They answer that it is the will of god. But the freethinkers would have liked to see all this with their own eyes before believing it.

Those who fortify their arguments with knowledge will tell you that the fathers of the church themselves have often admitted that no more miracles were performed in their times. Saint Chrysostom says expressly: 'The extraordinary gifts of the spirit were given even to the unworthy because the church then needed miracles; but today they are no longer given even to the worthy, because the church no longer needs them.' Then he admits that there is no longer anyone who resuscitates the dead, or even who cures the sick.

Saint Augustine himself, despite the miracle of Gervase and Protasius, says in his City of God: 'Why are the miracles that used to be performed no longer performed today?' And he gives the same reason: 'Cur, inquiunt, nunc illa miracula quae praedicatis facta esse non fiunt? Possem quidem dicere necessaria prius fuisse quam crederet mundus, ad hoc ut crederet mundus'['Why', they ask, 'are the miracles that used to be done, as you boast, not now done? I could say that they were necessary before the world believed, so that the world should believe'].

It is objected to the freethinkers that saint Augustine, in spite of this admission, nevertheless mentions an old cobbler of Hippo who, having lost his clothes, went to pray in the chapel of the twenty martyrs. When he returned he found a fish in whose body was a gold ring, and the cook who prepared the fish said to the cobbler: 'This is what the twenty martyrs give you.'

To this the freethinkers answer that nothing in this story contradicts the laws of nature, that natural laws are not in the least offended by a fish who swallows a gold ring, and a cook who gives this ring to a cobbler, that this is no miracle.

If these freethinkers are reminded that according to saint Jerome, in his Life of the Hermit Paul, this hermit had several conversations with satyrs and fauns, that a raven brought him every day for thirty years half a loaf for his dinner, and a whole loaf on the day saint Anthony called on him, they could again reply that all this is not absolutely against nature, that satyrs and fauns may have existed, and that in any case since this story is puerile, it has nothing in common with the true miracles of the saviour and of his apostles. Several good Christians have objected to the story by Theodoret about saint Simon Stylites. Many miracles that pass for authentic in the Greek church have been called in question by several Latin ones, just as some Latin miracles have been doubted in the Greek church. Then came the Protestants, who have much ill-treated the miracles of both churches.

A learned Jesuit who preached a long time in the Indies complains that neither his colleagues nor he could ever perform a miracle. Xavier laments in several of his letters that he does not have the gift of tongues. He says that he is nothing but a dumb statue among the Japanese. Nevertheless the Jesuits have written that he resuscitated eight dead people: that's a lot, and we must also take into account that he resuscitated them5,000 leagues from here. Since then some people have been known to say that the abolition of the Jesuits in France is a much greater miracle than those of Xavier and Ignatius.

Be that as it may, all Christians agree that the miracles of Jesus Christ and the apostles are incontestably veridical, but that we are entitled to doubt with all our strength some miracles done in recent times and which have not been positively authenticated.

For a miracle to be well established one would wish it to be performed in the presence of the Académie des Sciences of Paris, or the Royal Society of London, and the faculty of medicine, supported by a detachment of the regiment of guards to control the crowd of people whose indiscretion might prevent the operation of the miracle.

One day a freethinker was asked what he would say if he saw the sun stop, that is, if the movement of the earth round this body stopped, if all the dead resuscitated, and if the mountains in unison fell into the ocean, the whole to prove some important truth, such as versatile grace. 'What I would say?' answered the freethinker. 'I would turn Manichean; I would say that there is one principle which undoes what the other has done.'

Peter

In Italian, Piero or Pietro; in Spanish, Pedro; in Latin, Petrus; in Greek, Petros; in Hebrew, Cepha.

Why have the successors of Peter had so much power in the west and none in the east? This is like asking why the bishops of Wurzburg and Salzburg assumed regalian rights in times of anarchy, while the Greek bishops have always remained subjects. Time, opportunity, the ambition of some and the weakness of others have done and will do everything in this world.

The common opinion was added to this anarchy, and opinion is the queen of men: not that in reality they have clearly defined opinions, but words take their place.

It is reported in the gospel that Jesus said to Peter: 'I will give unto thee the keys of the kingdom of heaven.' The partisans of the bishop of Rome maintained about the eleventh century that he who gives the greater gives also the lesser, that the heavens envelop the earth, and that, Peter having the keys of the container, had also the keys of the content. If by the heavens be understood all the stars and all the planets, it is evident according to Thomasius, that the keys given to Simon Bar-Jona, called Peter, formed a master-key. If by the heavens be understood the clouds, the atmosphere, the ether, the space in which revolve the planets, there are no locksmiths, according to Meursius, who can make a key for such doors as those.

In Palestine keys were wooden pegs tied with a strap. Jesus said to Bar-Jona: 'Whatsoever thou shalt bind on earth shall be bound in heaven.' The pope's theologians have concluded from this that the popes had received the right to bind people to the oath of fidelity made to their kings, and to unbind them from it, and to dispose as they please of all the kingdoms. It is a magnificent conclusion. In the estates general of France of 1302 the communes said in their petition to the king, that 'Boniface VIII is a b - who believed that god binds and imprisons in heaven what this Boniface binds on earth.' A famous Lutheran in Germany(I think it was Melanchthon) had great difficulty in swallowing that Jesus said to Simon Bar-Jona, Cepha or Cephas: 'Thou art Peter [Pierre], and upon this rock[pierre] I will build my assembly, my church.' He could not believe that god could have used such a play on words, so extraordinary a jest, and that the power of the pope should be based on a pun.

Peter was thought to have been bishop of Rome, but it is well known that at that time and for long after there was no individual see. Christian society only took shape at about the end of the second century.

It is possible that Peter made the journey to Rome; it is even possible that he was crucified head down, although that was not the practice; but there is no proof of all that. We have a letter under his name in which he says that he is in Babylon: judicious canonists have maintained that by Babylon we should understand Rome. Hence if he had dated the letter from Rome we could have concluded that it had been written in Babylon. Such inferences have long been drawn, and so has the world been regulated.

There was a saintly man who had been made to pay dearly for a benefice in Rome. This is called simony. He was asked whether he believed that Simon Peter had been in Rome. He answered: 'I don't know about Peter, but Simon certainly has.'

As for Peter personally, it must be admitted that Paul was not the only one who was shocked by his behaviour. He and his successors have often and openly been resisted. Paul bitterly reproached him for eating forbidden flesh, that is, pork, black pudding, hare, eel, ixion and griffin. Peter defended himself by saying that he had seen the heavens open about the sixth hour, and a great cloth descend from the four comers of the sky, filled with eels, quadrupeds and birds, and that the voice of an angel had cried out: 'Kill and eat.' This is apparently the same voice, says Wollaston, that has cried to so many pontiffs: 'Kill everything, and eat the substance of the people.'

Casaubon could not approve the way in which Peter treated the good Ananias and his wife Sapphira. By what right, asks Casaubon, did a Jew, slave of the Romans, order or allow all those who believed in Jesus to sell their inheritance and put the proceeds at his feet? If some Anabaptist in London made his brethren lay all their money at his feet, would he not be arrested as a traitorous seducer, a robber who would infallibly be sent to Tyburn? Was it not horrible to put Ananias to death because, without saying anything, he held back a few crowns for his necessities and those of his wife when he sold his property and gave the money to Peter? His wife arrived when Ananias had only just died. Peter, instead of warning her mercifully that he had just caused her husband to die of an apoplexy for keeping a few oboles, and telling her to take care of herself, made her fall into the trap. He asked whether her husband had given all his money to the saints. The good woman answered yes, and died on the spot. What harshness!

Coringius asks why Peter, who thus killed those who gave him alms, did not rather kill all the theologians who had caused the death of Jesus Christ, and had him scourged more than once. O Peter! you kill two Christians who gave you alms, and you allow to live those who crucified your god!

Coringius evidently was not living in any of the homes of the inquisition when he put these daring questions. Erasmus noticed a very peculiar thing in connection with Peter: it is that the head of the Christian religion began his apostolate by denying Jesus Christ, and that the first pontiff of the Jews had begun his ministry by making a golden calf, and worshipping it.

Be that as it may, Peter is depicted as a poor man who catechized the poor. He is like those founders of orders who lived in indigence, and whose successors have become great lords.

The pope, Peter's successor, now won, now lost; but apart from his immediate subjects, about 50 million men on earth remain to him, subject in various ways to his laws.

To acknowledge a master three or four hundred leagues away; to wait before you think until that man has seemed to think; dare to give a final verdict only through commissioners appointed by this foreigner in a law-suit between your own fellow citizens; not dare to take possession of the fields and vineyards secured from one's own king without paying considerable sums to this foreign master; violate the laws of one's country, which prohibit a man from marrying his niece, yet does so legitimately by giving his foreign master a still greater sum; not dare to cultivate one's field on whatever day this foreigner requires one to celebrate the memory of an unknown whom he has sent to heaven by his private authority: this is part of what it means to acknowledge a pope, these are the liberties of the Gallican church.

Some other peoples carry their submission further. In our own day we have seen a sovereign ask the pope's permission to have some monks accused of parricide tried by his royal tribunal, failing to obtain this permission, and not daring to judge them.

It is well known that formerly the rights of the popes went further. They were far above the gods of antiquity, for these gods were merely said to dispose of empires, and the popes really did dispose of them.

Sturbinus says that those who doubt the pope's divinity and infallibility can be forgiven when it is considered:

that forty schisms have profaned the seat of saint Peter, and that twenty-seven have steeped it in blood;

that Stephen VII, son of a priest, disinterred the body of his predecessor Formosus, and had the corpse's head cut off;

that Sergius III, convicted of murders, had a son, by Marozia, who inherited the papacy;

that John X, the lover of Theodora, was strangled in his bed;

that John XI, son of Sergius III, was known only as a debauchee;

that John XII wag murdered in his mistress's house;

that Benedict IX bought and resold the pontificate;

that Gregory VII was the initiator of 500 years of civil war sustained by his successors;

that finally, among so many ambitious, bloody and debauched popes, there was an Alexander VI, whose name is spoken with the same horror as that of Nero and Caligula.

It is said that it is evidence of the divine nature of the papacy that it has survived so many crimes; but then the caliphs would have been even more divine had they behaved even more atrociously. This is the reasoning of Dermius, but the Jesuits have answered him.

The philosopher Julian, Roman emperor

Justice is sometimes done very late. Two or three authors, either mercenaries or fanatics, talk about the barbarian and effeminate Constantine as of a god, and call the just, the wise, the great Julian a scoundrel. All the others, who copied the first, repeat the flattery and the calumny. These almost become an article of faith. Finally the time for sound criticism arrives, and, after1,400 years, enlightened men review the cause that ignorance had judged. Constantine is seen as a man, successful in his ambitions, who laughed at god and at mankind. He had the insolence to pretend that god sent him a heavenly sign which ensured his victory. He soaked himself in the blood of all his family, and went to sleep in sloth; but he was a Christian, and was canonized.

Julian was sober, chaste, disinterested, brave, merciful; but he was not a Christian, and was for long regarded as a monster.

Today, having compared the facts, the documents, Julian's writings and those of his enemies, we are compelled to recognize that although he did not like Christianity it was pardonable for him to hate a sect sullied by the blood of all his family; that having been persecuted, imprisoned, exiled, threatened with death by the Galileans in the reign of the barbarous Constantine, he never persecuted them, that on the contrary he pardoned ten Christian soldiers who had conspired against his life.

We read his letters, and we admire him. 'The Galileans,' he says, 'suffered exile and imprisonment under my predecessor. Those who called each other heretics turn and turn about, massacred each other. I have recalled those they exiled, and freed their prisoners. I have returned their property to the outlawed. I have compelled them to live in peace. But such is the restless rage of the Galileans that they complain because they can no longer devour one another.' What a letter! what a verdict pronounced by philosophy against persecuting fanaticism!

In short, everyone who has studied the facts impartially recognizes that Julian had all the qualities of Trajan, except the inclination for which the Greeks and the Romans have so long been forgiven; all the virtues of Cato, but not his obstinacy and his bad temper; all that we admire in Julius Caesar, and none of his vices; he was as chaste as Scipio. In a word, he was in all things the equal of Marcus Aurelius, the greatest of men.

Nowadays we no longer dare to repeat, after the calumniator Theodoret, that Julian immolated a woman in the temple of Carrhae to propitiate the gods. We no longer repeat that in dying he threw with his hand some drops of his blood towards heaven, saying to Jesus Christ: 'You have vanquished, Galilean!' as if he had fought against Jesus in warring against the Persians; as if this philosopher, who died with so much resignation, had acknowledged Jesus; as if he had believed that Jesus was in the air, and that the air was heaven! These inaptitudes of people who are called fathers of the church are no longer repeated nowadays.

They were finally reduced to ridiculing him, as did the frivolous citizens of Antioch. They reproached him his unkempt beard and the way he walked. But master La Bletterie, you have not seen him walk, and you have read his letters and his laws, monuments of his virtues. What does it matter whether his beard was dirty and his walk hurried, so long as his heart was magnanimous and all his steps tended towards virtue?

One important fact today remains to be examined. Julian is reproached with wanting to falsify Jesus Christ's prophecy by rebuilding the temple of Jerusalem. It is said that fires came out of the ground which prevented the work. It is said that this was a miracle, and that this miracle converted neither Julian, nor Alypius, manager of the enterprise, nor any member of the court. Whereupon the abbé de la Bletterie says this: 'He and the philosophers of his court no doubt had recourse to their knowledge of natural philosophy to deprive the divinity of so striking a prodigy. Nature has always been the refuge of the incredulous, but she serves religion so aptly that they ought at least to suspect her of collusion.'

First, it is not true that the gospels say that the Jewish temple would never be rebuilt. It is true that the gospel of Matthew, obviously written after the destruction of Jerusalem by Titus, prophesies that not one stone would be left upon another of this temple of the Idumaean Herod. But no evangelist says that it will never be rebuilt. It is quite false that not one stone remained upon another after Titus had it pulled down. He preserved all the foundations, an entire wall, and the Antonia tower.

Secondly, what does it matter to the divinity whether there is a Jewish temple or a powder magazine or a mosque on the spot where the Jews slaughtered oxen and cows?

Thirdly, it is not known whether these alleged fires, which according to some burned the workmen, emanated from the walled enclosure of the city or from that of the temple. But it is difficult to understand why Jesus should have burned the emperor Julian's workmen when he did not burn those of the caliph Omar who, long after, built a mosque on the ruins of the temple, nor those of the great Saladin, who restored this same mosque. Did Jesus have so great a predilection for the mosques of the Moslems?

Fourthly, Jesus, having predicted that not one stone would remain on another in Jerusalem, did not forbid that it be rebuilt.

Fifthly, Jesus predicted several things the accomplishment of which has not been permitted by god. He predicted the end of the world and his advent in the clouds with great power and great majesty at the end of the generation then living. Nevertheless the world still lasts and apparently will last for some time.

Sixthly, if Julian had described this miracle I would have said that he had been deceived by a false and ridiculous report, I would believe that his enemies the Christians spared no effort to oppose his enterprise, that they killed the workmen and made people believe that those workmen had been killed by a miracle. But Julian does not say a word about it. He was busy then with the war against the Persians. He deferred for a time the building of the temple, and died before he could begin it.

Seventhly, this prodigy is reported by Ammianus Marcellinus, who was a pagan. It is very possible that it was interpolated by the Christians: they have been authentically accused of so many others.

But it is no less likely that at a time when people talked of nothing but prodigies and stories of witchcraft, Ammianus Marcellinus should have reported this fable on the word of some credulous mind. Since Titus Livius down to Thou inclusively all histories are tainted by prodigies.

Eighthly, contemporary writers report that at this time there was a great earthquake in Syria, that fire broke out in several places, and that several towns were swallowed up. Thus no miracle remains.

Ninthly, if Jesus worked miracles, would it be to prevent the rebuilding of a temple in which he himself had offered up sacrifices and had been circumcised? Would he not work miracles to Christianize so many nations which jeer at Christianity, or rather to make his Christians gentler and more humane, they who, from Arius and Athanasius to Roland and Cavalier in the Cévennes, have poured out torrents of blood and behaved like cannibals?

From this I conclude that nature is not in collusion with Christianity, as La Bletterie says, but that La Bletterie is in collusion with old wives' tales, as Julian says: Quibus cum stolidis aniculis negotium erat.

After doing justice to some of Julian's virtues La Bletterie nevertheless ends the history of this great man by saying that his death was a consequence of 'divine vengeance'. If that was so, all heroes who died young were punished by god, from Alexander to Gustavus Adolphus. Julian died the finest of deaths, pursuing his enemies after several victories. Jovian, who succeeded him, reigned a much shorter time than he, and reigned shamefully. I detect no divine vengeance, and I see no more in La Bletterie than a dishonest ranter. But where are the men who dare to speak the truth? The stoic Libanius was one of these rare men. He praised the brave and merciful Julian to Theodosius, the murderer of the Thessalonians, but master Le Beau and master La Bletterie are afraid to praise him to faithful parishioners.

Julian has been reproached because he gave up Christianity, as soon as he could do so without risking his life. This is to reproach a man, taken by thieves and enrolled in their gang with a knife to his throat, for escaping from these brigands. The emperor Constant, no less barbarous than his father Constantine, had soaked himself in the blood of Julian's entire family. He had just killed this great man's blood brother. The empress Eusabia had great difficulty in persuading Constant to allow the young Julian to live. In order not to be murdered this unfortunate prince had to accept a monk's tonsure to ensure and receive what are called the four minor orders. He imitated Junius Brutus, who pretended to be mad in order to outwit Tarquin's fury. He was senseless until the moment when, finding himself in Gaul at the head of an army, he became a man and a great man. This is what is called apostasy by the apostates of reason, if such a term can be applied to those who have never known it.

Montesquieu says: 'Woe to the reputation of any prince who is survived by an enemy faction.' Let us imagine that Julian had completed his victory over the Persians, and that, during a long and peaceful old age, he had seen his ancient religion restored, and Christianity annihilated with the sects of the Pharisees, Sadducees, Rechabites, Essenians, Therapeutes, with the worship of the Syrian goddess, and so many more of which no trace remains - then what praises would all the historians have lavished on Julian! Instead of the epithet of apostate he would have been given that of restorer, and the title of divine would not have seemed exaggerated.

Look at the way all our unworthy compilers of Roman history are on their knees to Constantine and Theodosius, with what baseness they palliate their crimes! Nero certainly never did anything comparable to the massacre of the Thessalonians. The Cantabrian Theodosius pretended to pardon the Thessalonians, and six months later he invited them to games in the municipal circus. This circus had room for at least15,000 persons, and it is certain that it was full. The people's passion for spectacles is notorious. Fathers and mothers brought children who could hardly walk. As soon as the crowd had arrived, the Christian emperor sent Christian soldiers, who massacred old men, youngsters, women, girls, children, without sparing a single one. And this monster is exalted by all our compiling plagiarists because, they say, he did penance. Good god, what penance! He did not give an obol to the families of the dead. But he did not go to mass. It must be admitted that one suffers horribly when one does not go to mass, that god is infinitely grateful to you for it, that it redeems all crimes.

The infamous continuator of Laurent Echard calls the massacre ordered by Theodosius a vivacity.

The same wretches who scribble Roman history in a bombastic style full of solecisms, tell you that Theodosius, before engaging battle with his rival Eugene, saw saint John and saint Philip dressed in white, who promised him victory. Let such writers sing hymns to John and to Philip, but let them not write history.

Reader, examine your conscience. You admire, you love Henry IV. But if he had fallen at the battle of Arques, where his enemies were ten to one against him, and where he was victorious only because he was a hero in the fullest sense of the word, you would not know him: he would only be the Bearnese, a guerilla, a relapsed heretic, an apostate. The duc de Mayenne would be a man sent by god, the pope would have canonized saint Philip, riddled though he was by the pox, and saint John would have appeared to him more than once. And you, Daniel the Jesuit, how you would have flattered Mayenne in your poor and arid history! how he would have 'pushed after him', how he would always have 'beaten' the Beamese 'hollow'! how the church would have 'triumphed'!

Careat successibus opto

Ouisquis ab eventu facta notanda putaat.

[I beg that he come to naught who thinks that the deed should be judged by its result.]

Prejudices

A prejudice is an irrational opinion. Thus throughout the world all sorts of opinions are instilled into children before they are able to use judgement.

There are universal and necessary prejudices, which constitute virtue itself. In all countries children are taught to acknowledge a god who rewards and avenges; to respect and love their fathers and mothers; to regard theft as a crime, selfish lying as a vice, before they can imagine what is a vice and a virtue.

There are therefore very good prejudices: they are those ratified by the judgement when one is able to reason.

Feeling is not mere prejudice, it is something much stronger. A mother does not love her son because she has been told that she must love him: she happily cherishes him despite herself. It is not out of prejudice that you run to help an unknown child about to fall into a precipice or to be devoured by an animal.

But it is out of prejudice that you respect a man dressed in a certain way, who behaves solemnly and talks in the same way. Your parents told you that you should bow to this man. You respect him before you know whether he deserves your respect. You grow in age and knowledge. You perceive that this man is a charlatan eaten up with pride, selfishness and guile. You despise what you revered, and prejudice yields to judgement. Out of prejudice you believed the fables with which your childhood was deluded. You were told that the Titans made war on the gods and that Venus was in love with Adonis. When one is twelve one takes these fables for truths, at twenty-one regards them as ingenious allegories.

Let us examine in a few words the different kinds of prejudices, so as to put our affairs into order. We shall perhaps be like those who, at the time of Law's system, realized that they had been counting on imaginary wealth.

Prejudices of the Senses

Is it not an odd thing that our eyes always deceive us, even when we see very well, but that on the contrary our ears do not deceive us? If your ear is in good order and hears: 'You're beautiful, I love you', it is quite certain that you were not told: 'I hate you, you're ugly.' But you see a smooth mirror, and it has been proved that you are mistaken, that in fact it has a very uneven face. The sun has a diameter of about two feet to your eyes. It has been proved to be a million times bigger than the earth.

It seems that god has put the truth into your ears and error into your eyes; but study optics and you will see that god has not deceived you, and that in the present state of things it is impossible for objects to appear to you otherwise than they do.

Physical Prejudices

The sun rises, so does the moon, the earth is immobile: these are natural prejudices concerning the physical world. But that crayfish are good for the blood because they too are red when boiled; that eels cure paralysis because they quiver; that the moon influences illnesses because it was once observed that a patient's fever increased during the waning of the moon: these notions, and a thousand more, were the errors of ancient charlatans, who concluded without reasoning, and who, being deceived, deceived others.

Historical Prejudices

Most histories have been believed without investigation, and this credulity is a prejudice. Fabius Pictor tells us that several centuries before his time a vestal going to draw water in her pitcher, in the town of Elba, was raped, that she gave birth to Romulus and Remus, that they were suckled by a she-wolf, etc. The Roman people believed this fable. They did not inquire whether there had been vestals in Latium at that time, whether it was credible that the daughter of a king should leave her convent with her pitcher, whether it was probable that a she-wolf should suckle two children instead of eating them. The prejudice established itself.

A monk wrote that Clovis, being in great danger at the battle of Tolbiac, vowed to become a Christian if he got through it safely. But is it natural to address oneself to an alien god at such a time? Is it not then that the religion in which one was born acts most powerfully? What Christian, in a battle against the Turks, would not address himself to the holy virgin rather than to Mohammed? It is also said that a pigeon brought the holy ampulla in its beak for the anointment of Clovis, and that an angel brought the oriflamme to guide him. Prejudice believed all the anecdotes of this kind. Those who know human nature are well aware that the usurper Clovis and the usurper Rolon or Rol became Christians in order more easily to control the Christians, just as the Turkish usurpers became Moslems more easily to control the Moslems.

Religious Prejudices

If your nurse told you that Ceres presides over corn, or that Vishnu and Xaca have several times taken human form, or that Sammonocodom came to cut down a forest, or that Odin is waiting for you in his hall somewhere in Jutland, or that Mohammed or somebody else made a journey into heaven; if then your tutor drove into your brain what your nurse engraved there, you will keep hold of it for life. Should your judgement seek to rise above these prejudices, your neighbours, above all the women, scream impiety and frighten you. Your dervish, fearing to see his income diminish, accuses you to the cadi, and his cadi has you impaled if he can, because he wants to command fools, and believes that fools obey better than others. And that will last until your neighbours and the dervish and the cadi begin to understand that folly is worthless and that persecution is abominable.

Self-love

A vagabond grandly asked for alms near Madrid. A passer-by said to him: 'Aren't you ashamed to carry on this infamous trade when you can work?' 'Sir,' replied the beggar, 'I am asking for your money, not for advice'; then he turned his back, preserving all his Castilian dignity. This gentleman was a proud vagabond; it took little to wound his vanity. He asked for alms out of selflove, and could not bear to be reprimanded by another self-love.

A missionary travelling in India met a fakir loaded with chains, as naked as a monkey, lying on his stomach, and having himself whipped for the sins of his fellow countrymen the Indians, who gave him a few farthings. 'What self-renunciation!' said one of the spectators. 'Self-renunciation!' answered the fakir. 'Know that I have myself lashed in this world only to pay you back in the other, when you will be horses and I a horseman.'

Those who have said that self-love is the basis of all our feelings and of all our actions were therefore quite right in India, in Spain, and in all the habitable world: and just as no one writes to prove to men that they have faces, there is no need to prove to them that they have self-love. This self-love is the instrument of our conservation; it resembles the instrument that perpetuates the species: it is necessary, it is dear to us, it gives us pleasure, and it must be hidden.

Wicked

We are told loudly that human nature is essentially perverse, that man is born the child of the devil, and wicked. Nothing is more ill-considered. For, old friend, you who preach that the whole world is born perverse, you warn me that you were born thus, that I must distrust you like a fox or a crocodile. 'Not at all!' you tell me, 'I'm regenerated, I'm neither heretical nor infidel, you can trust me.' But the rest of mankind, which is either heretical or what you call infidel, is nothing but an assembly of monsters; and every time you talk to a Lutheran or to a Turk you must feel sure that they will rob and murder you, for they are children of the devil, born wicked, one unregenerated, the other degenerated. It would be much more rational, much more elegant to say to men: You are all born good; consider how awful it would be to corrupt the purity of your being. We ought to have behaved to mankind as we behave to every individual man. If a monk leads a scandalous life, we say to him: 'Would you really dishonour the dignity of a monk?' A lawyer is reminded that he has the honour to be a royal councillor, and should give an example. In order to encourage a soldier he is told: 'Remember that you belong to the regiment of Champagne.' Every individual should be told: 'Remember your human dignity.'

And in fact, whatever is said about it, we always come back to that; for what is the meaning of the saying, so often used in all nations, search your heart? If you were born a child of the devil, if your origin were criminal, if your blood were composed of an infernal liquid, this phrase search your heart would mean: consult, follow your diabolic nature, be an impostor, a thief, a murderer, it is the law of your father.

Man is not born wicked; he becomes wicked, as he falls ill. Doctors come along and say: 'You were born ill.' It is quite certain that these doctors, whatever they say and do, will not cure him if his sickness is inherent in his nature; and these thinkers are very ill themselves.

Collect all the children of the universe, and you will see in them only innocence, gentleness and fear. If they were born wicked, evil-doing, cruel, they would show some sign of it, just as small serpents try to bite and little tigers to claw. But nature, not having given more offensive arms to men than to pigeons and rabbits, could not give them an instinct of destruction.

So man is not born evil. Then why are some of them infected by this plague of wickedness? It is because their leaders, being infected by the disease, communicate it to the rest of mankind, just as a woman attacked by the malady brought back from America by Columbus spread this poison from one end of Europe to the other. The first ambitious man corrupted the earth.

You are going to say that this first monster brought out the germ of pride, rapine, fraud, cruelty that is in all men. I admit, generally speaking, that most of our brothers can acquire these qualities; but does everybody have putrid fever, the stone and the gravel because everybody is exposed to them?

There are whole nations that are not wicked: the Philadelphians, the Banians, have never killed anyone; the Chinese, the peoples of Tongking, Laos, Siam, even Japan, have had no war for more than a hundred years. One of the great crimes that shock human nature is hardly seen once in ten years in the cities of Rome, Venice, Paris, London, Amsterdam, although in these cities cupidity, the mother of all crimes, is extreme.

If men were essentially wicked, if they were all born subject to a being as malevolent as he is unhappy, who inspired them with all his rage to avenge himself for his own suffering, we would see every morning husbands murdered by their wives, and fathers by their children, as we find at daybreak chickens strangled by a weasel who came to suck their blood.

If there are a billion men on earth, it is a lot. That would make about 500 million women who sew, spin, feed their little ones, clean their houses or huts, and gossip a little about their neighbours. I do not see what great harm these innocents do on earth. Out of this number of inhabitants of the globe, there are at least 200 million children, who certainly neither kill nor plunder, and about as many old or sick people who are not able to do so. At most there remain 100 million young people, robust and capable of crime. Of these 100 million, 90 million are regularly occupied in prodigious labour to force the earth to yield them food and clothing: these hardly have time to do wrong.

Among the ten million who remain are included the idle and the gregarious, who only want to enjoy themselves; men of talent, busy with their professions; magistrates, priests, obviously concerned to live pure lives, at least in appearance. So the only really wicked men who remain are a few politic individuals, whether secular or religious, who always want to create trouble, and a few thousand vagabonds who hire out their services to these intriguers. In fact, there are never a million of these ferocious beasts employed at one time; and in this number I include highwaymen. So there is at most on earth, in the stormiest times, one man in a thousand who can be called wicked, and even he is not so all the time.

There is thus infinitely less evil on the earth than is said and believed. No doubt there is still too much. Horrible misfortunes and crimes are seen, but the pleasure of complaining and exaggerating is so great that at the slightest scratch you exclaim that the earth overflows with blood. If you have been cheated all men are perjurers. A melancholic who has suffered an injustice sees the universe covered with the damned, just as a young voluptuary, supping with his lady after the opera, cannot imagine that unfortunates exist.

译者导读

乔纳森·斯威夫特（Jonathan Swift，1667—1745），英国18世纪杰出的政论家和讽刺小说家，也是英国启蒙运动中激进民主派的创始人。他一生写了很多具有代表性的讽刺作品，晚年发表的小说《格列佛游记》在中国家喻户晓。《澡盆故事》是他的另一部代表作，在世界文坛享有重要地位。

《澡盆故事》是一部意义深远的杰出的讽刺作品，发表于1704年。在这部作品中，斯威夫特把矛头指向教会，同时对当时贫乏的学术、浅薄的文学批评和社会恶习也予以抨击。他通过三兄弟的形象淋漓尽致地讽刺了天主教会、英国国教和喀尔文教派。他讽刺这些教派都自认为是基督教的正宗，遵照《圣经》的指示行事，事实上却阳奉阴违。虽然斯威夫特本人是英国国教的牧师（在书中他对英国国教的批评尚留有余地），却能大胆地批评基督教徒的虚伪和无耻。《澡盆故事》是英国启蒙主义者批评教会的重要作品之一，也是斯威夫特第一部重要的文学作品，是他的成名作。

《澡盆故事》还可以说是斯威夫特最为晦涩难懂的一部著作，因此它历来受到诸多批评家和语言学者的关注，这恐怕也是这部书享誉世界的原因之一。有西方学者曾揶揄说，斯威夫特之所以写这部书，目的就是为了让后人撰写揣测它的博士论文。为了降低中国读者阅读中译本的难度，我在这里不揣冒昧提出一些我对这本书的理解以及如何阅读的建议。

首先，书中的故事有一条主线，那就是上面提到的三兄弟违背父亲遗嘱对外套任意加工修改的故事，以及后续发生的一些事情。这条线索比较明白易懂，在这里就不多介绍了。

再有，除了这条主线以外，书中其他章节的内容显得比较零散，语言又很隐晦，读者在阅读过程中可能会遇到较多的问题，且难以将它们与那条主线融合。对于这部分内容的理解，历来有一种观点认为主要需要搞清作者开头的交代，也就是第一章所讲的内容。它对下文起着辐射和提纲挈领的作用。

在第一章里，作者提到三样木制的布道用具：讲道坛、梯子和巡回台。书中在介绍的时候称它们是“为那些愿意说个不停的演说家”准备的，而这正是这部分内容的主题：作者在书中主要讽刺的是说话的艺术。而且他对其中每一样用具的描写都有很深的寓意。首先，他在提到讲道坛的时候说到它的木头已经腐朽，能发出磷光，又说里面充满蠕虫，这其实是在影射登上讲道坛的牧师头脑充满蠕虫，所讲的“指引人走向光明”一类的道理不过如同朽木的磷光一般庸俗。

作者对梯子的描述与当时的社会风俗有一定关系。当时在绞架上绞死犯人往往能吸引大批观众，这就暗合了作者在这章最开头提到的要站在高处向听众讲话的说法，也有人认为这具有讽刺政治和宗教的双重含义。另外，当时的死刑犯通常在临刑前都发表“最后陈词”，而陈词的演讲稿多相互抄袭，而且有的在对犯人行刑之前就已印发，为的是让人群中靠后面的观众也能“听”清楚。作者下文所说的梯子上贴着海报等也都与此有关。至于巡回台，作者后来对它作过解释，说它指的是“江湖骗子”，这也有来由。当时有一些蹩脚产品的推销员经常站在凸出的台子上宣传和叫卖产品。

《澡盆故事》一书在1704年发表伊始就引发轰动效应，并引起教会的不满。于是斯威夫特借该书第五次再版的机会发表了一封“致歉信”。当然，我们知道像他这样的思想和语言大师是不可能真正“道歉”的，除了应读者要求对书中一些词语作了解释之外，他不过是借道歉之名，用他惯有的讽刺与“反语”的娴熟技巧，进一步深化他在书中的观点。

善用“反语”的技巧，也是后人对斯威夫特的重要评价之一，这一技巧在书中多有应用，他在书中也自称“所采用的是一种与从古到今任何其他血肉体系都截然不同的思维模式”。认识到这一点将有助于我们解读斯威夫特的思想。此外，这本书中许多类似的关联都比较隐晦，不易觉察。例如第九章的话题系由第八章引出；第十一章提到的狗，使人联想到第三章对批评家的描述；以及结语中提到的缪斯和睡神，呼应第一章等等。

书中的有些文字游戏或许并没有太多深意，使用拉丁文也是当时的一种风气。作者虽有此意，但此书毕竟不是一本纯供消遣的书，同时考虑到作者所处时代的修辞特点，译文较多地照顾原文。由于原文本身十分晦涩，译文更难以做到面面俱到，疏漏也在所难免。考虑到书中的前后关系复杂，其影射所指比较含糊，因此译者加了一些辅助阅读的注解，希望读者在阅读时能够有所体会。

摘自前言[1]

现如今世上的慧眼极多，犀利的目光似乎令教会和国家中的权贵陷入巨大的忧虑。他们担心这些谦谦君子们趁着长治久安的当儿，从教会和政府的薄弱处下手，寻衅取乐。为避免此种情况，近来有人煞费苦心搞了若干计划，消磨那些严厉质询者的棱角和锋芒，以阻止其对这类敏感话题刨根问底。他们已经将注意力集中到了一个计划上，且仍需要一些时间和金钱才能完成。但时间不等人，危险随着新知的涌现而不断增加，且全借助于笔、墨、纸（着实令人生畏），一有情况，不消一个时辰它们就变成各种宣传册和其他可供立即使用的武器弹药。因此有人提出，确有必要先考虑一套权宜之计，以在完整对策尚未成熟之前应对紧急情况。于是，几天前在一个庞大的委员会上[2]，一位远见卓识的观察家提出了如下重大发现——在船员中间有这样一个惯例，当他们遇到可怕的鲸鱼时，就会扔下一只空澡盆逗它，分散它的注意力，这样它就不会对船只造成破坏了。这一比喻马上就被神化，鲸鱼被说成是霍布斯[3]的利维坦[4]，它打趣所有多为干瘪、虚空、木讷、叽叽喳喳、循环往复的宗教和政府计划。就是这个海中怪兽，给我们时代的那些尖刻的睿智者提供武器弹药。而处于危险中的船只则很容易地被想象为它的对立面：国家利益。但是，如何定义这只澡盆却成了难题。尽管经过长时间的探讨和争论，它字面上的意思被保留了下来，并通过法令颁布说，为防止那些海中怪兽颠覆本来易于动荡的国家利益，怪兽需要通过一个“澡盆故事”[5]来分散它对猎物的注意力。看来我在这方面展示才智也还惬意，我有幸让自己卷入了这场游戏。

“澡盆故事”

第一章　缘起

无论谁要想在听众群中一呼百应，都必须不遗余力地往前钻、挤、拥、攀，以达到一个所有人之上的制高点。而在所有集会上，不论人们多么拥挤，我们总能观察到一个特有的现象，就是在他们头顶上仍有充裕的空间，但是如何到达那里却是一个难题。想要摆脱定数就像摆脱地狱一样难。

——evadere ad auras，

Hoc opus, hic labor est.[6]

对此，历代哲人的想法都是建造一座空中楼阁。但是，无论过去乃至今日的这种构筑物具有何种用途和声誉，包括在我看来带有几分谦恭的苏格拉底[7]为了冥想而用来装自己的吊篮，这些挖空心思的构想还是有两点不足。首先是基础太高了，高得连看都看不见他们，更不要说听见了。第二是所用材料的寿命太短，经不起风吹雨打。尤其是在我们西北这片大地上。

有鉴于此，为让这一伟大构想真正发挥功能，据我所知仅剩下三样东西。它们都是我们前辈们神奇的智慧结晶。他们认为，为了鼓励所有热心的探险者，应该为那些愿意说个不停的演说家准备三件木制品。那就是：讲道坛、梯子和巡回台。[8]至于围栏[9]，尽管它也是木头的，设计的用途也与前三者相同，但是由于它的级别或低下的地位，使用它会不停被同行打断[10]，因而无缘位列第四。木凳[11]也一样，无论它的鼓吹者如何强调它的地位和价值。因为，如果他们乐意认真研究它最初的设计，以及辅助设计的环境和附件，都会马上承认它如今的用途仍然与其原始构造完全一致，而且，从语源学上说，它的这两个方面也是吻合的，这个名字在腓尼基语[12]中就是一个意义非凡的词，其所指，按字面意思翻译，就是睡觉的地方。但是按一般理解，它指的是一个带有舒适长枕和软垫的座椅，很适合老迈并患有痛风的肢体：senes ut in otia tuta recedant[13]。感谢命运的安排，让那些人在这上面扯平。先是在他们侃侃而谈的时候别人睡觉，现在轮到别人絮叨他们大睡了。

但是，如果再没有其他任何理由将木凳和围栏排斥在演说器材之外，那么有以下这一条理由就足够了。那就是：将它们纳入其中显然会破坏一个数字，而这个数字正是我决心不论付出多么高昂的代价也要大书特书的。对此我模仿了其他许多哲人和大人物所推崇的审慎方法，他们在分类学方面的主要技能渐渐让他们对某个神秘数字产生了兴趣，使这一数字在他们的想象中变得神圣起来，以至于他们不惜强迫公理伦常为它让路，在自然界各个方面，通过给一些强行配对和任意驱逐另一些，让物种要么减少，要么组合，要么改变，只为了迎合这个数字。不错，在所有其他数字中，正是美妙绝伦的数字“三”寄托了我无限悠长的情思和经久不衰的兴趣。[14]在目前正在排印、下一季即将出版的刊物中，有我一篇对这个数字的颂词，我通过无可辩驳的推理，不但在“三”的大旗下简化了论证的常规和原理，还从它的两大敌手“七”和“九”那儿带回来一些逃兵。

言归正传，我要说的演说器具的头一件，不论从地位还是尊严上，都非讲道坛莫属。在这个岛国有若干种讲道坛，而我只青睐用苏格兰古木制成的那种。它非常适合这里的气候。如果它快要腐朽，那么不但传声的效果更好，而且还有见于下文的诸多其他理由值得一提。至于形状和大小，我所喜爱的完美型是特别窄的那一种，没有过多的雕饰。最重要的是，它不带顶罩（从古代惯例看，这应该是在所有集会上正常使用的唯一一种不带顶罩的讲道坛）。也就是说，由于与示众的颈手枷颇为相似，它会对人的耳朵产生巨大的影响。

至于梯子我无需多言。外国人一看便知，它是我们国家的骄傲，我们对这种器械的理解比其他任何国家的人都更为深刻。登上梯子的演说家抓住听众的不仅有和风细雨，还有在早期发表的讲话[15]中述及的整个世界，在我看来那真是英语口才宝藏的精粹。为此，我听说那位名人兼书商约翰·丹顿所搜集的忠实而苦涩的集子即将出版。那是十二卷对开本，还带有铜版印刷插图。这书的用途非凡，令人称奇，而且行业价值也很高。

最后一件演说器具是巡回台。它的搭建充满智慧，sub Jove pluvio, in triviis et quadriviis.[16]而且它还是前面两件东西的枢纽，演说者时而青睐其中一个，时而又青睐另一个，视它们受瞩目的程度而定。三者之间有严格、永久的联系。

从以上严密的分析不难看出，为了在听众中引起注意，确实需要一个优越的位置。但是，尽管这一点已达成共识，但其缘由却说法不一。在我看来，没有几个哲人对此找到了真正的、合乎自然规律的答案。而我至今所见的最深刻，经过最充分思考的解释是：空气是浓重的物质，因此，根据伊壁鸠鲁[17]的理论，会不停地往下沉。而当空气中又加载了话语的重量之后，下沉就会更快。至于话语，鉴于它能给我们留下深刻印象，因而也是浓重的物质。因此它必须从一个高处发出，否则的话，它既不能很好地到达目的地，也不能充分发挥功能。

Corpoream quoque enim vocem constare fatendum est, Et sonitum, quoniam possunt impellere sensus.[18]

通过我平常的观察，我更乐于接受这一观点了。我曾多次观察到，在这些演说家的演讲集会上，所有听众都自然而然张大了嘴巴，仰头使之保持与地平线平行，并与从地心到天际的垂直线相交。有了这样一个姿势，加上如果所有听众挤得足够紧密，每个人在离开的时候就能把自己的所得全部带回家，少有或毫无遗落。

我承认，在今天剧院的设计和构思上，还有一些更为精致的东西。首先，正厅的座位区域是下凹的，比舞台低，正合乎我上面所作的分析推理。话语无论多么沉重，是铅还是金，都可以塞进一些批评者的嘴巴，我想他们也同样会自然地张着大嘴巴准备好了接受这饕餮盛宴。再有，包厢被设计成围绕正厅的圆形，高于舞台，为的是尊重那里的女士。因为她们在展现风韵和柔情方面的聪明才智，需要排成队欣赏，或者，围成圈自然更好。声色的妩媚，暗涌的狂想，通过她们轻浮的动作飘送至中间区域，然后被那里的人们用冷漠的理解定格或冻结。夸张的言辞，插科打诨，这些轻浮的话语自然飘得最高，最终将在屋顶消失。但是还好，幸亏那位有远见的设计师还为此设计了第四个位置，称为十二便士廊[19]。对于这里的人来说，那些话正合他们的口味，于是便贪婪地捕获它们。

然而，上述有关演说容器或接收器的半科学半逻辑学的推理还存在很可观的象征意义。它作为一个形态，一个象征，一个影像，一个符号，代表着作家这个大社团的共识，也就是他们必须通过这些途径使自己大大高于芸芸众生的凡俗世界。讲道坛夸夸其谈大英帝国现代圣贤的作品，仿佛是他们把常人的低级趣味和推理提纯并精神化了。其实质乃是前述的有关腐朽木头的问题。这有两方面原因，一是因为朽木的材质能照亮黑暗，[20]二是因为它的孔洞里充满蠕虫。[21]这就像一个有两个把柄的造型，很符合演说家所具备的两大基本素质。同时他的作品也有两种不同的命运。[22]

梯子是真实题材故事和诗歌的充分象征，一大批作家的出名都要归功于它们。说到真实题材故事，是因为……Hiatus in MS……[23]说到诗歌，是因为演说的人的确是通过歌声perorare[24]的，因为在慢慢向上攀爬的过程中，命运必将在他们距离顶级很远的时候就唾弃他们[25]，因为这是与财产优先权转移有关的问题，还因为这是混淆meum和tuum[26]的问题。

在巡回台的下面摆着的则是一些用于取悦普通人的书籍，包括“六便士智慧”“威斯敏斯特[27]趣谈”“趣闻杂谈”“笑话大全”等等。由此可见，文丐作家以及有关文丐的作品[28]在近年来与时间的战斗中终于大获全胜，并修剪它的翅膀，剪断它的指甲，打磨它的牙齿，翻转它的计时沙漏，磨钝它的钩刀[29]，还拔下它鞋上的钉子。我的这部新作也正要斗胆以此名义推出，因为我刚刚有幸获得成为这个杰出的兄弟会一员的殊荣。

殊不知，我并非不清楚近些年来文丐作品是如何因诸多偏见而衰落的，也并非不了解两个后来发起的社团是如何不遗余力地奚落文丐及其作品，把嘲笑他们在智慧和学识的圈子里与其所处的地位不符。他们自己的良心自然清楚我的所指，整个世界也不会是这般熟视无睹的旁观者，看不见格雷沙姆学会[30]和威尔咖啡屋[31]所作的努力，在我们的废墟上树立起的榜样和声望。但是当我们深思他们的行为，觉得既不正义，又不体面，且无责任心，又不合常理的时候，这对我们来说就是更为彻骨的悲哀，不论是在感情还是在道义方面都是如此。因为，世界和他们自己岂能忘记，更不消说我们自己是如何清楚详细地知道，这两个学术团体都是我们所栽培，我们所浇灌的？有人告诉我说，我们的两个对手最近联手提出了一比高下的倡议，并向我们发起挑战，想要从图书的重量和数量这两个方面比试一番。作为回应，我得到我们校长的许可，恭敬地提出两点意见：首先，我们说，这个提议本身就像阿基米德为一桩小事所提[32]的那样，没有实施的可能性。因为他们如何能找到有足够大刻度的衡器来比试第一方面，又如何能找到有足够计算能力的数学家来比试第二方面呢？其次，我们准备好了接受挑战，但前提是必须找一个与此无关的第三方，让他拿出不偏不倚的公平态度来判定每一本书、每篇论文和小册子最应属于哪个社团。这件事，上帝知道，目前还很难定下来。因为我们准备好做一个列有几千本书的目录，按理说，它们都应当冠以我们兄弟会的名字，但是反叛了的新派作家却背信弃义地提出其他名字。有鉴于此，我们觉得将决定权交由作者本人不大符合我们的审慎态度。我们的对手通过阴谋策划，造成我们的严重不和，我们中的许多人已逃向他们，而我们最亲近的朋友也开始独往独来，似乎不屑于与我们为伍。

我授权对这一无情的令人不快的话题所作的回应，仅此而已。由于我们极不情愿挑起这样一个如果持续下去必将会损害各方利益的事端，因而更希望友善地解决问题。我们将遵循我们的方针，只要这两个浪子回心转意，离开那些使他们沉迷的酒桌和娼妓——新近有迹象表明他们所研究的方向可能让他们沉迷于此——我们就张开双臂欢迎他们，并像娇惯他们的父母一样为他们祝福。

但是，我们社会的笔墨产品先前所得到的普遍关注（与尘世间一切短命的事物一样）存在的一个最大缺陷是当今在大部分读者身上的一条肤浅的静脉。这些人永远不可能透过事物的外表看清本质。这就好比说，智慧是一只狐狸，经过长时间的追猎，最终要靠发掘才能得到；智慧是一块干酪，越是浓缩的，就越密实、越家常、表皮越粗糙，而且，对于一个英明的盘子来说，有了蛆虫才越发好；智慧是牛乳加马德拉葡萄酒[33]，越是下面的越美味；智慧是一只母鸡，我们不能不关注它的叫声，因为那与鸡蛋有关；最后，智慧是一个坚果，需要你用智慧来辨别，否则它会崩掉你的牙齿，而你得到的却只是一条虫子。鉴于这些重要事实，文丐中的智者一直以来都倾向于将他们的知识和技艺用不同的文体或寓言包装起来，这与其说是真正的需要，不如说具有更多矫揉造作的成分。这样的运载工具，通常都是金碧辉煌的四轮马车，其表面的雕饰一时间让旁观者眼花缭乱，以至于无心关注或想象坐于其中的车主的情况。这是一个遗憾，尽管我们司空见惯。因为我们对待毕达哥拉斯[34]、伊索[35]、苏格拉底以及其他前辈的态度都是如此。

但是，应我的朋友们的一再请求，不让世界抑或我们自己继续受这种误解的困扰，我对我们社会最杰出的作品作了一次完整的、充满艰辛的专题旅行；它们除了具有用来取悦肤浅读者的美丽外表之外，深处还蕴藏着尚鲜为人知的所有科学艺术中最精致完美的东西。这是我十分愿意通过解扣或解索，通过汲取或解剖来展示的。

这个大部头是几年前开始动笔的，执笔人是我们中最为杰出的一员。他从《列那狐[36]的历史》着手，但遗憾的是，他既没有活着看到文章出版，也没有再继续这一如此有意义的研究。这实在令人惋惜，其实这是因为他所发现并与朋友交流的东西，如今已被广泛接受。我相信任何一位有识之士都毫不怀疑他的作品是人类知识的集大成之作，是我们国家所有奥秘的指南或启示录。但我的进度要快多了，已完成了几十部书的注释。我将从中挑选几条展示给公正的读者，以说明我的目的所在。

我着手的第一本书是《拇指先生》[37]，作者是毕达哥拉斯学派的哲学家，这部隐晦的著作讲到灵魂转世的整个轮回，[38]分析了各个阶段灵魂的演进过程。

其次是《浮士德博士》，由阿提庇乌斯[39]执笔。他是一位值得我们记住的博学之士，他在984岁的时候发表了这本书。这位作者的生命完全靠仙丹和通灵术维持，而浮士德和海伦[40]的婚姻则十分明显像公龙和母龙的躁动。

《惠廷顿和他的猫》[41]，作者是一位名为杰胡达·汉纳西的犹太学者。其中包含对耶路撒冷犹太教法典首卷的注释篇的辩护，以及对巴比伦的犹太教法典的注释篇的偏爱，这与平民百姓的观点是不一致的。

《乡下人和黑豹》[42]，这是一位在世的知名作家的代表作，旨在写一部完整的从斯科图斯[43]到贝拉明[44]一万六千名学者的简介。

《汤米·波茨》[45]，出自（据说是）同一作家的另一篇作品，作为附录补充于其中。

《愚人村的智者及附录》，这是一部极有教义的作品。它才思泉涌，对那些流传于英法等国家的现代社会知识和智慧提出正当的辩护，并抨击古代的假说、傲慢和无知。这位不知名的作者对此主题的分析之透彻，使有眼光的读者很容易感受到从此以后任何有关这一话题的争论都略显重复。最近，我们社会的一位精英人士发表了一篇有关这部书的摘要。

对于有见识的读者，以上介绍或许能让他对整个研究的结果有所了解或领略。目前我的心思和精力全都集中于此。如果在我临死之前能把这件事圆满完成，我就会认为一段不幸人生的有生之年总算没有虚度。不仅如此，实在说，这已超出我的奢望：从尽心服务国家而磨损的鹅毛笔，从对教皇制度的褒贬，从汤盆计划[46]、异己名单、被迫服从，从对生命和命运的问候、特权、财产、道德自由、给朋友的信，从被不断转变折磨得衰败不堪的理解力和理念，从一个被敌对派系无情摧残了一百多处的脑袋，从被痘疹折磨的身体（这些痘疹曾遭到鸨母和医生的恶治。而后来的事实证明他们是我和政府的公开敌人，为了他们的宗派争执而在我的鼻子和胫骨上实施报复）等等所有这一切中，我都不敢有上述奢望。在三朝统治期间我曾为三十六个派别写了九十一本小册子，但是当我发现国家再没有给我和我的笔墨以机会的时候，我很乐意退出，转而走更适合我的哲学家的路子。而让我感到心满意足的是，我度过的很长一段人生都是以不冒犯他人为准则的。

话说回来，读者的正直让我坚信，我所列出的简单书目可以轻松清除我们社会所有其他作品中显然由于嫉妒和无知所滋生出来的造谣中伤，说这些作品除了其中的机智和风格使它们具有一般的娱乐消遣功能以外，对人类别无他用。对此，我深信，迄今为止我们最精明的敌人也尚未提出过异议。我的这篇文章，在更深刻和更深奥的部分，都是紧紧因循了最受称道的原创作品。并且，在它全部完成之际，经过缜密考虑和构思，我完全采用在现今我们社会特有的方式为它冠名。之所以取这样的名字，是希望它进入宫廷以及市井的一般谈话。

坦白说，我看到一些我十分景仰的作家，追逐时尚，把书名搞得十分复杂有趣。而我自己在标题命名上则比较自由。不错，书作为头脑的孩子，也像其他可人的孩子一样，理应得到洗礼和五彩缤纷的命名。而我们大名鼎鼎的德莱顿[47]甚至走得更远，不遗余力地引进了一批教父。[48]显然，这是具有更多优点的一大进步。但遗憾的是，这一值得称道的创新没能得到很好的培育，时至今日尚未形成普遍效法的趋势。果真如此的话，这位权威定然是首开先河了。我的努力也没有跟随这一有益现象。但是我很清楚，请教父往往要付出令人难堪的代价。这虽然只是我的想象，我却有充分的理由相信这一点。因为让我无法搞清症结究竟在哪儿的是，在我用全世界的思想和痛苦把我的文章分成四十份，并请求四十位我熟识的精英为我赞助的时候，他们却都认为这是需要慎重考虑的问题，并婉言拒绝了我。

第二章

从前有一个男人，他有三个儿子[49]，全由他的妻子一胎所生，分不清谁排行第几，就连助产士也分不清。这位父亲将死的时候三个孩子年纪尚幼。他在临死前把他们叫到病榻前嘱咐说：

“孩子们，我没有置办过也未继承得什么不动产，所以我一直都在考虑给你们留下点什么有意义的东西。经过慎重的考虑，我花钱给你们每人置办了一件新外套，就在这儿。我要告诉你们，这外套有两大奇功，一是如果仔细穿着，它可以一直不破不旧，伴随你们终生，二是它们可以随着你们的身体一起长大，增长增宽，永远适合你们的身材。来吧，在我临死前让我看着你们把它穿在身上。喔，很好。记住，孩子们，要仔细穿着，还要经常刷洗，保持干净。在我的这份遗嘱里有如何穿着和保护这件外套的详细说明。你们必须严格遵守，以免受到我列出的每一项疏忽或违反条规的惩罚。所有这些都与你们未来的命运息息相关。我还要你们真正像亲兄弟那样共同生活在一个屋檐下，和睦相处。只有这样你们才会兴旺。”

故事讲到这里善良的父亲就死去了。三个儿子便一同开始追寻他们的未来。

恕我不和读者絮叨在这以后最初的七年当中他们三位都有哪些经历，唯一需要提及的就是他们都信守了父亲的遗言，把外套保管得非常妥善。他们周游了几个国家，遇到过几个巨人，还杀死了若干恶龙。

说话间他们都到了成家立业的年龄，于是都来到城里，和那里的女人们谈情说爱，其中他们最为中意的有三位女性，在当时都享有很高声誉。她们是女公爵、女郡主和女伯爵[50]。在和她们第一次见面的时候，我们这三位冒险家遭到了极大的冷遇。三人睿智的头脑马上就猜到了其中的缘由，于是通过学习这座城里的良好风尚，他们很快就有所改进。他们写书、集会、作诗、吟唱、交谈、不言不语。他们酗酒、斗殴、嫖娼、野宿、骂街、擤鼻涕。他们参加戏剧的首演，出没于巧克力屋[51]，殴打看守和警察，躺在货物上，获得喝彩。他们诈骗出租马车夫，拖欠店主的钱款，还睡他们的老婆。他们杀死镇长，把乐师从楼梯上踢下去，在财主家蹭饭，在赌场闲荡。他们谈论从未去过的沙龙，谈论与从未谋面的绅士一起进餐，装作与某公爵夫人耳语，其实一言未发；他们把洗衣女工随手写的字条说成高雅的情书；他们有意做出从豪门庭院走出的假象，其实从未进去过；他们在sub dio[52]受到皇室隆重接见；他们把一家公司的职员熟记于心，将其作为谈资在另一家公司高谈阔论。更主要的是，他们长期与那些在议院里沉默寡言却在咖啡屋里高谈阔论的议员团保持着接触，靠每天晚上拾人牙慧参与政见。他们还被一大群弟子包围着，争着抢他们的施舍。这三兄弟还学得另外四十项诸如此类的本领，毋庸一一赘述。其结果是他们成为城里最知名的才艺大师。但这仍然不够，上文提到的那三位女性还是对他们置之不理。要说清其中的原委，我须征得读者的原谅和耐心，且让我先说另一段重要故事，这是当时那位作家没有讲清楚的。

就在这一时期，出现了一个新派组织，其纲领声名远播，尤其是在上流社会的体面人中尽人皆知。这个组织崇拜一种偶像。这偶像，如其教义所言，通过一种制造工艺每天都能造出人来。他们将这偶像置于房屋的最高处，位于一个三英尺高的祭坛上，身姿与波斯皇帝十分相似，他坐在那里，双腿在身下交叉。此神的识别标记是一只鹅。[53]据此有学者推测，他的真身来自朱庇特神殿。在他的左面，祭坛的下方，地狱似乎正敞开着，以获取他创造出来的动物。为避免此种情况发生，他的几位牧师每隔一小时就将一些尚未被赋予生命的造物，或团块，有的甚至是已有生命的完整肢体扔进去，而那可怕的深渊立刻贪婪地将它们吞噬。这景象令人毛骨悚然，不忍目睹。那只鹅也位于稍逊一等的神圣所在，或称deus minorum gentium[54]。它前面摆放的祭品是一种每小时喝一次人血的动物。它在国外十分有名，据称是埃及猴科动物所喜爱的。每天有数以百万计的这种动物被宰杀，以满足此神的口腹之欲。那个偶像还被作为帆桁和针[55]的发明者加以崇拜，究竟是作为海员的守护神还是有什么其他神秘的名目，一直尚不十分清楚。

对此神的崇拜者还有其自身的一套信仰体系，所依据的基本原则如下：他们认为宇宙是一件大衣服，笼罩一切，认为地球被空气笼罩，空气被星星笼罩，星星被primum mobile[56]笼罩。看看我们地球上的世界，你就知道那是一件完整而时尚的衣服。那被称为大地的不就是一件绿色的精制上衣吗？那大海不就是它的丝光马甲吗？再看看万物的创造，你就会发现大自然的神工是如何雕饰恋爱中的植物的。再观察山毛榉的树冠是如何被漂亮的假发装饰的，白桦树又是如何穿上白缎子紧身上衣的。归根结底，人类自身何尝不是一件精巧的衣服，或带有各种装饰的完整套装呢？至于人的身体，那更是毋庸赘言，分析一下他们是如何获得思想的，你会发现他们全都是在按部就班地完成一件衣服。无需多言，难道宗教不是一件斗篷，诚实不是一双在泥土中磨破的鞋，自爱不是一件大衣，虚荣不是一件衬衫，良心不是一条裤子，虽然遮挡着淫荡和肮脏，却随时会因此种目的而滑落吗？

若这些postulata[57]都被承认的话，接下来我们就该分析那些被世人误称为套装的造物缘何成为真正最高等的动物了，或者，说得高雅一点，理性的动物，或人类。要说其中的原因，很明显，难道他们不是活的、会动的、会说话，还会从事其他一切与人有关的活动吗？美貌、智慧、风度和教养难道不是与他们密不可分吗？一句话，我们所看到、听到的都只有他们。难道不是他们在街道上行走，充斥于国会、咖啡屋、剧场和妓院？的确，这些被俗称为套装或衣服的动物，据一些文字记载，还有其他一些称谓。如果谁的服饰是一条金链，一件红色长袍，一根白棍，一匹骏马，那他就被尊称为市长大人。如果谁将貂皮或其他毛发装饰于某处，我们就称他为法官，如果谁能将纯亚麻衬里和黑缎子联系在一起，我们就称他为主教。

这一职位中的其他一些，主体虽然基本相同，但在一些细节方面更为精致。他们提出，人是综合了两套衣服的动物，其中的一套来自自然，另一套来自上天。也就是肉体和灵魂。灵魂是外在的衣服，肉体是内在的衣服。后者是ex traduce[58]，前者则是每天生成的外延。他们还通过经文对此予以证实，因为我们的存在、活动以及生命都发生于其中。此理同样可用哲学证实，因为他们所有人都在所有人之中，所有人也都在其个体之中。他们还说，如果将二者分开，将会发现肉体不过是一具没有知觉的令人厌恶的尸体。从各种征兆看，外在的衣服必定是灵魂。

这套宗教体系还有另外几条附属教义，令人津津乐道。特别是，人的思维也正是其中的佼佼者以此种方式演绎而成。刺绣是纯粹的智慧，镶金边是和谐的谈话，金饰带是巧妙的应答，蓬松的长假发是幽默，沾满粉末的外套是善意的玩笑——实现所有这些都需要足够的谋略和精妙的技巧，需要有远见的安排，以及严格遵循时代风尚的要求。[59]

以上对哲学和神学之精髓的扼要总结，是我付出大量心血、阅读和汇集古代作家思想的成果；所采用的似乎是一种与从古到今任何其他血肉体系都截然不同的思维模式，而所为并非仅仅取悦或满足读者的好奇；乃是为了令其对故事下文的来龙去脉了然于心，并了解在那久远的过去人们的处世态度和观点，这样才能更清晰地认识那时人们的所作所为。因此，我建议读者用极大的专注反复细读我的此番叙述。现在我且放下这一话题，仔细收拢故事的主要线索继续讲述。

鉴于上述观点的普遍流行，以及在宫廷和城市的所有高雅场所都奉为行动的准则，我们这三位冒险家在如此处境中有些不知所措了。因为，一方面他们所看中的那三位女士，我们前面已经提到过她们的名字，永远都处于时尚的最前沿，憎恶所有不及她们的人，认为他们一钱不值。另一方面，他们父亲的遗嘱又说得非常清楚，只要遗嘱上找不到支持或肯定的，不得在衣服上增加或更改一丝一毫，否则将受到严厉的惩罚。再看看父亲所留给他们的衣服，真乃是上好的布料精心缝制而成。其精细程度让人绝看不出任何缝合的痕迹。但同时它又十分简朴，几乎没有任何装饰。就这样，在他们来到城里还不到一个月的时候，肩章出现了——简直满世界都是肩章——没有佩戴肩章就休想走近三位女士的ruelles[60]。“那个人没有灵魂，”人们会惊呼，“他的肩章在哪儿？”三位兄弟很快就从痛苦的经历中发现了他们的迫切需要。走在大街上横遭他人四十次的轻蔑羞辱；如果他们去戏院，看门人就会把他们带到十二便士区；如果叫渡船，船夫会对他们说：“我坐在前面。”[61]如果他们去酒吧，店员会大叫：“伙计，我们这儿不卖麦芽酒。”如果去见一位女士，在门口接待他们的男仆会说：“请留言。”身处如此尴尬的境地，他们连忙求助于父亲的遗嘱。他们一遍又一遍地细读，却始终找不到任何有关肩章的内容。究竟该怎么办？何去何从？——服从是必须的，但肩章似乎也非常必要。经过长时间的考虑，三兄弟中较为有学问的一个说，他想到了一个折中办法。确实，他说，遗嘱中没有提到肩章，totidem verbis[62]没提肩章。但是他推测其中包含类似的意思，或totidem syllabis[63]。这一解释立即得到其他二人的赞同。于是他们又开始在遗嘱中寻找。但是也许是晦气使然，整个遗嘱中连第一个音节也没有找到。沮丧之余，最初提议的那位兄弟又鼓起勇气说：“兄弟们，就算我们在totidem verbis和totidem syllabis都没有找到，但是还有希望。我敢保证，我们用tertio modo[64]，也就是totidem literis[65]一定能够找到。”他的这番话又得到另外二人的赞许。于是三人开始了新一轮的仔细寻找，果然很快就找到了S，H，O，U，L，D，E，R这几个字母[66]。但是有意和他们作对的晦气再次从中作梗，他们竟然找不到K[67]。这可把三人难坏了。但是那位挑头的兄弟（从现在起我们该给他取个名字了）又有主意了。他说字母K是一个新近出现的不合法的字母。讲究学问的时代都不用这个字母，古代文献中就更没有了。固然，他说，单词Calendae[68]在Q.V.C.[69]有人在书写时会用K开头，但那是错误的。在更为规范的正式文件里它都是以C开头的。因此可以说，在我们的语言里让“肩章”的“章”带有K这个字母是一大错误。因而从现在开始他会注意把所有的“章”字都拼写成以C开头。到此，所有的问题都迎刃而解——肩章明明白白是jure paterno[70]。于是我们这三位先生都戴上了最大最炫的肩章。但是，人的满足感持续的时间总是有限的，在那个追逐时尚的年代自然也不例外。肩章在风行了一段时间过后，我们必须承认它开始落伍了。因为从巴黎来了一位先生，衣服上装饰着五十码长的金饰带，完全符合当下月份的正宗宫廷时尚。于是两天后社交场上出现的所有男人身上都被金饰带包裹了起来。任何敢于不佩戴金饰带就出门的人都遭人厌弃，自然也不会受到女士的青睐。在如此严峻的情势下，我的三位骑士又当如何呢？他们在肩章的问题上已经有一个污点了，而在求助遗嘱这件事上，除altum silentium[71]以外什么也没有出现。但肩章毕竟是一个模糊的、轻微的、不确定的污点。而这金饰带则十分明显是一个未经允许的改动，aliquo modo essentiae adhaerere[72]。因此需要得到明文规定的支持。但是此时的那位上文提到的有学识的兄弟读了Aristotelis dialectica[73]，尤其是读了de interpretatione[74]精彩部分，教导读者要从某一事物以外的一切事物中寻找这一事物的意义。这就如同演说《启示录》的讲解员，对其文字内容虽然一窍不通却仍然可以成为先知。兄弟们，他说，要知道遗嘱是duo sunt genera[75]，口头的和书面的。不错，我们面前的遗嘱手稿上虽然没有提到金饰带，也没有与之有关的规定，但是si idem affirmetur de nuncupatorio, negatur[76]。还记得吗，兄弟们，在我们还小的时候，有一个人曾经说过，他听到爸爸的朋友说，他如果知道他的孩子在任何时候能得到足够的钱买金饰带的话，他一定会支持他们买。哦，上帝！另一个兄弟大叫起来，千真万确！的确是这样，第三个也随声附和，我记得清清楚楚。于是他们轻松得到了教区里最大的金饰带，行走起来的绅士风范大为光艳。

这样的时尚生活过了没几天，一种火红的绸缎衬里又出现了。布店老板很快就把衬里的样式送到三位绅士面前。尊敬的阁下，他说，我的康威殿下和约翰·瓦尔特先生都在昨天晚上用同样的布料做了衬里，明天早上十点以前我就能做好，剩余的布料连给我夫人做一个针垫都不够。于是三人又开始翻看遗嘱，因为眼下的事情依然需要得到认可。在正统作家笔下，衬里是外套的主体。他们找了很久也没有找到任何与此有关的现成文字，只找到几句父亲要他们注意防火的忠告，还告诫他们在入睡前要熄灭蜡烛[77]。这些内容，尽管目的明确，也非不言自明，但从整体上看还不具有构成命令的分量。因此，这位有学识的兄弟说，为避免更多的踌躇，并不让难堪的局面再度出现，我记得还曾见过带有附录的遗嘱，附录肯定是遗嘱的一部分，与之具有同等效力。现在我考虑我们面前的这份遗嘱，因为还缺少一个附件，所以尚不完整。因此我要在合适的位置巧妙地把它加上——对此我早有考虑——那本是我们祖父的看门人所写。谢天谢地，其中他讲了很多有关这种高雅颜色绸缎衬里的内容。这番话立即得到其余二人的赞同。于是按照遗嘱附件的技术要求，一卷老羊皮纸被附在了遗嘱上。绸缎衬里也就顺理成章地做上了。

次年冬天，镶边缝纫商协会雇用了一个演员，为的是上演一出新喜剧。他身上的衣服到处都镶着银边。自然，由于当地的良好传统，这很快就成为了时尚。这三个兄弟又开始在遗嘱中搜寻。而出乎他们意料的是，他们居然找到这样一段文字：我严格要求我的三个儿子不得在他们的所述外套上镶银边……违者将受到处罚。至于处罚的内容，因为过长恕我从略。一阵沉默之后，那位我们已经几次提到的博学的兄弟又发话了，他说自己很擅长批评，曾发现有一位不知姓名的作家提到，那份遗嘱里的“镶边”一词实际上还可以解释为“扫帚”。因此他提出，显然需要对这段文字增加注释予以澄清。对此兄弟中的一个却表示不赞同，因为按照语言的规范，“银”这个词在与之搭配的“扫帚”释义下无法正常理解。但得到的回答是，应该从神话和寓言的意义上来理解这个词。可他仍旧不同意，进而还解释了父亲禁止他们穿带有镶边衣服的原因——是担心这样显得不自然、莽撞。但不等他说完，那位兄弟就反唇相讥，指责他对神话出言不逊。毫无疑问，神话是非常有用和重要的，不应对其吹毛求疵或刨根问底。总之，此时父亲的权威已大打折扣。这一折中办法再次成为任凭他们把衣服镶满银边的合理依据。

过了一阵，一个古老的、沉寂多年的时尚又复活了，那就是印度妇女儿童的肖像刺绣。三兄弟都清楚记得，父亲一直都非常讨厌这一时尚。为此他在遗嘱里写了好几条，以强调他对刺绣的极端厌恶，以及他对自己儿子们违反此条规定的强烈诅咒。尽管如此，三个儿子的外套上还是不出几天就夸张地展现出了这一时尚。他们的理由是，刺绣的图案已和当年或父亲遗嘱所指的大不一样。此外，他们也并非在父亲严令禁止的意义上穿着它。因为刺绣是好的传统，对公众有巨大的好处，所以对遗嘱中的这些强硬条款显然需要作一些于我有利的解释，应该cum grano-salis[78]地理解。

由于在那个时代，时尚不断更替，这三兄弟厌烦了为层出不穷的破例不断找借口。于是他们下决心：哪怕冒再大的风险也还是要顺应潮流，三人经过商议，一致决定将父亲的遗嘱锁进一个结实的小盒子，带出希腊或意大利（究竟是哪一个记不清了），不再为研读它而劳神费心，只在他们认为适当的场合才提一下父亲的权威。结果没过多久又出现一种带有无数小斑点的衣服式样。其中的大部分点是银色的。对于这些斑点，有学者声称，ex cathedra[79]。而他们应该清楚记得，那完全是jure paterno[80]。确实，这一时尚所显示的比遗嘱中直接提到的内容更多一些。但是作为父亲的共同继承人，他们有权为公众利益，totidem verbis[81]，增加若干条款，哪怕这并不能从遗嘱的字面意思推导出来，否则multa absurda sequerentur[82]。有了这一规矩，在下一礼拜日他们来到教堂时，外套上都布满了小斑点。

我们上文多次提到的那位博学的兄弟，在整条街以及邻近的街道上成为首屈一指的学者，以后发制人闻名于世，并得到某位大人物[83]的垂青，还受邀到他家做客，并成为他孩子们的老师。在那位大人物死后，他正是靠一贯严守父亲遗嘱的做法，通过转让将其财产过户到自己及后代的名下。在他占有的领地上，他让乡绅靠边站，并让自己的两位兄弟接替了他们。

第三章　题外的话：关于批评家

尽管到目前为止我在任何情况下都尽可能仔细地、最大限度地效法我们时代杰出样板所倡导的写作规范和方法，但是记忆上的缺陷还是让我犯了一个错误。这着实令人不快，需要立即纠正，然后我才能继续故事的主要情节。我要为我们的好先生——批评家——说几句话，并对他们提出忠告、祝福和恳求。很惭愧，我承认，在我尚未交代这样一个必要情节之前就说了许多，真是个不可原谅的疏忽。为弥补这一点，恕我斗胆地先从我们通常所理解的这个词的由来和渊源入手对他们的人品和技艺作一简单综述，然后再粗略概括一下他们的过去和现状。

关于在今天的日常谈话中如此频繁出现的批评家一词，依我阅读古代书籍和文献的记载，有时分指三类各不相同的人。首先，它可解释为给世界或他们自己的发明提出规矩的人。这样一来，细心的读者就能对学者的作品有独到的见解，并对真正高雅、绝妙的精品形成自己的品位，还能欣赏每一种文体或风格之美，并将其与破坏美的败笔区分开来。在他们平常的阅读中，他们发现那些错误和缺陷，那些令人厌恶的、做作的、枯燥的和不相干的东西的谨慎态度，就像一个清晨走在爱丁堡大街上的行人，时时警惕处处小心沿路的脏东西。这倒不是因为他对那些污物的颜色或外观有什么特别的好奇，更不消说翻弄或把玩，而只是希望自己在走过去之后能尽量保持干净。看来这类人的态度尽管十分错误，还是从字面上理解批评家的，认为他们工作的主要内容就是赞扬和推卸责任，那些决心在鸡蛋里面挑骨头的批评家是像决心绞死一切前来受审之人的法官一样残忍的人。

其次，批评家还指修补家，他们保护古代经典不受虫蛀、污损和尘土的侵扰。

如今这两类批评家都早已见不到了。因此我也无须再为他们浪费口舌。

第三类最为高尚的批评家可称为“真正的批评家”，其渊源也尤为古老。任何一个真正的批评家都是天生的英豪，直接来自莫摩斯[84]和海布里斯的高贵谱系。他们生了佐伊勒斯，他生了泰格利乌斯，他生了大某某；他生了本特利、赖默、沃顿、佩罗尔特和丹尼斯；[85]他生了小某某。

而这一类批评家才是让我们的联邦有史以来获益无比巨大的一类，以至于出于对他们的感激和景仰我们把他们说成来自上天，与赫克勒斯[86]、特修斯[87]和珀尔修斯[88]等等这些人类伟大的观察者齐名。但是历史功勋再大也无法阻挡居心叵测之人的诋毁。因为有人提出，这些古代英雄虽因与许多巨人、恶龙和强盗交战而声名显赫，但是对人类来说他们本身都是比那些被他们杀掉的怪物更可怕的人。因此，为了他们的功德更加圆满，当所有怪物都被消灭以后，他们应该对自己也实施同样的裁决。正如赫克勒斯的大度而为，[89]给自己赢得了比他最好的同伴更多的神庙和景仰者。因此我猜想，许多人会认为，真正的批评家应该在自己的任务完成的那一刻，马上用鼠药或麻绳自裁，或从某个适当的高度跳下，这样才更符合公众认知方面的要求，而任何针对如此伟大的光辉形象所提出的指摘，都必然在其动作尚未完成之前就烟消云散了。

现在，从这种源自上天的批评及其名副其实的英雄壮举中，我们不难发现真正的古代批评家的具体作为。那就是，在知识的世界里徜徉，为猎取或发现其中蕴含的巨大的错误，像从山洞中揪出卡科斯[90]一样昭示其不为人知的谬误；像描述海德拉[91]的头一样夸张地演示它们，像把奥吉亚斯[92]的牛粪耙拢一样一个不落地收集它们；或者像驱赶某个心怀叵测的危险飞禽一样，它像贪吃树上的果子的斯廷法罗斯鸟[93]，正企图从知识之树上抢夺最好的树枝。

以上分析将有助于我们对真正的批评家给出适当的定义。他们发现并收集作家的错误，这进一步准确无误地反映出，任何人如果查看所有那些古代批评家让世界荣耀的作品，都会立即从作品的线索和要旨中发现，作者们的观点相差无几，并且都犯有作家曾犯过的疏忽、混淆、遗漏之类的错误。再有，不论作品所谈论的主题如何，其想象力具有且充斥着其他作品的缺陷，以至于其中最不好的东西也渗入他们自己的作品。这样一来，整部作品简直就像是他们给自己提出的批评意见。

在按照最崇高的、世所公认的意义大致讲完批评家的出身和作为以后，接下来我要反驳一些人的不同观点。他们以作者的沉默和默认为反驳理由，伪称批评家如今所采用的艺术手法，以及我这里所说的，都是现代的事情。因而大英帝国和法国的批评家并不具备我所描述的那般光荣的历史出身。那么，如果我可以澄清，我要说恰恰相反，正是古代作家所描述的真正批评家的人品和职业操守，与我所给出的定义十分吻合，那些人提出的作家沉默的严厉反驳，也站不住脚。

坦白说，对这一普遍的错误在很长时间以来我负有一部分责任，对此如果不通过我们高尚的现代人的帮助，我就永远不能推卸责任。为改善我的思想和国家的利益，我不分昼夜地刻苦研读他们的颇有教益的作品，通过不懈的努力，我作了很多关于古人薄弱方面的有益研究，最后得到一张完整列表。而且它无疑表明，其中所展现的古代精华都是由后来的作家发现并揭示的。[94]此外，那些古代作品所揭示的最了不起的发现，不论是艺术还是自然方面的，全系现代人超验的智慧发现。这些都清楚表明，古人值得称道的美德十分有限，对于那些待在角落里苦于与现代事物交流太少的人们来说，他们所表现出的对古人的盲目崇拜也可以休矣。充分考虑这些因素，以及人性的各个方面，我很容易就得出这样的结论：这些古人非常清楚他们的诸多不足之处，因而必定会在他们作品的某些段落里，努力通过讽刺或歌颂真正的批评家来消除、软化或转移读者挑剔的锋芒，而采用的方法就是模仿他们的大师——现代人。鉴于讽刺与歌颂都很常见，而我通过长期有效地研究前言和序言得到了很多有关的说法。于是我毅然决定通过细细研读最古老的作家，尤其是那些反映最远古时代的作家，来看看我究竟能从这两者的对比中发现些什么。这十分出乎我的意料，尽管他们都曾偶然有过作为真正批评家的特别论述，却总是受到恐惧或希望的左右，在涉及这方面话题的时候他们都十分小心谨慎，不敢超出神学和象形文字[95]的范畴。[96]我认为，正是这一点给了肤浅的读者以口实，要求作者对古代真正的批评家保持沉默。尽管错综复杂，为之分类却是十分必要和自然的，很难想象任何具有现代眼光和趣味的读者会忽略它们。因此我将从汪洋大海中找出几个实例，我深信，它们一定能无可争议地澄清这一问题。

很值得关注的一点是，在谈论这一高深莫测的话题时，那些古代作家都专注于类似的象形文字，只是出于爱好和智慧将其改编为不同故事。首先，保萨尼阿斯[97]的观点是，正确的写作完全归功于批评家制度。我认为，他的意思不外乎以下对真正批评家的描述。他说，他们属于喜欢撕咬书中多余部分和赘生物的那类人，学者经过长时间研究这些书，从自己的角度发出警告说，要从书中剪除多余的、腐烂的、僵死的、枯萎的、畸形的枝桠。而他的这番睿智之见却源自以下寓言故事：阿戈斯[98]的纳夫普里亚人[99]看到一株被驴[100]撕咬过的葡萄藤生长得更好，结出了更多的果实，从而学会了给葡萄藤剪枝。而希罗多德[101]对同样的象形文字，却说出更直白的语言，几乎是in terminis[102]。他是如此大胆，竟然把批评家归于无知和邪恶之属。公然用我认为不能再直白的语言对我们说，在莱比亚[103]西部有一种有犄角的驴；对于此一说，克特西亚斯[104]也添枝加叶，说印度也有同样的动物。他还说，由于其他所有的驴都没有胆汁，而这种有多余胆汁的家驴肉特别苦，不能食用。[105]看来古代作家不用直白的语言探讨这一话题的原因，是由于他们不敢公开将矛头指向如此强大、可怕的批评家。他们的声音是如此令人生畏，令所有的作家一听到连手中的笔都会掉落在地。于是希罗多德从作家的角度向我们讲述，锡西厄人[106]的一支人马众多的军队是如何在听到一只叛逆的驴叫声后在惊慌和恐惧中投入战斗的。从那以后，一些有深刻思想的语言学者便推断说，英国作家对于批评家的恐惧是来自于我们对锡西厄人祖先的恐惧。简而言之，这种恐惧是如此之广泛，以至于随着时间的推移，那些有心在描述若干时代的批评家时更自由公开自己观点的作家，都因感到以前的象形文字过于接近其真实原型而不得不放弃对它们的讨论，进而想出另外一些更审慎、更模糊的替代话题。出于同样的原因，狄奥多罗斯[107]也不敢多言，只说在埃利孔[108]的山里有一种奇特的野草，它发出一种危险的气味，会毒死敢于嗅它的人。而卢克莱修[109]也给出完全相同的描述：Est etiam in magnis Heliconis montibus arbos, Floris odore hominem tetro consueta necare.[110]

但是我们上文提到的克特西亚斯却比其他人更勇敢，他和与自己同时代的批评家相处惯了，因此很希望在身后留下至少一个他向这整个行当复仇的深刻印记。他的用意是如此昭然若揭，我简直弄不懂那些否认古代真正批评家的人是如何将其忽略了的。因为，假借描写印度的许多奇特动物，他写下如下深刻的文字：他说，有这样一种蛇，它同其他蛇一样没有牙，因此不能咬。但是它特别爱呕吐，它的呕吐物不论落到什么东西上，那东西都会立刻腐烂变质。这种蛇多见于出产钻石的深山，它们还时不时地排出毒液，任何人沾上这种毒液，大脑就会从鼻孔飞走。

古人中还有一类批评家，从分类上说难以与前者分开。但是从成长和成熟度上说，他们似乎是生手，或初学者。而正是由于他们职业上的这一区别，他们经常被认为自成一类。这些年轻学生的主要业务是经常去剧场，学习如何找出剧目的最糟糕之处，并将其记录下来，然后向老师作详细分析。就这样，他们像小狐狸一样在小范围的运动中成长起来，最后变得敏捷而强悍，能捕捉到大猎物。不论古代人还是现代人都承认，真正的批评家有个特点，与妓女和市政参议员都一样，那就是不会改变称号或本性。而年老的批评家自然也是从年轻时候过来的，他们的至善和成就也无非是年轻时就具有的才干的提高。就像大麻，尽管能收获麻籽，但有自然学者告诉我们，它不是好东西，会使人窒息。我对这种创作很欣赏，或至少我很喜欢它才思敏捷的前言，这要归功于那些年轻的从业者们，泰伦提乌斯[111]曾以malevoli[112]为题一再赞扬了他们。

毫无疑问，真正的批评家制度对于学问方面的联邦是绝对必要的。因为人类的行当各有不同，就像地米斯托克利[113]和拥戴他的人，有的会拉小提琴，有的可以把一个小镇变成一座大城市。而这也不会、那也不会的人理应被踢出人类的行列。无疑，为避免这种处罚，第一批批评家就此诞生了。同时还出现了暗中诋毁他们的声音，说真正的批评家不过是个技工，为了自己的行当，像裁缝一样凑集了一堆廉价的材料和工具。还说批评家和裁缝在工具和才干方面确实有可比性，裁缝的痛苦就是批评家一本平庸的书的铅字，其智慧和学识是靠熨斗来展示的。并说，造就一个学者需要多少批评家，造就一个人就需要多少裁缝。他们还说批评家和裁缝都同样大胆，他们使用的工具也基本上是一样的尺寸等等。对于这样的不实之词可以有多种回敬。我可以首先肯定它是一种污蔑。恰恰相反，要想和批评家脱离干系所付出的代价，比和你所能想到的其他任何人脱离干系都高，这是不争的事实。就好比作为一个真正的乞丐，有钱的候选人们施舍的每一个银币都是他的价值，而在真正成为批评家之前，却要花费一个人思想中的所有好品质。对于吃亏的交易来说，这可以说是无心议价。

在用了如此长的篇幅求证批评的历史，及其原始状态之后，我要分析一下这个领域的现状，并展示它和它古老的过去是多么一致。有一位作家，他的作品在很多年前就全部失传了。他在书的第五卷第八章提到了批评家，说他们的作品就是学识的镜子。这句话，我按照字面的理解，作者的意思肯定是，不论谁要想成为完美的作家，必须注意看批评家的书，以它为鉴修改自己的作品，就像照镜子一样。现在无论谁只要想到古代的镜子是黄铜制成的，并且sine mercurio[114]，就会立刻将其适用现代真正批评家的两大品质，并且必然得出结论说，它们一直是，并且必将永远都是不变的。即黄铜是持久的象征，并且，在它表面经过一定的抛光处理之后，就可以反映出前面的物体，而无需在其背面涂抹水银。批评家的所有其他本领无须一一提及，因为它们都包含于这两大品质之中，或可以归结于此。但是我要总结三句格言，它们即可作为现代真正批评家与假批评家区分的标志，也将大有裨益于那些致力于这一有用而光荣的事业的杰出人士。

第一点是，与其他所有才学相反，如果批评意见在批评家的头脑中是第一时间形成的，它就被认为是最真实的和最好的。这就像捕鸟者总认为第一个目标最有把握一样，如果他不再找下一个的话，通常都会拿下第一个目标。

第二点是，真正的批评家具有游走于最杰出的作家之间的智慧，他们作出选择所依赖的是直觉。这就像老鼠寻找奶酪，或黄蜂寻找最好的果子。当国王骑在马背上的时候，他必然是这支军队中最肮脏的人，而那些向他献殷勤的人则是玷污他最甚的人。[115]

最后，真正的批评家在研读一本书的时候，就像一只在宴会上的狗，它的思想和肠胃都取决于客人丢下的东西。因此总是在骨头最少的时候才叫得最欢。

说到这里，我想向我的赞助人——真正的批评家——的致意可以告一段落了。并且这也可以弥补我先前对他们的沉默。也许我以后还将继续沉默下去。我认为我很值得他们作为整体将我玩弄于股掌之间。在他们的期待中，我将大胆继续我的前文已经欣然开头了的冒险故事。

第四章　“澡盆故事”

至此，我所有的努力和研究已将作为读者的你带到一个你一定听说过的大革命时期。上文多次提到的那位博学的兄弟自己得到了一所温暖的房子，于是他马上就对你趾高气扬了起来。除非好心的读者用你那高尚的襟怀坦诚赞许一番他的想法，否则我担心从此以后你即使遇见他也不知道他就是故事的主角。他的角色、他的服饰以及他的态度都发生了巨大的改变。

他告诉他的两个弟兄，他希望他们知道，他是大哥，因此也就是父亲的唯一继承人。不仅如此，没过多久他就不许他们叫他哥哥了，而要叫他彼得先生。过了一阵他又要求他们称他彼得老人，再后来又要他们称他为彼得老爷。为了使这一伟大的称号名副其实，他很快又考虑到，如果不能找到一个比自己目前出身更好的背景，这个称号就难以维持。于是经过深思熟虑，他终于设法向策划兼艺术大师的方向发展，并在这方面大获成功，世上的许多具有现代时尚和现实用途的著名革新、窍门、机械等都完全归功于彼得老爷的发明。我将从这些发明中挑选最主要的几项加以描述，并不过多涉及它们的形成过程。因为我认为发明家们在这方面尚未达成一致。

我希望，如果我的这部作品被翻译成外语（我可以毫不夸张地说，我收集材料的艰辛，叙述的真实可靠，以及所谈问题对于公众的巨大效益，都将证明这是值得的），那么若干国外科学院的值得尊敬的院士，特别是法国和意大利的，就会欣然接受拙文所提供的普遍知识。我还要特别敬告那些最值得尊敬的师父们，也就是东方的僧侣。正是为了他们的缘故，我所使用的词汇和短语都极为适合翻译成任何一种东方语言，尤其是汉语。因此我在写作的过程中一想到整个世界或许都因为我的劳动而收获良多，就感到非常惬意。

彼得想到的第一个任务是购买据说是最近才在terra australis incognita[116]发现的一片陆地。他从发现者（尽管有些人怀疑他们是否真的去过那里）手上买过来这样一大片土地，价格非常合算。然后将它分成若干个州转手卖给一些经销商。他们打算往那里殖民，带了很多人前往，结果船在航行中遇难。于是彼得又把这片大陆卖给其他客户，就这样一次又一次地转卖，每次都获得同样的成功。

我要提的第二项任务是他至高无上的治疗虫子的方法，尤其是那些在脾脏内的虫子。[117]接连三个晚上，病人吃完晚饭后就不得再吃任何东西，只要他上床睡觉，就要小心地向一面侧身，当他感到累了要换到另一侧时，他必须同时把双眼限制在同一个对象上，没有明显的时机就绝不能两端一起放气。只要认真按照这个处方去做，虫子就会不知不觉地通过汗液排出，经由大脑升空。

他的第三个发明是建立一所耳语室[118]，为的是公众利益以及消除忧郁症或疝气之类的困扰。它同样也有益于所有窃听者、医师、助产士、小政客、反目成仇的朋友、念念有词的诗人、快乐或绝望的情人、鸨母、国王的私人顾问、侍从官、寄生虫和弄臣。简而言之一句话，它有益于所有充满太多的气不能不放的人。一头驴子的头被放置于十分方便的位置，以至于另一方可以很随意地让嘴和它的任意一只耳朵搭话：离耳朵要近，仅留少许空间，这样就能借助这畜生耳朵所特有的飘忽不定的能力，通过打嗝、呼气或呕吐收到直接的效果了。

彼得另一个非常有益的项目是为各种烟斗、现代狂热的殉道者、诗集、影子……以及河流办理保险。[119]保护所有这些都不会受到火灾的侵害。对此我们友好的社会可能很容易发现自己只不过是这些原文的誊写员，尽管对于行为人来说，两者中不论哪一个都对他十分有益，而且对公众也如此。

彼得还获得了木偶和西洋镜原作者的身份。由于其巨大的实用价值已众所周知，我就不再多说了。

他的另一项非常了不起的发明，就是那著名的万能泡菜[120]。他明确提出，家庭主妇们的日常泡菜除了给死肉和某些蔬菜保鲜以外，没有更多的用途。而他所研发的高投入、高技术含量的泡菜则可以用来保鲜房子、花园、城镇、男人、女人、孩子，还有牛。而且保鲜的效果就如同琥珀中的昆虫一般完美。目前这种工艺制成的泡菜在味道、气味和形象上，和家常的黄油、牛肉和鲱鱼没有什么区别，并且经常非常成功地得到应用。而要说它那些了不起的优点，那可就完全不一样了。彼得只需加入少许魔力粉，就会百分之百获得成功。这项活动要在月亮升起的适当时间通过喷撒实施。而腌制的对象，如果是一所房子，那它就绝对不会再受任何蜘蛛、老鼠、黄鼬的骚扰；如果是一只狗，那它就再无疥癣、狂犬病和饥饿之忧了。此工艺还曾百试不爽地用于去除孩子身上的疮痂、虱子和头癣，并且绝不妨碍对象正在做的任何事情，无论是在床上还是在台上。

但是，在彼得所有的珍稀物品中，他最得意的还是一组公牛。其种群是那些看守金羊毛[121]的动物的直系后裔，得以非常幸运地被他保存了下来。尽管有人曾假装好奇地观察这些牛，进而对其品种的绝对纯洁性提出质疑，认为它们在一些方面与其祖先相比已经有所退化，而在另一些方面又因和其他品种杂交而变得有所不同。据记载，科尔喀斯Colchis[122]公牛的四蹄是黄铜的，但这是否由于野蛮的放牧和经营，或由于其他父母种系的混入而产生了变异，或由于密谋私通，或由于其祖先高贵的精液细胞曾在某种程度上受损，或由于在如此漫长的时间过程中必然产生的退化，而造成最初的原始本然在后来罪恶的世界里堕落了，这些都不得而知。总之，不论原因究竟如何，彼得那些公牛的金属蹄子确实随时间的侵蚀而严重退化，现在变成了铅的。但是，属于它们血脉特有的可怕的咆哮却完好地保留了下来，包括能从鼻孔喷火的本领。这一点，尽管连它们的许多反对者都承认这是它们超群之处，其实也没有看上去那么邪乎可怕。那只不过是由于它们的日常进食使然——爆竹和烟花。然而，他们却有两个独特的标志，使它们极其明显地不同于一般公牛，而且，我还从没有见到过任何对其他动物的描述像贺拉斯[123]这样把它们相提并论的：

Varias inducere plumas；[124]

和

Atrum desinat in piscem.[125]

就是这种有鱼尾巴的公牛，偶尔也能像鸟一样在空中飞翔。彼得给它们派了几个用场。有时他会用它们吓唬淘气的男孩，让他们安静下来。有时他也会派给它们十分重要的差事。这说起来极其令人兴奋（但谨慎的读者恐怕不一定相信），也就是从它们高贵的祖先金羊毛的守卫士那里演化出整个家族的敏感的口味。他们一如既往地贪恋黄金，如果彼得把它们送出国，哪怕只得到一个小小的赞美，它们也会立即咆哮、吐痰、打嗝、撒尿、放屁、喷出着火的鼻涕，并且一直不停地转圈，直到你赏给它们一块金子。但是在得到魔力粉后，他们就变得像羊羔一样十分安静。总之，不管是通过主人私下默许或鼓励，还是自己贪图黄金的本性，还是两者兼有之，它们其实并不比彪悍、放肆的乞丐强多少。如果它们得不到施舍，就会让女人流产，让孩子抽风。时至今日，这些人还常常把精灵和妖怪称作牛乞丐[126]。它们最后变得非常麻烦，扰得四邻不安，以至于西北部的一些绅士豢养的正宗英国斗牛犬[127]一直袭击它们，直到今天还能感觉到。

我还不能不提彼得的另一个非凡的项目，从中可以看出他的确是具有高深造诣的发明大师。当纽盖特监狱[128]的某位犯人被判处绞刑后，彼得就会以一定数额的金钱作为交换条件，提出为他减刑。这位可怜的罪犯想尽办法变卖家当凑足的钱，换来的是彼得老爷写有如下内容的一张纸条——

“各位市长、行政长官、狱卒、警员、法警、死刑犯人等，我们得知，判处死刑的某某仍在你们或你们中某人的手中。我们责成并命令你们，见字后立即让此人回到他自己的居所，不论他是因谋杀、鸡奸、强奸、乱伦、亵渎圣物、叛国、渎职等何种罪名获罪。你们仅凭此字条即可确保安然无事。倘若你们不照此办理，就让你们和你们的来世见……去吧。此致，衷心地与你们告别。

你的最卑微的

人上人，

皇帝彼得”

那些相信他花言巧语的可怜人，不但失去了生命，还耗尽了所有钱财。

我希望从后人的佼佼者中挑选出有资格对这篇精心打造的文章评头论足的人，能细细品味其中的某些隐语。他们中所有没被vere adepti[129]的人都可能有草率下结论的危险，尤其是一些离奇神秘的段落中的arcana[130]，为简洁起见被合到了一起。因而在品评过程中需要划分。而且我确信，艺术界未来的子孙们将对我这一如此有益的innuendo[131]无比感激。

不用我多说，读者一定很清楚，世上很多有价值的发明都取得了巨大的成功，尽管我在此正当提出的仅为其中极少的一部分。因为我的初衷是，只介绍那些最有利于公众效法的发明，或是最能展现发明家的奇思妙想和智慧的发明。因此，如果此时彼得已成为超级富豪，我们并没有必要感到惊讶。但是，可惜！由于他的大脑如此长时间地过度运转，他的精神终于出现了恍惚和分裂的症状，继而开始错乱。简而言之，由于性情高傲、专注事业和无赖作风，可怜的彼得变得越来越离谱，竟然开始想象世界上最离奇古怪的事情。在他犯病的高峰期，他和那些通常因为高傲而变得疯狂的人一样，竟然称自己为全能的上帝，有时还自称为宇宙的霸主。我曾见过他（我的作者说）戴着三顶旧皇冠高帽，三顶帽子一个摞一个巍峨地戴在他头上，[132]腰带上挂着巨大的一串钥匙，手里还拿着一根钓鱼竿。在这种装扮下，如果任何人出于礼貌上前去拉他的手，他都会十分优雅地，像一只受过良好教育的狗一样，把脚伸给他们。如果他们拒绝他的这种礼貌，他就会把脚抬起到他们裤腰的高度，然后对准他们的嘴巴踢上该死的一脚。从此以后这种礼节就被称为敬礼。无论谁走过他面前如果不发出由衷的赞美，都会被他那强有力的呼吸把帽子吹掉，落到污泥里。与此同时他的家里全乱套了，他的两个兄弟的日子也不好过。他的第一桩boutade[133]是在一天早上将他们的妻子踢出门外，连他自己的太太也不例外。然后他们叫人到大街上把最先碰到的三个在街头表演的女人带回来，取而代之。过了一段时间，他又把地窖的门给封了，不给他的兄弟们一点吃喝。有一天，彼得在城里一位地方官的家中做客，聆听了他模仿其同侪的口吻，对他的牛腰肉进行的称赞。“牛肉，”这位大人说，“是肉中之王，其中包含鹧鸪、鹌鹑、鹿肉、野鸡、李子布丁和奶油的精华。”彼得回到家中以后，感到很有必要看一看他自己的学说，按其所默认的牛腰肉烹饪出来，再添加到他的黑面包里是何种效果。“面包，”他说，“亲爱的兄弟，是生命的支柱，其中含有牛肉、羊肉、小牛肉、鹿肉、鹧鸪、葡萄干布丁和奶油的精华。为完成这一切的混合，需要一定量的水，与起软化作用的酵母或曲子混合在一起，形成一种健康的发酵液，并渗入到面包的肌体内。”在得到如此确定的结论以后，第二天晚餐时城市宴会的所有礼节性主餐就都是一道黑面包了。“来，兄弟们，”彼得说，“吃吧，不要客气；这是上好的羊肉，要么等一下，让我来，我来帮你们。”他一面这样说着一面舞弄刀叉做出一系列庄严的仪式动作，切下两片高贵的面包，并各放到一个盘子里递给他的两个弟兄。这两兄弟中较年长[134]的一个，也不是第一次领教彼得的这套把戏了，便用很谦恭的语言评价这一神圣赠物。“我的老爷，”他说，“我觉得你这一高贵的赠与行为可能有一个错误。”——“哦，”彼得说，“看你高兴的样子，说吧，就让我们听听是什么可喜的事情让你合不拢嘴。”——“那倒不是，我的老爷。只是，除非我受骗了，不然的话，阁下，您刚才欣然脱口而出有关羊肉的词语，想必不会让我全心全意的寻找落空吧。”——“怎么，”彼得诧异道，“这我就完全不懂了。”这时弟弟赶忙插话纠正说：“我的老爷，我哥哥八成是饿坏了，所以急切地盼望看到阁下曾经许诺我们的羊肉。”——“祷告吧，”彼得说，“请让我和你一起，你们要么拿出要么装出比我所赞成的更多的快乐，如果你们不喜欢自己的那一块，我可以另外再给你们切一块，我认为这就是一整块前腿肉。”——“那么，我的老爷，”第一个发话的兄弟问道，“难道在你看来这始终是羊的前腿肉？”——“祷告吧，先生，”彼得说，“吃你的饭吧，不要无礼，如果你不介意的话。我现在还不想再给它添加作料。”但是另一个兄弟被彼得所表现出的一脸严肃所激怒，有点按捺不住了：“上……，我的老爷，”他说，“我只能说，通过我的眼睛所见、手指所触、牙齿所咬、鼻子所闻，它不过是一片干面包而已。”这时另一个兄弟也插话说：“我这辈子还从来没见过这样像十二便士面包的一块羊肉哩。”——“看看你们，二位先生，”彼得愤怒地叫道，“为了让你俩知道你们不过是两只瞎眼的、十足的、无知的、任性的小狗，我只好使用如下证据了：我对上……发誓，这是伦敦肉类市场所能见到的真正的、上好的、天然的羊肉；上……诅咒你们这两个永远不相信这一切的家伙。”这铁一般的证据一出，当然再没有任何反驳的余地了。慌乱中那两个反对者竭力支吾并掩盖他们的错误。“是啊，当然，”第一个说：“经过更深入的考虑……”——“嗯，”另一个打断他说，“现在我感到这东西好多了。老爷确实有充分的理由说服我们。”——“很好，”彼得说，“来，孩子，给我的酒杯里斟满波尔多红酒，我全心全意地敬你俩一杯。”这两个弟兄，高兴地看到他怒气全消，便回以他们最诚挚的谢意，说他们很乐意维护他的主人地位。“那是当然的，”彼得说，“我并不是一个不讲理的人。我不会拒绝你们所言中任何合理的部分。葡萄酒，如果饮用适度，就是兴奋剂，也给你俩一人一杯；这是真正的从葡萄中提取的天然原汁，并非由你们所诅咒的葡萄酒商所酿造。”说到这里，他又递给他俩每人一大块黑面包，并命令他们喝掉，且不必担心，因为它对他们不会有丝毫伤害。这两兄弟，在完成了在这种微妙场合通常需要做的一套仪式动作以后，久久地看着彼得并相互对视，琢磨着事态将如何发展。但他们最后还是决定不再挑起新一轮的争端。由他爱怎么说就怎么说吧，他现在多半正处于疯病的巅峰期，辩论和规劝只会让他更加不可理喻。

我之所以把这段故事原原本本地讲出来，是因为它作为主要原因引发了一场重大的、世人瞩目的分裂。分裂在这三弟兄之间大约同时发生，而且从此以后再没有和好过。但是对于这一点我将在另一章中讲述。

然而，可以肯定的是，彼得老爷即使在他神智十分清醒的时候，在一般谈话中也总是很露骨地表现出极度的任性和不容分说，而且永远都是宁死不承认自己有丝毫错误。此外，他还有一项可怕的本领，就是在任何场合撒弥天大谎，不仅如此，他还发毒誓说这都是真的，并诅咒在场所有哪怕是装出对他有一丝怀疑的人下地狱。有一次他发誓说，他家里有一头牛，在吃了一顿草料之后挤出的牛奶填满了三千座教堂；更为不可思议的是，这些牛奶永远不会坏。还有一次他谈论起一根属于他父亲的旧路标，说它上面的钉子和木料足够建造十六条战船。有一天他又谈起一种中国货车，说它轻得可以在群山上乘风破浪航行，“上……，”彼得说，“这有何奇妙？我向上……发誓，我还曾看到过一个用石灰和石头建造的大房子在海洋和陆地上游走（假定它时而也要停下来吃东西），飞越了两千多德国里格的距离。”再有就是那最精彩的部分了，他总是一边讲述一边百般发誓说，他自有生以来从不说谎，一个字也没有说过。“我向上……发誓，先生们，我告诉你们的都是事实；见……吧，我永远诅咒那些不相信我的人。”

无需多言，彼得因此而臭名昭著，周围邻居都坦言他是个不折不扣的无赖。而他的两个兄弟也早已厌烦了处处受他的不公平待遇，终于决定离开他。但是首先他们谦恭地向他提出期望得到父亲那份久违了的遗嘱。而他非但没有满足他们的请求，反而骂他们是婊子养的、强盗、叛徒等等，用尽了一切能够想到的难听字眼。然而有一天他在国外推广他的项目的时候，这两兄弟看到了时机，于是回来找到了遗嘱，通过copia vera[135]他们这才发现自己上当受骗有多严重。父亲在遗嘱里说他们三人是平等的继承人，并严格规定，不管他们谁得到什么都应该三人平分。照此办理，他们的下一行动就是砸开地窖的门，品尝美酒，提提精神并安抚内心的伤痛。在抄写遗嘱的过程中他们又发现禁止淫乱、离婚和分居的规定。于是他们休掉了小妾，找回了自己原配的妻子。就在这一切还没有停当的时候，从纽盖特监狱来了一位律师，问彼得老爷是否愿意为一个明天即将上绞架的死刑犯减刑。这两兄弟回答他说，他竟然找一个本身更应该被绞死的人为将被绞死的人减刑，真是太荒唐了。同时他们也了解了我上文刚刚交代的他的种种骗术。他们建议这位律师去找国王看看能否为朋友减刑。正在这闹哄哄的当儿，哈！彼得回来了，身后还跟着一哨人马。他集中起所有家丁，骂出数不清的脏话和诅咒，毋庸一一赘述。并以压倒性优势将这弟兄二人踢出了家门，从此以后不许他们再靠近他的屋檐半步。

第五章　关于现代人的题外话

我们，这些被世界誉为现代作家的人，所付出的努力如果不能大有裨益于全人类的福祉，那就永远不可能实现流芳百世、名垂青史的梦想。这，哦万物，就是你的仆人——我——的远大理想！

Quemvis perferre laborem

Suadet, et inducit noctes vigilare serenas.[136]

正是出于这样的目的，我才耗费了如此多心血和精力，在人的躯体上通过解剖发现其内在本质，并阅读了大量有关各种器官的有益书籍，包括内在和外在的器官，直到尸体的气味让我再也无法继续保存它。通过如此巨大的付出，我终于完全了解了每根骨头的精确位置和形态，因此很乐于在这里为所有对此感兴趣的先生和其他人展示完整的解剖图。但是在这个本来属于题外话的章节中，我不能离题太远。因为我知道有些作家把题外话包装在另一个题外话里，使之像一个扑朔迷离的魔盒。我只简单说明一点，通过对人类本质的深入剖析，我有了一个全新的、重要的、奇特的发现。那就是，造福人类有两种途径：教育和消遣。在刚才我提到的那些材料中（世人或许有一天会看到它，如果它的魅力大到足以让我的某位朋友想去偷一本，或让某位我景仰的先生急不可耐地想一睹为快的话），我已经进一步证实，人类现今倾向于从消遣中获得大大多于教育的益处。他们的通病是大惊小怪、没有正形、哈欠连天。在当今无所不包的智慧和学识的汪洋大海中，教育似乎已没有多大余地了。但是在我的那本对于伟大时代极具权威性的教材中，我已成功将教育全面拔高，而且，这一杰作从头至尾都在十分艺术地把这两个层面糅合在一起，一层是有用的，另一层是dulce[137]。

当我想到：我们五光十色的现代人已经大大掩盖了古代人的微弱光芒，把他们排斥在所有时尚的商业活动之外，这还不算，我们的那些卓越的城市精英竟然还对古人是否曾经存在的问题产生严重分歧，而对此我们可以从杰出的现代人本特利[138]博士有益的劳动和呕心沥血的著作中得到十分满意的答案，当我想到所有这一切的时候，我不禁深深感到，没有哪个著名的现代人曾尝试过在一本体积小巧的便携书里写出如此无所不包的庞大体系。它包括所有已知的，或人们相信或想象的，或在生活中实践过的事情。但是我必须承认，这样的奇迹不久前曾被一位伟大的巴西哲学家想到过。他提出的方法是，通过某种神秘程序获取一个秘方，这是他英年早逝之后我在他遗留下的文件里发现的。在这里，出于我对现代学人的深厚感情，我向他们展示这一秘方。毫无疑问，有朝一日它将启发某位有才华的实践者。

在所有的现代艺术与科学作品中，你根据自己的喜好任意挑选出用小牛皮做书脊、封底印有文字的精美书籍，不论它是由哪一种你喜欢的文字写成，你把它们in balneo Mariae[139]进行提炼，注入Q.S.[140]的罂粟精华，用从药剂师那里得到的三品脱忘川[141]的水混合，并仔细清理掉其中的sordes[142]和caput mortuum[143]，让其中所有不稳定的成分挥发掉，你只保留第一道萃取物，然后再将其蒸馏十七次，直到剩下约两特拉姆[144]的重量。你把它装在一个小玻璃瓶里，密封好，搁置二十一天。这时你就可以开始写你的天主教专著了。每天早晨在你空腹时，先摇晃小瓶，摇出三滴仙液，用鼻子将其猛烈吸入。十四分钟之内，它就会在大脑（如果有的话）里溶解。这时你的脑海中就会立即浮现出无数的摘要、介绍、提纲、精粹、全集、节录，excerpta quaedams[145]，florilegias[146]等等。而且全都井然有序地从你的笔端涌出，有条不紊地落到纸上。

我必须承认，正是有了这一秘方的帮助，尽管impar[147]，我却可以冒险尝试一件连某位名为荷马[148]的作家都未曾实现甚至尝试过的如此大胆的事情。尽管他本不是个没有能力的人，且对于一位古人来说，也还算有几分天资，我却发现了他的许多错误，这使我不能原谅他的骨灰，如果他还有任何骨灰留下来的话。因为尽管我们很清楚他的作品所涉及的是一个包括人、神、政治乃至机械力学的完整的知识体系，但是很显然，他完全忽视了一些方面，而在其他方面也极其不完美。首先，作为一个他的门徒所称的杰出的秘法家，他的opus magnum[149]极度的贫乏和蹩脚，他似乎只肤浅地读过森迪沃格斯[150]、贝曼[151]或《灵智魔学》[152]，而他对sphaera pyroplastica[153]也有很多错误理解，以致造成无法挽回的疏忽。如果读者同意这一严厉的谴责，vix crederem autorem hunc unquam audivisse ignis vocem[154]。在机械方面，他也有不少同样明显的错误。因为，我曾带着现代智者常有的最真诚的实践精神阅读他的作品，却丝毫也无法弄清那件有用工具的结构，也就是一个节约装置。为了它，若没有现代人的帮助，我们可能至今仍然在黑暗中摸索。但我还有一个比这更加尖锐百倍的问题要诘问这位作者，我是说他对这一领域的一般法则，以及英格兰教会的原则和纪律的极度无知。他的这一缺点确实使他，以及所有古人都成为我了不起的朋友沃顿[155]先生正当的严厉谴责的对象，这位神学学士[156]的无与伦比的题为“古代与现代的学识”的论文无论是在其轻松的格调、泉涌的才思，还是作者对这一吞云吐雾的飞行物用途的伟大发现，抑或在其矫情的口才风格方面，都从来没有得到足够的重视。因此，当我笔下的这篇文章行文至此，我深深有感于它给予我的巨大帮助和启发，因而我情不自禁地要公开表达对这位作家的敬意和谢忱，以彰显对他的公正待遇。

但除了上文提到的这些荷马的疏漏以外，好奇的读者一定还会在这位作家的作品中发现其他一些并非完全由他负责的缺陷。因为从他所处的时代到现在，尤其是在最近三年或三年左右的时间里，每一知识领域都得到了如此长足的发展进步，因而他的构想已不可能像他的鼓吹者所宣称的那样，是非常完美的现代发明了。我们轻易地承认是他发明了指南针、火药和血液循环。但是我敢向他的仰慕者发起挑战，在他的所有作品中找出关于这类行为动机的完整说明：难道不是他放任我们自己去寻找政治博弈的艺术？还有什么比他有关茶经的长篇大论更蹩脚和难以令人满意？至于他的被后来人追捧的无须借助汞的唾液分泌法[157]，依我的知识和经验看来，更是极不可信的。

正是为了弥补这样一些重大缺陷，我才在朋友长久的劝说下被说服，拿起了笔。并且我敢保证，明智的读者在这里绝对找不到任何可以在人生紧急关头使用却被忽略的东西。我相信我已经囊括和穷尽了人类想象力所有可能上及和下达的所在。特别是，我推荐的这一研读学者著述的发明是所有其他人全然不曾想到的。对此，我只需在无数事例中略提一件，那就是，我帮助一知半解的人们学习的新方法，此法亦可称为“深学浅读法”，一个有关捕鼠器的新新发明；一个通用的推理规则，或按每个人的自身条件，再加上一个动力强劲的捕捉猫头鹰的机器。所有这些，聪明的读者一看便知，都是我在这本书的若干部分中着力论述的。

我认为，对于我正在写作的这篇文章的美妙和高明之处，我已极尽彰显之能事，因为在这个讲究礼貌和学识的时代，作者倾向于纠正居心不良的批评者或彬彬有礼的无知读者，已成为一种最受称道的时尚与幽默。此外，近来还有几篇著名的作品见诸文坛，有诗歌，也有散文。其中，如果作者对大众的深厚情感和伟大人性不能使他产生愉悦，从而对作品内在的崇高和神圣进行很好的细致描写，那么我们能在其中发现庄严和神圣丝毫踪迹的可能性，就只有千分之一。[158]拿我自己来说，我不否认，不管我在这里说了什么，它都更为适合放在前言里说，并且更适合采用通常用于前言的写作风格。但是我认为能得到那无比尊贵的最后的作家殊荣也很惬意：作为最新一代的现代人，我主张我绝对的权利。而我的后来人的身份给了我对所有前人专制的权利。正因为有了这一权利，我极不赞成并坚决反对那种把前言当作一本书的节目单的惯常做法。因为我一直认为，对于大投机商和其他有奇思妙想的零售商来说，以下的做法是极为轻率的：在门口挂一幅所售商品的大图片，下面加上雄辩的解说词：这节省了我多达三个便士的金钱。这样的招牌让我的好奇心得到了彻底的满足，因此我根本无心再走进店去，虽然我还常常会听到那位演说家般的促销店员最后的时断时续的演说词：先生，我敢保证，我们这就开始。这就是现代前言、书信、广告、简介、绪论乃至器具给读者的最真实的感受。这种技巧在最初曾经十分吸引人。我们伟大的德莱顿把它用到了极致，并取得了令人难以置信的成功。他时常信心十足地对我说，如果不是他如此经常地在前言里向读者保证他是这个世界上如此伟大的一位诗人，读者很可能会怀疑甚至忘掉这一点。这也许是对的吧，但是，我更担心他的教育偏离了方向。他似乎在教人在某些方面变得更聪明，却从未真正打算他们这样。因为看到当今许多和我们年龄相仿的热心读者，翻看前言和献辞（是很常见的现代简洁版）就像看拉丁文，看了四五十页就厌烦了，懒得再往下看。尽管另一方面，必须承认，已知有很大一部分人继而成为批评家或智者都是只看前言不看其余部分的。这使我认为可以公平地将读者分为两类。现在，对我自己来说，我自认为属于前一类。因此，我用现代人的眼光来分析我自己的作品之美，并展示其中的亮点。我认为最好的办法是在正文中展示，正如我现在所作的。因为这样可以给我们的文章十分可观地增加篇幅，这一点是任何一位娴熟的作家都绝对不会忽视的。

在对我们最新作家所形成的习惯表达了我的一番敬意和谢忱，并通过并非刻意而为的长长的题外话，通过无缘无故地非难一切，并通过良苦用心和机智的语言，拿出对自己极大的公正和对他人极大的诚实揭示了我的优点和其他人的缺陷之后，现在我非常乐意继续我的主要话题，以最大限度地让读者和作者都感到满意。

第六章　无稽之谈

前文说过，彼得老爷与他的两个弟兄分道扬镳，把他们赶出了家门。从此他们重又回到了广阔的世界，且对世间的一切都不敢相信了。这些情况倒是恰好给作家的写作增添了合适的素材，对于伟大的冒险家来说，悲惨的境遇总能带来最大的收获。世人也能从中感知慷慨的作者与普通的朋友在素养上的差异。一般认为，普通朋友只能同富贵，不能共患难。而慷慨的作者就不一样了，他善于在粪土中发现英雄，并从这里逐步将他扶上王位，然后就戛然而止了；对自己的一番苦心并不期待多少回报和感谢。而这正是我要模仿的范例，我已将彼得老爷赋予一个高贵身份，并给了他相应的称号和足够他享用的金钱。现在我把有关他的话题暂且放一放，因为常人所具有的慈悲之心让我不能不帮他落难中的两兄弟一把。当然，我也绝不会忘记我作为历史学家的天职，脚踏实地地追寻着真理，无论发生什么事情，也无论它将带我走向何方。

且说这一对被命运和志趣紧紧联系在一起的落魄兄弟，总算找到了一个住处一起住下。在那里他们第一次有了空闲时间。于是他们开始反思自己充满无数不幸和烦恼的过去，一时间对自己究竟做错了什么百思不得其解。无奈中他们忽然想起父亲的遗嘱，谢天谢地，他们总算重新得到了遗嘱的正本。于是他们立即将它拿了出来，并庄严决定，改正所有违反遗嘱的错误，并在今后的行动中严格按照规定的要求办事。遗嘱的主体（读者应该不至于忘记）是有关他们穿着那件外套的引人入胜的规则。通过仔细核对，两兄弟把每一个时期的实践活动与规定的条文逐一比较，发现还从来没有见过比它们之间差别更大的两种事物，在遗嘱的每一点上都有可怕的、彻底的违反。于是他们立即一致决定，按照父亲的遗嘱把衣服改回原样。

但是，对于那些迫不及待想知道故事结局的急性子读者来说，我有必要打断他们一下，以便让我们作家作一些适当的铺垫。我要说的是，此时这两兄弟的身份也今非昔比，并且有了各自的名分。其中一个给自己取名马丁，另一个取名杰克。这两人曾在他们的兄弟彼得的威压下一度十分友好，因为对于同病相怜两人来说，这是明智之举。厄运当头的人如同处身于黑暗之中，对所有的颜色都分辨不清，但当他们重新回到世界上，开始在光明中相互展示自己的时候，他们所从事活动的现状突然让他们发现，他们有着非常不同的处世态度。

说到这里，严肃的读者可能会指责我作为一个作家记忆力太差。而一个真正的现代人又是丝毫不会受制于这样的缺点的。因为记忆力作为思想对过去事物的存储，是一种对于我们这个辉煌时代的学者来说全然不发生效力的能力。他们只和发明创造打交道，所有的事情都是他们自己想出来的或互相讨论出来的。正由于此，我们非常合理地认为，拿我们伟大的健忘症作为论点，是难以染指我们伟大的智慧的。我应该是在此手稿的大约五十页前，就得体地向读者提到了一个了不起的彼得，带动了他的两兄弟，在外套添加了所有那些时尚的零碎儿，即使过时了以后他们也没有拆除其中任何一样。也就是说，所有增加的东西都依旧在衣服上保留着。可想而知，它成了你所能想象的最离奇古怪的大杂烩。这样说吧，在他们分手的时候，衣服原来的样子可以说一丝一毫都难以看到了，能看到的只有无数的花边、丝带、镶嵌、刺绣和斑点。我的意思是那些银点，因为其余的斑点都脱落了。还算幸运，这件已经在某个角落里被忘却了很久的衣服，被这两兄弟找到了。在他们决心按父亲的遗愿把它改回原样的时候，它就是上述的样子。

他们二人不约而同地开始了这项伟大的工作。他们时而看看外套，时而看看遗嘱。马丁先下手了。他把衣服抖一下，就有许多银点纷纷落下。接着他又抓了一把，一下就拉下来近10码长的花边。这个时候他犹豫了：他很清楚地知道仍然有大量的工作要做。然而，当最初的热度过后，他的情绪开始冷却。于是他决定采用较温和的方法继续其余的大量工作。他小心地撕下那一个个银点，以免把衣料撕破。上文我们曾经提到，这些银点含有银的成分，缝缀它们的工人也很聪明，采用了双线密缝，以防脱落。下一步马丁决定拆除外套上大量的金花边，他对每一个针脚的处理更加谨慎，并且还把所有的碎线头也都清理干净，这花费了很长时间。接下来，他开始拆除那些刺绣的印度男人、女人和孩子的图案。看官应该还记得，这些都是他们的父亲在遗嘱上明确提出强烈反对的。拆除它们不但需要精细的手法，而且需要极度的耐心。他拆了好一阵，才把其中的一部分完全拆干净，另外一些只是从表面上看不到了。还有一些绣得非常密实，拆起来非常麻烦，很难在不损伤衣料的情况下完全拆干净。此外，还有的刺绣原本就是用于掩盖或修补外套上面的瑕疵的，绣工与衣料已成为一体。于是他决定，对于这些还是以保持原样为好，以免衣服的原始布料受到任何损伤。他认为，只有这样才是对父亲遗嘱的真正目的和用意最好的遵从。以上就是我对马丁所实施的这场伟大革命的尽我所能的描述。

然而，他的兄弟杰克所经历的冒险故事却非常奇特，使我们不得不用剩余的大部分篇幅来描述。对于同样一件事情，他采取的却是完全不同的态度和策略。他对彼得给他的伤害一直记忆犹新，并耿耿于怀。这给他带来的刺激和冲动，大大胜过对父亲任何命令的遵从，因为对于前者来说，后者至多也只不过处于次要和服从的地位。不仅如此，他还给自己这种复杂的心态取了一个似是而非的名字，名曰热情。这或许在所有语言中都是一个意义非凡的词。关于这一点，我想在我对热情所作的一番历史-神学-逻辑学的精辟阐述和分析中已得到充分证明。其中我展示了它是如何先从一个概念发展为一个词，又如何在一个炎热的夏天成熟，从而成为一种有形的物质。这部巨著有对开本三大卷，我已决定马上出版，并采用现代社会常用的从订阅人身上赚钱的方式，而不必怀疑这块宝地上的贵族和上流社会人士所给予我的所有可能的鼓励，因为现在他们对我可能有何种作为已经领略一二了。

且说这位杰克兄弟，在这种复杂心态的驱使下，满怀愤懑地思量着如何对彼得的暴行实施报复，而马丁的软弱妥协又加剧了他的愤怒，于是他下定决心。“这个无赖，”他说，“把吃喝锁起来，把我们的妻子赶跑，骗走我们的钱财，给我们可恶的面包屑充当羊肉，最后还把我们踢出家门；这个恶棍，我们必须以眼还眼，以牙还牙！这还不算，大街小巷里人人都反对他。”就这样，他自我调动情绪，让怒火膨胀到最高点。其结果是，头脑中微妙的改革冲动促使他决定立即着手行动，他用三分钟所做的事情大大超过马丁数小时的作为。因为，好心的看官，你一定能理解，热情一旦达到狂热的程度就有几分失去理智了；而这个时候的杰克正处于这种状态，而且已达到极致。于是就出现了这样的情况：由于他在撕去一堆金丝带时动作过猛，他把整个外套从上到下撕成了两半。而做针线活又不是他的长项，因此他除了将撕开的外套用粗线绳和串肉扦子连缀起来，也没有其他更好的方法。然而无穷无尽的麻烦接踵而至（我是含着眼泪记录这一实情的），当他开始拆刺绣的时候，由于天生笨手笨脚、脾气急躁，又看到数以百万计的针脚需要极度的精细和耐心才能拆除，他一气之下把整个刺绣连同它附着的布料一起撕了下来，并把它扔进狗窝，并疯狂地继续撕扯：“啊，好兄弟马丁，”他一边撕扯一边说，“为了对上帝的爱，学着我一样做吧，撕、扯、拉、剥，一切的一切，这样我们就和那恶棍彼得彻底不一样了。哪怕给我一百英镑，我也不愿意在身上留下一丝一毫可能引起邻人怀疑我与这样一个恶棍有相似之处的证据。”但是，这时候的马丁却非常冷静和镇定。他请求他的兄弟，为了所有的爱，不要对他的外套实施任何伤害，因为他永远不可能再得到另一件同样的外套了。还提醒他说，他们所做的这件事与他们对彼得的任何成见无关，仅仅是为了遵守父亲在遗嘱中的规定。他应该记得，无论彼得犯了什么样的错误，造成多大的伤害，他毕竟是他们的兄弟。为了报复，就一味采取冤冤相报的方法反对他，这种想法要不得，应该努力克服。的确，他们的好父亲所作的有关他们穿着此外套的规定非常明确，但是其中对他们三人之间的和睦、友好、互助和情谊方面也有同样严格的规定。因此，假如得理不饶人本来不可取的话，为加强团结并化解矛盾而为之，那就更不可取了。

如此这般，马丁用开头那种严肃认真的口吻继续说教，所言势必构成一场令人难忘的道德讲座，给我的读者的身心带来巨大的教益，而这也正是伦理的终极目标。但是此时此刻的杰克却早已因不耐烦而不知去向了。在学术争执中，作为学者在提出质疑时应有的淡定，还从未引发过如此强烈的反感。在很多情况下，争执就像一个不平衡的天平，总是重的一边压倒轻的一边，并使之抬高、受迫。当下所发生的情况正是如此，马丁所言之重压倒了杰克之轻，迫使他逃之夭夭，以表示对手足兄弟的反感。总之，马丁的耐心把杰克激怒了。然而，真正让他倍受煎熬的还是眼下自己兄弟的外套这般完好无损，并恢复到了以前的清白状态；而他自己的这件，不但破得使里面的衬衫显露无遗，而且在那些未受到他猛烈撕扯的部位，依旧保留着他兄弟彼得留下的烙印。现在他看起来就像一个饱受欺凌的醉汉，一个因拒绝交出诈骗款而新近被投入纽盖特监狱的犯人，一个当场被抓住又被柜台女郎高抬贵手放走的商店扒手，一个穿着旧天鹅绒裙子任由势利之手摆布的鸨母。不管像其中哪一个，还是所有的都像，这个满身烂布条、破花边和大窟窿的可怜的杰克如果现在看到自己的外套还和马丁的一样，他一定会非常高兴，但是，如果他看到马丁的外套和自己的一样，他一定会更加倍地高兴。然而，鉴于这两种情况都不大可能发生，他感到需要另辟蹊径，文过饰非。于是他努力（按他自己的说法或用意）收集狡黠的辩词，用以说服马丁回心转意，让他把自己也搞成衣衫褴褛、破烂不堪的样子，并承认自己前面所说的那番话都是无稽之谈。在尽一切努力作好这些准备以后，可惜！孤立无援的杰克所能做的仍不过是用无数粗俗的语言攻击和谩骂他的兄弟，抓狂、语无伦次。总而言之，这两兄弟之间产生了巨大的分歧。杰克立即另外找了新居所，没过几天就传来确切消息说，他的智慧已经耗尽。此后不久他又出现在国外，表现出病态大脑所能呈现的最离奇古怪的胡思乱想症状，进一步证实了上述消息。

现在，在街上遇到他的小男孩们开始用多个名字称呼他。有时称他秃头杰克，有时称他打灯笼的杰克，有时称他荷兰杰克，有时称他法国老休，有时称他乞丐汤姆，有时称他北方敲门的杰克。正是这些名称中的一个或几个或全部，由聪明的读者去取舍，催生了伊奥利亚[159]最杰出的也是流行的教派。时至今日，这里的人们仍对这位著名的杰克充满景仰与怀念，将他尊为他们的始祖和创始人。至此我已将此人的来历和为人十分详细地介绍了一番，以满足世人的好奇。

——Melleo contingens cuncta lepore.[160]

第七章　关于题外话的题外话

我经常听到用三言两语概括的《伊利亚特》[161]，但对我来说幸运的是，我更经常看到《伊利亚特》中的三言两语。毫无疑问，人生从这两者中都能得到极大的裨益。但是，世界究竟更应该感谢其中哪一个，我想把这作为一个值得深入探究的问题留给对此感兴趣的人们。对于后者的发明，我认为学术界应主要感谢现代人对题外话的改进：对知识的后期精加工类似于对我们国人口味的精加工。而这种口味，对于味觉极佳的人来说，是经过各种复合材料调配的，呈现于开胃汤、杂烩菜、浓汁肉丁和蔬菜炖肉中。

事实上，生活不很富裕的人，不免感到一种压抑的困扰，声称十分讨厌这种礼节性的发明；对于饮食口味一说，他们倒是也赞成这样的类比，却大胆提出，这一实例本身是对品味的莫大玷污和诋毁。他们告诫我们说，将五十种调料混杂一处加入菜肴的时尚，最初的形成就是为了迎合一种邪恶、堕落的口腹之欲，也是为了一种疯狂的体质：如果看到一个人吃完鹅、野鸭或者山鹬的头部和脑髓之后拼命找什锦菜，说明他想得到能对付更海量饮食的胃和消化力。他们还进一步肯定，题外话对于一本书来说就如同一支外国军队来到一个大谈国民需要拥有自己的心和手的国度，往往要么征服当地人，要么把当地人驱逐到最贫瘠的角落。

然而，这些傲慢的抨击者所反对的一切表明，如果把写书的人限制在致命的除了直奔主题其他一概不能写的框框里，那作家群体的数量将很快减少到极其微不足道的数目。应该承认，如果我们目前的处境与希腊、罗马人相同，在学识尚处于摇篮之中，需要扶持和培育，并被冠以创新美名的时期，那么写出大部头的真实故事乃是比较容易的事情，无需偏离主题而言他，借此渲染或深化主题。但是知识的滋长就像一支驻扎在一个富裕国家的数量庞大的军队的成长，开头几天尚可以由自己所在土地的产品供养，一旦给养耗尽，他们势必要到远方去寻找食物。至于从朋友还是敌人那里寻找，也就不重要了。与此同时，邻近的田野被践踏和蹂躏，变得贫瘠干燥，除了暴土扬沙，不再出产粮食。

可见，我们的经历已和我们的先辈完全不同，聪明的现代人对此看得很清楚。我们这个时代的人发明了一套成为学者或智者的更为快捷和可靠的方法，无需经受读书和思考之苦。目前使用图书最有效的方式有二，可任选其一。第一种方法是将它们视为议员，记住其头衔和名号，然后就可以吹嘘与之相识了。相比之下，第二种方法其实更可取、更有价值，且更文雅，那就是仔细阅读索引部分。因为它是整本书的纲要和指南，就如同鱼尾巴的功用。由于从大门进入知识的宫殿需要大量时间和程式，所以时间不多、不喜欢程式的人往往选择从后门进入。由于各类艺术都飞速进展，因此更容易从后面进攻。就像医生要了解整个身体的状况，往往只观察后面的排出物。因此，人们获取知识从一本书的后部分着手，就像男孩将弹丸瞄准麻雀的尾巴。因此，了解人生的最佳途径是注意后端，这是聪明人的方法；因此，科学的发现就像赫克勒斯的公牛，[162]从后面追踪；因此，老学问的揭秘就像旧丝袜，从脚下开始。不仅如此，作为拥有大量军事原则的体系，近来科学大军的规矩日益严密，总体上看正进行大规模的集体探索活动。对于它给我们带来的福祉，我们完全应该感谢其体系与纲要，它使我们现代的科学巨匠，像谨慎的放贷人一样，用他们的辛劳和汗水造福于我们这些后辈。唯有辛勤劳动播撒的种子，才可能让后人坐享其成，让我们在这高贵的年代获得如此特殊而丰厚的收获。如今让人变得聪明、有学问、高贵的方法越来越多，日益普及，且有了较固定的形式，因此作家的数量也势必相应增加。其结果，必然导致他们之间不断产生摩擦。此外，还有人说，目前自然界已不再有足以让人另立一个名目，并为之编纂一部书的新事物出现。这话是一个非常出色的数学家告诉我的。他用数学定理对此作了完整的演示。

或许，这一说法会遭到那些坚持物质无限论的人们的反对。他们不承认任何一种事物可以被穷尽。为了回答这个问题，让我们分析一下当今社会所发明并培育出的一种最高级的现代智慧。作为所有智慧的一部分，它结出的果实最多、最美。其中，尽管有一部分遗存是古人留给我们的，但依我的记忆，还全然没有被破译或编辑形成体系以供现代社会使用。因此，以我们的名义，我们可以确信，从某种意义上说，它的发明和完善都是由现代人一手完成的。我指的是现代人所拥有的从男性和女性的pudenda[163]及其正常用途中演绎出象征、影射和应用艺术的享誉甚高的智慧，绝对令人惊讶、舒畅和愉悦。再有，看到发明中与这些渠道无关的时尚成分微乎其微，不禁让我时常想到，我们时代和我们国家的那些快乐天才都是古代对印度矮人的象征性描写所产生的预言效果所造就的。这些矮人的身高不过两英尺；sed quorum pudenda crassa, et ad talos usque pertingentia。[164]目前我一直在很好奇地研究近期出现的最直观展现这种美的作品。尽管这里的静脉时常流血，而且人用尽所有吃奶的力气保持其扩张、胀大并通畅，就像西徐亚人[165]。他们有一个习惯，就是给母马的私处吹气，这样可使它产奶更多。但是我有一个忧虑，就是这样一来那里必然越来越干燥，且不可逆转，而且需要一些新的智慧fonde[166]提供可能的帮助，否则我们对此就只能满足于在那里不断重复，在其他场合也一样。

对于我们现代人的智慧无法计算出不可穷尽的事物的这一说法，以上所述给出了有力的论据。那么，除了增加索引和减少卷本这些最后的招数以外，我们还能做什么呢？必须大量收集语录，并按字母顺序编排。为此，尽管无需和作者协商，但必须和批评家、评论家以及词汇学家谨慎协商。最重要的是，对于聪明地收集到其中最佳部分、鲜花和格言的人，必须通过学识中的所谓细筛子和粗钓丝对其认真处理。[167]尽管我们并不清楚接受它们处理的究竟是珍珠还是鱼饵，因而也不清楚我们究竟应看重留在筛面上的，还是落到筛底下的东西。

通过这些方法，在几周之内就涌现出许多能够驾驭最深奥、最广泛的主题的作家了。可如果他脑袋空空的，怎么写出内容丰满的普通书籍呢？如果你放松在环境、方法、风格、语法或创新等方面对他的约束，赋予他但凡有机会就去抄袭别人、放弃自己主见的普遍特权，那么，无须更多的材料，他就能完成一部可以堂堂正正摆在书店的书架上的作品，并且带着它那用纹章图案加工的精致书名标签，体面地、永久地待在那里，不让任何学生的手指翻动、弄脏，也不会在图书馆的黑暗中不断轮回，而当大限来临之时，却愉快地接受炼狱的审判，以升上天空。

假如没有这样的许可，那如何指望我们这些现代智者有机会展现我们所收集的材料呢？这些材料的主题成千上万，各不相同，且缺一不可；一旦缺少它们，世人无限的喜悦和受益将被剥夺，使我们在暗淡无光中葬于被遗忘的角落，永不得救赎。

正是这些元素使我得以在有生之年见到作家们联手在竞争中胜过行会中的所有其他弟兄。这让我们自得其乐，还包括来自我们祖先西徐亚人的许多快乐。他们用笔的数量之多，就连从雄辩的希腊语中都难以找到更恰当的形容词，只能说在遥远的北方地区人们几乎不能旅行，因为那里鹅毛满天飞。[168]

本章题外话的长度说明了它的重要程度，而眼下我也已尽我所能为它安排了一个适当位置。如果明智的读者能找到其他更合适的位置，我这里授权给他，可以把它放到任何他喜欢的角落。现在我可要回到更重要的正题上了。

第八章　无稽之谈

在伊奥利亚有一位学者认为，宇宙万物起源于风。根据此种理论，整个宇宙的产生，以及最后的归宿都如此：我们用吹出的气息点燃并使之旺盛的自然之火，终有一天会告吹。

Quod procul a nobis flectat fortuna gubernans.[169]

这就是其adepti[170]对他们的anima mundi[171]的理解，也就是精神或呼吸或风的世界，因为，如果通过自然的细节来观察整个体系，你会发现这是毫无争议的。无论你喜欢将一个人的forma informans[172]称为spiritus, animus, afflatus，还是anima[173]，这些名字除了形态不同，不是都表示风——也就是构成一切化合物质及其最终归宿的基本元素——的意思吗？再说，生命又是什么，难道不是我们常说的从鼻孔呼出的气息吗？因此，自然学家认为风还在我们尚无法说清的某种神秘现象中起作用，这一论断是完全合理的。且不说诸如turgidus[174]和inflatus[175]这样好听的名字既可以指emittent[176]又可以指承受器官。

根据我所收集的古人的记录，我发现他们的信条有三十二条，这里没有必要一一细说。但是其中发展出的几条最重要的规则，绝不能不提。譬如以下这条格言就很有分量：在所有化合中，由于风所占的比例很高，并促成化合，因此这些化合物中的佼佼者必然含有大量的primordium[177]，可见在所有造物中人类是最完美的，并且还被慷慨的哲学家赋予三种不同的animas[178]或风。而伊奥利亚的智者又慷慨地添加了第四种，其重要性和修饰作用不亚于前三种。这就叫作quartum principium[179]，分别位于世界的四个角落，并成就了著名的秘法家帕拉切尔苏斯[180]将人体置于这四大基点相关位置的学说。

出于这一原则，他们的下一个信条是，人在来到这个世界上的时候就带着一定数量的风，它源自那另外四种，可称之为quinta essentia[181]。这一精妙教义普遍适用于人生所有紧要关头，并能发展成为任何门类的艺术和科学，还可以通过某种教育手段得以神奇地精馏和扩充。当此风膨胀至完美程度，就无须保留、硬撑或强压了，而可以自由地传递给人类。由于这些原因，以及其他一些同等重要的原因，聪明的伊奥利亚人宣称，打嗝[182]的本能是理性造物最高尚的行为。为了培养此种艺术，使之更好地为人类服务，他们采用了多种方法。在一年的某些季节里，你会看见他们中数量众多的祭司，个个张大嘴巴面向狂风。而在其他时候，你能看到数百人在一起围成一个圈，每人手拿一副风箱，对准旁边人的臀部吹气，把他吹鼓，成为大酒桶的形状。因此，他们通常非常得体地把自己的身体称为气囊。在通过诸如此类的手段胀大，达到足够饱满程度的时候，他们便立即离开，为公众的利益，将自己囊中所得的大部分注入到他们信徒的皮囊里。在这里我们必须申明，他们之所以把所有的学问都尊奉为从同一原则演变而来，是因为，首先，大家都一致承认并肯定，学识使人饱满。其次，还可以通过以下三段论法来证明这一点：话语不过是风，学识不过是话语，因此，学识不过是风。由于这样的原因，他们中的哲学家，在学校就是通过打嗝来向他们的学生阐述其所有学说和观点的，而学生们也因此获得了各种各样雄辩的口才。但是，他们中那些杰出的智者最棒、最显著的特点是一个特定的神态，这神态明确无误地表明精神对其体内物质的扰动达到了何种程度或强度。因为，在嗝逆之后，风与气味同时发了出来，首先，在湍流和气动作用下，它会在人体内的小小世界引起震动，使人咧嘴、缩腮，使双眼眼球暴突。此时此刻，他们打出的嗝不但被视为无比神圣，而且越酸越臭越好，被他们卑微的追随者带着无限的欣慰全盘接受下来。并且（为了使这一过程更趋完美），由于人的生命气息是从鼻孔呼出的，因此最好、最有益、最生动地接受它的途径，也是经过那里，以便在其通过的时候给他们以嗅酊般的刺激。

这四种气就是他们的神。他们将其视为激活宇宙并遍布于其中的精神予以崇拜，并且相信唯此四种气就足以给人以所有灵感。然而其中最主要的，也就是令他们latria[183]的，是万能的“北”。这是一个古老的神，受到希腊大都市人的最高级别的尊敬：omnium deorum Boream maxime celebrant[184]。这个神，虽然被认为无处不在，但在更深邃的伊奥利亚人看来，拥有一个独特的居所，或（用正式语言表述）一个coelum empyraeum[185]。他更习惯于出现在这里。此居所坐落的那个地区，古希腊人都知道，名为Σμοτία[186]，或黑暗的土地。虽然这一点曾引起很大争议，但无可争议的一点是，伊奥利亚人中最优秀之辈都认为自己源于类似的一个名字，其祭司也世世代代从中获得最精妙的灵感。他们亲手将灵感从那些气囊的源头找出来，并在所有国家的非教会派的新教徒中释放。而这些人在此之后便天天气喘吁吁，不论是在过去、现在还是永远的将来。

不错，他们的神秘仪式就是这样进行的。有学问的人都知道，古代的艺术鉴赏家有一项发明，就是用气囊或储气桶保存并携带风，这对于长期的海上航行有很大帮助。而今这一有用技艺竟然失传了，实在令人遗憾，尽管我不清楚潘西罗鲁斯[187]是如何粗心大意，竟然把它遗漏了的。这是一项应归功于埃俄罗斯[188]本人的发明，这一教派的名字也源于此。不仅如此，他们为了纪念这位创始人，至今还保存下来大量这样的桶，并且在他们的每个殿里都安放一个，事先把上盖去掉。每逢庄严的日子，祭司就钻进桶里。在这里，他在按上面提到的方法作好一切准备之前，还要用一个神秘的漏斗将他的下身和桶底连起来，桶底通过北面的裂缝或罅隙接受新鲜灵感。于是你看到他立即膨胀到桶的形状和大小。在这种状态下，作用在下方的精神仿佛在向他发话，他把整场风暴注入他的听觉，它从ex adytis et penetralibus[189]发出，并非没有莫大的痛苦和不安。而吹进来的风作用在他的脸上就如同海风，先是让脸先变黑，继而增加皱纹，接着破裂成泡沫。神圣的伊奥利亚人就是用这种方法向他们气喘吁吁的门徒传达神谕的。他们中有的人在神圣之气出来之后便贪婪地张大嘴巴，有的则不停地吟唱对风的颂歌，并随着自己哼唱的节奏轻轻地来回摆动，以表达他们的神灵之微风的安抚作用。

正是这种祭祀习惯，使一些作家认为伊奥利亚人属于世界上非常古老的人种。由于我上文提到的神秘交易与其他古代圣贤的方法几乎完全相同，灵感均来自于某些藏而不露、奇臭无比的气源，不但将它传给祭司很痛苦，对人们产生的影响也基本上是一样的痛苦。事实上，这一过程还经常由女性提供者来主持或引导，一般认为她们的器官更有利于接受那些神圣的风，以更大的容器让风进入和通过，并顺带为其增加淫欲的成分，这就好比通过必要的安排，从肉欲的淫荡变为精神的渴望。为支持这一深邃的猜想，还有人进一步强调说，这一女祭司习俗至今仍保留于一些现代伊奥利亚教派中。人们同意接受她们来自上述容器的灵感，就像她们的女巫先祖一样。

一个人只要不断给他的头脑以刺激和约束，他那永不停歇的思想就会本能地在两个极端的世界之间遨游：高与低，善与恶。通常，在他头脑中闪现的第一道灵光总把他带入最完美、光鲜和高尚的遐想，直到其飞升至他自己以及视线所及的范围以外，且无法确切感知至高和至低这两个极端是多么靠近的时候。然后，他又以同样的飞行方法和路线，垂直落到最低点，就如同一个人向东行进却来到西边，或者画一条直线，画得足够长就成了一个圈。难道是我们天性中恶的一面总使我们喜欢用相反的意念装饰每一个高明的想法，还是我们用以解释事物的推理，像太阳一样，只能照亮地球的一半，让另一半不得不留在阴影和黑暗中，还是总朝向思想中的最高尚、最美好方向飞翔的幻想已错过目标，疲劳过度，像一只死去的天堂鸟一般突然坠落到地面，还是经过如此这般的形而上学推理，我尚且没有完全错过其真正的原因，而这一在如此复杂条件下伴随我的命题，其实是全真的？这就像人类最不文明的部分也有某种途径或方法，从概念上爬到上帝或至高权力的高度，因而他们一般都不会忘记给自己的恐惧添加一些可怕的想象，这尽管不能更好地，却能在一定程度上让他们对魔鬼有所容忍。[190]而这一过程似乎是再自然不过的事情，因为它发生在想象力被极度拔高的人身上，其拔高度和那些身体被拔高的人一样；因此，随着他们为类似向上的意念而高兴的同时，却也同样为万丈深渊的前景感到恐惧。所以，在选择魔鬼的时候，人类的通常方法一直是，无论基于实际行动还是视觉感官，挑选那些他们所塑造的神最为反感的事物。这也正是伊奥利亚教派所采取的方法，他们把对两种本性之恶的恐惧和仇恨附在自己身体上，并且在此两种恶与他们所崇拜的神灵之间建立起永久的敌意。而这两种恶中的一个是变色龙，灵感不共戴天的仇敌，它充满蔑视地吞噬着他们所敬之神的巨大影响力，却连打嗝这样微小的回报都不肯付出。另一个称为Moulinavent，[191]是个巨大的可怕怪物，它有四条强悍的胳膊，与神进行着永不停歇的搏斗，不但能巧妙地躲避他们的打击，还能以更多的打击回敬他们。

著名的伊奥利亚人就是这样与神和魔鬼周旋的。这使他们在当今世界成为如此著名的一族，同时，那礼貌的拉普兰人[192]，毫无疑问，是一个最有代表性的分支。因此，对于这样的人，我不能不以正当的理由在此大加颂扬，因为他们显然为了利益和志趣而与他们的兄弟，我们中的伊奥利亚人如此紧密地联合在一起，不仅从同一批发商那里购买风，而且用同样的价格和方法向非常类似的客户兜售。

那么，不论上文所描述的这个系统完全系由杰克发明，还是如一些作家所言，是从德尔菲[193]的原版抄袭而来，仅经过某些补充和修订，以适应具体时间和环境，我对此不得而知。但有一点我可以肯定的是，杰克至少给它带来了一个新的转折，使它形成了我上文所演绎的衣服及式样。

对于这样一个社会，我对其中的成员有一种特殊的景仰，而他们的观点和习俗却一直受到其反对者出于恶意和无知的极度歪曲和中伤，我一直都在寻求机会为他们正名。因为我认为，消除偏见，将事物最原本、最真实的面貌公之于众，是人类最伟大、最优良的品德。所以我要大胆地这样做下去，除了良心、荣誉和感激之外，我没有考虑个人得失。

第九章　题外话：关于一个联合王国疯病的起源、利用和改进

对于这样一个著名教派，其声誉所系、不容以任何方式歪曲的一点是，它的兴起和确立都归功于我上文所描述的那位创始人杰克。此人神智颠倒，大脑因错乱而失常，这也就是我们通常所说的精神紊乱，或称为疯狂或狂躁。因为，只要我们观察一下世上所有由一个人发起的最大规模行动，不论是通过征服建立新帝国，在哲学领域新的突破和进展，还是新宗教的发明和传播，我们都会发现，其创始人的正常思维发生了巨大的改变，这见于他们的饮食、教育、某些主导性的脾气性格，受到某种特殊的空气或天气的影响。此外，人类思想中的某些个性想法，容易在一些偶然出现的特定情况下相互碰撞，产生火花，尽管最初看上去微不足道，却能引起燎原大火，激发人生最绚丽的壮举。伟大的转折并不总是出自孔武有力的双手，往往也会在适合的条件下应运而生。灵动之气一旦进入大脑，思想的火花无需外来的火种点燃。因为人的上层所有就相当于空气的中层，尽管本质上形成的过程迥异，但最后产出的实质和效用却是相同的。雾气从地表生成，浊气从粪堆生成，蒸汽从大海生成，烟气从火焰生成，所有的云都具有相同的成分和形状。从茅厕发出的气味，其提神作用与功效，丝毫不亚于祭坛上的熏香。凡此种种，我认为，都可以说明我自己。不仅如此，如果没有阴云受到扰动，大自然就永远不会下雨。同样，禁锢在人脑中的思想，必须受到下方器官所发出气体的扰动和侵袭，才能孕育发明并培养成果。可见，尽管上述这些气体来源的复杂性毫不亚于大气，但是它们产出的成果却由于土壤的不同而在种类和品性上截然不同。下面我举两个实例来证明并解释我的这一论断。

一位伟大的王子[194]组建了一支强大的军队，给自己的金库充满无数宝藏，还建立了一支无敌舰队。所有这些计划他丝毫没有向他的重臣或挚友透露。转瞬间世界就充满了杀气。邻近的王国个个十分恐慌，不知道战争风暴何时来临，各地的小道政治家们也纷纷猜测，莫衷一是。一些人认为他已经制定好了称霸世界的计划。另一些人经过分析认为，他的目标是推翻教皇，改革并重建宗教，也就是他自己曾经笃信的宗教。还有一些人更为睿智，认为他是要到亚洲去制服土耳其并恢复巴勒斯坦。处在所有这些计划准备的过程中，某位通过这些症状收集疾病特征信息的御医，企图尝试治疗。在手术实施的过程中，他竟然打破了气囊，把气体放了出来。没等采用任何手段完成补救，那不幸的王子就气绝身亡了。现在，读者是否迫不及待地想要了解这股气究竟来自何处，竟然长时间吸引那些国民的眼球？究竟是何种神秘动力，莫测源泉，竟能让如此美妙的引擎转动起来？后来人们发现，整台机器的运转不过是幕后的一位女性所致，她的一个眼神就引发隆起，但在尚未发射之前，她却被转移到一个敌对的国家。处于这样尴尬的境地，王子该如何应对？他尝试那位诗人的能容纳corpora quaeque[195]的诗句，但落空了，因为，

Idque petit corpus mens unde est saucia amore：

Unde feritur, eo tendit, gestitque coire.[196]

在漫无目的地使用各种和平手段的努力之后，聚到一处的部分精气升高并燃烧起来，转而阴沉，继而愤怒，转动位于脊髓腔上的头颅，上升至大脑。一个泼皮因为被某个娼妓甩了而产生的打碎她家窗户的冲动，与一位伟大的王子自发筹组强大的军队，一心梦想攻城拔寨、驰骋疆场、凯旋的冲动，如出一辙。

——Teterrima belli

Causa——[197]

另一个实例出自我读过的一个非常古老的故事。有一个强大的国王[198]，为了取乐，在长达三十年的时间里交替不断地攻取、失守城池。他打败敌军，又被敌军打败。他把王子赶出他们的领土，吓唬孩子并抢走他们口中的面包和黄油。不论是否是他的臣民，不论朋友还是敌人，不论男女，他都一概烧杀抢掠。据记载，不同国家的哲学家们在探讨其中的原因、性质、道德和政治背景的时候产生了很大的分歧，难以找出解释这种现象的根本原因。最后，气体或精神占据了这位英雄的大脑，并在其中不断循环，进而占领了身体中那个提供zibeta occidentalis[199]的著名区域，并在那里聚集形成一个肿瘤。有了这一说法，当时的世人便不再争执不下了。上述重大结果就是由于精气在此壅滞，不再继续运行所致。同样的精气如果在上层运行，可以征服一个王国，下降到直肠，就造成肛瘘。

下面让我们研究分析在哲学领域引进新思想的伟大人物，以期找到以下结果：究竟出于灵魂的何种本能，得以让凡人在自己的头脑中产生冲动，为所有人都表示无法理解的事物，构建新的思想体系，并以恁般高涨的热情推而广之：这样的冲动究竟萌发自什么样的种子，这样的伟大发明家究竟仰仗其何种人格，从而获得数量众多的门徒。因为显而易见，这些人中最主要的几个，不论是古代的还是现代的，都被他们的敌人误解为疯子或精神错乱。事实上，除了他们的追随者中为数不多的几个，其余的都被所有人误解为疯子或精神错乱。对于语言和行为的正常规范，他们所采用的推理方法截然不同于凡夫俗子简单粗糙的推理；对于他们中的几个典型，我大体上赞同他们今天的继任者现代精神病学的原则分析，并将对其中的精华和原理作适当的深入研究，采用类似于伊壁鸠鲁、第欧根尼[200]、阿波罗尼奥斯[201]、卢克莱修、帕拉切尔苏斯[202]以及笛卡尔[203]等人的方法。这些人如果还在世，不论与他们的追随者紧密联系还是分开，在我们这个没有区别的时代，都将招致放血、鞭挞、枷锁乃至卧薪黑牢等危险。在自然规律或状态下思考的人，为什么会想到将其他所有人的思想局限在与自己思想的长度、宽度和高度完全一致的框框里？然而这却是所有创新者在思想的王国里首先想到的问题。伊壁鸠鲁曾希望，在某个时刻，出于某种机缘巧合，所有人的观点在经过无休止的相互碰撞之后——锋利与柔润，轻与重，圆与方——骤然一致起来。同时，通过某种clinamina[204]，统一于某个原子或虚空点上，就如同宇宙万物起源于虚空。笛卡尔曾说，他在自己死之前看到了所有哲学家的情绪，就像许多小星星遨游在他的浪漫国度，并被他的旋涡所淹没并溺死。现在，我倒很乐意听听，如果不用我所阐明的在较低器官所生成的气体作用于大脑，并在那里精馏成概念，而对此我们贫乏的母语尚没有其他更合适的名字可以描述，只能称之为疯狂或狂躁，对此类特定人群的这种想象力还能有其他的解释吗？因此，现在就让我们来设想一下，所有这些伟大的哲人都无不给他们自己以及他们的理论招徕了一批盲从的信徒，这究竟是为什么。而在我看来其中的原因很简单：在人类理解能力的和谐世界里，有一根特殊的琴弦，它分成若干段，每一段的音调都完全相同。假如你能巧妙地找到与之一致的键位，并轻轻地敲击它，如果你的运气足够好，弹出的音与它们的完全一致，那么在某种神秘谐振现象的作用下，那几根弦就会同时发出声音。这种情况的出现取决于技巧和偶然性，因为，如果碰巧你弹出的音不那么准，高了或者低了，那么你的教义就不会有人追随，相反你将被作为疯子捆绑起来，只能得到一些活命的面包和水。因此，最好的办法是对这一高深的技巧进行甄别，在不同的时间对不同的人有针对性的采用。在这方面西塞罗[205]就很聪明，他在给一个英格兰朋友写信的时候，除了其他内容，他还谨慎写下了谨防被我们的出租马车夫欺骗（当时的他们似乎和现在差不多，都是些反复无常的无赖）的精彩文字：Est quod gaudeas te in ista loca venisse, ubi aliquid sapere viderere。[206]恕我大胆直言，这是一条不归路，从伦常事理来说如此不通的是，在一些人中间不过是个傻瓜的你，在另一些人中可能被视为智者。希望我所认识的某些绅士能把此话作为及时的暗讽在心中掂量掂量。事实上，这的确是那位高贵的绅士，我最聪明的挚友沃顿先生的致命错误。他是一个表面看上去注定有更大发展和成就的人，不论你是否考虑他的信念或样子。绝对没有人在进入公共视线的时候，有比他传播一种新宗教时更适当的身心准备。啊，设想一下：那些快乐的人才，因误用虚妄的哲学，进入适合他们的梦想和愿望的渠道，在那里扭曲心灵和表情是如此高尚的行为，以至于对此愤愤不平的下层世界都不敢直言有什么地方出了问题，或直言他的大脑已不幸进水。对此就连作为他兄弟的现代主义者，都像不肯领情的人一样不禁大声耳语，声音之大正在顶楼上写作的我都听到了！最后，从古至今，凡喜欢研究狂热之源流的人，如果沿这条肥水不断寻根求源，就会发现它的源头和下游一样污浊和不平静：而最大的发现就是气体中的嗅酊，世人称之为疯狂。并发现，如果没有它，世界不但不能得到两个伟大的祝福——征服和秩序——甚至所有世人还不幸会对看不见的东西具有相同的认识。[207]然而，以前有一种postulatum[208]认为，这股气从何而来并不重要，重要的是在何种角度上它作用于传播和理解，或它的升华将到达何种大脑。这是一个非常微妙的切入点，它为明智而好奇的读者分清了若干理由，大脑区区数值上的差异，如何在同一种气体的作用下产生如此巨大差异，成为区别亚历山大大帝、莱顿的杰克[209]和笛卡尔先生等人品的唯一分界点？这里所讨论的问题是我所经历的最抽象的；是对我的心智最强有力的考验：因此我希望读者也拿出最大的诚意。因为下面我还要继续索解这一棘手问题。

人类具有某种

Hic multa desiderantur[210]

我认为这就是问题的答案。如此这般勉强地度过这个难关之后，我相信读者会同意我的结论，那就是，如果现代人认为，疯狂只是大脑受到发自较低器官的某种气体的影响造成的某种扰动或错乱，那么这种疯狂正是那些发生在帝国里、哲学里和宗教里的伟大革命的源头。因为大脑如果处于自然的条件和状态下，就会引导它的主人以常人的方式宁静地生活，而不会产生丝毫要民众服从自己的权力、推理或愿景的念头。并且他越是用人类学习的通常模式规范自己，就会越远离将自己的某个特殊想法发展成派系的倾向，因为这让他明白自己的软弱无能和人们的顽固无知。但是当一个人的奇想超越了理性，想象力与感觉器官的具体感受发生了冲突，其中的常识判断和理解都被踢出九霄云外，他让自己首先成为第一个改变信仰者，那这信仰一旦有了指针，也就不难吸引他人了。不论作为外因还是内因，妄想都具有同样强大的作用。花言巧语和美好愿景对于耳朵和眼睛的作用，就相当于胳肢对于触觉的作用。那些我们最珍视的生活中的娱乐和乐趣不过是对感官的欺骗和玩弄。因为，如果我们认真考虑我们通常所谓的幸福究竟是什么，以及它与理解或感觉的关系，我们就会发现，它所有的特征和属性都符合这样一个简单的定义：一个永恒的骗局。首先，对于思想或良知来说，很明显的一点是，想象的威力大大胜过客观事实，而理性也在其中发挥作用。因为想象力可能引起的革命，比起真正耗费金钱或资源所能得到的要更为神奇得多。人类的这种偏执所造成的结果也并不怪他们自己，如果我们考虑到，辩论通常发生在过去的事情和认知的事情之间，那么问题症结仅仅是，无论想象中的事物是否被恰当地描述为存在于记忆中的事物，记忆都可以作为一个公正的凭据，并且非常有利于想象，因为它是公认的一切事物的诞生地，其他一切都至多不过是事物的坟墓。再说，如果我们采纳这一有关幸福的定义，并用感官作为参照来分析它，就不得不承认它们之间完美的吻合。所有我们遇到的事物，如果不通过幻想的渠道加以理解，是何等模糊和平淡！同样，在自然的镜子中显现的一切事物是何等渺小！因此，如果没有人为媒介的帮助，虚假的灯光、精选的折射角度、添枝加叶，那么普通人的幸福指数才会达到很高的水平。假如世人能认真考虑这一点（对此我有充分的理由怀疑），人们就不会将他们最高的智慧用于揭露缺点和暴露阴暗面的艺术。[211]这种做法不论是好是坏，在我看来都与摘掉面具相仿，而这不论在现实世界还是剧场演出中从来都是不允许的。

从程度上说，轻信倒是比好奇更为平和的思想活动，但是不及将事物的表面与深入其内部的所谓哲学相关联的智慧，而这种哲学带回的严肃信息和发现是，事物的内部毫无用处。所有事物最初呈现给人的两种感觉是视觉和触觉，而从这两种感觉只能分析出事物的颜色、形状、大小及其表面实际存在的或经工艺加工的东西，仅此而已。然后就要运用拥有大量工具的推理，其中包括切割、扩张、碾压、穿刺等，以提供它们实质上相异的证据。现在，我要说所有这一切都是极度反自然的。自然的一个永恒的法则是将她最好的一面呈现出来。因此，为了以后能够节省所有这些昂贵的解剖费用，我坚持认为很有必要在这里告诉读者，在以上这些结论中推理显然是正确的，对于我所认识的大多数具有肉体的事物而言，外在的远远比内在的更可取；而我最近的研究分析使这一点得到了更充分的证实。上周我看到一个女人脱去衣服，你很难相信这让她本人变得多么糟糕。昨天我要求在我面前脱去一具美男尸体的衣服，这时我们才惊奇地发现，在一套衣服里隐藏着多少未知的缺点。然后我打开他的大脑，他的心，他的脾，我真切地发现，我们的每一步操作越是往下进行，所发现的缺陷就越多、越大。从这一切中我公正地为自己形成这样一个结论，无论什么样的哲学家或策划者，如果能发现焊接或修补自然缺陷或不足的艺术，那他们和那些当今因放大并暴露缺陷而受到如此尊敬的人（例如认为解剖是医学的终极目标的人）比起来，都是更为出色的人，是他们把更有用的科学教给我们。那些被命运和处世态度置于某个位置，可以方便地享受这一高尚艺术成果[212]的人，可比伊壁鸠鲁，是满足于分离表层和图像的印象，使之作用于对事物外表的感知的人。[213]这样的人，真的很聪明，榨取自然的营养，让哲学和理性去舔舐那些酸屑与糟粕。这就是福运的高贵与精明，可称为对上当的执迷，是在一群无赖中充当傻瓜的平静状态。[214]

再说疯狂。毋庸置疑，根据以上我所作的系统分析，每一物种都从冗余的气体中获益，因此，由于一些种类的狂暴能为肌肉提供双倍能量，说明也有其他东西能给大脑增加活力、动力和精神。然而，经常发生的情况是，这些积极的精神一旦占领大脑，就变得像在他人废弃空无一人的住房徘徊，由于无所事事，要么只好带着房子的一部分消失，要么待在家里把它从窗口整个儿扔出。[215]这就是疯狂的两个主要分支的神秘表现，对此不少哲学家的研究不如我深入，误认为这种区别来自于不同的原因，并草草把第一种归因于缺少，把第二种归因于冗余。

我认为，上述情况说明，按我所作的推理分析，主要关键点在于给冗余的气体派上用场，并谨慎为其调整时机。这样一来就完全有可能在一个联邦国家产生红衣主教和天主教的功效。因此，一个人，选对适当的时机，跃入一个海湾，在那里变成英雄，就被称为国家的救星。另一个虽采用同样的步骤，可惜时机不对，致使疯狂所形成的烙印与记忆发生抵触。正由于这显著的差异，我们才受到这样的教导：满怀敬意与挚爱地重复库尔提斯[216]的名字，满怀仇恨与蔑视地重复恩培多克勒[217]的名字。同样，人们通常认为老布鲁特斯[218]是为了公众的利益才扮演傻子和疯子的角色。但这些都只不过是同样冗余的气体长时间无用武之地所致，用拉丁语说就是ingenium par negotiis[219]；或者，如将其尽我所能译成英语，就是一种狂躁，若不将它用于国家大事，它就永不安定。[220]由于这些原因，以及其他一些同等重要但不一定同等有趣的原因，我这里要高兴地拥抱一个我一直在寻找的机会：我有一项十分高尚的事业要推荐给爱德华·西摩[221]爵士，克里斯托弗·马斯格雷夫[222]爵士，约翰·鲍尔斯[223]爵士，约翰·豪[224]先生以及其他爱国人士，那就是，他们应该申请通过一项法案，任命一批委员对疯人院及有权投送人员、文件和记录的相关部门进行检查，并且要深入检查到每个学员和教授的优点和资质；对其性情和行为诸方面要进行最细致的观察，以区别并匹配他们的才干，他们可能为国家机关发明令人称奇的民用和军用仪器，在程序上采用我在这里谦恭地提出的方法。我希望大度的读者看在我对那高尚社会崇高敬意的分上，允许我对这一重大议题表达我极大的诚意，而我也曾一度有幸成为它不值一提的一员。

是否有任何学员将毫无价值的东西撕得粉碎、咒骂并亵渎神灵、咬牙切齿、口吐白沫、并把尿壶泼向观察者的脸？那就让检查委员运用他们那令人羡慕的权力给他一个骑兵团，将他和其他人一道送到弗兰德斯[225]。还有另一个人说个没完、含混不清、又打哈欠，又大嚷大叫，既无标点又无停顿？那是被放错了位置的多么了不起的人才！应立即为他提供一个绿包和一些纸[226]，再给他口袋里塞三个便士[227]，让他去威斯敏斯特会堂。你也许还会发现第三个人在严肃地丈量他的茅屋，那是一个颇具远见和洞察力的人，尚未崭露头角。因为这就像摩西，ecce cornuta erat ejus facies[228]，走在适当的地方，用适当的严肃而庄重的神情向你乞讨，还述说很多的艰难时事、税收和巴比伦的娼窝[229]。晚上八点钟关闭并锁上他的小屋的木窗户，梦到火、扒手、法院的常客以及特权之所在。现在，如果所有这些诉求的主人与他的弟兄们一道被打发到城市里，那它们将导致怎样的结果！再看第四个，他在不断深入地自言自语，时不时咬着自己的拇指，面部表情不断随内心的盘算和设计发生变化；时而飞快行走，眼睛盯在手里拿的报纸上；一个大量节省时间的人，没有灵敏的听觉，也没有长远的目光，却有更好的记忆；一个永远匆忙的人，一个实业的伟大孵化器和增殖机，擅长无言的耳语的高超艺术；一个对单音节词[230]拖长音无限崇拜的人，一个随时准备毫无保留地向任何人谏言的人；一个早已忘记单词常用的意思，却令人钦佩地记得其发音的人，语言支离破碎，因为总被意外情况打断。如果你在他最常消磨的时间段来到他的壁炉旁边，[231]他会说，先生，给我一个便士，我将为你放歌一曲，但是你要先付钱（因此才有这样的俗语，更有这样的实践：为歌舍钱）。这是一场多么完整、面面俱到的法庭技巧演示，却因用错了地方而完全失落了！走近另一个茅屋（你先得捂住鼻子），你会看到一个粗暴、阴森、肮脏、邋遢的人，与自己的粪便为伍，满身是自己的尿液。他饮食的最佳部分是经加工的自己的排泄物，它先是腐败蒸发，继而不停盘旋，最后再吸入体内。他的面色是肮脏的黄色，有稀疏的胡须，与他饮食的首次衰变很相配，并与其他那些出生并成长在粪便里的昆虫无异，从那里获得自身的颜色和气味。出自这种公寓的学生惜字如金，但是对呼吸比较随意：他伸出手准备接受你的施舍，得到之后便立即回到他以前的行当。现在，想一想沃里克巷[232]的学会竟然不再关心如此有用的成员的回归，难道不令人吃惊吗？正是这样的成员（如果通过上述外表就能确定），将成为那高尚群体的最大亮点。另一个学员在你面前趾高气扬，撅起嘴，睁大眼睛，并很优雅地向你伸出手来要求亲吻。看守劝你不要害怕这直率的人，因为他不会伤害你，而且他是唯一被允许自由出入前厅的人，而那里的演说家让你明白，这个严肃的人是一个因自傲而走火入魔的裁缝。这个出色的学员还有其他许多好品质，恕我这里不再一一述及。听我说，假如所有这一切有关他的说法、他的动作、他的作派显得不特别自然，不与环境相吻合，那才是怪事呢。

我还不至于那么小气，竟支持许多有情人、小提琴手、诗人和政治家的观点，认为通过这样的改革就可以让世界复原了。除了有如此大量的人才，他们的智慧和学识，如果我可以冒昧肯定的话，现在是被埋没，或者至少被误用了，而把他们派上用场能给国家利益带来明确的好处之外，公众将得到的更为实质性的巨大好处是，正如对他们的调查所展示的那样，所有这些人不但非常优秀，而且在若干方面已达到完美的程度。这，在我看来，一如我上文的明确展示，必将再通过一个简单的例子来加强：即使我本人，这个说出如此伟大真理的作者，也是一个想象力难以驾驭、动辄信口开河的人。从长期的经验中我已经观察到，我的思想是一个轻佻的骑手，时常会落马。因此，如果没有庄严地承诺抒发我的思想，或诸如此类的承诺，我的朋友为了人类的普遍利益就永远不会放任我单独行动。对此，我的那些温柔的、坦诚的、彬彬有礼的、职业生涯充满现代慈善和温情的读者，恐怕很难相信。

第十章　“澡盆故事”

近年来作者群和读者群之间的礼尚往来，成为在一个非常精致的年代难得正解的话题。几乎没有一个剧本、小册子或诗集出现的时候不带有一篇充斥着世界对此书广泛接受和赞誉的前言。只有天知道，所有这些究竟是在哪儿、什么时候、怎样或被谁接受了。然而出于对这样一个值得称道的习惯应有的尊重，我在这里也要将我卑微的谢意献给元首阁下和议会两院，献给国王最尊贵的枢密院的议员们，献给尊敬的法官们、神职人员、贵族、这片土地上自由的民众；并以一种更特别的方式，献给我在威尔的咖啡屋、格雷沙姆学会、沃里克巷、穆尔菲尔德[233]、苏格兰院[234]、威斯敏斯特会堂、伦敦市政厅的弟兄和朋友们，简而言之，献给所有居民及其家人，无论他们在法庭、教堂、营地、城市还是乡村，感谢他们的慷慨和对这本神圣著作的普遍接受。我带着极度的感恩接受他们的赞许和好评，并将尽我所有微薄之力，抓住一切机会回报他们。

同时我很欣慰地感到命运对我的眷顾，使我如此幸运地降生在这个书商和作者利益共享的时代。这两者，我可以很有把握地肯定，是当今在英格兰仅存的感到满意的两大派系。如果你问一位作者，他最近出版的作品是否成功，当然，他会感谢他的星座，世人对它非常看好，他没有任何抱怨的理由：然而，上……，写这本书他只花了一周时间，而且是从他的各种紧急事务中抽时间断断续续拼凑起来的。对此你十有八九会在其前言中看到更多，他会让你看前言。而要了解更多的书你就要去找书商了。你作为顾客来到书商那儿，会遇到类似的情况：上帝祝福他，他的作品销路很好，现在已经是惊人的第二版了，而且店里仅剩下三本。于是你开始讨价还价：先生，我们本来是不减价的，但考虑到你可能是回头客，你认为多少钱合适就出多少钱吧。“请别忘记向你的每个朋友推荐这本书，只要他们来买，价钱都和你的一样优惠。”

如今，那些伟大作品中精彩部分感动世人的情况时有出现；但这究竟应感谢什么样的机遇或条件，这个问题尚未得到认真考虑。若没有天阴下雨，没有醉汉守夜，没有糟糕的脾气，没有医学疗程，没有昏昏欲睡的星期天，没有使人沉迷的骰子，没有裁缝长长的账单，没有乞丐的钱包，没有发昏的头脑，没有炎热的太阳，没有造成便秘的饮食，没有想要的书，没有厌学的情绪：倘若没有所有这一切，以及其他许许多多难以计数的理由（特别是一个出于审慎考虑而疏于提及的误服硫黄的理由），我怀疑作者和作品的数量将会缩小到看上去极为可怜的程度。为进一步证实这一点，请听听一位著名穴居[235]哲学家的论断：不错，他说，一些愚蠢的成分显然是作为人类本性一部分的附属品，而我们能做的只不过是选择倾向于将它暗藏于身还是明戴于身，同时我们也无须对通常如何确定它刨根问底，只要我们牢记：它和人能力的关系就如同它和液体的关系，最轻的总是在最上面。

在英国这个著名的岛国有一个微不足道的小文人，他藏有非常大量的书籍，读者对此人并非完全陌生。他擅长经营一类有害的作品，称为二流作品，但他通常私下把它归到一流作品的名下。我很容易就联想到，只要我的这本书一放下笔，这个机灵小子就会前来偷盗它。对待我就像他曾经对待布莱克摩尔[236]医生、莱斯特兰奇[237]及其他很多不知名的人物一样残忍。因此，为了伸张正义，我向伟大的马鞍修理专家、人类的爱神本特利博士请求援手，希望他用他那最现代的思维考量一下这一莫大的冤情：假如事情果真如此发生，一个作用于屁股、形式上属于二流作品的马鞍，由于我的罪恶，必须被错误地安在我的背上，他就会立即当着世人的面，[238]愉快地为我解除这一负担，并把它带回自己家里，直到真正的畜生认为需要它。

同时我在这里要发布如下宣言，我决心把多年来我一直精心筹划的宏伟构想整体上限定在这一本书里。因为我的话匣子一旦打开，我就希望，为了我亲爱的国家的特殊利益以及全人类的普遍利益，一口气把所有的话都倾倒出来。因此，友好地考虑到我的客人的数量，以及他们要在一顿盛宴中享用我的所有款待，我不屑于将剩下的饭菜放在柜橱里。客人们吃剩下的可以送给穷人，餐桌下面的狗可以啃骨头。这，在我看来，比起邀请这些人明天再来品尝残羹剩饭，是更为慷慨的做法。

如果读者能充分认识到我前面所谈内容的分量，我相信这一定会对他的思想观念产生奇妙的革命性影响，而且他还将对接受并享受这一神机妙论的最后部分作好了倍加充分的准备。读者可以分为三类：肤浅的、无知的和有识的。而我有幸让我的笔触完全适合他们每一类的天赋和长处。肤浅的读者会因感觉怪异而大笑，这就清理了他们的胸腔和肺部，还能控制他们的脾气，省下最无辜的利尿药。而无知的读者，他们与前者之间的区别非常微妙，会发现自己目瞪口呆，这对治疗眼部疾患十分有益，帮助提升并活跃精神，还非常有助于排汗。然而对于读者中真正的有识之士，尤其是那些在别人熟睡时被我好心唤醒的以及在别人醒时熟睡的读者，会在这里找到足够的素材以供他下半生揣摩。在这里，作为我热切的希望，我谦恭地提出一项实验，请每个基督教国家的国王在他的领土内选出七位学识最为渊博的学者，把他们关在七个屋子里七年时间，命令他们给这篇综合论述写七篇详细注释文章。我敢断言，无论他们的若干猜想有什么样的区别，都将是明明白白、不带明显失真地从此文本推导而来。同时还有一点我要认真请求，如果这些陛下允许的话，请在方便的时候尽快实施此项行动。因为我有一个强烈的愿望，就是在我离开这个世界之前，体验一把我们这些神秘主义作家很少在有生之年体验到的名声，不管这名声是一个被嫁接在主干上的几乎不能生长的果实，更不要说在主干腐朽入土之前成熟，还是一只猛禽，和其他伙伴一道，被腐肉的气味引诱到一具尸体旁，还是它[239]认为只有站在坟头上，自己的喇叭才音色最美，传得最远，因为这里高出地平面，且下面的墓室可以起到共鸣的作用。

的确，对于无名作家来说，一旦他们在这黑暗王国找到死亡的良好归宿，那对于他们的成名，不论在品类上还是在程度上，都是莫大的幸福。由于夜晚是一切事物之母，明智的哲学家认为所有著作的成功都与其黑暗的程度成正比。因此，真正被照明的（也就是最黑暗的）就招致了如此难以计数的品评，致使其学术嫁接的可能性催生出无数作者本人可能永远想象不到的意思，却被合法地认为是这一切的执笔者。这样作家的言语就像种子，尽管是随意撒的，但当它们落在一块多产的土地上时，结出的果实却远远超出播种者的希望或想象。

因此，为了促进如此有益的一项工作，我将在这里略表一下有关暗讽的话题，对于那些分工对这一妙不可言的著述努力提出普遍批评的可敬人士来说，这或许会有巨大的帮助。首先，对于数字“0”我有一个非常神秘的谜，它乘以7并除以9。[240]同样，如果蔷薇十字会[241]的某个虔诚的弟兄热切地连续祈求长达六十三个早晨，并满怀赤诚之心，然后根据说明在第二和第五章调换某些字母和音节，就一定会领悟到整部巨著的全部精髓。最后，任何人只要不畏艰难地计算出这篇文章所用的每个字母的数量，并精确地总结出这些数量之间的区别，给每一区别都找一个合情合理的解释，就会发现其结果将是对他的劳动丰厚的回报。但是他必须对Bythus[242]和Sigé[243]十分小心，并一定不要忘记Achamoth[244]的品质；à cujus lacrymis humecta prodit substantia，à risu lucida，à tristitia, et à timore mobilis。[245]这其中尤金尼厄斯·菲拉莱蒂斯[246]犯了一个不可原谅的错误。

第十一章　“澡盆故事”

在如此宽阔的领域徜徉之后，现在我要欣然将我的故事收尾了，并且从此用较为均匀一致的步调结束我的旅程，除非行进途中我看到什么精彩的景色。对此虽然我目前没有看到任何征兆也不抱任何期望，但是如果这样的情况真的和我不期而遇，我请求我的读者能够原谅我，并允许我引你一道看完这道风景。因为写作就像旅行；如果一个人急于回家（我承认我从来不这样，家里可没有那么好的事情让我轻松），而他的马又因长途骑行和崎岖的道路而疲惫不堪，或者本来就是匹老马，那我明确建议他走最直、最普通的道路，不管它多脏。但是我们一定会碰到这样的人，充其量算是卑鄙的同伴，他每走一步都会给自己和旅伴身上溅上泥；他们所有的思想、祈愿、谈话都完全围绕着旅途终点的话题，每次溅起泥浆、趔趄或跌倒，他们都彼此衷心地祝愿对方见鬼去。

另一方面，如果一个旅行者和他的马匹都精神饱满，所带的钱包也鼓鼓的，还有一整天的时间，那他一定会挑干净、好走的路；还会和他的伙伴打趣取乐。但是如果难得出现这样的情况，让他和他的伙伴们一起来到一个令人愉快的场景画面，无论是艺术的还是自然的，或是两者兼有的，这时如果他们表示拒绝，不管出于无知也好，疲劳也好，见鬼，就让他们先走吧，他可以在下一个小镇赶上他们。当他到达那里的时候，他的马像一阵旋风般呼啸而过，男女村民和孩子们都跑出来诧异地观看，上百条狗在他身后边跑边吠，如果他挑其中最大胆的一条抽它一鞭子，它多半会夹着尾巴消失而不会报复；但是如果有哪条犯贱的杂种狗胆敢过于靠近挑衅，那它的腿上一定会得到他那匹骏马无意扬起的后蹄的一记回敬，这同样也不输什么，只见那条狗一瘸一拐嗥叫着跑回家去。

下面我将开始总结杰克的奇异冒险经历：关于他的现状、前途和命运，毫无疑问，细心的读者一定还清楚记得，我在前面某章节的结尾处已经提到过。因此，他的下一个关注点必定是，从那两个先行者身上总结出一套理念，以赋予将要发生的事情真正符合自己理解的意义。

杰克不仅非常慎重地把他头脑的第一次革命说成引发了伊奥利亚的流行教派，而且还使它成功进入到了一套花样百出的新奇思想体系，他丰富的想象力使他抱定的某些观念，虽然表面上十分不合常理，却自有其玄机和意义，同时也不乏追随者的质疑和改良。因此对我所收集到的这方面的翔实材料，不管是通过了解传统还是认真阅读收集到的，我都要非常生动地加以复述，并在笔触所及的范围之内，尽可能形象地反映其高度和宽度。我也绝不会提出问题，而他们会提供大量高尚的事例，说明这样一个人的思想转变是如何激励他们把一切付诸文字的。他能产生影子，却无须借助太阳的帮助；他还能把影子打造成物质，也无须借助哲学的帮助。他特有的天赋在于将意象和寓言固化成文字，并把已成文的东西精炼成图景和秘诀。

杰克已将他父亲的遗嘱做成精致的副本，在一大张羊皮纸上工整誊清。由于下定决心扮演一个最孝顺的儿子，他成为可以想象的对遗嘱最关注的人。尽管其中关于那件外套的保养和穿着，我已多次告诉读者，是用非常直白、简单的语言写成，包括如何正确保管的说明以及服从和违反要求所带来的奖惩，然而他却开始接受一种奇想，认为这其中有更深的隐情，因而在最深处一定还有很多很多秘密。“先生们，”他说，“我要证明这张羊皮纸是肉、饮料、衣料，是魔法石和万能药。”在兴高采烈地说完这番话后，他决心将它用于人生必要的且最微不足道的场合。他有一种方法可以让它成为任何他所需要的形状，在他睡觉的时候它是睡帽，在下雨的时候它就是一把雨伞。如果某个脚趾疼，他会撕下一块包在那个脚趾上；如果痉挛突然发作，他就在鼻子底下焚烧它两英寸；如果他的胃感到胀满不适，就吞下落在一个银便士上的所有灰烬；所有这些都无不灵验。与这些文雅举止相应的是，他谈话的语言也完全是他意志的写照，而且他把自己的口才完全限制在这一领域范围内，不敢说出一个超出该范围、缺乏权威性的字眼。一次，在一个陌生的房子里，他的话突然被紧急情况打断，当时的情况不允许过于冗长的言语，他又缺乏机敏的反应，以在那种意外的场合得体地构思出一句要求走后门的权威短语，于是他只好选择最谨慎的做法，招致在此情况下常出现的处罚。从此人类所有修辞集之大成也不能让他把自己洗刷干净了，因为，在就此紧急事件查阅遗嘱的时候，他发现在接近末尾处有一个段落（不知是否誊写员自己添加的）似乎禁止这样做。

他把不在他的肉食面前祷告定为他的宗教生活的一部分，不由任何人分说，正如那句谚语所说，像基督徒的样子吃他的食物。

他有一种特别的嗜好，喜欢火中取栗[247]和吃燃烧着的蜡烛的紫色烛花。他能以难以想象的敏捷动作掐下灯花并吞下，这样他的肚子里就燃起一团永不熄灭的火，由于这团火，他的眼睛、鼻子和嘴里都不断冒烟，这使得他的头在黑夜里就像一头驴的颅骨。一个淘气的男孩在那里面放了一个小蜡烛，把他的君主陛下的臣民都吓了一跳。这样一来他回家就不需要其他东西照亮自己了，只是执着地说，一个聪明的人就是他自己的指路明灯。

走在大街上时他会闭上眼睛。如果他撞上柱子或掉进阴沟里，这两件事他总是会碰上一样或两样都碰上，他就会告诉在一旁讥讽他的学徒，他已无条件地将自己完全交托给了命运的安排或打击，并且通过长期的经验他早已发现，试图和命运抗争或躲避命运的打击都是徒劳的，无论谁胆敢尝试其中任何一样都必然碰得头破血流。“这是命中注定的，”他说，“在出生的前几天，我的鼻子与这个柱子就已注定有一场遭遇，因此大自然才会让我和它同时出现在这个世界上，让我和它成为同胞。现在，我的眼界打开了，事情很有可能比这更糟糕，一个具有敏锐眼光的人每天会遭遇多少次如此可诅咒的跌倒？此外，领略一切的眼睛只有在这些感官都脱离正轨的时候才最为敏锐。因此我们才会看到，比起那些过度相信并依赖视觉神经的人，盲人行走的步伐，及其行为与判断，都加倍小心。正常人的视觉神经会因极其微小的意外而失灵，一滴水或薄膜就能完全惑乱它；就好比一盏灯淹没在一群咆哮着冲上街头的恶霸中，把它自己及其主人都置于暴徒的拳打脚踢之下。而如果暴露的虚荣心受到抑制，他们走在黑暗中，就能够逃过一劫。再进一步说，如果我们留意观察那些受到赞誉的灯具的作用，定会看到它与其命运相比还要糟糕很多。的确，我是在柱子上碰伤了鼻子，但那是因为此时我的命运要么就是忘了，要么就是认为没有必要拉我一把，或给我以任何躲避的提醒。但是绝不能仅凭这一点就说服现代人或后人将鼻子交由眼睛做主，这可能是失去鼻子最迅捷的途径。哦，眼睛，你这盲目的领路人，我们脆弱的鼻子的可悲的监护者，照我说，你执着于映入视野的第一道悬崖，竟然把我们可怜的、听你摆布的身体拖向毁灭的边缘。啊！那边缘已经腐烂，我们脚下一滑，跌了下去，冲向一个海湾，沿途没有救命的灌木阻挡我们下滑；这下滑没有一个凡人的鼻子能够经受得住，除了银桥之主巨人劳尔卡库[248]的。因此，哦眼睛，最好不过，以伟大的正义的名义，你就好似在污秽和黑暗中给人照亮的愚蠢的灯，终让他们掉进深渊或可怕的沼泽。”

我所复述的杰克这番话，比起他本人杰出的口才，以及他在如此深奥问题上的推理能力，都不过是九牛一毛而已。

除此之外，在吸引热情方面，他还是一个伟大的设计者和改进者，他引入了一个新的神，此神已经会聚了一大批崇拜者，有的人称之为巴别塔[249]，有的人称之为混乱，它在索尔兹伯里平原[250]有一个哥特式结构的古老寺庙，以其圣殿的盛名和朝圣者的欢庆闻名于世。

当他要搞恶毒的恶作剧时，他便下弯膝盖，上翻眼睛，开始祈祷，哪怕正在水沟里。那些了解他的恶作剧的人都和他保持一定的安全距离；而每当陌生人被好奇心吸引，走到近前发笑或听他念祷词的时候，他会突然用一只手掏出钻头并把尿全撒在他们的眼睛里，周围的所有其他人也用泥浆溅污他们。

冬天他只穿很薄而且宽松的衣服，并且不扣扣子，以让周围的热量进入，夏天他穿很厚并包裹严实的衣服，以阻隔周围的热量。

在政府所有的革命时期，他总能让自己的辩词成为绞刑司令官的公文，而在行刑之际，他要做的十分拿手的事情不是别的，唯有长长祈祷而已。[251]

他有一个肌肉发达而活动灵敏的舌头，伸出来能够到他的鼻子，并从那里发出奇特的演讲。在这些王国里他也是第一个开始改善西班牙在驴叫方面成果的人，他自己的大耳朵永远都竖立着暴露在外，他把这项艺术演绎得如此完美，以至于要想通过观察或听声音来区分原身和替身，有非常大的难度。

他受到一种疾病的困扰，这种病与所谓的被狼蛛叮咬的情况正好相反，会在听到音乐，尤其是一组风笛的声音之后变得像疯狗一样。[252]但是他又可以通过到威斯敏斯特大厅，或到比林斯格特[253]，或到一个寄宿学校，或到皇家交易所，或到政府咖啡屋里转两三圈治好这种病。

他并不是一个害怕颜色的人，但是非常讨厌所有的颜色，[254]并且由于这个原因，他极度厌恶画家，厌恶之深使他走在街上发作的时候，会在口袋里塞满石头，一看到图画就向它投掷。

由于这种生活方式，他十分频繁地清洗自己。他经常会跳入没过头顶的水中，[255]哪怕是在冬季，但出来的时候总是注定比下去的时候更脏，如果他还能更脏的话。

他是第一个发现从耳朵输入催眠药剂秘方的人，它是一种复合剂，包括硫黄和基列[256]乳香，外加一点大便。

他腹部贴着一大块人造刺激性材料的膏药，它的烧灼作用可以使他发出呻吟，就像著名的肉砧板受到炽热的烙铁的炙烤。

他会站在街头的转角处，呼喊经过那里的行人，对一个大叫说：“尊贵的先生，请在我的皮套裤上狠狠打一巴掌。”一会又对另一个说：“我忠诚的朋友，请在我的屁股上踢一脚。夫人，我能恳求你高抬贵手赏我一记可爱的耳光吗？高贵的船长，为了上帝的爱，请痛打我一顿吧，用你的拐杖打在我可怜的肩头。”[257]当他用这番诚挚的恳求换来一顿痛打，足以让自己的思想和身体都充分膨胀以后，他就会带着莫大的安慰回到家中，用惊人的话语表达自己给公众利益带来好处。“看看这些伤痕”，他边说边露出肩头，“是一个可恶的土耳其士兵今天早上七点钟给我留下的。当时我费尽力气才把这土耳其壮汉赶走。邻居们，请再看这里，我的头也得到应有的重创，如果可怜的杰克的头再软一点，那你们早就会看到教皇和法国国王在你的妻子和你的仓库中间了。[258]亲爱的基督徒们，伟大的莫卧儿[259]也已经到来，到达白教堂了，却没有吞噬男人、女人和孩子们（上帝保佑我们）！你们得感谢我这可怜的身体。”

非常值得注意的一点是，杰克和他的兄弟彼得彼此之间看似甚至有几分虚假的厌恶或反感有一种非凡的效果。[260]彼得最近因为一些恶行不得不潜逃，并且，因为害怕警察，他不到天黑很少外出。他们俩的住所是这座城市的两个相隔最遥远的角落，每当他们的机缘或志趣驱使他们去国外，他们总会选择最不适合的时间，以及他们可以想到的最怪异的路线，为的就是避开对方。然而，尽管采取了这些办法，相遇却是他们永恒的宿命。这其中的原因很容易理解，因为他们的狂热和脾性都有相同的基础，我们可以把他俩看作一个圆规的两只脚，扩展程度相同，且全都固定在同一个中轴上，尽管开始移动的方向相反，但终将在圆周的某个点上会合。此外，最为不幸的是，杰克还与他的兄弟彼得极其相似。他们不仅在志趣和性情上相同，而且在形态、身材和相貌上也十分接近。两人的相似度是如此之高，以至于无比频繁发生的情况是，一个法警抓住杰克的肩膀大叫道：“彼得，你是国王的犯人。”还有一次，彼得的一个最亲近的朋友张开双臂欢迎杰克，并说：“亲爱的彼得，我真高兴看到你，你的祈祷给了我对付蠕虫的美妙良方。”这，我们不难看出，就是杰克苦苦经营了这么长时间所得到的难堪的回报，他看到自己所有努力是如何与他许给自己的唯一目的和意图相抵触，可怎样才能避免如此可怕的效果对他这样一个脑袋和心脏的冲击呢？不幸的是，他那件可怜的外套上残留着所有惩罚，东方升起的太阳走进他生活，每一天都让它们显现无遗。他雇了一个裁缝帮他缝补衣领，可是这让领口变得很紧，几乎使他窒息，还让他的眼珠子凸了出来，乍一看全是眼白。对于衣服所剩无几的主体部分，他每天要在粗糙墙壁上摩擦两个小时，以磨掉残余的花边和刺绣；但同时持续施以相当的暴力，就像对待一个异教的哲学家。然而，所做的这一切结果仍然令他大失所望。因为一般来说，破烂衣服在本质上与华丽衣服很有相似之处，两者从外表上看都飘着很多零碎儿，这在一定的距离之外，或在光线不好的情况下，或对于视力较差的人来说，并不容易分辨清楚。因而在这些情况下，杰克和他的破衣服给人的第一印象是一种很可笑的炫耀打扮，衬托出他十分类似的人品和气质，却挫败了他的一切试图制造区别的努力，并使他们二人如此相似，以至于他们各自的信徒都常常被彻底蒙骗了。Desunt non-nulla.[261]

有句古老的斯拉夫尼亚谚语说得好，对付人和对付驴一样，要想稳稳操控他们就必须有一个控制他们耳朵的好方法。而我认为，我们完全可以相信此说得到了这样一条经验的反复证实：

——Effugiet tamen haec sceleratus vincula Proteus.[262]

因此，广泛阅读我们祖先中不同人物和不同时期的格言对我们大有裨益。因为，如果看一看原始记录，我们就会发现，没有任何革命的规模和频繁程度可以和人类的耳朵相比拟。以前曾经有一个抓住耳朵不放的奇特发明，我认为，我们完全可以理直气壮地认为那是artes perditae[263]，对此，考虑到这一艺术在后来的世纪里不仅减少到非常可悲的程度，而且那些少数流传下来的也退化到只会嘲笑我们鼎盛时期的高超技巧，难道还有什么可怀疑的吗？假如仅切掉一只雄鹿的一只耳朵就可以让这一非遗传缺陷传遍整座森林，那我们为什么还要惊叹在我们的先人和我们自己的耳朵上所发生的如此复杂的修剪和切割的神工呢？的确，在我们这个岛屿靠美德统治的时期，许多的努力都致力于提高我们耳朵的再生长。其比例之巨大不仅对于外向的人来说是一种显摆，而且对于内向的人也是一种恩典。此外，自然主义者认为，如果在身体的上半部分有一些东西隆起的话，比如耳朵和鼻子，那么在下半身也必然有对偶。因此，在那真正虔诚的时代，每一次集会，仗着天赋，男人们总是很开放地暴露自己的耳朵及其对偶部位。因为希波克拉底[264]告诉我们，一旦耳朵后面的静脉被切断，男人就会变成阉人；而女人们在用它们来领悟和教化的时候一点不落后，和那些已经使用某法的人有关的女人们，非常关切地环顾四周，希望通过这样一个构想——其他人——怀上一个合意的后代；那些乐善好施的候选人很多，务必要选耳朵最大的，那样种群就不会因他们而退化。最后，这些虔诚的姐妹们都将该部位所有非凡的膨胀视为凸显热情或精神的寄托物，并像接受恩典一般由衷赞许她们坐上的每个人头，特别是传教士的，他的耳朵通常是最大的。因此，他总是频繁而明确无误地将所有优点示人，而在他诗兴大发的时候会头头是道地谈论一件，有时也谈论另一件。从这一习惯衍生出了布道的整个过程，并在那些行业人士中一直延续至今，其风格可以用短语头头是道来形容。

这就是圣徒们用以增大那部位的整个过程，并认为它在任何情况下都灵验。但前提是，在时间的长河中不要出现一位残酷的国王[265]。他曾提出一套血腥的迫害计划，直指一切超过一定指标的耳朵，因此有些人喜欢用黑布或帽子把他们的突出物包起来，有人干脆用假发遮盖。这些耳朵有的被割掉，有的被斜着剪去，而大多数被连根切除。但是在我的有关耳朵历史的简单回顾中，我临时决定把后话交由公众去接续。

从以上简短的有关耳朵早先的受难史，以及将它们过去生长的情况搬到现实中的小小努力中显然可以看出，我们能够依赖一个如此短小、如此脆弱、如此光滑之物的理由，实在微乎其微，任何人要想紧紧抓住别人，都必须借助其他方法。其实，一个观察人性足够细心的人会发现很多抓手，其中人的六种感官的每一种都是一个，此外还有连接激情的许多抓手，以及连接智慧的若干抓手。说到最后这些抓手，好奇心是其中之一，并且，与所有其他的相比，它抓得最牢靠。对于一个生性懒惰、缺乏耐心、呼噜连天的读者来说，好奇心是策马的马刺，是嚼口的辔头，是穿鼻的铜环。一位作家有了这样的抓手就肯定能够抓住读者，在这点上一旦找对了路，那么对方的所有反抗和挣扎都无济于事，只能成为任他摆布的阶下囚，直到他因为累了或厌烦而放手的时候。

因此，作为这篇无比玄妙文章作者的我，就是因为在这里采用了上述抓手，这才超乎想象地牢牢抓住了我可爱的读者。其实我早就该放手了，但我一直都不十分情愿，让他们在追随本书仅剩的部分的时候被带入我们与生俱来的冷漠中。我只能说，尊敬的读者，为了你我的安宁，我的心病与你完全一样，害怕失去或弄乱我的稿纸，也就是我这些故事的剩余部分。这些故事充满了意外事件、转折和冒险，它们既新奇、出乎意料，其所有关键点又都在情理之中，符合我们这个高尚时代的精致口味。但是很可惜，现在我只能尽我最大努力归结众多头绪中的几个了。其中包括有关彼得是如何得到国王的木凳的保护的完整描述[266]，以及他与杰克在他们共同的一项计划上取得的一致，那就是，在某个风雨交加的夜晚，将兄弟马丁引诱到负债人拘留所，扒光他身上的所有衣服；马丁如何全力以赴向他们展示他的一双美妙的鞋跟[267]；一项新的反对彼得的授权如何出台，如何使杰克一瘸一拐地离开彼得，并偷走了他的保护符据为己用；杰克服饰的碎布条如何在宫廷和城市成为时尚，他如何骑上一匹高头大马[268]并吃上奶油蛋羹[269]等等。关于所有这一切（以及其他一些我一时想不起来的故事）的细节，全部都无可挽回地被遗忘了。这一莫大的遗憾定将让我的读者们相互扼腕叹息。但是如果他们认同以下忠告符合他们的若干基本准则，并看在这本书从开篇到此处在我们之间业已建立的友谊的魔力的份上，请不要对意外事件反应过度以致对健康产生不可逆的损害——现在我要尽一位成名作家的在程序上的义务，完成此书的最后部分了，这是一位有尊严的现代人一定不能忽略的。

结语

不论做任何事情，如果拖的时间太长，都会很容易，但不一定经常，和做的时间太短一样，半途而废。对于脑力劳动，尤其如此。那位高尚的耶稣会士[270]（但愿他的心灵得到安息）率先大胆以书面形式承认，图书必须和服饰、饮食以及娱乐一样符合季节性的要求，并让其形式和法国其他事物相比得到更大的改善，更好地服务于我们高尚的民族。而我要斋戒到一本错过潮流的书被人遗忘的时候，就像白天的月亮，过汛期一周的鲭鱼。没有人会像购进这本书的书商一样在乎我们的天气，他略微懂得在一个干旱的时节应该推出什么样的图书，并在晴雨表预示大雨将至之前摆在最显眼的位置。[271]当他看到这部作品，并将它与他的历书核对之后，他明白告诉我说，他已经明确考虑过篇幅和主题这两件最为重要的事情，并认为除非再等很长一段时间，且必须等到出现一个对于芜菁甘蓝[272]来说是非常艰难的一年，它才会有销路。对此，由于我的希求十分迫切，我想知道，如果在这个月出版，他认为还要什么条件。他往西面看了看回答我说：“我估计不会出现坏天气。但是如果你能找到一个引人入胜的名目（但不是诗），或在……上的简短的叙述，那它八成会形成燎原之势。但是如果它销售不畅，其实我已经雇了一位作家在写一篇反驳本特利博士的文章，我相信它一定有利可图。”

我们商议了很久才达成一项权宜之计，就是如果来了这样一位顾客，充满信心地希望了解作者，他就随便挑选一个当周时尚排行榜上的智者名字，并像私密好友般地说给他。而如果德弗[273]的最新剧目正好在榜上，那我倒更乐意他是康格里夫[274]。这，我要说，是因为我对我可敬的读者的口味有透彻的了解，并且通常都带着极大的兴趣观看一只被从蜂蜜罐上赶走的胃口极佳的苍蝇，直接落在大便上享用美餐。[275]我要对所谓深奥作家这一话题说几句话，这样的作家最近数量骤增，而且我非常清楚，明智的世人都决定将我也归于这一类。因此我认为，说到深奥，它和作家的关系就如同它和井的关系。一个眼力很好的人能看到最深的井底，除非井里有水。而常见的情况是，当井底干燥得除了泥土一无所有的时候，哪怕它距离地面只有一码半的深度，也会有人认为它深不可测，其原因再简单不过，因为那里漆黑一团。下面我想尝试分析一个在现代作家中十分常见的现象，就是不知所云：在已经把某个话题说透了以后，仍然不肯停笔。有人称之为智慧心魔，在身体死去之后它仍旧继续前行。说真的，在需要的时候，似乎没有什么知识比辨识能力掌握在更少人的手里。一个作家在写完一本书的时候，他和他的读者就已经成为相识已久、不忍分别的老朋友了。因此我时常把写作想象成参观，告别时的繁文缛节或许比先前的所有谈话更冗长。一篇文章的结尾类似一个人生命的尽头，也有人将它比作宴会的结束，其中的大多数人都对分手心有不甘，ut plenus vitae conviva[276]。因为人们在酒足饭饱以后往往喜欢坐下来，哪怕只是打盹或小睡，以打发当天剩余的时光。但是，在最后这点上我和其他作家截然不同。如果，通过我所有的努力，我能对人类如此躁动不安的休息有所贡献的话，那就太让我喜出望外了。我认为这对于一个人们想象中的智者的作为来说并非离经叛道。因为在希腊有一个十分懂礼貌的民族，曾为睡眠[277]和缪斯女神[278]建立起同样神圣的殿堂，并相信这两个神之间业已建立起最牢固的友谊。

对我的读者我还有最后一个请求，希望你不要指望从这本书的每一行或每一页都得到同样多的乐趣和教益，请给作者留一些使小性或偶尔不着调的空间，同时也给自己留一些同样的空间。用这样的心态认真思考一下：你在不论恶劣的天气里还是阴雨天走在一条街道上，对那些闲居之人从窗口发出的对你在此种状况下的步态或衣着的指指点点，要能够坦然面对。

在运用头脑的策略上，我的观点是，标新立异的才是主人，至于寻找适当的方法和理由，那是仆人的事情。我之所以这样分类的原因，从我时常想要卖弄智慧的特定事实上看，是因为我在很多情况下既不聪明，也不完美，更词不达意。[279]而对于现代人无视任何这种概率的做法，我是绝对忠实的执行者，不论执行它们的痛苦有多大，或有多么不合时宜。因为从我努力搜集的七百三十八条杰出现代作家的至理名言中，包括通过细细的研读消化而形成的我这本平常的小书，我发现，我经过五年努力所找到的能够塞进日常谈话中的书，不超过一打。而在这一打中又有半数因对象不合适而失败，剩余的一半我费尽心机，采用各种手段予以推荐，可最后我还是决定放弃了。正是这种必然由我承担的失望（恕我直言），给我带来了最初的修成作家的启示。从那时起，在我的一些特定朋友中，我发现这成为他们普遍的抱怨，而在我其他的朋友中，情况也变得基本类似。因为我提到很多有价值的、却在推理中被遗忘或摒弃的词语，在印刷品中获准同意或优先采用后，都顺利通过并得到认可和尊重。而由于得到出版商的特许和鼓励，我已成为用它们渲染各色事件和情节的绝对的主人，以展示我获得的所有才华。我早已发现我所作observanda[280]的出版对于收获来说已太过冗长。因此我需要暂停一下，直到通过触摸世界和我自己的脉搏，我发现新的必须动笔的机会。

[1]本书早期版本的前言比较长，这里仅保留了其中第一段。——译者注

[2]英国议会的一般性会议，斯威夫特曾多次指责其为党派自我标榜的现成发明。——译者注

[3]霍布斯（Thomas Hobbes，1588—1679），英国政治哲学家。其代表作《利维坦》（Leviathan）包括“论人”“论国家”“论基督教国家”和“论黑暗王国”四个部分。——译者注

[4]利维坦是海中怪兽的名字，《圣经》中邪恶的象征。——译者注

[5]英国人文主义者、政治家、作家托马斯·莫尔（1477—1535）曾用“澡盆故事”（a tale of a tub）一语来形容无聊的谈话。这一短语还曾被英国著名演员本杰明·琼森（1572—1637）和小说家丹尼尔·笛福（1659—1731）等人使用过。在作者所处的时代，澡盆的形状类似一只大木桶。——译者注

[6]拉丁文，意为：逃到上层空间去，这就是任务，这就是工作。出自维吉尔（Virgil）的叙事诗《埃涅伊德》（Aeneid）6.128-9。

[7]苏格拉底（Socrates，公元前469—前399），古希腊哲学家。阿里斯托芬曾在剧作《云》中揶揄他的“新式教育法”。——译者注

[8]讲道坛指的是教堂里供讲道教士站立的高于听众的小台子（暗指教士）；作者下文还提到，讲道坛很像用于示众的颈手枷。梯子是用来爬上高台的（暗指死刑罪犯）。十八世纪英国常见的绞架和强迫死刑犯爬上绞架的梯子与此相似。巡回台指的舞台上的演员。作者自己曾解释说，它指的是“江湖骗子”。因为它也有“舞台”的意思，因此在下文作者才会联想到剧场的舞台。——译者注

[9]此处原文为bar，围栏，指法庭上围住法官和律师所坐位置的区域。这个词还指法律工作或职业。——译者注

[10]这里指在法庭辩论中律师经常相互打断对方的话。——译者注

[11]这里指法官。他们在庭审过程中坐在木凳（bench）上。——译者注

[12]腓尼基是古代犹太民族文明的发祥地，腓尼基语属于闪语族。——译者注

[13]拉丁文，意为“可以让老年人悠闲安逸地休息”。出自贺拉斯（Horace）的《讽刺诗集》（Satires）1.1.31.

[14]此处暗指的是当时的主要教派热衷的与“三”有关的争论，如“三位一体”“三神论”等。——译者注

[15]此处指梯子旁侧张贴的海报，上面写有将被绞死的罪犯的最后陈词。这种海报在当时定期出版。斯威夫特本人曾于1722年写过一篇假想的“最后陈词”。另见有关“梯子”的前注。——译者注

[16]拉丁文，意为“阴雨天空下，交叉路口旁”。

[17]伊壁鸠鲁（Epicurus，约公元前342—前270），古希腊杰出唯物主义和无神论者。——译者注

[18]拉丁文，意为：我们必须承认声音也是物质的，因为它能刺激感官。出自卢克莱修（Lucretius）的《物性论》（De Rerum Natura）4.526-7。

[19]英国伊丽莎白时期剧场的观众席通常有若干层，这里指的是其中最高、票价低廉的一层。——译者注

[20]朽木能发出磷光。此处暗指教士（教会）所声称的“指引人走向光明”一类的说法。——译者注

[21]此处暗示教会的腐朽。——译者注

[22]作者此处暗讽狂热的教士虽然心中有一团火，头脑却空洞无物，因而其作品有两种命运：要么被烧掉，要么被虫蛀。——译者注

[23]意为“此处原稿有脱漏”。在手稿中有意留下缺陷是斯威夫特喜用的伎俩。

[24]拉丁文，意为“祈求”。这里指陈词结束时的狂热呼号。——译者注

[25]指刽子手行刑。——译者注

[26]拉丁文，意思分别为“你的”和“我的”。整句大意为，由于绞刑犯的抢劫罪行，因而混淆了所有权的归属。——译者注

[27]伦敦市的一个行政区，英国议会所在地。——译者注

[28]Grub-street原为伦敦一条街的名字，因这里的住户大多因写野史和小品而得名。此后任何无价值的作品都被称为文丐作品。——译者注

[29]此处原文为scythe，指死神所用的把人钩下地狱的类似镰刀的工具。它如果钝了就不容易钩到人了。——译者注

[30]在格雷沙姆学院（Gresham Collage）聚会的英国皇家学会。——译者注

[31]威尔（Will）在女修道院花园所开的咖啡屋。此处作者借它和格雷沙姆学院暗讽当时所有的文艺界和科学界名流，称他们都师承“文丐”。——译者注

[32]此处指的是阿基米德所说的“给我一个支点，我将撬动地球”。——译者注

[33]此处原文为sack-posset，其中sack为产自西班牙Madeira岛的一种白葡萄酒，posset为一种传统的乳制饮料。——译者注

[34]毕达哥拉斯（Pythagoras，约公元前580—约前500），古希腊哲学家、数学家。——译者注

[35]伊索（Aesop，约6世纪），古希腊寓言作家，相传原为奴隶，善讲故事，讽刺权贵。有《伊索寓言》传世。——译者注

[36]列那狐（Reynard the Fox）的故事源于希腊罗马的口头传说，讽刺中世纪动物故事组诗中的主角。——译者注

[37]Tom Thumb，瓦格斯塔夫（Wagstaffe）所作的寓言故事，完成于1711年，内容是讥讽严肃古板。——译者注

[38]故事中的拇指先生因只有拇指大小，经常被人吞掉，但是又总能活着回来参与另一个故事。——译者注

[39]阿提庇乌斯（Artephius，生卒年月不详），一位生活于12世纪前后的炼金术士，他在一篇文章中自称活了1025岁。其作品的法文版曾一度较为流行。——译者注

[40]在马洛（Marlowe）所著的《浮士德》中，浮士德盼望得到世界上最美的女子。于是特洛伊的海伦（传说中世上最美的女子）就出现在了他的面前。——译者注

[41]Whittington and His Cat，见于公元14世纪的一本民间故事，讲述了惠灵顿通过将猫卖给老鼠肆虐的国家而从穷小子变成富有商人，后来成为伦敦早期市长的故事。——译者注

[42]The Hind and Panther，约翰·德莱顿于1687年所作的著名诗篇。参见下文有关其人的注释。——译者注

[43]斯科图斯（Dun Scotus，生卒年月不详），著名神学家。——译者注

[44]贝拉明（Robert Bellarmin，1542—1621），意大利枢机主教、神学家，在欧洲宗教运动改革时期为天主教辩护。——译者注

[45]Tommy Pots，当时流行的一首抒情诗歌。——译者注

[46]此处原文为meal-tubs，应指Meal-tub Plot，系1678年查理二世执政时期揭露出的一个假想的谋杀他的“天主教阴谋”。——译者注

[47]德莱顿（John Dryden，1631—1700），英国17世纪后期最伟大的诗人，写过三十多部悲、喜剧和大量诗歌。——译者注

[48]暗指德莱顿为得到赞助曾将自己翻译的维吉尔的作品献给多位伯爵、侯爵等要人。下文提到的把文章分成四十份等语也与此有关。——译者注

[49]本书下文提到了他们的名字。其中彼得暗指罗马天主教会，马丁（路德）暗指英国国教教会，杰克（喀尔文）暗指新教后裔。

[50]这三个名字原文为法文，意思分别为贪婪、野心和狂妄。

[51]此处原文为chocolate-house，是当时对“咖啡屋”的雅称，社会精英聚会的地方。——译者注

[52]拉丁文，意为“在露天”。通常的皇室接见活动都在室内进行，不可能在露天。——译者注

[53]此处作者有意把鹰说成鹅。——译者注

[54]拉丁文，意为“稍逊一等的神”。——译者注

[55]此处作者意在讥讽古代的神可由于任何奇怪的原因而被人崇拜。——译者注

[56]拉丁文，意为“首动”，指地球最外面的可动层。此说源自古希腊天文学家托勒密的宇宙理论，认为地球是宇宙的中心。——译者注

[57]拉丁文，意为“条件”或“基本原理”。——译者注

[58]拉丁文，意为“来自父母的灵魂”。——译者注

[59]以上几段作者有意模仿教义争论的语气，将争论的主要焦点——灵魂和道德比作时尚和服饰，并为下文作铺垫。——译者注

[60]法文，指时尚妇女早晨在卧室进行的社交聚会。——译者注

[61]通常船夫应坐在客人后面。——译者注

[62]拉丁文，意为“在这些文字中”。——译者注

[63]拉丁文，意为“在这些音节中”。——译者注

[64]拉丁文，意为“第三种方法”。——译者注

[65]拉丁文，意为“在这些字母中。”——译者注

[66]这几个英文字母拼起来意为“肩”（shoulder）。——译者注

[67]“肩章”一词的英语为shoulder-knot，后半部分开头的字母为k。——译者注

[68]拉丁文，亦作Kalendae，意为“每月的第一天”。——译者注

[69]拉丁文，意为“在一些古老典籍中”。——译者注

[70]拉丁文，意为“父亲授予的权利”。——译者注

[71]拉丁文，意为“毫无声息”。——译者注

[72]拉丁文，意为“在一定程度上影响主旨”。

[73]拉丁文，意为“亚里士多德的逻辑学”。——译者注

[74]拉丁文，意为“解释”。——译者注

[75]拉丁文，意为“可分为两类”。——译者注

[76]拉丁文，意为“如果在口头遗嘱里曾提到同样的内容，那就可以拒绝”。

[77]此处暗示对地狱心存敬畏，抑制肉欲。——译者注

[78]拉丁文，意为“有所保留”。——译者注

[79]拉丁文，意为“来自要职”。——译者注

[80]拉丁文，意为“父亲赋予的权利”。——译者注

[81]拉丁文，意为“在这些文字中”。——译者注

[82]拉丁文，意为“将造成混乱”。——译者注

[83]暗指在罗马帝国率先确立基督教合法地位的君士坦丁大帝。——译者注

[84]莫摩斯（Momus），希腊神话中的非难、指责与嘲弄之神。——译者注

[85]从这些名字的拼音上看，它们从古希腊人名逐渐越来越像现代普通英国人名。——译者注

[86]赫克勒斯（Hercules），希腊和罗马神话中力大无比的英雄，宙斯与阿尔克墨涅之子。——译者注

[87]特修斯（Theseus），希腊神话中雅典的英雄和国王，他杀了米诺陶并统一阿提卡。——译者注

[88]珀尔修斯（Perseus），希腊神话中宙斯之子，杀死女怪美杜莎的英雄。——译者注

[89]希腊神话中赫克勒斯因爱上伊俄勒而遭到妻子得伊阿尼拉的嫉恨，她给他送去一件沾有剧毒血的长袍，赫克勒斯一触到它即死去。——译者注

[90]卡科斯（Cacus），古罗马宗教所信奉的神，根据罗马诗人维吉尔的描写，他是火神伏尔甘的儿子，生性邪恶，偷走巨人的牛群藏于山洞，后因一母牛嗥叫而被赫丘利发现，将其杀死。——译者注

[91]海德拉（Hydra），希腊神话中的九头怪蛇。——译者注

[92]奥吉亚斯（Augeas），希腊神话中的厄利斯王，拥有大群牲畜，曾命令赫克勒斯在一日之内把他全部肮脏无比的厩房打扫干净。——译者注

[93]斯廷法罗斯鸟（Stymphalian bird），希腊神话中破坏庄稼和果实的凶悍的大鸟，翅膀、爪子和喙都是金属的。厄利斯王要求赫克勒斯完成的十二项任务之一就是射杀此鸟。——译者注

[94]针对十七世纪作家多有动辄征引古人的习惯，作者在这里有意反说是现代人教育了古人。——译者注

[95]此处原文为Hieroglyph，指古埃及象形文字，亦指任何意义不明确的符号。——译者注

[96]作者在这里讽刺的是，古代作家虽然谈论批评，却不敢超出古代神话和埃及象形文字的范畴。——译者注

[97]保萨尼阿斯（Pausanias，？—约公元前470），古埃及旅行家和地质学家。——译者注

[98]阿戈斯（Argos），古希腊的一个城邦，位于伯罗奔尼撒半岛东北部，靠近阿尔戈利斯湾。青铜器时代早期开始有人居住，在斯巴达兴盛前是古希腊最强盛的城邦之一。——译者注

[99]纳夫普里亚人（Nauplians），希腊重镇纳夫普里亚（位于伯罗奔尼撒半岛，曾归属阿戈斯）城中的居民。——译者注

[100]“驴”的英文是ass。而原文在这里（包括下面几次提到的“驴”）用了大写的ASS，似与作者所说的“象形文字”（以驴暗指批评家）有关。——译者注

[101]希罗多德（Herodotus，约公元前485—约前425），希腊历史学家。——译者注

[102]拉丁文，意为“创新”。——译者注

[103]莱比亚（Lybia），似为虚构的地名。——译者注

[104]克特西亚斯（Ctesias，公元前416—？），古希腊医生和研究埃及与印度的历史学家。——译者注

[105]犄角和胆汁等语暗合前面讲的“多余的枝桠”。——译者注

[106]锡西厄人（Scythians），古代居住在西徐亚的游牧民族中的一员。——译者注

[107]狄奥多罗斯（Diodorus，约公元前4世纪），古希腊历史学家，美加拉学派哲学家。——译者注

[108]埃利孔（Helicon），希腊的山名，两股神圣泉水的发源地。——译者注

[109]卢克莱修（Lucretius，约公元前93—约前50），古希腊哲学家、历史学家、诗人。——译者注

[110]拉丁文，意为：在埃利孔的高山上竟有一种树，其花朵的气味可以杀死一个人。出自卢克莱修的《物性论》6.774-5.

[111]泰伦提乌斯（Terence，公元前186—前161），罗马共和国时期著名的剧作家。——译者注

[112]拉丁文，意为“恶毒的”。——译者注

[113]地米斯托克利（Themistocles，约公元前524—约前460），希腊政治家，将军，据说他受到底层民众的拥戴，却经常和贵族产生摩擦。——译者注

[114]拉丁文，意为“没有水银”。——译者注

[115]作者的语言总是充满揶揄的口气和反语。上段末句系有意反说，实指批评家的第一个目标也可能找错，此段末句意为国王在批评家眼里总是最肮脏的。——译者注

[116]拉丁文，意为天主教认为的在天堂和地狱之间的“炼狱”。

[117]这里指忏悔和赎罪。

[118]即忏悔室。

[119]即放任它们。

[120]即圣水。

[121]“金羊毛”的故事来自古希腊神话和传说。佛里克索斯被一只神赐的金毛羊所救。后他将羊献祭给宙斯，金羊毛则给了埃厄特斯国王，后者又将金羊毛转献给战神阿瑞斯。阿瑞斯把它钉在阿瑞斯圣林中一棵橡树上，让火龙看守。全世界都相信这金羊毛是无价之宝，许多英雄和王子都梦寐以求。忒萨利亚王子伊阿宋曾带着希腊众英雄坐着大船阿耳戈斯号前往科尔喀斯去取金羊毛，并与火龙搏斗。此处作者将公牛说成源自火龙系有意调侃。——译者注

[122]古代地理学中黑海东端高加索南部的三角地带，在希腊神话中它是美狄亚的故乡，阿耳戈斯英雄们的目的地，一块非常富饶和巫术盛行的地方。——译者注

[123]贺拉斯（Horace，公元前65—前8），古罗马杰出诗人、讽刺作家。——译者注

[124]拉丁文，意为“身披五色翎毛”。

[125]拉丁文，意为“下肢的形状像一条黑鱼。”以上两句出自贺拉斯（Horace）的《歌集》（Ars Poetica）第三卷，2-4.

[126]此处原文为bull-beggar，英语俚语，指可怕的妖怪或智力低下的人。——译者注

[127]此处原文为bull-dog，为一种头大、嘴扁、腿短的强壮、凶猛的狗。——译者注

[128]英国伦敦西面的著名监狱。——译者注

[129]拉丁文，意为“彻底说服”。——译者注

[130]拉丁文，意为“秘密”。——译者注

[131]拉丁文，意为“影射”。——译者注

[132]暗指罗马教皇象征无上权力的三重冕。——译者注

[133]拉丁文，意为“动作”。——译者注

[134]此处原文如此，似与前文有矛盾。因前文曾说这三兄弟分不清长幼。——译者注

[135]拉丁文，意为“权威版本”。——译者注

[136]拉丁文，意为：这使我勇于承担任何使命，指引我在宁静的夜中搜寻。出自卢克莱修的《物性论》1.141-2.

[137]拉丁文，意为“甜蜜的”。——译者注

[138]本特利（Richard Bentley，1662—1742），英国古典学研究史上的一位重要人物，英国剑桥大学三一学院的创始人，学识渊博，长于典籍校勘，著有《致约翰·穆勒书》《图斯库路姆论辩集》等书。——译者注

[139]拉丁文，意为“放进注满热水的浴缸”。——译者注

[140]拉丁文，意为“足量的”。——译者注

[141]此处原文为Lethe，忘川，忘却之河，是希腊神话中冥府的五条河流之一。——译者注

[142]拉丁文，意为“糟粕”。——译者注

[143]拉丁文，意为“残渣”，亦指炼金术过程中产生的废料。——译者注

[144]古希腊的重量单位。——译者注

[145]拉丁文，意为“杰出的专家”。——译者注

[146]拉丁文，意为“其他方面专家一览”。——译者注

[147]拉丁文，意为“怪异”。——译者注

[148]荷马（Homer，约前9世纪——前8世纪），古希腊游吟诗人，创作了西方文学最伟大的两部作品《伊利亚特》和《奥德赛》。——译者注

[149]拉丁文，意为“巨著”。——译者注

[150]森迪沃格斯（Sendivogus，生卒年月不详），著名的波兰炼金术士和化学家。——译者注

[151]贝曼（Behmen，生卒年月不详），德国基督教神学家。——译者注

[152]《灵智魔学》（Anthroposophia Theomagica），威尔士哲学家、诗人托马斯·沃恩（Thomas Vaughan）所著，主要内容为研究自然魔幻以及精神与自然一体化。——译者注

[153]拉丁文，意思不详，似指“圆形物体”。——译者注

[154]拉丁文，意为“那么我几乎不相信这位作者曾片刻感受到激情的力量”。

[155]应为威廉·沃顿（William Wotton，生卒年月不详），与作者同时代的一位神学家。——译者注

[156]这里作者将沃顿说成“学士”系有意打趣。——译者注

[157]汞中毒可引起大量唾液分泌。——译者注

[158]此处作者意在调侃那些喜欢（在前言中）对自己作品自吹自擂的作家。——译者注

[159]伊奥利亚（Aeolists）是古希腊在小亚细亚的西北部沿海地区的一个殖民地，荷马在作品中也曾提到此地。——译者注

[160]拉丁文，意为“按缪斯女神的引诱触摸一切”。出自卢克莱修的《物性论》4.9。

[161]荷马史诗《伊利亚特》的篇幅很长。——译者注

[162]希腊神话中，赫克勒斯的第十个任务是到世界的尽头抓捕吉里昂的公牛，一种有三个身体的怪兽。——译者注

[163]拉丁语，意为“生殖器”。——译者注

[164]拉丁语，意为“但他们的生殖器却非常巨大，直达脚踝”。——译者注

[165]西徐亚人（Scythians）是公元前9世纪以前生活在阿尔泰山以东地区的游牧民族。——译者注

[166]拉丁文，意为“基础”。——译者注

[167]此处指接受知识的不同方法。——译者注

[168]西徐亚在希腊北面。在作者所处的时代写作还用鹅毛笔。——译者注

[169]拉丁文，意为“但愿指引我们的命运不要让这样的命运靠近我们”。出自卢克莱修《物性论》5.108。

[170]拉丁文，意为“追随者”。——译者注

[171]拉丁文，意为“世界之灵”。——译者注

[172]拉丁文，意为“获悉的形态”。——译者注

[173]拉丁文，分别为“精神”、“意识”、“灵感”和“灵魂”。——译者注

[174]拉丁文，意为“肿胀”。——译者注

[175]拉丁文，意为“膨胀”。——译者注

[176]拉丁文，意为“生殖或喷射器官”。——译者注

[177]拉丁文，意为“最初成分”。——译者注

[178]拉丁文，意为“意识”。——译者注

[179]拉丁文，意为“四大原则”。——译者注

[180]帕拉切尔苏斯（Bumbastus Palacelsus，1493—1541），出生于艾恩西德伦（今瑞士）的医师，炼金家，曾发明多种新药。——译者注

[181]拉丁文，意为“基本成分”。——译者注

[182]此处原文为belching。作者自己曾解释说，它指的是“牧师在古希腊圣贤殿堂向古人发出预言时的动作”。——译者注

[183]拉丁文，意为“对全能的天主顶礼膜拜”。——译者注

[184]拉丁文，意为“北，诸神中最杰出的一位”。——译者注

[185]拉丁文，意为“至高的天”。古人认为天共有十一重，而上帝和天使处在这至高的一重。——译者注

[186]希腊文，意为“黑暗、阴暗、夜晚”。——译者注

[187]潘西罗鲁斯（Pancirolus，生卒年月不详），希腊哲学家，《失传与新发明的艺术》（DeArtibusperditis，＆c.）一书的作者。——译者注

[188]埃俄罗斯（Aeolus），希腊神话中的风神。——译者注

[189]拉丁文，意为“从内部凹处”。——译者注

[190]此处的两个长句十分晦涩，前句大意是说，人的头脑总倾向于走两个极端，因此作者用了一些高低、黑白的比喻；后句大意是说最不文明的人也可能相信上帝，而一旦有了上天和上帝，就会有地狱和魔鬼。——译者注

[191]法文，为一种带有四个分支的磨坊。——译者注

[192]指挪威北部以及瑞典、芬兰的土著人。——译者注

[193]德尔菲（Delphos），最重要的古希腊阿波罗神殿所在地，古希腊人认为这里是世界的中心。——译者注

[194]指法国亨利四世（Henry IV，1553—1610），法国波旁王朝的第一代国王。

[195]拉丁文，意为“若干人体”。——译者注

[196]拉丁文，意为：身体的活力产生于被爱欲折磨之后：它为了爱奋力拼搏，充满渴望。出自卢克莱修的《物性论》4.1047和1054。

[197]拉丁文，意为“发动战争的最可怕的原因”。

[198]指法国路易十四（Louis XIV，1638—1715），他在位时兴建凡尔赛宫。

[199]拉丁文，意为“麝香”。——译者注

[200]第欧根尼（Diogenes，约公元前5世纪），希腊哲学家，《论自然》是其重要著作。——译者注

[201]阿波罗尼奥斯（Apollonius，约公元前262—前190），古希腊数学家，其专著《圆锥曲线》为古代科学巨著之一。——译者注

[202]帕拉切尔苏斯（Palacelsus，1493—1541），出生于艾恩西德伦（今瑞士）的医师，炼金家，曾发明多种新药。——译者注

[203]笛卡尔（Des Cartes，1596—1650），法国数学家、哲学家，将哲学从传统的经院哲学解放出来的第一人。——译者注

[204]拉丁文，意为“弯曲”或“扭曲”。——译者注

[205]西塞罗（Cicero，公元前106—前43），罗马杰出的政治家、律师、古典学家、作家。——译者注

[206]拉丁文，意为“你应该庆幸自己来到了一个使你自己看上去有些智慧的地方”。出自西塞罗的《论演说》（Epistulae ad Familiares）7.10。

[207]作者这里的意思是，人如果不疯狂就不会有精神或宗教方面的信仰，不会相信看不见的东西。——译者注

[208]拉丁文，意为“理论”。——译者注

[209]此处指三兄弟中的杰克（喀尔文）。——译者注

[210]拉丁文，意为“此处缺失很多字”。系作者有意为之的打趣之笔。——译者注

[211]这里是说如果人们彻底幸福了，只会想象，那他们就不会揭露谬误或指摘他人缺点了。——译者注

[212]指上文提到的焊接或修补自然缺陷的艺术。——译者注

[213]指通过感官（感知）产生想象的人。——译者注

[214]此处还是有意反说，作者所谓的傻瓜，实则聪明，以聪明而积极的态度生活。——译者注

[215]作者此时的语无伦次是在模仿疯子的思维。——译者注

[216]库尔提斯（Curtius）是神话中的古罗马英雄，据传在公元前362年罗马广场出现一道深沟，预言师说，要把罗马最宝贵的东西扔下去深沟才会合拢，于是他只身纵马跃入深沟。——译者注

[217]恩培多克勒（Empedocles，约公元前490—约前430），古希腊哲学家，据说他自封为神，跃入埃特那山火山口自杀，以让他的信徒们相信他是神。——译者注

[218]老布鲁特斯（elder Brutus，约公元前6世纪末），古代历史中的传说人物，布鲁特斯的父亲，凯撒的朋友，一说后来谋杀了凯撒。——译者注

[219]拉丁文，意为“平息事端的能力”。——译者注

[220]暗指政治家都是疯子。——译者注

[221]爱德华·西摩（Edward Seymour，生卒年月不详），英国贵族政治家。——译者注

[222]克里斯托弗·马斯格雷夫（Christopher Musgrave，生卒年月不详），英国贵族政治家。——译者注

[223]约翰·鲍尔斯（John Bowles，生卒年月不详），英国贵族政治家。——译者注

[224]约翰·豪（John Howe），具体不详，可能是与作者同时代的一位清教徒。——译者注

[225]中世纪欧洲的一处伯爵领地，包括现比利时的东佛兰德省和西佛兰德省以及法国北部部分地区。——译者注

[226]英国议会在威斯敏斯特会堂召开。其间有意提出议案的议员要将书面议案放在主持人座椅背后的绿袋子里。这里所说的纸应为写议案用的。——译者注

[227]当时法官乘坐出租马车的费用。——译者注

[228]拉丁文，意为“他的脸上闪烁着光芒”。——译者注

[229]此处原文为the whore of Babylon，为基督教中一个邪恶之地。——译者注

[230]通常指yes和no。——译者注

[231]此处似指这样的人经常闲坐在壁炉旁。——译者注

[232]英国皇家医学会所在地。——译者注

[233]穆尔菲尔德（Moorfields）是伦敦的一个区，著名的穆尔门（moorgate，伦敦城的一处大门）所在地。——译者注

[234]苏格兰院（Scotland Yard）是一个警察局的名字。——译者注

[235]Troglodyte，指的是许多古希腊哲学家经常谈到的一种穴居人。——译者注

[236]布莱克摩尔（Blackmore，1654—1729），英国医生、诗人，曾为英王威廉三世和女王安妮的御医。——译者注

[237]莱斯特兰奇（Lestrange），可能指英国作家罗杰·莱斯特兰奇（Roger L'Estrange，1616—1704），最早期的英国记者和小册子作者。——译者注

[238]此处戏讽本特利喜欢显摆。另见有关本特利的前注。——译者注

[239]这里指“名声”。——译者注

[240]因为这是神秘的谜，所以没有意义。——译者注

[241]蔷薇十字会是基督教中的一个由玄学者组成的半神秘组织。——译者注

[242]Bythus，在相信直觉说的早期基督教诺斯替（Gnostic）教派的教义中，它是至高的神，此词亦含有“深奥”的意思。——译者注

[243]Sigé，意为诺斯替教义中的与神相通，此词亦含有“安静”的意思。——译者注

[244]Achamoth，不详。可能是诺斯替教义中的另一个神。此词亦含有“智慧”的意思。一说以上三词都属于诺斯替教派使用的隐语。——译者注

[245]拉丁文，意为“巨大的财富来自他的眼泪，光彩的财富来自他的笑声，不可预知的财富来自他的忧伤和恐惧”。

[246]英国诗人、哲学家沃恩（Vaughan）写《灵智魔学》所用的笔名，另见有关《灵智魔学》的前注。作者此处说他犯了不可原谅的错误似为揶揄之笔，意在激励读者去看他的书。——译者注

[247]此处原文为snap-dragon，指当时流行的一种游戏，即将白兰地倒入碗中点燃，再放入一些葡萄干之类的小果料，游戏者徒手快速从火中取出果料并吃掉。——译者注

[248]劳尔卡库（Laurcalco），塞万提斯的小说《唐吉诃德》中的一个人物。——译者注

[249]巴别塔（Babel），《圣经》中记载大洪水后人们在巴比伦所建造的塔，见《创世记》11：1—9。——译者注

[250]索尔兹伯里（Salisbury）平原，在英国中部，以其史前石柱遗址闻名。——译者注

[251]指克伦威尔和他的同盟者在决定处死查理一世时向上帝求援。——译者注

[252]指英国非国教派人士对教堂音乐的反感。——译者注

[253]比林斯格特（Billingsgate），位于英国伦敦东南的一个市场。——译者注

[254]暗指非国教派人士对英国所有教堂的装饰、雕像以及图画颜色的指责和非难。——译者注

[255]指浸礼。——译者注

[256]巴勒斯坦古地名，以盛产乳香闻名。——译者注

[257]此段意在暗讽狂热的布道令人难堪。狂热者总是乐于接受虐待，认为与其巨大的德行价值比起来，痛苦微不足道。——译者注

[258]此句的大意是，如果杰克（即他自己）不替他们挨打，那意大利教皇和法国国王的军队早就来霸占他们的妻子和财产（仓库）了。——译者注

[259]莫卧儿（Mogul），指历史上征战四方的蒙古人。——译者注

[260]以上几段（及下文）意在戏讽新教后裔（非英国国教者）与罗马教廷的狂热教徒虽表面上冲突很大，但因多有相似之处而经常被混淆，并且他们还经常不期而遇。——译者注

[261]拉丁文，意为“缺少一些字”。

[262]拉丁文，意为“桀骜不驯的海神普罗特斯仍能挣脱锁链”。出自贺拉斯的《讽刺诗集》（Satires）2.3.71。古希腊神话中的海神普罗特斯（Proteus）具有变换身形的本领。

[263]拉丁文，意为“失传的艺术”。——译者注

[264]希波克拉底（Hippocrates，约公元前460—约前377），古希腊著名医学家，他所创立的医学道德规范至今仍应用于医疗行业。——译者注

[265]指查理二世（Charles II，1630—1685），他于1670年复辟后曾提出改宗天主教，并迫害不肯顺从的教士，在朝野引起很大不满。——译者注

[266]指詹姆斯二世（James II，1633—1701），他在位期间从1687年开始强化天主教的政策，允许天主教徒进入长老会，并颁布“信教自由令”，天主教徒因而得到保护和纵容。下文提到的杰克离开彼得，并偷走了他的保护符等语亦应与此有关。——译者注

[267]只有跑在别人前面才能让别人看到自己的鞋跟。——译者注

[268]似指当时的长老会员埃德温（Humphry Edwyn），他为人傲慢拘礼，曾当选伦敦市长。——译者注

[269]奶油蛋羹是当时市长餐桌上的常见食品。——译者注

[270]指奥尔良的佩里（Père d'Orleans），法国教士。耶稣会是天主教的一支，由罗耀拉（Ignatius of Loyola）于1534年创立。——译者注

[271]在英国，如果气候干燥少雨，人们会倾向于室外活动，看书的人就会减少。——译者注

[272]turnip，一种广泛种植的产于欧亚大陆的植物，根形似萝卜，呈黄色或白色，可食用。

[273]德弗（Thomas Durfey，1653—1723），英国剧作家、讽刺作家和歌词作家，智者，在当时很有名。——译者注

[274]康格里夫（Congreve，1670—1729），英国摄政王复辟时期的杰出讽刺喜剧作家、小说家。——译者注

[275]这里作者含蓄地将德弗（Durfey）比作大便，在更广意义上指时尚中的“智者”都一钱不值。——译者注

[276]拉丁文，意为“这样的聚会充满活力”。——译者注

[277]此处原文为Sleep，系作者想象的古罗马众神之一。——译者注

[278]缪斯（Muses），希腊神话里一群来历不明的女神，被认为是诗歌、文艺和科学的保护神。——译者注

[279]以上两句的大意是，和第一位的标新立异相比，方法得当、合理是第二位的，作者因此结论说，只要他（以智者姿态）标新立异，就既不聪明，也不完美，更词不达意。——译者注

[280]拉丁文，意为“观察”。——译者注

From The Preface

The wits of the present age being so very numerous and penetrating, it seems the grandees of church and state begin to fall under horrible apprehensions, lest these gentlemen, during the intervals of a long peace, should find leisure to pick holes in the weak sides of religion and government. To prevent which, there has been much thought employed of late, upon certain projects for taking off the force and edge of those formidable inquirers, from canvassing and reasoning upon such delicate points. They have at length fixed upon one, which will require some time as well as cost to perfect. Meanwhile, the danger hourly increasing, by new levies of wits, all appointed (as there is reason to fear) with pen, ink, and paper, which may, at an hour's warning, be drawn out into pamphlets, and other offensive weapons, ready for immediate execution, it was judged of absolute necessity, that some present expedient be thought on, till the main design can be brought to maturity. To this end, at a grand committee some days ago, this important discovery was made by a certain curious and refined observer — that seamen have a custom, when they meet a whale, to fling him out an empty tub by way of amusement, to divert him from laying violent hands upon the ship. This parable was immediately mythologised; the whale was interpreted to be Hobbes's Leviathan, which tosses and plays with all schemes of religion and government, whereof a great many are hollow, and dry, and empty, and noisy, and wooden, and given to rotation: this is the leviathan, whence the terrible wits of our age are said to borrow their weapons. The ship in danger is easily understood to be its old antitype, the commonwealth. But how to analyse the tub, was a matter of difficulty; when, after long inquiry and debate, the literal meaning was preserved; and it was decreed that, in order to prevent these leviathans from tossing and sporting with the commonwealth, which of itself is too apt to fluctuate, they should be diverted from that game by a Tale of a Tub. And, my genius being conceived to lie not unhappily that way, I had the honour done me to be engaged in the performance.

译者导读

《论人类》是由英国政治家、哲学家托马斯·霍布斯（Thomas Hobbes，1588—1679）所写的一本具有较强思辨性质的书籍。托马斯·霍布斯出生于英国的一个牧师家庭，毕业于牛津大学。他生活的年代处于欧洲启蒙运动时期，当时欧洲出现了许多反对封建专制统治和教会思想、强调人权的代表人物，托马斯·霍布斯也是其中之一，他受到欧洲启蒙运动的影响，反对君权神授，奠定了西方政治哲学发展的基础，是近代第一个在自然法基础上系统发展了国家契约学说的资产阶级启蒙思想家，他的思想对后来的孟德斯鸠和卢梭产生了较大影响。

《论人类》分为“导言”“论人类”“论国家”和“论黑暗王国”四个章节。书中运用类比等多种方法说明了客观存在产生的原因、表现和实质，支持了启蒙运动所宣扬的思想，让人们对自然界中存在的事物有了更加理性的认识。其中闪烁的理性主义无论对当时还是现在都具有深远意义。

在“导言”中，作者首先提出了自己的观点：把国家比喻成人类创造的用于保护自身的机器人。

在“论人类”中，分别对人类的感觉、想象、思维逻辑顺序、语言、幸福与痛苦进行了理性客观清晰的阐述。关于人类的感觉，霍布斯认为感觉是由于外在物体，或客体对每种感觉器官进行压迫产生的。霍布斯认为人类的想象是有限的，他把想象分为简单想象和复杂想象，并说明梦是人们睡眠时产生的想象。对神灵的想象和崇拜无益于社会的稳定，应该予以消除。人类的思维逻辑顺序分为无计划的不连续思维和受到约束的连续性思维，同时举例说明人类受约束的连续性思维和动物的受约束的连续性思维有何不同。霍布斯称语言为“最高贵最有益的发明”，接着阐述了语言带来的益处和坏处、名词的分类，以及使用词语时需要慎重考虑，才能达到预期目的。关于运动的内在开始，霍布斯首先将动物的特有运动分为两种：生命运动和自主性运动，而想象是自主性运动的开始。当存在于想象中的微小运动——意向，开始倾向或远离产生的事物时，就是欲望（渴望）或厌恶。欲望（渴望）和厌恶是人与生俱来的，在两者之间的称为轻视。相同的情感，人们在具有不同的主观情感倾向时，会赋予不同甚至完全相反的名称，例如，“人们认为能成功，那么欲望就称为希望；同理，认为不能成功，那么欲望就称为失望”。关于人类的幸福与痛苦，霍布斯提到了人类期望的平等，而当不平等出现时，就会因为竞争、猜疑和为争得荣誉发生争吵。当国家的权力无法震慑臣民时，和平就会消失，人人为战的战争状态就会出现。这样人们就会生活在痛苦之中。可以发现，霍布斯自始至终都在论述中加入了国家的作用，这也是霍布斯国家契约学说的一种体现。

在“论国家”中，作者首先阐述了国家形成的原因、产生和过程。由于人类不同于蚂蚁和蜜蜂等政治动物（亚里士多德语），它们除了根据自己的判断和欲望引导之外，没有其他引导。而人类则不然，人类会为了利益、荣誉等等进行竞争，最终结果导致战争。而人类的目的是“要保全自己进而获得更满意的生活”，自然法则又没有足够的力量保证人类的安全。因此，为了保证人类的安全，就要“把他们所有的权利和力量赋予一个人格，或赋予一个集体，通过多数声音统一他们的意志”，这样统一于一个人格的一群人就称之为国家。关于臣民的自由，霍布斯坚持臣民的自由是有条件的自由，是在遵守国家法规前提下的自由，霍布斯提到“主权是国家的灵魂”，臣民服从国家的目的是受到国家的保护。接着，霍布斯提出了六种削弱和危害国家安全存在的因素并一一进行批判，最终回到本节开始提出的观点“如果人们真能使用他们所认为拥有的理性，他们就能保证国家的安全，至少不被内部疾病而毁坏”。本章是霍布斯表述其国家契约观点最突出的章节，字里行间处处透露出国家契约的思想。

在“论黑暗王国”中，霍布斯着重介绍了空虚哲学，并用大量例子证明空虚哲学的荒谬以及它们对公共国家带来的危害。霍布斯认为“休闲是哲学之母，而国家是和平与休闲之母”。在一个国家中，用个人的欲望作为衡量标准是错误的，个人的行为不能成为衡量标准，作为衡量标准的应是法律，即国家的意志和欲望。最后，霍布斯提到了十二种说法，将上述荒谬哲学带来的黑暗转化成自身利益并指出其本质予以批判。

本书篇幅不长，却处处闪烁着霍布斯理性和智慧的光芒。阅读是一种好的休息方式，阅读经典读物，能起到开阔视野，增长知识的作用，更能锻炼思维，培养独立思考能力，可谓一举多得。现在就让我们一同走进霍布斯的思想世界吧！

导言

自然是上帝创造并掌管世界的艺术，万物不同，道理相通，人类仿照上帝的艺术创造出一种人造动物。把生命仅仅看作是四肢运动，其源头是本身内部具有的一些主要部分，那么，我们为什么不能说，同手表一样，类似于通过弹簧和齿轮实现自我驱动的发动机的所有自动机器都拥有人造生命呢？它的“心脏”就是一个“弹簧”；“神经”则由许多“弹簧”构成；“关节”是许多“齿轮”，让整个身体运动起来，这就是创造者希望设计出来使整个身体可以活动的东西吗？艺术还要模仿拥有理智的人类——他们是自然的绝世之作。通过艺术，伟大的利维坦（LEVIATHAN）被创造出来，又叫联邦或国家，它们是人类，但仅仅是人造人类；保护和防卫能力是利维坦保护真实人类所需，因此其身高和力量远远大于真实人类；“主权”是“人造灵魂”，没有它，整个身体就如静止的尸骸；法官及其他司法官员构成“人造关节”；“褒奖”和“惩罚”（与主权地位相联结，每一个关节、身体每个部分都被调动起来行使职责）是“神经”，这和真实人体运转方式相同；社会中所有特别成员的“资产”和“财富”是力量；Salus Populi（人民安全）是其职业；顾问是利维坦需要的万事通，他们为利维坦提供建议，是“记忆”；“公平公正”和“法律”，是“人造理性”和“意志”；“和谐”是“健康”；“停滞”是“疾病”；“内战”是“死亡”。最后，组成身体政治的“条约”和“条款”结合，类似于上帝创造天地时宣布的“法令”，即“让我们创造人类吧”。

为了论述这个人造人类的本质，我将考虑如下问题：

第一，人造人类这一物质和创造者；两者都是人类。

第二，“条款”形成的原因以及达成的依据；一个主权国家的“权利”和“权力”（“权威”）是什么；保持政权和政权消亡的原因是什么。

第三，基督教共和国是什么。

第四，黑暗王国是什么。

关于第一点，最近有一种说法十分盛行：“智慧”不是通过“读书”获得的，而是通过解读认识“人类”获得的。由于绝大多数人不能给出拥有智慧的其他证据，因此这些人十分喜欢展示他们在解读认识人类上的收获，即在背后对他人进行无情的攻击指责。但也有另一种说法尚未被人所理解，按照这种说法，如果他们愿意不辞辛劳付出，就能真正学会解读理解他人，这就是Nosce Te ipsum, Read Thyself（《诺斯克泰普撒姆，了解自己》）：其现在的意义是赞同宽恕国家或当权者对从属的残暴行为，抑或鼓励地位较低的人们对优于他们的人采取不恭行为。与上述意义不同，其原本意义是教育我们，一个人同另一个人具有相似的思想和感情，任何人在一种情境中进行“思考”“判断”“推理”“希望”“恐惧”等活动时，他们审视自身，考虑其所作所为，就应理解和知道他人在类似情境中拥有的类似思想和感情。我所说的相似感情，是为所有人共有的感情，包括“渴望”“恐惧”“希望”等；而不是引起上述激情的物体，即让人产生“渴望”“恐惧”“希望”等情绪的物体：由于每个人的素质和受教育差别很大，且它们十分容易被排除在我们拥有的知识之外，以至于人类被玷污、困惑的内心，加上支离破碎、消亡、虚伪和错误的知识，让人们很难寻找人的内心世界，只有探索人内心世界的人才能了解。虽然我们有时能通过人们的行为发现他们的想法，然而不把他们同我们自身作比较、对所有情况进行区别，只以一个随时可能改变的事例为证，无异于没有钥匙而去开锁，由于过于信任或过于缺乏自信，大部分结论可能被蒙蔽欺骗。按照事例本身解读认识人类，他本人可能是好人也可能是坏人。

如果让一个人通过其他人不完美的行为解读他们，这些人只能是他为数不多的熟人。对于一个要治理整个国家的人，必须解读理解自己，不是某个个别的人，而是全人类：做到这一点虽然很困难，难于学习任何语言或科学；然而，当我制定好条理清晰的解读方式后，剩下的疑问只有他是否还不是那样的。因为这种知识不允许进行其他论证。

论国家

论国家的成因、产生和定义

（我们看见本性热爱自由、统治他人的人类生活在国家里）使自己受到束缚，其最终原因、目的和计划是要保全自己进而获得更满意的生活。这就是说，让他们自身摆脱战争的痛苦境地。当没有可见力量震慑人们，并以惩罚使他们惧怕而遵守契约等及第十四章、第十五章中提到的自然法则，战争就是人类自然激情的必然结果。

自然法则（如公正、公平、谦虚、仁慈，以及[总之]欲实施和被施加，）若没有一些力量给人们造成恐惧而使他们遵守，那么其本身就和那些把我们带向偏激、骄傲、仇恨等的自然激情不容。契约，若没有武力维持实行，则是空洞的文字，也就根本没有保障人类安全的力量。因此，虽然拥有自然法则，（当人们有遵守的意志并且通过这么做能够带来安全时才会遵守，）但若没有树立力量或没有足够的力量保证我们的安全，那么每个人都可以依法依靠自身力量和计谋对其他所有人保持警惕。所有以小族群为单位居住的人，在这些地方，抢劫他人成为一种行业，且这远远没有到违背自然法则的地步，他们抢劫所得越多就越荣耀。在这里人们只遵守荣耀法则，即戒掉残忍，留人生路，留给他们农用器具。过去小族群这么做，如今城市和王国只不过是更大的族群，面临危机、惧怕入侵或可能给予入侵者任何帮助，（为了他们自身安全）就尽其所能扩张领土，通过公开武力或秘密计谋征服或削弱他们的邻国，由于缺乏其他保证，这么做是恰当的，且这一荣耀被后世所铭记。

少数人联合也不能够给他们带来这种安全。因为在少数人中，一方或另一方增加一点就能够获得力量上的巨大优势，这一优势足以给一方带来胜利，因此鼓励侵略的产生。我们是否信任一个群体能够带来足够安全并不取决于人数的多少，而是取决于其同我们所恐惧敌人数量的比较。当敌人数量优势并不是明显到可以决定战争结果，从而推动其尝试侵略时，才是真正安全的。

即使有如此巨大的群体，如果他们的行为受到个人判断和欲望的引导，就不能期望他们对共同敌人进行防御，也不能期望他们对互相伤害进行保护。因为一旦在使用他们力量的最好方法上不能达成一致，他们就不能互相帮助，而只能相互妨碍，并且因为互相反对使他们的力量消失殆尽。这样他们就很容易被极少数团结起来的敌人所征服，而且为了自身利益，他们很容易在没有共同敌人时相互为战。因为如果我们可以假设许多人在没有共同权力使他们畏惧的情况下就能达成一致、遵守公正和其他自然法则，我们也可以假设全人类这么做，那么世界上就从不会有、也不需要有任何政府或国家了，因为没有服从也会拥有和平。

人们在一个有限时期内，例如一场战斗或一场战争中被统治或被一种判断所指引，这对于渴望终生安全的人们来说，是不足以保证的；因为尽管他们团结一致努力抵抗外国敌人并最终取得胜利，但之后当他们没有共同敌人或者一部分人认为他是敌人，而另一部分人认为他是朋友时，他们必然会因为利益的不同而陷入分歧，然后在他们之间爆发战争。

的确，一些生物，例如蜜蜂和蚂蚁，都能和平地共同生活（因此亚里士多德把它们列为政治生物）。但它们除了受各自的判断和欲望引导之外，别无其他；此外它们也没有语言互相表明自己所想对全体有利。因此有些人可能想知道为什么人类不能如此。我的答案是：

第一，人类不断地为了荣誉和尊严而竞争，这些生物则不然。因此人们中间就会产生嫉妒和仇恨，最终引发战争，而在这些生物中则并非如此。

第二，在这些生物中，共同利益和个体利益没有差别。它们的本性倾向于个体利益，而它们通过个体利益获得共同利益。但是人类只会欣赏杰出的事情，他们的快乐产生于同他人作比较。

第三，这些生物在管理它们共同事务的过程中，（和人类不同）用不到理性、看不见也不认为它们能看见其中的任何缺点。然而在人类中，有很多人认为自己比其他所有人更加聪明、更有能力掌管这个国家，这些人就努力进行改革和创新，一个人用这种方法，一个人用另一种方法，由此引发分歧和内战。

第四，尽管这些生物使用一些声音告知同类它们的需要和感情，但它们没有语言，不会像人类一样用语言进行表达，把善说成恶，把恶说成善，夸大或减小明显的善恶程度，随心所欲地使他人不快，扰乱和平。

第五，无理智的生物不能区分伤害和损失，因此只要它们安逸生活，就不会感到同类的侵犯。而当人类处在最安逸的时刻则最麻烦，因为此时他最想展示他的智慧，并且爱控制管理国家的人的行为。

最后，这些生物的一致性是自然的，而人类的一致性则仅仅依靠人为契约。因此毫无疑问需要另外一些东西（除契约外）以保证他们的协议坚实持久，这就是让他们感到畏惧的共同权力，指导他们作出利于共同利益的行为。

建立一个能外御侵略，内防伤害的共同权力，保证他们依靠自己劳动和产出的果实丰衣足食生活满意，只有唯一一条路：即把他们所有的权力和力量赋予一个人，或赋予一个集体，通过多数声音统一他们的意志。这就是说，指定一个人或一个集体来代表他们的人格，每个人都承认他所赋予权力的人在共同和平和安全方面作出的行动或命令。在这种行为中，人们将自己的意志服从于他的意志，将自己的判断服从于他的判断。这不仅仅是赞同或协调，这是他们真正意义上的统一，统一于一个人格，这个人格是由所有人制定的契约选出的。就像每个人都对其他人说：“我放弃约束自己的权力并把它授权给这个人格或这个集体，条件是你也以此方式放弃你约束自己的权力并授权给他或集体。”做到这一点后，如此统一于一个人格的一群人就称之为国家，拉丁语为CIVITAS。这就是伟大的利维坦的产生，或称为（更尊敬地说）现世上帝，我们在永恒上帝下得到的和平与保卫便是从它那里来的。通过国家内每个人赋予它的权威，它可以使用人们赋予它的极大权力和力量。通过恐惧，它能够将人们的意志组织起来，对内获得和平，对外互相帮助共同抵御外来敌人。它是由国家的实质构成的。（给它定义）就是由一大群人互相签订契约，每个人都是授权方，授权给一个能代表所有人的人格行动，使这个人格可以使用一大群人的力量和方法，为大家的利益、和平和共同防御考虑并行动。

担任这个人格的人称为主权者，拥有主权，其他所有人都是他的臣民。

获得主权有两种方法。第一种，通过自然力量，例如一个人让他的后代服从于他的统治，如果他们拒绝服从，主权者就会毁灭他们；或通过战争让敌人屈服于他的意志作为获得延续生命的条件。第二种，人们在内部达成协议，自愿服从他们相信的某个人或集体，因为他们相信所信之人或集体能够保护他们对抗其他所有人。后者可以称为政治国家或制度国家。前者称为获取的国家[……]

论臣民的自由

自由指的是没有阻碍（说到阻碍，我指的是运动的外界障碍），可以同样适用于无理性、无生命的创造物以及有理性的创造物。任何被捆绑或包围的事物，若只能在一定空间内移动，而这一空间又被某些外界物体所阻碍，我们就说它没有超越这一空间的自由。所有生物当它们被墙或链子束缚或限制时，当水被堤坝或容器阻挡，否则就会流向更大的空间去时，我们就说它们没有毫无外界阻碍地运动的自由。但当运动障碍存在于事物本身时，我们就不说它没有自由，而说它缺少运动的力量，正如一块静止的石头或一个因病卧床不起的病人。

根据这一词语恰当和普遍接受的意义，一个自由人就是在他的力量和智慧所能达到的范围内，可以毫无阻碍地按照他的意志做事的人。但当自由一词被用于物体之外的任何事物上时，就是滥用，因为不存在运动的事物，就不存在阻碍。因此，（举个例子）当说到这条路是自由的这句话时，并不指这条路拥有自由，而是指在路上行走的人可以毫无阻碍地行走。当我们说送礼物是自由的时候，并不指礼物本身是自由的，而是指送礼物的人不受任何法律或契约的约束，可以自由地送礼物。因此，当我们自由地说话时，并不是声音或发音本身是自由的，而是指没有法律要求说话之人以其他方式说话。最后，自由意志一词的使用，也不是指意志、欲望或倾向的自由，而是指人的自由，即他在按照自身意志、欲望或倾向做事时没有阻碍。

恐惧和自由是相容的。当一个人因为惧怕船只沉没而往海里扔东西时，他是十分愿意这么做的，并且如果他不愿意可以不这么做。因此，这是自由之人的行为。一个人有时会偿还他的债务，仅仅因为他对入狱充满恐惧，因为没有人妨碍他不还债，这就是自由之人的行为。一般来说，人们因为惧怕法律而在国家内的一切行为都是他们有自由忽略不做的。

自由和必然性是相容的。比如水不仅仅有自由，也拥有顺着河道向低处流的必然性。同理，在人们自愿所做之事中也是一样，（因为自愿所做源于他们的意志）自愿所做也就源于自由。但是由于人们源于其意志的每一行为、每一欲望和倾向都来源于某种原因，而这一原因又存在于连续原因链条中的另一个原因中（上帝手中的第一环节就是所有原因之源），这些行为源自必然性。所以对于能发现这些原因之间联系的人，人们所有自愿行为的必然性就很明显了。因此，上帝既看到并安排万物，也看到人们按照自己意志做事的自由，并让自由不多不少带有上帝意志的必然性。因为虽然人们可以做许多上帝没有要求也没有授权的事情，但要是没有上帝的意志为原因，人们就不会对任何事物有激情和欲望。假设上帝的意志不能保证人们意志的必然性，而保证人们意志所依赖的一切都具有必然性，人类的自由就会和上帝的全能和自由相矛盾相阻碍。（对于目前的问题来说）这就足够说明唯一可以称为自由的自然自由。

作为人，为了获得自由并以此保护自己的生命，制造了一个人造人，就是我们所称的国家。他们也制造了称为民法的人造链条，通过相互立定契约，将他们赋予主权的人或集体的舌头系在链条一端，另一端系上自己的耳朵。这些链条捆绑本质上是脆弱的，虽然不能靠其本身难以折断维持，但仍然可以通过链条断裂之后产生的危险来维持。

我现在要说的臣民的自由只是相对于这些链条束缚的自由。因为世界上没有任何一个国家的法规多到约束人们的一切行动和话语（这是不可能的）：这就是说，在法律允许的所有行为中，人们有自由按照自己的理性去做对自身最有利的事情。因为如果我们把自由的恰当意义看作人身自由，那就是说，不受链条和监狱的束缚，他们再去吵闹争取这种自由是十分荒谬的，因为他们现在已经享有这种自由了。另外，如果我们把自由看作法律豁免自由，像人们现在这样争取这种自由也是荒谬的，靠这种自由，所有其他人都成为自己生命的主人了。尽管这很荒谬，但这就是他们所要求的，他们不知道法律没有一个人或许多人拥有并执行武力就没有权力保护他们。因此，臣民的自由只存在于主权允许的行为内，例如买卖、与他人签订契约、选择自己的住处、饮食、行业和采用他们认为合适的方式教育子女等等。

但是我们不明白至关生死的主权因为这种自由而被废除或限制。因为这里已经表明，在任何情况下主权代表对臣民所做的一切都不能被恰当地称为不公正或伤害，因为每个臣民都是主权一切行为的授权者，所以除了他自己是上帝的臣民因而必须遵守自然规律之外，他对任何事从不缺少权利。因此在一个国家可能或经常会发生一个臣民可以受主权的命令被杀死，而双方都没有做对不起对方的事。杰普撒（Jeptha）让他女儿为祭祀而牺牲就是如此。在这种或类似情况下，像他这样死去的人有自由这么做，然而他这样被处死却没有受到伤害。一个主权君主处死一个无辜臣民时，也是同样道理。因为尽管这种行为违反公正裁决、违背自然法则（就像大卫杀死乌利亚一样），对乌利亚来说并没有受到伤害，但对上帝造成了伤害。乌利亚没有受到伤害的原因是他已经把做他愿意的事情的权力交给大卫了。上帝受到伤害的原因是大卫是上帝的臣民，自然法则禁止他做一切不公正的事情。这一区别在大卫自己忏悔时已经确认了，他说“我向你犯罪，唯独得罪了你”。（《诗篇》第五十一章）同样，当雅典人将国内势力最强的人放逐十年时，他们认为自己没有做任何不公正之事，并且他们从来不问被放逐的人犯了什么罪，而只问他造成了什么伤害。不仅如此，他们还命令放逐不知道的人。每个公民都把他的贝壳带到市场上，把他希望放逐的人的名字写在贝壳上而不用真正起诉他，有时候就把亚里斯泰迪斯（Aristides）放逐了，因为他公正的声誉。有时候把粗俗卑鄙喜欢开玩笑的人放逐了，比如希帕波鲁斯（Hyperbolus），因为他喜欢开玩笑。但我们不能说雅典主权人民没有放逐他们的权利，或者雅典人没有开玩笑的自由或缺乏公正。

古希腊和古罗马人的历史与哲学以及在他们接受政治观点的著作和讨论中，经常提到的自由不是个人的自由，而是国家的自由。这种自由和没有民法或国家时每个人应有的自由相同，效果也一样。因为在没有主人的人群中，永远是人人与邻为敌的战争。人们没有遗产留给儿子，也不会期望从父亲那里得到什么，物品和土地没有所有权，没有安全可言，但每个人都有完全和绝对的自由。因此独立存在的每个国家（不是每个人）都拥有绝对的自由根据自己的判断（就是说根据主权代表者或集体的判断）做最利于他们的事。但他们生活在永恒的战争中，在他们国界内，前线全部武装起来，大炮指向周围国家。说雅典人和罗马人是自由的，指的是他们是自由的国家，不是哪一个人拥有反抗他们代表的自由，而是说他们的代表者有自由抵抗或入侵其他民族。如今在路加城角楼上写着巨大的字：自由。但是没有人能因此推测这个国家的哪一个人比君士坦丁堡的人更自由或者能免除更多兵役。不论一个国家是君主制还是民主制，自由都是一样的。

但是人们很容易被自由这个幌子欺骗，因为缺少区分的判断力，误将只属于公共的权利当成私人遗产和与生俱来的权利。当这种权利被某个在这个领域出过书而闻名的权威肯定时，发生叛乱和政府更替就不足为奇了。在西方世界中，我们从亚里士多德、西塞罗和其他生活在民主国家的希腊和罗马人身上接受关于国家制度和权利的观点。这些人并没有从自然原理中导出这些权利，而是把自己民主国家的做法转到他们的书上，就像语法学家根据当时的做法描述语言规则，或通过荷马或维吉尔的诗作描述诗歌规则一样。（要避免雅典人更换政府的欲望）雅典人民被教导说他们是自由人，而所有住在君主制国家的人民都是奴隶。因此亚里士多德就把它写进《政治学》中，在该书第六篇第二章中写道：“在民主国家里，人们认为自由是理所当然的，因为一般人认为生活在任何其他政府统治之下的人都没有自由。”和亚里士多德一样，西塞罗和其他著名作家把罗马人的意见作为他们提倡的民事原则的基础，这些罗马人被教导憎恨君主制，最初就是他们废掉了统治者、共享罗马主权，后来是他们的继承者。通过阅读这些希腊、拉丁作家的书，人们从童年开始就学会了一种习惯，（在虚假的自由下）喜欢暴乱、热衷毫无顾忌地控制主权者的行动，之后再控制这些控制者，弄得鲜血横流。我想我可以实在地说，从来没有任何事比这些西方世界学习希腊和拉丁语付出的代价更大了。

现在谈一谈臣民真正自由的具体情况。这就是说，尽管统治者下了命令，但是如果出于公正，什么事是可以拒绝去做的。我们要考虑的是，当我们建立国家的时候，我们失去了哪些权利。或者说（实际说的是一回事），当我们所有人都认可主权者或集体的时候，我们自己丧失了哪些权利。因为在我们服从的行为中，既有我们的义务也有我们的自由；因此它们要通过一些论据进行推测。没有哪个人的义务不是从他自己的一些行为中产生的，所有人生而平等，这对所有人都是一样的。这种论据必须从“我授权给他一切行为”或从服从此人的人的意图中推测出来（这种意图要通过他服从的目的来理解）。臣民的义务和自由就必须从这些词语（或其他等价词语）或从主权建立的目的，即臣民内部的和平以及对共同敌人的防御中去推导。

因此，第一，主权是根据人与人之间建立的契约而建立，而由其他方式获得的主权则是通过被征服者对胜利者，或孩子对父母的契约建立的。很明显，在不能依据契约转移权利的所有这些事上，每个臣民都有自由。我在前面第十四章[5]已经说明，不能为人们提供保护的契约是无效的。因此，如果主权者命令一个人（尽管宣判公正）去杀害、中伤自己，或对侵犯自己的人不予抵抗，或拒绝食物、空气、药品或其他维持生命所必需的东西，这个人就有不遵守契约的自由。

一个人如果受到主权者或当权人关于其犯罪的审问，（在没有赦免保证的情况下）他就不用必须承认罪行。因为没有人（如我在同一章所证明）受到契约的强制去控告自己。

同样，一个臣民对主权的承认包含在这些话中：我授权他的所有行为并对他的所有行为负责。这对他本身之前拥有的天赋自由没有任何限制。因为允许他杀我，但当他命令我杀害自己时，我就没有必要这么做。有一句话是这样说的：“如果你愿意，杀了我或我的朋友”，另一句话说：“我将杀了自己或我的朋友。”由此得出：

没有人因为词语本身要杀害自己或其他任何人。因此一个人由于受到主权者命令处理任何危险或无荣誉的事而具有的义务，并不取决于我们服从的词语，而取决于意图，并且要根据事情的结果来理解。所以，若因为我们拒绝服从就会影响建立主权这一结果时，我们就没有自由去拒绝，反之则有自由去拒绝。

据此，一个人接受命令成为士兵去同敌人作战，尽管主权者有权利因为他拒绝出战而将他处死，在很多情况下他仍然可以正当拒绝，比如他找到了一个能胜任的士兵代替他的位置。因为在这种情况下他没有无视国家的兵役。对于生来胆小的人也应特别对待，不仅仅对妇女（人们并没有期待她们担负如此危险的义务），对那些像女人一样胆小的男人也是一样。军队打仗时，一方或双方都有逃跑的情况，当他们出于恐惧而不是叛变而逃跑时，他们的行为就不能被认为是不合理的，而是丧尽荣誉的。同理，逃避战斗不是非正义的，而是怯懦。但是他自己应征入伍或接受军饷，就不能以胆小为借口。此时他不仅有义务开赴战场，也不能不得到长官允许就逃跑。当国家的防御立刻需要所有能够参战的人武装起来时，所有人都有义务，不然国家建立起来而又没有决心或勇气保卫国家，一切都是无用的。

没有人拥有因为保护一个有罪或清白的人而同国家武力进行对抗的自由，因为这会使主权者失去保护我们的方法，因而对政府的实质具有破坏作用。但是如果大批人一起不正确地对抗主权者或已经犯下一些死罪，并且都知道自己难逃一死，他们是否有自由联合起来相互帮助、互相防御呢？当然有，因为他们保卫的是自己的生命，有罪之人和清白之人一样都能够这么做。他们第一次违反义务时是不正确的，之后他们拿起武器虽然是为了保护他们已经做的，但这就不是一个新的不正确的行为了。如果他们这么做仅仅是为了保护自己，那么这根本就不是不正确的。但在赦免他们后，通过自我防卫的请求继续帮助或保卫其他的人就是违法的。

至于其他自由，取决于法律的规定。在主权没有规定规则的情况下，臣民就有按照自身考虑选择去做或不做的自由。因此，根据主权者认为是否最方便，在一些地方自由较多，一些地方较少，一些时候较多，而另一些时候较少。例如，在英格兰有一段时间一个人可以凭借武力进入他自己的领地（驱逐非法占有它的人）。但后来，这种武力进入的自由因为议会中（由国王）制定的法律而停止。在世界一些地方，男人有拥有许多配偶的自由，在其他地方，这种自由是不被允许的。

如果一个臣民根据先前的法律在债务、土地或物品所有权、兵役或任何肉体惩罚和罚款上与主权者进行争论，这个臣民拥有为自己在主权者制定的法官面前上诉的自由，就像他起诉另一个臣民一样。因为主权者通过先前法律而不是他的权力来获得自己所要求的东西，因此他声明他的需要不会超过法律的规定。如此这样，诉讼就不违背主权者的意志，而臣民也有要求旁听自己案件的自由，并根据法律作出判决。但是如果他依靠自己的权力要求或获得任何东西，在这种情况下，就没有法律行为。因为他一切的所作所为都是依靠自己的权力、都是依据每个臣民的授权作出的，他对主权者提起诉讼就是起诉自己。

如果一个君主或主权议会赋予所有臣民或任何臣民一种自由，但这个赋予成立却不能为臣民提供安全保障时，这个赋予就是无用的，除非他直接声明或将主权交给他人。因为（如果这是他的真实想法）他就会公开地用清晰明白的语言声明放弃或让出主权，但是他没有这么做。我们可以理解为这并不是他所想所希望的。这种赋予产生于不知道自由和主权之间的矛盾。因此主权仍然被保留下来，进而所有行使主权所必需的权力都被保留下来，例如宣战、求和、司法、任命官员、任命议员、征税以及第十八章中提及的其他权力。[6]

臣民对主权的服从不会长于主权者的权力能够保护他们的时间。在没有任何其他人能够保护他们的时候，人们与生俱来保护自己的权利是不会通过契约而放弃的。主权是国家的灵魂，一旦离开了身体，身体各部分就不会从灵魂上接受任何运动。服从的目的是保护，一个人无论在自己或他人的武力中发现这种服从，人的本性就会服从和保持这种武力。虽然按照建立主权的人们的意图，主权是永恒的，但其本质不仅会由于外来战争而暴毙，也会因为人们的无知和激情，从建立主权开始，内部就有许多不和谐的种子。

如果一个臣民在战争期间入狱，或他本人，或谋生手段在敌人警戒之中，若以臣服于胜利者为条件换取生命和人身自由，他有自由接受这种条件，在接受这种条件之后，他就要臣服于俘获他的人，因为他没有别的办法保护自己。如果他在外国以同样条件被拘留，也是一样。但是如果一个人入狱或被束缚，或不被信任给予人身自由，他就不能被认为受到契约束缚而服从。因此，如果他能力允许，是可以通过任何手段逃跑的。

如果一个君主为了自己和继承人要放弃主权，他的臣民就回到了绝对的天赋自由状态。因为尽管大自然可以宣布哪些人是他的儿子，哪些人是他最近的亲属，但谁是他的继承人仍然完全取决于他的意志（如前面章节所说）。如果他不要继承人，那也就没有主权和臣服了。如果他死的时候没有人们都知道的亲属，也没有宣布他的继承人，这种情况也是一样。因为这时没有人们所知的继承人，因此也就没有应遵守的臣服。

如果主权者驱逐他的臣民，在被放逐期间他就不是主权者的臣民。但是如果他是被外派出差，或外出旅游，那么他仍然是主权者的臣民。但是这取决于主权者之间的契约，而不是取决于臣服的契约。任何进入他国领土的人，都应服从当地的法律，除非他同主权者关系友好而具有特权或特别许可。

如果一个君主在战争中被俘而臣服于胜利者，他的臣民就不用遵守原先的义务而改为履行胜利者规定的义务了。但是如果君主入狱，并且失去了人身自由，他就不应该被认为放弃了主权，因此他的臣民就有义务服从原来任命的官员，这些官员不是以自己的名义而是以君主的名义行使统治。由于君主的权利仍然存在，问题就只剩下管理了。这就是说，只剩下地方法官和政府官员的问题了。如果君主无法任命这些官员的话，那么就应当认为他同意之前任命的那些人。

[……]

论削弱国家或使国家解体的因素

虽然生命有限的人类制造的东西不可能是永恒的，但如果人们真能使用他们所认为拥有的理性，他们就能保证国家的安全，至少不被内部疾病所毁坏。因为根据自身的性质，国家在建立之初就设计成与赋予它们生命的人类、自然法则和正义一样长存。因此，当国家面临非外部暴力而是内部动乱要解体时，错误不在人类，因为他们是质（Matter），而在创造者（Makers）和发号施令者身上。因为最后当人们对混乱的冲突和杀戮感到厌倦后，就满心渴望将自身形成一座坚固持久的大厦。因此既缺少制定合适法律的艺术来规范人们的行为，又缺少谦虚和忍耐将自己现有杰作中粗糙累赘的部分除掉，他们没有一位十分能干的建筑师的帮助，建造的最多只能是摇摇欲坠的建筑，这种建筑物很难撑过他们所处的时代，以后肯定会砸到他们后代的头上。

因此，在一个国家的病症中，我首先要提及那些由于建立中存在的瑕疵引起的病症，这和由先天缺陷所造成的身体疾病相似。

其中一种就是：获得王国的人有时对于保证国家和平与国家防御必要力量的不足也能感到满足。从这一点就会出现，当为了恢复公共安全而使用搁置的权力时，这似乎就是一种不正当的行为，就会让许多人（当这种情形真的发生时）起来反叛。由患病父母所生孩子的身体也是一样，这些孩子逃脱不了夭折的命运，或因为治疗由先天毒素引发的顽疾而引起脓包或结痂。君主们放弃一些这种必要的权力，并不总是（尽管有时）由于不知道自己职责所必须做的是什么，而更多时候是出于希望将来能按他们的意愿重新获得。在这里他们的理由并不好，因为这种让他们遵守承诺的理由会被外国利用同他们进行对抗。这些国家为了自身臣民的利益很少会放过削弱其邻国的机会。因此坎特伯雷的大主教托马斯·贝克特就受到教皇的支持反对亨利二世，因为在威廉一世即位时发誓不侵犯教堂的自由，就免除了教士对国家的服从。同样，威廉二世借助男爵的帮助从他哥哥那里继承了王位，这便使男爵的势力增加到与主权难以共存的地步，他们发动针对约翰王的叛乱时，法国人为他们提供了帮助。

这种情况不仅仅出现在君主制国家。因为在古罗马共和国，国家的支柱虽然是罗马元老院和罗马人民，但元老院和罗马人民都不能拥有所有权力，这首先就引起了提比流斯·格拉齐、该犹斯·格拉齐、卢修斯·萨图尼努斯和其他人的叛乱，后来就变成了在马里乌斯和西拉领导下的元老院和人民之间的战争，然后在庞培和恺撒统治时期消灭了民主并建立起君主制国家。

雅典人民约束自己不能做一件事：任何人都不能提出为了萨拉米斯岛而重新发起战争，否则将被处死。如果梭伦没有在外装疯卖傻，后来扮成疯子的模样和习惯，向他身后结队而行的人提出这个问题，他们的城门外就会有时刻严阵以待的敌军。所有权力受到极小限制的国家都会被迫经受这种伤害或更替。

其次，我要说由煽动言论导致的国家疾病。其中一种就是：每个平民都是善行与恶行的法官。这在没有民法的纯自然状态下是正确的，在公民政府法律没有进行规定的事情上也是正确的。然而，对善行和恶行的衡量标准显然是民法，法官是立法者，他永远是国家的代表。从这一虚假原则来看，人们会在心里算计，同国家命令进行争论，然后根据自己的判断决定遵守与否，这样国家就被扰乱和削弱了。

另一种与公民社会相矛盾的是“一个人作出的任何违背良知的事都是罪过”。这源于将自己设想成善恶判断者。由于一个人的良心和判断是同一种东西，既然判断会出错，那良心也会出错。因此，尽管他不服从任何民法，他所做的一切违背良知的事都是罪过，因为除了自己的理性就没有其他任何法则可以遵守了。然而，对于生活在一个国家的人就不是如此了，因为法律是公共良知，是他已经承诺要遵守的。否则在主观个人良知差异如此巨大的情况下，国家必然会混乱，因为没有人会在看到极大个人利益时，选择服从主权。

大众还普遍地接受这种教育：“信仰和圣洁不能通过学习和理性获得，而要通过超自然的灵感或灌输获得。”若承认这一点，我不明白为什么每个人都要为他的信仰提出一个理由，为什么每个基督徒不能是一个先知，为什么每个人要用自己国家的法律而不是自己的灵感作为行动准则。如此我们就又陷入了自己判断善恶的错误中；或者把那些假装得到超自然灵感的个人当作善恶的判断者，进而导致公民政府的解体。信仰源于所听，所听来自于那些指引我们走向讲话者的偶然。这些偶然都是全能的上帝策划的。这些偶然并不是超自然的，而仅仅是产生每种效果时，因为数量很多而无法观察到。信仰和圣洁确实不十分常见，但它们不是奇迹，而是在上帝认为合适时通过教育、训练、改正以及其他自然方法使它们在选民中产生效果。这三种有害于和平及政府的观点在这个地方主要源于胸无点墨的神职人员口中和笔下，他们把《圣经》中的文字拼在一起，不顾违背理性，尽其所能地让人们认为圣洁和自然理性是不能共存的。

第四种有害于国家性质的观点是：拥有主权的人要服从民法。毫无疑问，所有主权者要服从自然法，因为这种法律是神订立的，任何人和国家都不能废除。但是主权者自身可以不服从自己，即国家制定的法律。因为服从法律就是服从国家，服从国家就是服从主权代表者，就是服从自己。这就不是服从，而是不受法律约束。这种错误是因为将法律置于主权之上，将一个法官和惩罚他的权力置于他之上。这样就创造出一个新主权者，同理又会有第三个主权者惩罚第二个主权者，如此不断进行下去，给国家带来混乱，导致国家解体。

第五种倾向于国家解体的教义是：每个人对其物品都具有绝对所有权，而这种所有权不包括主权者的权利。事实上每个人都有除开其他所有臣民权利的所有权。他仅从主权者那里获得权利，而不受主权者保护，其他每个人都对这些物品具有同等权利。但如果主权者的权利也被除去，他就不能行使公民赋予他抵御外敌、保护安全的职责了，进而国家就不存在了。

如果臣民所有权不排除主权代表对他们拥有物品的权利，就更不能排除他们司法或行政的能力，他们在这些部门代表主权者本人。

第六种教义明显直接地违背国家本质。这种说法是：主权可以分割。所谓的分割国家权力就是让国家解体，因为被分割的主权会互相摧毁。对于这些教义，人们主要是看着那些依据自身所学而不是立法权的法律专业人员。

同虚假教义一样，邻国政府的例子也让人们改变之前已经固定的形式。因此犹太人被鼓动起来拒绝上帝，并拜访先知撒母耳依照其他国家的方式选出国王。希腊少数城池也因为贵族和平民的煽动叛乱不断受到骚扰。几乎每个国家都会有一部分人希望仿照拉西德蒙人，而另一部分人希望仿照雅典人。我相信很多人都满意地看着英格兰因为模仿低地国家而引起最近出现的麻烦。他们认为变得富裕只需像他们那样改变一下政府的形式足矣。因为人类天性就喜欢新奇，当他们看到邻国用某种方式变得富裕，就激励了他们也这样做，他们就不可能不对那些唆使他们这么做的人感到满意了。最开始他们是喜爱的，但他们又会对持续的混乱感到悲伤，就像发痒的热血之人，他们会用指甲挠发痒的地方，直到他们不能忍受疼痛为止。

至于专门反抗君主制的叛乱，最常见的原因之一就是阅读关于古希腊、古罗马政治的历史书籍。从这些书中，那些年轻人和不具备坚定理智的人从他们军队的伟大战绩中获得了强烈的喜悦感，也对他们所做的一切感到满意，心中想象他们的伟大繁荣不是从哪一个人的好强中得来的，而是从平民政府的形式中得来的，他们没有考虑到因为政策不完善而导致的经常性叛乱和内战。我是说阅读这类书籍人们就会杀死他们的国王，因为在希腊和拉丁作家的书以及政治论述中，任何人杀死他们的国王都是合法且值得称赞的行为，只要他杀死国王之前称之为暴君。他们不说弑君，即杀死国王合法，而说弑杀暴君，即杀死暴君是合法的。从同种书里，生活在君主制国家中的人们有一种看法，即生活在民主制国家的人们享受自由，但生活在君主制国家中的所有人都是奴隶。我说的生活在君主制国家中而不是生活在民主政府统治下的人们拥有这种观点，是因为生活在民主政府统治下的人们找不到这种事情。总之，我不能想象有什么比不让谨慎的大师们修改这些书，去除其中有害部分就直接允许这些书被公开阅读更有害于君主制国家了。我会毫不犹豫地将这种毒害比作被疯狗咬伤，医生将这种病称为恐水症，或惧水病。因为被咬的人会一直口渴而又怕水，就像这种毒要把他变成一只狗。因此，当一个君主制国家的状况被民主作家不断狂咬，它需要的正是一个强有力的君主；但又由于某种暴力恐惧症，或惧怕被强烈统治，当人们拥有了这样的君主后，又会感到害怕。

正如有些人认为人有三个灵魂一样，也有人认为一个国家可能有不止一个灵魂（即多个主权者）。并建立最高权力与主权对立，建立教规与法律对立，建立神权与民权对立。他们用一些本身无所指的词语和区别扰乱人们的思想，让他们思想中朦胧地显示出有另外一个看不见的王国，正如黑暗中的精灵王国。现在明显可以看出，民权和国家权力是同一个东西，最高权力、制定教规的权力和授予宗教人员特权的权力意味着一个国家。可以得出，一个地方有主权者，又有最高权力者，一方可以制定法律，而另一方就可以制定教规，同一个臣民或同样的臣民就有两个国家，这个王国自身会分裂，无法继续存在。尽管可以对世俗和神进行毫无意义的区分，它们仍然是两个王国，每个臣民必须服从两个统治者。由于神权挑战了宣布什么是罪的权力，因此也就有权宣布什么是法律（罪，正是对法律的侵犯）；同理，民权也挑战宣布什么是法律的权力，每个臣民都必须服从两个统治者，他们都要人们把他们的命令当成法律遵守，这是不可能的。或者只有一个王国，要不就是国家权力的民权服从神权，这样只有神权而没有统治权；或者神权必须服从世俗权力，这样就仅仅存在最高世俗权力。因此当这两种权力相互对抗时，国家就会陷入内战和解体的巨大危机。由于世俗权力是可见的，从自然理性方面看更加明显，这就只能使相当一部分人一直倾向于它。神灵权力尽管只存在于经院学派区别的黑暗和晦涩词语中，由于人类对黑暗和鬼魂的恐惧大于任何其他恐惧，就不会有能够扰乱并有时能摧毁国家的党派了。这种疾病可以不恰当地比喻为癫痫（犹太人认为这是一种由于灵魂占据身体导致的病）。由于在这种病中，有一种非自然的灵魂或风进入大脑，阻碍了神经根部，并使之剧烈运动，使本应由大脑灵魂力量引起的运动消失，因此在这些部位引起剧烈不规律的运动（人们称之为痉挛），得了这种病的人由于感觉已经被剥夺，有时会掉进水中，有时会掉入火里。在国家中也是一样，当神灵的权力借助人们对惩罚的恐惧和对奖励的渴望（这两者是国家的神经）来推动国家运作，而不是通过本应通过的民权（这是国家的灵魂）运作国家，此外用奇怪晦涩的词语让人们的理解窒息，以此定会误导人民，不是运用压迫使国家灭亡就是让国家燃起内战的硝烟。

有时在一个纯粹的世俗政府中也不止有一个灵魂：例如税收权就起到营养作用，这取决于全体大会；行为和命令权是行动能力，这取决于一个人；立法权是理智能力，这取决于以上两者和第三者偶然性的同意。由于有时没有同意良好法律的施行，国家就会面临危险。但更多时候则是由于缺乏生命必需的营养和运动。因为尽管极少数人认为这样的政府不是真正的政府，而是国家三个派系中的一个，称之为混成君主制国家。然而事实是，这并不是一个独立的国家，而是三个独立的派系；它也不是一个代表，而是三个代表。在上帝的王国里，可能有三个独立而不破坏上帝统一的人进行统治；但在人统治的地方，由于意见各不相同，就不可能是上述情况。因此如果国王代表人民的意志，全体大会也代表人民的意志，另外一个大会也代表一部分人民的意志，那么他们就不代表相同意志，也不是一个主权者，而是代表三种意志和三个主权者。

我不知道我能把一个国家的这种不正常状态准确地比作人身体的什么疾病，但是我见过一个人在他一侧又长出一个人来，有自己的头、胳膊、胸部和胃；如果在他的另一侧又长出一个人来，那么这个比喻就准确了。

到现在为止，我所列举的国家疾病都是最严重的，患病当下十分危险。除此之外还有并不十分严重的疾病，但也要加以注意。首先，为国家必需的用途而筹集资金的困难，尤其是面临战争时。这种困难来自于一种观点，这种观点认为每个臣民对其土地和物品都有所有权，主权者的使用权排除在外。这样就会出现，在主权者预见到国家所需和危险时（发现由于人民的固执，征得的金钱不能上缴国库），他应当面对危机并将危机遏制在萌芽的时候，却尽其所能拖延，而当他不能继续拖延的时候，会用法律策略向人民施压，获得微不足道的金钱，当这些钱财不够时，最后他就只能运用暴力手段开金钱之源，否则国家就会灭亡。一般来说，运用这些极端手段后，人民的情绪最终会平静，否则国家一定会灭亡。由此我们可以把这种病疫十分贴切地比作疟疾，疟疾的症状是肌肉部分僵化或被有毒物质堵塞，血液通过静脉向心脏输送，心脏就不能（像本应的那样）从动脉获得血液，由此首先会产生发冷收缩，四肢颤抖，之后产生热量，强力推向心脏为血液打开通道。而在这之前，它可能会通过降温来稍稍恢复精神使自己得到满足，直到（如果身体条件足够强壮）最后冲破阻塞部位，将有毒物质通过汗液排出，若是（身体条件太弱）的病人，就会死亡。

同样，一个国家有时有一种疾病，和肋膜炎类似。那就是当一个国家的财政运行失控，由于公共税收的垄断或控制使过多钱财掌握在一个或几个人手中，就像肋膜炎中的血进入肋膜，造成发炎，伴有发烧和强烈针刺痛感。

同样，一个有权势的臣民的名望，（除非国家对他的忠诚具有非常高的信任）是一种危险的疾病。因为人民（本该从统治者权力那里获得行动命令）会通过奉承和具有野心之人的声誉而不再服从法律，而是服从另一个人，而人们对这个人的品德和目的毫无所知。这种事情一般来说对一个民主政府的危害比对一个君主制政府的危害更大，因为民主国家的军队力量雄厚，人数众多，这样就很容易将他们伪装成人民。尤利乌斯·恺撒就是运用这种方法获得人民支持反对元老院，使自己成为元老院和人民的主人。这种赢得民心拥有野心之人的做法就是明显的叛乱，并可以同巫术的效果相当。

国家的另一种疾病是城镇规模过大，这样国家就可以从自己的城市中组建起人员庞大的军队并负担其支出。自治城市过多也是一样，它们像一个巨大国家中的许多小国家，就像人肠道中的蠕虫。我在此要作一些补充，那些冒牌政治家对绝对权力提出异议，他们中的大部分人来自人民中的渣滓，由于被虚假知识蒙蔽，就一直干涉基本法律骚扰国家，就像医生称为蛔虫的小蠕虫一样。

我们可以进一步补充，无法满足的领土扩张欲望或贪念，外加敌人多次造成的不可治愈之伤，还有已经征服而未统一的领土，常常是一种负担，失去它相对于保留它的危险更小。懒惰享受、虚荣浪费也是一样。

最后，在战争中（对外或对内战争）敌方取得最后胜利，到了己方力量不能控制战场时，就不能对忠诚的臣民加以更多保护了，这时国家解体，每个人都有自由根据自己的判断选择保护自己的方式。因为主权者是给予国家生命和运动的公共灵魂，当灵魂不在时，四肢就不再受它的支配，就如同人的尸体不受离开躯体的灵魂（尽管灵魂不朽）支配一样。虽然主权君主的权利不会因为另一个人的行为而被消灭，但臣民的义务可以被消灭。因为渴望得到保护的人可以去任何地方寻求保护，当他得到保护时，就有义务（不假装表现出他是出于害怕而臣服）尽其可能保护好他受到的保护。但是一旦一个集会的权力被镇压，其权利最后也同样完全消失。因为集会本身已经消失，进而主权就不可能再重建了。

[……]

论黑暗王国

从空虚哲学和难以置信的经外传说而来的黑暗

哲学就是对一切事物产生的方式进行推理得到性质，或根据事物性质推理得到其可能的产生方式，最终产生在物质和人的力量允许范围内生活所需的效果。因此，几何学家从图像的结构中找出它的许多性质，从这些性质出发，通过推理得到新的构成方法，最终达到丈量土地、水域以及其他无限用途。同样，天文学家从太阳和恒星在天空中不同位置的升起、下落和运动找出产生昼夜更替、四季轮回的原因，通过这些来记录时间，并找到了类似的其他科学。

定义十分明确地告诉我们，不能把包括谨慎推测的原始知识（即所说的经验）当成哲学的任何部分；因为它不是由推理而来，在野兽和人身上都可以找到它，它仅仅是对过去发生的一连串事件的记忆，对其中极小事件的忽略就会改变结果，进而破坏谨慎推测的最终预期。然而从正确的推理中得到的不是别的，正是普遍、永恒不变的真理。

因此我们不能将任何错误结论用哲学一词冠名。因为用他理解的词语作正确推理的人永远不会得出错误结论。

任何人通过超自然启示所得到的也不能称为哲学，因为他得到的不是由推理而来。

由权威书籍进行推理所获得的也不能称为哲学，因为他所获得的不是从由因及果或由果及因的推理而来，这不是知识，仅是信仰。

推理能力是语言使用的结果，因此通过推理发现和语言本身一样古老的普遍真理不是不可能的。美洲野蛮人不是没有一些好的道德警句，此外他们也有有限的算术知识对不大的数字进行加减运算，但他们不会因此成为哲学家。早在人类以橡子和水为生时，就有少量玉米酿酒植物分散在田野和树林中，但那时人类并不懂得它们的价值，也就不会为了获取它们的营养去种植它们。同样的，从一开始就有各种正确、普遍存在并有利于人类的推理，比如自然植物，但其数量很少，而人类没有任何经验，也不懂得方法，也就是说，除了野草以及对普通植物的错误认识和猜想，他们对播种和种植完全没有认知。其原因是人们在获取生活必需品和防范邻居之外就没有休闲时间了。而当伟大的国家建立后，这一切才会改观。休闲是哲学之母，而国家是和平与休闲之母。哪里有伟大繁荣的城市，哪里就首先有哲学研究。印度秘密信仰的信奉者，波斯的魔术家、占星家，埃及和迦勒底的神父都被算作最古老的哲学家，这些国家也被列为最古老的王国。在希腊和其他西方国家（也许不比卢卡或日内瓦面积大）拥有和平之前，他们对对方充满相同恐惧，或除了观察对方而没有空闲观察其他事物时，哲学不会出现。最后，当战争使希腊这些较小城池统一成少数规模较大的城池时，才有来自希腊几个地区的七个人获得了贤人的名誉。他们中的一些人以道德和政治警句闻名，其他一些人以研究迦勒底和埃及人的学术成果，即天文学和几何学而闻名。但我们当时从未听说过任何哲学学派。

在雅典人打败了波斯军队后，获得海上统治权，进而获得了爱琴海、亚洲、欧洲所有岛屿和沿海城市的统治权，慢慢变得富有，在国内外没有工作的人无事可做，只能（如《使徒行传》第十七章第二十一节圣卢克所说）聊聊新闻，或向城市里的青年公开讲授哲学。每个大家都会为讲学找一个位置，柏拉图找了一个叫学院的公共场地，其名字源于一个雅典学园，亚里士多德在一个叫潘的庙宇里讲学，称为律西昂，有些人在拱廊、柱廊下，或商人摆地摊的走廊中讲学。有些人在另一些位置通过教学或观点争论打发他们的闲暇时光。有些人则在任何地方，只要那里能让城市中的青年聚集在一起听他们演讲。这就是卡尔涅阿德斯在罗马当使者时所做的，导致卡托建议元老院将其迅速赶走，因为他担心青年人因喜欢听卡尔涅阿德斯的美好言论（他们这样认为）而腐蚀他们的举止。

因此，他们进行授课或争论观点的任何地方都被称为学院（Schola），该词在他们口中就是休闲的意思，争论在他们口中就是讽刺，即消磨时光。哲学家们本身也以他们的学派为名，他们中有些人就是以这些学派命名的，信仰柏拉图学术的人称为学院派，亚里士多德的追随者因为他教学的走廊而称为逍遥学派（又：亚里士多德学派），那些芝诺的学徒在拱廊、柱廊中学习，则称为廊派，由于他们经常在那里聚集闲谈或闲逛，好像我们就应称他们为莫菲尔德人、保罗教堂人或交易所人。

然而人们非常喜欢这种习惯，一时间很快传播到欧洲和非洲的绝大部分地区，因此几乎这些地区的每个国家都公开建立学校并保持讲座和辩论。

古代我们的救世主时期之前和之后，犹太人中也有学派，但是是他们的法律学派。虽然它们被称为犹太教堂集会，即人民的集会。然而法律规定基本是在每个安息日进行阅读、阐释和辩论的，因此它们的本质同公开学派没有什么不同，仅仅是名字上的差异罢了。这种犹太教堂集会不仅存在于耶路撒冷，在每个犹太人居住的外邦人的城市中也都存在。在大马士革就有这样一个集会，保罗曾进去过并进行迫害。在安提阿、以哥念和塞萨洛尼卡的其他集会中，他也进去辩论过。位于利伯丁（Libertines）、科里尼亚（Cyrenians）、亚历山大（Alexandrians）、希里亚（Cilicians）和亚洲其他地区的犹太教堂集会都是如此，这就是利伯丁学派以及位于耶路撒冷以外地区犹太人的学派。正是这些学派中的人同圣司提凡进行辩论的（《使徒行传》，第六章第九节）。

但是这些学派有何用处？如今的科学究竟有多少是源自于他们的理解和辩论呢？几何学是自然科学之母，然而却不是他们所带来的科学。柏拉图是希腊数一数二的哲学家，他禁止那些不懂一定几何知识的人加入他的学派。许多人对这种科学进行研究，给人类带来了很大好处，但从未提及他们的学派，也没有几何学家的任何派别，他们也没有哲学家的头衔。这些学派的自然哲学，与科学相比简直就是做梦，他们的语言毫无意义、可有可无。如果教授哲学的人没有深厚的几何知识积累，就不能避免上述情况。因为自然通过运动而产生作用，如果没有对线、形的比例和性质的知识，就不可能知道运动的方式和程度。他们的道德哲学不过是对他们的激情的描述。因为在没有世俗政府的情况下，行为规则就是自然法则，在世俗政府之内，则是民法。这种法则决定了什么是诚实、什么是不诚实，决定了公平与不公平，决定了普遍情况下什么是善，什么是恶。鉴于他们根据自己的喜好和厌恶制定善恶的规则，然而人们的好恶各不相同，就意味着不存在普遍同意的事情，于是每个人（只要他敢）都按照他们眼中善的标准行事，直到国家颠覆。他们的逻辑应该是采用推理的方法，但实际上却是一些用来迷惑那些提出问题的人的词语和发明。总之，没有任何事比老哲学家（如西塞罗所说，他就是其中之一）都不支持的事更荒谬了。我相信在自然哲学中没有什么比亚里士多德的形而上学更荒谬的了。他在《政治学》中所说的是与政府最不相容的东西，在《伦理学》中所讲的是最无知的东西。

犹太人的学派最初是摩西律法的学派，摩西下令（《申命记》第三十一章第十节）每七年中的最后一年，在帐篷宴会上应向所有人宣读这律法，让他们听见并学习。因此（俘虏后）在每个安息日宣读律法除了让人们熟悉他们应该遵守的训诫和向他们解释先知的著作外，不应有其他目的。但我们的救世主对他们的许多谴责可以表明，他们用自己虚假的注释和苍白的经外传说误解了法律文本。他们对先知的了解很少，所以他们既不承认先知预言的基督，也不承认他所做的一切。因此，通过他们在犹太教堂集会中的讲座和争论，他们将法律原则变成了一种关于不可理解的上帝和灵的虚无空想的哲学。他们将最容易经过曲解而支撑他们达到目的的《圣经》模糊晦涩之处，以及他们祖先难以置信的传统混合在一起，将自己的怪想和虚无的哲学以及神学理论混合，创造出了这种虚无空想的哲学。

现在所说的大学是在一个或同一个城镇中集合起来的许多学派，在一个政府管理之下形成的组织。大学中主要学派有三个方向，即：罗马宗教、罗马法律和医学。至于哲学研究并没有什么地位，只是罗马宗教的女佣罢了。并且由于亚里士多德的权威是那里唯一盛行的学派，因此这种研究不是真正的哲学（其性质不取决于作家）而是亚里士多德学。对于几何学，由于它不屈服于任何事物而只服从严格的真理，所以直到最近为止它是完全没有地位的。如果哪个人凭借自己与生俱来的天赋在这方面取得了任何程度的完美，一般他会被认为是魔术师，他的艺术只能用恶魔般的加以形容。

现在谈论一下部分来自于亚里士多德，部分来自于盲目理解的具体虚无哲学的教义，这些教义首先传入大学，然后传入教会。我将首先讨论它们的原理。有一种其他所有哲学应该依靠的原始哲学，其主要由最普遍名称或名词意义的正确界定。这种界定是为了避免推理中的模糊和模棱两可，一般称为定义，例如物体、时间、地点、物质（Matter）、形态、要素、主题、物质（Substance）、偶然、权力、行为（Act）、有限、无限、量、质、运动、行为（Action）、激情和其他解释人们对物体的性质和来源所必需的多种定义。这些和类似术语的解释（就是意义的确定）作为亚里士多德哲学的一部分，在经院学派中一般称为形而上学，这就是其名称，但意义却不一样。因为那里所指的是写在或位于他自然哲学后的书籍。但是经院学派却把它们当作超自然哲学的书籍，因为形而上学可以同时拥有这两种意义。书中所写的大部分内容确实难以理解，也和自然理性存在巨大冲突，以至于任何认为可以用它来理解任何事物的人必须认为它是超自然的。

从混合有《圣经》的形而上学而组成的经院学派神学来看，我们可知世界上存在某种与物体相分离的要素，它们被称为抽象本质和实体形式。要解释这个术语，在这里需要多加注意。另外，我要向不习惯这类讨论的人表示抱歉，因为我是要向那些习惯的人阐述。这个世界（我不仅仅指凡间，喜欢凡间的人是凡人，我也指整个宇宙，也就是全部存在事物的全部物质）是有形的，这就是说，是物体的，它拥有范围和大小，即：长度、宽度和深度。物体的每个部分也是物体，也有类似的范围和大小，因此宇宙中的每个部分都是物体，不是物体的东西也就不是宇宙中的一部分。因为宇宙即是所有，不是宇宙中一部分的事物即不存在，所以在任何地方都不存在。但也不能由此说灵是不存在的，因为它们也有范围和大小，因此它们是实在物体，虽然一般说话时只称可见可触的事物为物体，即有一定不透明度的物体。但对于灵来说，它们称之为无形物体，这个词语更加表示尊敬，因此可以更虔诚地形容上帝，至于上帝，我们不考虑什么词语能表明他的性质，那是不可以理解的，我们需要考虑的是用什么词能够最好地表达我们尊敬他的愿望。

为了知道他们依据什么说存在抽象本质和实体形式，我们将要考虑这些词语的确切所指。词语的使用是为了记录我们自己的想法，并向他人表明我们心中的想法和概念。有一些词语是被感知事物的名称，正如作用于感官并在我们的想象中留下一个印象的各种物体的名词。另外一些词语是关于想象本身的，这就是说，是关于我们所见或记忆中所有事物的观念或大脑中的图像。另外一些是名词的名词，或不同种类语言的名词。例如：普遍、复数、单数，都是名词的名词，定义、肯定、否定、真、假、三段论、讯问、承诺、协议，都是某些语言形式的名词。另一些词则用来表示一个名词和另一个名词间的推论或抵触关系。例如当一个人说：“人是一种物体”时，他指的是物体这一名词是人这一名词出现后出现的，是同一事物——人所对应的许多名词中的一个名词。它们之间的推论是由“Is”（是）这个字联结起来的。和我们用“Is”（是）字一样，拉丁人用他们的动词“Est”（是），希腊人用Eσu的各种变化来联结。我不知道世界上所有其他国家是否有他们的语言来表示这个字，但是我肯定他们不需要这种字，因为将两个名词按照一定顺序放在一起，符合他们的习惯，就可以像“Is”“Bee”或“Are”一样表示词语之间的关系了（因为正是习惯给予了词语力量）。

假设有一种语言没有对应Est、Is或Bee的任何动词，而使用这种语言的人进行推测、总结和各种推理的能力一点不比希腊和拉丁人差。如此一来，从它派生以及根据这些词语而来的最常使用的更多词语，例如实体、本质、必须、必须性，是什么呢？因此它们不是事物的名称，而是一个我们所知的符号，用它表示我们设想中一个名词或限定性词语对另一个词语的推论关系。例如，当我们说“人是一个活着的物体”时，并不表示人是一个东西，而活着的物体是另一种东西，Is（是）或Beeing（是）又是另一种东西。我们的意思是，人和活着的物体是一回事。因为“如果他是人，那么他就是一个活着的物体”是用Is（是）表示的真实正确的推论。因此，成为一个物体、走路、说话、生活、看见以及类似不定式同有形、行走、讲话、视力等类似名词所指的相同，正如我在其他地方更加充分表述的一样，都是无所指的名词。

但是（可能有人会说），在这种类型的著作中，我只意在说明政府和服从学说的必要内容，把书弄得如此微妙难懂是什么目的呢？我写书的目的就是让人们不再受他们的折磨，建立在亚里士多德虚无哲学基础上的独立本质的教义，用毫无意义的名词让人们受到惊吓，进而不服从他们国家的法律。就像人们用一件空的紧身上衣、一顶帽子和一个弯曲的棍子吓唬鸟类，不让它们接近谷物一样。因此基于这一点，当人死去并下葬后，他们说他的灵魂（即他的生命）会从他的身体中脱离并独立行走，夜晚在墓地中可以看见。基于同一点他们说，一片面包的形状、颜色和味道在不存在面包的地方也存在。同样，信念、智慧和其他美德有时是从天上灌输进人体的，而有时是吹进去的，好像品德高尚的人和他们所具有的品德可以分成很多部分一样，还有其他许多东西用来削弱臣民对他们国家主权者的依赖。如果一个人希望“服从”能被灌输或吹进他的体内，那么还有谁会遵守法律呢？谁不会去服从可以创造上帝的司祭，而服从统治者和上帝本身呢？那些害怕鬼魂的人谁不会对那些能够制造圣水并将鬼魂赶出他们体内的人怀有极大尊敬呢？这些例子就足以说明亚里士多德的实体和本质能给教会带来多大错误。可能他知道这是虚假哲学，但害怕苏格拉底的命运，因此仍然将它作为符合且确证他们宗教的东西写出来。

一旦陷入独立本质的错误，他们就会被卷入随之而来的许多其他荒谬之中。由于他们把这些形式看成是真实的，他们就有义务给它们安排一些空间。但由于他们认为这些东西是无形的，不存在任何范围和大小，并且所有人都知道空间就是范围和大小，只能用有形的事物填满，这样他们就被迫用一个区别来支撑他们的信用，说他们事实上在任何地方都没有界限，而限定的词语仅仅是文字而已，这些文字在这种情形下毫无意义，只在能够隐藏他们虚无性的拉丁语中产生作用。因为一个事物的界限除了它本身空间的测定和规定外什么都不是，因此作出区分的两个词语就是一样的。尤其是他们说人的本质就是他的灵魂，他们确定灵魂的全部都在他的小指上，也存在于他身体的其他每个部分（不论多小），整个身体中的灵魂并不比身体任何一部分中的灵魂多。有谁会认为上帝相信这种荒谬之言呢？但是那些认为躯体之外存在与躯体分离的灵魂的人则必须相信它。

当要他们讲述无形实体如何经受痛苦，如何经受地狱之火和炼狱的折磨时，他们却无言以答，只能说他们不知道火焰如何烧毁灵魂。

再者，由于运动是空间的改变，而无形实体是不具有空间的，因此他们很难将如下事情变成似乎具有可能性：灵魂如何能够离开身体去往天堂、地狱或炼狱；人的鬼魂（我可以加上它们出现时穿的衣服）如何能于夜间在教堂、教堂庭院和其他墓地徘徊。我不知道他们能否回答这些问题，除非他们说它们是在限定地行走而不是受界限地行走，是它们的灵在行走而不是躯体在行走。因为这种牵强无理的区别对任何难题都同样适用。

关于永恒的意义，他们不将它看作是时间的无穷延续。因为这样他们就不能说出为什么上帝意图以及对即将发生的事物的规定，不发生在他对相同事物的预知之前，如同有效原因出现在结果之前或行为人出现在行为发生之前；关于不可理解的上帝本质的大胆观点，他们也不能给出理由。但是他们会告诉我们，永恒是时间的停滞，即停顿的现在（经院学派如此称呼），他们和其他人都不理解，最多用“停顿的现在”表示空间的无限广阔。

人们在内心通过对各部分进行计数来划分一个物体，对这些部分进行计数时，也就对这些部分填充的空间进行了计数。因此在设计这些部分时，我们只有同时设计出这些部分需要的空间。所以，任何人都不能想象出比所需空间更多或更少的部分。但是他们会让我们相信，通过上帝的全能，一个物体可以在同一时刻出现在很多地方，许多物体也可以在同一时刻出现在同一个地方。仿佛是说，承认了神圣的能力，可以使存在的东西不存在，曾经存在的东西并不存在。这只是他们对本应怀有崇敬和爱慕的神和不可理解的自然在哲学上争辩而必然产生不一致的一小部分。这些定语不能说明神是什么，但应该用我们能够想到的最好的称呼表达我们尊敬他的愿望。但是那些冒险从这些尊敬定语中对他的本质进行推理的人，在最开始就失去了他们的理解，陷入无穷无尽的困境之中。就像一个疏于朝堂礼仪的人遇见了一个比他通常打交道的更伟大的人时，在门口就跌跌撞撞，想要稳住身体不跌倒，衣服却滑落下来；穿上衣服时，帽子又掉了，混乱的情况一个接一个，他才会发现自己的惊慌失措。

下面说物理学，它是对自然事件从属或低一级原因的知识。他们除了一些空话什么都没有提出来。如果你想知道为什么某种物体会自然地朝地面掉落，而其他物体则自然地上升，经院学派就会根据亚里士多德的理论，告诉你掉落的物体是重的，正是物体的重量导致了它们掉落。但是如果你问他们重量是什么意思，他们就会将其定义为朝着地心运动的努力。因此物体下落的原因就是一种要处在下面的努力。这就是说，物体下落或上升的原因是它们要这么做。或者他们会告诉你地心是重的物体的休息和存放处，因此它们努力到那里。就像石头和金属如同人类一样拥有欲望，可以辨认它们将要去的地方，或者它们喜欢休息而人类不喜欢，又或者一片安装在窗户上的玻璃还没有掉到街上安全。

如果我们要知道为什么同一个物体（不给它增加什么的情况下）在某个时候看上去比其他时候更大，他们说，当它看上去小一些的时候，是因为它凝缩了；当它看上去大一些的时候，是因为它变稀薄了。什么是凝缩和稀薄呢？凝缩就是同一物质比之前质量减轻了，而稀薄就是质量相比之前增加了。就像存在一种没有确定质量的物质，质量不是别的，只是物质的确定。这就是说，我们以此说一个物体比另一个物体大（多）或小（少）。或者好像一个物体在被创造出来时根本没有质量，之后再根据人们希望物体密度更大或更小而多加或少加一些东西。

至于人类灵魂的成因，他们说，通过加入而创造和通过创造而加入。

而感觉的原因，就是个体的普遍性，即物体的显现或幻影。当幻影被眼睛看见时，就是视觉，当它被耳朵听见时，就是听觉，能被舌头品味时，就是味觉，被鼻子嗅出时，就是嗅觉，被身体其他部分感觉到时，就是感觉。

对于意志——即进行特定行为的意愿，形成的原因，他们把其归因于能力，即人类普遍拥有的有时想做一件事，有时又想做另一件事的能力，这就是所说的意图。这就把能力当成了行为的原因，就像一个人把人们的善行与恶行归因于他们具备行善与作恶的能力。

在很多情况下，他们把自己的无知当成了自然事件的原因，但却用其他词语进行掩盖。就像他们说，运气是偶然事件发生的原因，而偶然事件就是他们不知道发生原因的事件。他们还把许多结果归因于超自然的神秘性质：即他们不知道的性质，因此（如他们所想）其他人也同样不知道。他们还把许多结果归因于同情、反感、相反特性、特殊素养和其他类似词语，它们既不表示产生它们的人，也不表示它们产生所依赖的操作。

如果这种形而上学和物理学不是虚无哲学，那么就不存在任何虚无哲学，圣保罗也不需要警告我们避免它了。

至于他们的道德和世俗哲学，也是一样或更加荒谬。如果一个人做了非正义行为，就是说，与法律相冲突的行为，他们就说上帝是法律产生的最初原因，也是这一行为和其他所有行为的最初原因，但肯定不是非正义行为——即不遵守法律行为的最初原因。这就是虚无哲学。人们同样可以说，一个人既画了一条直线，又画了一条曲线，这是其他人造成的不协调。这就是在知道前提之前，预先得出结论的所有人的哲学。他们假装能够理解不可能理解的事，把尊敬的定语说成本质的定语，因为这一区别是用作保持自由意志教义的，即人的意志不服从上帝的意志。

亚里士多德和其他异教哲学家根据人的欲望定义善恶。只要我们认为他们是根据自己的法则统治所有人，这样就很好。因为如果人们除了自己的欲望之外就没有其他法则，那么就不可能存在善行与恶行的法则。但是在一个国家中，这个衡量标准是错误的，个人的行为不能成为衡量标准，作为衡量标准的应是法律，即国家的意志和欲望。而这一教条并没有得到贯彻实施，人们还是根据自身的激情判断自己的善恶、判断他人和国家行为的善恶。人们完全不考虑公共法律，而是根据自己的看法称为善或恶。不只是发过誓必须无条件遵守上级的僧侣和助理僧侣，每个臣民都应认为自己受到自然法则的约束而服从世俗主权者。这种关于善的个人衡量标准不仅是虚无的教义，也是对公共国家的危害。

认为婚姻与贞节或节欲存在冲突，因此把它们当成道德罪行的说法也是虚无和虚假哲学。这些人以贞节和节欲为由不许教士结婚。他们坦白，以贞节、节欲和纯洁为名义，要求祭坛侍者和圣礼管理者一直和女人保持距离，而这只是教会的一项制度。他们把夫妻合法同居称为无贞节以及非节欲行为，因此人们将婚姻当成一种罪，至少是一点儿都不纯洁、不干净的东西，所以这些人是不适合作为祭坛侍者的。如果法律是因为夫妻同居是非节欲、有违贞节而制定，那么所有婚姻都是罪恶的。如果对于献身上帝的人来说这是一件十分肮脏的事情，那么做更多自然、必要和日常工作的所有人都不配成为司祭，因为他们更不干净。

制定禁止司祭结婚规定的秘密基础不是轻而易举的事情，它不会依据道德哲学的这种错误，也不会依据相比婚姻生活更愿独自生活而制定此规。后者从圣保罗的智慧而来，他意识到在福音传播者受迫害的时期，他们被迫从一个国家到另一个国家传教，照顾妻儿是多么不方便的一件事。该规定的制定是依据教皇们和后来的司祭们把自己变成牧师，也就是在这个世界上上帝王国唯一继承人的企图，对于上帝王国，有必要让他们远离婚姻，因为我们的救世主说过，他的王国来到之际，上帝的子民们既不能迎娶，也不能出嫁，而应像天上的天使一样，也就是说，成为灵。既然他们已经以灵之名自称，那么（在不需要时）允许自己拥有妻子就是一件不协调、不一致的事情。

他们从亚里士多德的世俗哲学中学到，除了平民国家以外的所有国家（例如当时的雅典）都称为暴政国家。他们称所有国王为暴君，由征服他们的拉塞得孟尼人建立的三十个贵族统治者被称为三十暴君。他们把民主之下人们的状况称为自由。暴君最初所指不过是君王，但在希腊大部分地区的这种政府被废除之后，暴君一词在原本拥有的意义之外，还有平民国家对其的憎恨。就像在罗马废除国王后，国王一词便为人们所憎恨。因为对所有人来说，用带有鄙视意义的词形容强大敌人的巨大过错是十分自然的事情。当同一些人对民主统治或贵族统治不满时，他们不用寻找一些臭词表达愤怒，而是用现成的词：无政府状态来表达，并把另一个称为寡头统治或少数人的暴政统治。侵犯人民的不是其他，而是他们并不是按照每个人希望的方式被统治，即作为公共代表，不论是一个人还是大会全体认为合适的方式被统治，即受一个专制政府的统治。他们因此骂他们的上级，从不知道（也许在内战之后会知道一点点）如果没有这样的专制政府，这种战争将会永远继续下去，他们认识到，是人和武力使法律具有力量和权力，而不是语言和承诺。

因此亚里士多德的政治学中有另一个错误，即：在秩序井然的国家里，进行统治的不是人，而应是法律。一个具有正常感觉的人，尽管他不能读写，但怎么会看不到他受着自己惧怕、并相信在他不服从时会被伤害或杀害的人们统治呢？谁会相信在语言和文字的背后没有权力之手和权力之剑在操纵呢？这是有毒害的错误之一，因为这些错误诱导人们在不喜欢他们的统治者时，就依附于称统治者为暴君的人，并认为对这些暴君发动战争进行反抗是合法的。而牧师有时却在讲坛上宣扬珍视这些错误。

他们的世俗哲学中还有另一个错误，这一错误既不是从亚里士多德、西塞罗，也不是从其他任何异教徒那里学到的，即尽管人们的语言和行为都符合规范，却通过对他们所持信仰进行检查和质询，把仅是行为规则的法律权威扩展到每个人的思想里和良心上。如此一来，人们不是由于回答了他们的真实思想而受惩罚，就是因为害怕惩罚而不吐真情。的确，当一个世俗管理者想雇用一个传教的官员时，可以询问他是否愿意传此教义，如果他拒绝，就可以不雇用他。但是当他的行为并不为法律所禁止时，强迫他控诉自己的观点是违背自然法则的，特别是喜欢说教的那些人，如果一个人对基督教信仰的条目具有错误见解，那么这个人应该受到永远、极度的痛苦折磨。如果一个人知道犯这种错误的危险如此之大，他又与生俱来就关心自己，为什么不让自己的灵魂根据自己的判断去尝试，而要根据任何其他不关心自己罪行的人的判断行动呢？

对于一个平民来说，他没有国家的权力，就是说，没有代表国家的人允许他按照自己的精神解释法律，这就是政治学中的另一个错误，但是这个错误既不来自亚里士多德，也不是自其他任何异教徒哲学家而来。因为他们没有一个人否认制定法律的权力中含有在他们认为需要时解释法律的权力。《圣经》中所有有法律的地方都是由国家的权力制定的，因此，《圣经》难道就不是法律的一部分吗？

还有同一种错误，即除主权者外，任何人限制他人拥有国家没有限制的权力。例如，让凡夫俗子向法律给予其自由的人传教是不合适的。如果国家让我传教或讲道，即如果国家没有禁止我，那么就没有人能够禁止我。如果我发现自己身处美洲的偶像崇拜者中，作为一个基督徒，虽然我没有从事司祭一职，我也应认为在收到罗马命令之前传播基督教是一种罪。在我开始传教后，难道我不能解答他们的疑惑并向他们解释《圣经》吗？或者说，难道我不能传教吗？但针对这一点有些人可能会说，如同为他们进行圣礼，必要性必须建立在一个具有足够说服力的任务上，这是正确的。但还有另外一件事也是正确的，对任何事来说，在必要时就宽免，当没有法律禁止它时，就不需要宽免。因此，否定世俗主权者没有否定的职能就是剥夺了合法的自由，这同世俗政府的教义相矛盾。

由经院神学博士们引入的虚无哲学的例子不止这些。其他人如果愿意可以自己去看。我只想补充的是，经院神学的作品大部分是无足轻重的一串串奇怪和粗野之词，要不就是不同于通用拉丁语的词语，这样就能向西塞罗、法罗和所有古罗马文法家进行炫耀。如果谁想要证明真实与否，可以让他（如我之前所说）看看自己能否将任何经院神学作品翻译成任何现代语言，例如法语和英语，或任何其他丰富的语言。因为如果大部分内容不能让人理解的话，用拉丁语表达也不能让人理解。这种毫无意义的语言，虽然我不能说它是伪哲学，但它具有隐藏真理、让人们认为他们已经得到真理而不坚持深入研究的性质。

最后，从虚假或不确定的历史而来的错误，这是圣人生活中虚构奇迹的传说。罗马教会博士根据幽灵和鬼魂的历史声称他们对地域、炼狱和驱魔的作用，还有在理性和《圣经》中没有依据的作用。他们还把所有那些传统称为未记录的上帝语言，但那些仅仅是愚蠢的传说。尽管这些传统也分散于古代神父的著作中，但那些神父也是人，也可能轻易相信虚假传说，并提出观点说明他们相信的东西是真理，（依据圣约翰的建议）检查灵的人（见《圣约翰书信》第四章第一节）其作用仅仅是对有关罗马教会权力的所有事情（这种滥用不是他们没有产生怀疑就是通过权力获益），因为草率地相信传说而怀疑不信任他们的证据。最真诚的人，如果他没有关于自然原理的大量知识（例如神父们就是这样），他们一般就很容易草率地相信传说。因为从本质上讲，最本分的人最不会怀疑其具有欺骗目的。教皇格雷戈里和圣伯纳德有一些鬼魂幽灵之说，说他们在炼狱中，我国的贝达也有类似之说；但是我相信这些传说只是从其他人那里听说的。但如果他们或其他任何人依据自己的知识讲述任何类似的故事，他们最多也只能确认这些是虚无的传说，却能发现他们的弱点或欺诈。

介绍了虚无哲学，我们还可以讲一下被那些既没有合法权威也没有足够学识来对真理进行判断的人压制的真正哲学。我们的方向表明，所有精通人类科学的人现在都承认有恰好相反的事物。随着时间一天天流逝，其表现得越来越清楚，每一日和年的变化是由于地球运动决定的。然而，人们在他们的著作中只是假定了这一推论，并为支持和反对意见敞开大门，就受到了教会的惩罚。但这样做的理由是什么呢？是因为这样的观点违背真正的宗教吗？如果这些意见是正确的，就不可能如此。因此，就让有资格的评判员首先对其进行检查吧，或者让那些假装知道相反观点的人去驳斥吧。是因为它们违反既有宗教吗？就让它们在教授这些传教者们的君主的法律，即在世俗法律下沉默吧。因为即使是教授真正哲学的人违反法律时，也可以合法地惩罚他们。是因为它们赞同叛乱或骚乱而使政府陷于混乱吗？就让那些负责公共秩序的人，即世俗权威用他们的权力惩罚这些人，让他们安静吧。因为教会权力会（在他们服从国家的任何地方）用自己的权力谋取权力，虽然他们称之为上帝的权力，但实际上是篡夺。

由这种黑暗而来的利益及其归属

西塞罗怀着崇敬的心情提到一位叫卡西的严厉的罗马法官，因为卡西在处理犯罪案件时有一套惯例，即（当目击人不能提供充分证据时）询问原告，这就是说，被告方因被起诉事件获得了或期望获得什么利益、荣誉或其他满足。因为在推测中，没有什么比获得利益的行为更能清晰地说明当事人的问题。在此，我想以同样规则检查，是什么人用这些与人类和平社会相违背的教义让这一部分基督教国家的人民误信了如此之久。

首先，有一种错误，即：目前地球上的教会激进分子就是上帝王国（即荣耀之国、乐土，而不是恩泽之国，这只是应许之地）与尘世利益相连。第一，教会的牧师和传教者作为上帝公使，有权利管理教会。因此（由于教会和国家是相同人格）他们就成为国家的长官和统治者。既有这一头衔，教皇就说服所有基督教信徒相信违背他的旨意就是违背基督教本身。其他基督教信徒若与他有任何分歧（受到灵权的迷惑）就要放弃服从他们的合法统治者，这事实上就是统治整个基督教世界的君王。因为尽管最初是基督教皇以及罗马帝国允许（他们承认这一点）授予他们为世俗国家的官员最高祭司长，享有基督教义最高教授者的权利，但在经过分裂和解体后，就不难在已经臣服于他们的人们身上强加上另一个称为圣彼得权利的头衔。这不仅是保护他们号称的所有权力，也要把同样权力拓展到其他基督教省份中去，虽然这些省份已经不联合在罗马帝国中了。这种普遍君主制的利益（考虑到人们对统治的渴望）就是一个充分的推测，号称具有普遍统治权并长期享有它的教皇就是此教义的创造者，他以此获得了统治权，这一教义就是：目前地球上的教会就是基督王国。因为承认了这一点，就必须要承认基督在我们中间有一些助理人员，基督通过他们向我们传达他的指令。

在一些教会否认了教皇的普遍统治权后，人们就有理由推测，在所有这些教会中的世俗主权者们应该收回他们之前不慎从自己手中让出的权力。在英格兰事实就是这样，只不过国王任命管理教区政府的人坚持他们是上帝任命的，既没有篡夺最高统治权，也独立于世俗权力之外。他们似乎是在承认国王可以任意剥夺他们行使职责的情况下，才发起篡夺。

但是在长老会掌权的地方，虽然禁止教授许多其他罗马教会的教义，然而基督王国的教义已经来到，其开始于我们的救世主复活之时的教义仍然被保存着。但是“对谁有利”呢？他们希望从中获得什么利益呢？教皇也希望如此：对人民拥有统治权。但是人们除了把他们的合法君主开除出教会，进而让他在自己的王国远离所有公共祭神职位，并且在他用暴力试图重获职位时能用暴力阻止他之外，还为了什么呢？在不顾世俗统治者的权力，将任何一个人开除出教会，剥夺他的合法自由、篡夺一种统治他们兄弟的非法权力之外，还为了什么呢？因此，宗教黑暗的创造者就是罗马教会和长老会教士。

在此之下，我也要提及帮助他们在获得灵的统治权之后，保持灵的统治权的教义。第一种说法是：“教皇在他的公职上不会犯错。”因为相信这一点的人，谁不会时刻听候他的命令呢？

第二种说法是，不管在什么国家，所有其他大主教的权力既不是从上帝那里直接获得的，也不是从他们的世俗统治者那里间接获得的，而是从教皇那里得来的。基于这种教义，每个基督教国家里都有很多有权势的人（主教就是这类人），他们依赖于教皇，服从教皇，虽然他是一个外国君主。通过这种方式，他就有能力（就像他多次所做的那样）针对不根据他的喜好和利益进行统治的国家发起内战。

第三种说法是，其他所有司祭、修道士和辅助修士都可以从民法权力中得到豁免。因为通过这种方式，每个国家的大部分人都能享受到法律的益处，并且受到世俗国家权力的保护，却不用支付任何公共开支，也不会像其他臣民一样因为犯罪而受到惩罚。因此，他们除了教皇之外谁都不怕，并且他们只依附于教皇，支持他的普遍君权。

第四种说法是，给予司祭们（在《新约》中就是长老的意思）司祭的称谓，上帝是他们的国王时，在犹太人中，这一称谓就是世俗统治者和公共牧师的头衔。此外，将主的晚餐作为祭祀，让人们相信教皇对所有基督徒都有摩西和艾伦对犹太人拥有的权力，这就是说，大司祭当时拥有世俗和神的一切权力。

第五种说法是，婚姻是一件圣事，给予了神职人员判断婚姻合法性的职责，继而认定哪些后代是合法的，再进一步认定谁具有王国的继承权。

第六种说法是，拒绝承认司祭的婚姻可以保证教皇对国王的权力。因为，如果一个国王是司祭的话，他就不能结婚，不能将其王国传给他的后代。如果一个国王不是司祭，那么教皇就会对国王和他的臣民行使神权。

第七种说法是，从秘密忏悔中他们可以获得比关于教会图谋情报更有价值的，关于国王和世俗国家大人物密谋的情报，并以此保证他们的权力。

第八种说法是，通过将圣人经典化并宣布谁是殉道者来保证他们的权力。如果教皇通过驱逐出教会来宣布他们是异教徒或教会的敌人，即（根据他们的解释）教皇的敌人，他们就可以引诱头脑简单的人们用生命同世俗统治者进行顽强抵抗。

第九种说法是，通过给予每个司祭传播基督教义、聆听忏悔和宽恕及封存罪来保证自己的权力。

第十种说法是，通过炼狱教义、借口外部工作以及放纵，神职人员变得更加富裕。

第十一种说法是，通过鬼神学和驱邪术以及其他相关东西，他们让（或者他们自以为让）人民对他们的权力更加畏惧。

最后一种说法是，大学（全部是由教皇权力建立和管理）里教授的亚里士多德的形而上学、伦理学和政治学，草率的区分、粗俗的术语和经院学者的晦涩语言，使他们的错误不被发现，并让人们把虚无哲学的鬼火误当作福音的光芒。

如果以上这些还不充分，我还可以补充他们的其他黑暗学说，其好处在于对建立凌驾于基督教人们合法统治之上的非法权力有助益，或者对建立起的权力的维持有益，或者对维持这种权力的人的世俗财富、荣誉和权威有益。因此根据之前所说的“对谁有利”的规则，我们可以公正地宣布，教皇、罗马神职人员和其他所有试图在人们心中建立这种错误学说，即：当前世界上的教会就是《旧约》和《新约》中他提到的上帝王国，这些人就是所有灵的黑暗。

但是在皇帝以及其他基督主权者的政府之下，这些错误和教会职责的侵犯，先是悄悄混进并扰乱了他们的财产和臣民的安宁。虽然他们因为缺少对后果的预见、对传道士阴谋的洞悉而受到同样的损害，但也可以认为是他们使自己和大众受到了损失。因为没有他们的允许，最初煽动之说就不可能公开传播。我说他们在开始时就可以阻止这些言论的传播。但是人们的心一旦被那些宗教人士占据，任何人都没有办法进行补救。上帝在对人类反对真理的所有阴谋进行及时摧毁上从未失败，我们只需等待上帝在愿意时提供补救办法。上帝很多时候都容忍敌人和他们的野心膨胀到一定高度，让产生的这种暴力打开前辈因为戒心封住的眼睛，并让人们因贪求太多而一无所获，就像彼得渔网中的鱼太多，一阵挣扎后弄破了渔网。然而那些没有耐心的人，在他们臣民的眼睛打开之前就力争抵抗这种侵占，却增加了他们所要抵抗的力量。因此我不责备腓特烈大帝为我国哈德良教皇执掌马鞭，因为当时他的臣民的意向安排就是如此，如果他没有那么做，他就不可能继承帝国。但是我要谴责的那些人的权力在开始是完整的，由于在属于他们领域的大学内伪造出这些学说，当继位教皇们登上所有基督教主权者的王座，任意践踏他们和他们的人民时，他们就不得不为这些人执掌马鞭。

人们内心捏造的东西是如何编织而成的，也可以以同样方式解开，其方法是相同的，只不过顺序就颠倒了。这个网最初由权力的要素构成：智慧、谦恭、真诚和使徒的其他美德。人们皈依、服从使徒是出于尊敬而不是义务。他们的良知是自由的，他们的语言、行动只臣服于民权。后来长老们（随着基督教徒的增加）聚集在一起考虑他们应该教授什么，并遵守不教授任何与他们会议规定相悖内容的原则，让人们因此认为有义务遵守他们的教义。如果当他们拒绝，就拒绝与他们为伍（当时这被称为开除教籍）。这不是因为把他们当作不信仰宗教的人，而是因为把他们当作不遵守的人而拒绝与他们为伍。这是在他们的自由之上打的第一个结。长老越来越多，主要城市或主要区域的长老们就拥有了掌管较小区域长老的权力，并恰如其分地给自己加上主教的称谓，这是在基督徒的自由之上打的第二个结。最后，罗马的主教因为皇城的关系，就自然而然拥有了掌管整个帝国其他所有主教的权力（这一部分是皇帝自身的意志，一部分是最高司祭长的称谓，最后当皇帝变弱时，就通过圣彼得的特权获得）。这就是第三个，也是最后一个结，也是教皇权力的全部综合和结构。

因此要通过同样方式来分析或解决，但是要从最后打的结着手，就像我们看到的英格兰高于政治的教会政府的解体一样。首先，伊丽莎白女王解除了教皇的权力。之前主教依据教皇的权力行使职权，而现在则要依据女王及其继承者的权力行使职权。他们仅仅是通过保留“按照天律”的说法，才被认为是直接接受上帝权力的命令。这样第一个结就打开了。之后，英格兰的长老们最近推翻了主教制度。这样就打开了第二个结。几乎与此同时，长老们的权力也被解除了。因此我们又回到了独立原始基督教徒的身份，去自由追随他们最喜欢的任何人，如保罗、矶法、阿波罗。如果这样没有竞争，不根据我们对牧师感情来衡量基督教义（使徒曾经在《哥林多后书》中斥责过这种错误）也许是最好的。第一，除了福音，不应有任何权力凌驾于人类良知之上，使道德信仰作用在每个人身上的并不永远根据种植浇灌它的人的目的，而是根据让它生长的上帝的目的。第二，有人教授说每个小错误中都蕴藏着大危险，就要求拥有理性的人接受其他任何人的理由或人群中的多数声音，这对他们来说是不合理的，这比他拿在十字架上的救赎来冒险好不了多少。而传教士们也不应因为失去了古时的权力而不高兴；因为谁都没有他们清楚，权力要靠获得权力的美德保持，即通过：智慧、谦恭、明晰教义和对话时的真诚来保持权力。依靠压制自然科学和自然理性的道德是不能使权力得到保持的。通过模糊的语言、妄称自己学富五车也不能保持权力；通过装神弄鬼的欺诈也不能保持权力。也不能用其他错误，比如对教会牧师而言不仅是错误，更是丑闻，当人们镇压他们的权力后迟早会摔跤的错误来保持权力。

但是在世界接受了现今激进的教会也就是《圣经》新约和旧约中所说的上帝王国的说法后，获得属于这些方面职位的渴望，尤其是基督助理人员这一伟大职位和获得了主要公共职位的人的渴望逐渐变得那么明显以至于失去了牧师职责拥有的内心尊敬。因为世俗国家中，那些拥有所有权力的人中最聪明的人，只需要获得君主的同意就可以不再进一步服从君主。自从罗马主教不得不承认自称是圣彼得继承人为最高主教之后，他们整个集团，或称之为黑暗王国，就可以被不恰当地同精灵王国作比较；也就是同英格兰老妇们所说的关于魔鬼和精灵在夜间闹鬼的传说作比较。如果一个人要探究这个伟大教会国家的起源，那么他很容易就能感觉到，教皇职位不过是死去的罗马帝国的鬼魂戴着皇冠坐在坟墓上而已。因为教皇职位也是突然从异教权的废墟上出现的。

他们在教会和公共法令中使用的拉丁语，目前在世界上任何国家都不是常用语言，这不是古罗马语言的鬼魂又是什么呢？

无论哪个国家的精灵，都只有一个普遍国王，我们的一些诗人称之为奥伯伦王，但是《圣经》中称为别西卜——恶魔之王。同样，无论教士在谁的领土内，只承认一个普遍国王，即教皇。

教士们是精神上的人，是鬼的神父。精灵和魔鬼居住在黑暗、偏僻的地方或墓地中。而教士们行走于晦涩的教义、修道院、教会和庭院中。

教士们有他们自己的大教堂，无论它们建立在哪个城镇中，通过圣水之德以及称为驱魔的某种魔力，就有力量将这些城镇变为城市，也就是帝国都城。精灵们也有它们拥有魔法的城堡，一些巨大的魔鬼主宰着城堡周围地区。

精灵们不会被抓起来讯问它们造成的伤害。因此教士们也从民事法庭上消失了。

教士们运用结合有形而上学、奇异之事、传说和滥改过的《圣经》的一些魔力带走了年轻人对理智的运用，教士们这么做并不为其他，只是让年轻人按照他们的命令行事。同样，据说精灵们将小孩儿从摇篮中带走，把他们变成天然傻瓜，因此一般人称他们为小“妖精”，经常搞恶作剧。

精灵在什么魔法店或操作室中施展魔法，老妇人们也不确定。但是教士的操作室则非常有名，就是人们从教皇权威那里接受他们教义的大学。

当精灵对任何人感到不满时，据说他们会派小“妖精”给他们点儿教训。当教士们对世俗国家感到不满时，也会派他们的小“妖精”，即迷信和受迷惑的臣民，通过宣传蛊惑言论给他们的君主一点儿教训，或让一个被承诺迷惑的君主去教训另一个君主。

精灵不会结婚，但是它们中间存在梦淫妖和有血有肉的凡人交配。教士也不结婚。

教士们通过对他们无比崇敬的无知之人的捐赠和什一税搜刮土地。在关于精灵的传说中，它们也进入牛奶厂，从牛奶中吸取奶油，饱餐一顿。

精灵王国使用何种钱币，精灵的传说故事中并没有记载。然而尽管教士们付钱时，是通过宣圣、赦免和弥撒的方式进行的，但他们在收钱时使用的却是和我们一样的钱币。

对于这一点以及存在于教皇和精灵王国之间的相似点，还可以进行补充，即：由于精灵不存在，而老妇人或老诗人的神话仅存在于无知之人的印象中，因此教皇的神权（在他自身世俗领土范围之外）仅存在于听到虚假传奇、虚假传说和对《圣经》的错误解释后，害怕被开除教籍的被迷惑的人心中。

因此，对亨利八世和伊丽莎白女王来说，分别用他们的符咒把他们赶走就不是一件非常困难的事了。但是谁又知道罗马之灵现在已经出去，在中国、日本、印度等干旱贫瘠的土地上传教，没有回来的可能，甚至带来大量比他还坏的灵，进入并居住在打扫干净的房子里，使得结果比最初更糟呢？因为现在不仅仅只有罗马教士假称上帝王国存在于世，并以此从中获得一种不同于世俗国家权力的另一种权力。关于政治学学说，以上就是我想讲的所有内容。在我审阅修改之后，会在本国公开，接受批评改正。

译者导读

夏尔·波德莱尔（1821—1867），法国19世纪著名的诗人和文学评论家，最具影响力的现代艺术批评家之一。他被誉为“现代主义之父”，代表作包括诗集《恶之花》，散文诗集《巴黎的忧郁》《人造天堂》，文学评论集《浪漫派的艺术》和艺术评论集《美学珍玩》等。在波德莱尔的一生中，对他影响最深的作家是美国作家埃德加·爱伦·坡，自1848年7月至其去世的17年间，波德莱尔坚持翻译坡的作品，在本书中也能看到坡对他的影响。

提起波德莱尔，中国读者最先想到的可能是他的诗集《恶之花》。然而，令他最初闻名于巴黎文坛的并不是他的诗歌，而是他的文学评论：“论1845年的沙龙”和“论1846年的沙龙”。本书收录了他的三篇艺术评论：“现代生活的画家”“欧仁·德拉克洛瓦的人生与作品”“论1859年的沙龙”。

“现代生活的画家”是波德莱尔论述现代美学和现代性最为深刻、最有预见性的一部著作。“现代性”在法国19世纪中期是一个新概念，波德莱尔是少数应用此概念的人之一。在本文中，波德莱尔用“现代性”来形容同时代的一位艺术家贡斯当丹·居伊的艺术追求。其中对贡斯当丹·居伊的赞美之词，曾引起极大争议。这篇文章也是现代艺术理论的奠基石，文中关于现代性观念的生动“寓言”影响深远。它更是典型的波德莱尔式散文，处处灵光乍现，趣味横生。

对于自己欣赏的艺术家，波德莱尔会毫无保留地大加颂扬。在“欧仁·德拉克洛瓦的人生与作品”中，波德莱尔称画家德拉克洛瓦是一位独特的艺术家，前无古人，后无来者，具有无可替代的重要性。作为《恶之花》和《巴黎的忧郁》的作者，波德莱尔厌倦安格尔的“古典”和完美，偏爱德拉克洛瓦的“浪漫”和印象，这是很自然的，对德拉克洛瓦的褒扬也在情理之中。

在“论1859年的沙龙”中，波德莱尔批评了展览作品的平庸，他认为，“想象力变得不可信，高贵受到蔑视，一味追求技巧”是艺术家水准下降的主要原因。对于波德莱尔来说，艺术创造的基础是想象。艺术的想象是“才能的王后”。想象是一个神圣的功能，它能够立刻察觉到世界中特定的隐藏关系，能够补充自然的不足。在“现代大众与摄影”一篇中，他写道，“我们对‘真’的品位，压迫并扼杀了对‘美’的品位”，摄影出现了，它闯入艺术的领域，成为后者的死敌。摄影一旦“侵犯了无形和想象的领域，侵犯了任何只是因为人们将灵魂投入其中才获得价值的事物，我们就该倒霉了”。再一次阐述了想象力对于艺术至关重要的观点。

波德莱尔一直坚持油画与雕塑评论的写作，直到生命的最后时刻。但是，他一直没有对艺术进行过系统的研究，与之相关的文章也不过是一些偶然的片段。它们或是对展览（当时被称为沙龙）的评价，或是对个体艺术家的讨论。尽管存在这些缺陷，波德莱尔的艺术思想是必须引起重视的，特别是在“现代艺术”方面，因为他引领了新时代的到来。

现代生活的画家

一、美、时尚和幸福

在所有社交圈，甚至在艺术圈中，都不乏这样的人，他们进入卢浮宫，从许多虽非一流但最有意思的画作前快步走过，不屑一顾，然后出神地站在一幅因成为雕塑作品而家喻户晓的提香[1]或者拉斐尔[2]的作品前，而后心满意足地离开，不止一位心中暗想：“这座美术馆我已了然于心了。”还有一些人，读过波舒哀[3]和拉辛[4]的一两本书，就自以为对文学史了如指掌了。幸好不时有一些好打抱不平之人，出现在批评家、艺术收藏家、艺术爱好者和好奇之士中，宣称我们无法只从拉斐尔或拉辛的作品中得到全部；小诗人也值得我们欣赏，他们也创作了一些有分量、令人愉悦的事物；最后，不管我们多么热爱一般的美，即第一流的诗人和艺术家所传达出的美，如果忽视特殊的美、应时之美和风俗特色，便是犯了错误。必须承认，这些年来，社会在这方面有了一定进步。今天的收藏家开始追捧上个世纪的一些讨人喜欢的彩色雕塑作品，显示出潮流已经转向大众所需要的一个方向。第伯柯尔特[5]和圣·欧邦[6]等人的名字，也列入值得研究的艺术家的词典中。但这些代表的都是过去，而我此时要讨论的是反映我们当代社会生活的绘画作品。过去是有趣的，不仅在于今天的艺术家能从中汲取美感，而且在于它本身的历史价值。同样的说法也适用于“现在”。我们从当代绘画作品中得到的愉悦，不仅来自它传达出的美感，还来自它作为“现在”的本质特征。

现在，我面前有一套时装图样，最早的是大革命时期的，最近的大约是执政府统治时期的。这些服装具有艺术和历史的双重魅力；尽管在许多愚笨之人，那种貌似深沉实无深度的人看来，它们是非常可笑的。在画作中它们经常被表现得漂亮和巧妙，而在我看来至少同样重要的是，在所有或几乎所有图样中，我欣喜地发现了一种时代的道德态度和美学价值。人们自创的审美观，影响了他的整个服装，衣领的或皱褶或硬挺，身姿的或弯曲或笔挺，随着时间推移，甚至微妙地改变了他的面部特征。人们最后看起来像他理想化的自我形象。这些图样可以被表现得美，也可以被表现得丑。表现得丑，就成为漫画；表现得美，则成了古典雕像。

穿着这些服装的女人看不出明显区别，不同的只是她们面部呈现出的或雅或俗的程度。这有生命的物质让原本僵硬的画面变得柔和起来。即使在今天，观者依然可以想象，一个男人穿着这件束腰外衣在走路，一个女人在那件披肩下耸肩。今天，也许某个剧院会上演这么一幕，我们的祖先穿着那时最时尚的服装，觉得自己魅力四射，正如我们今天穿着自己简约时尚的服装（当然也有它们的魅力，但更多是一种道德和精神上的魅力）所感受到的那样。如果它们被有悟性的演员穿上，赋予了生命力，我们会讶异自己曾经轻率地嘲笑它们。过去如保留着它幽灵的动人之处，会重获生命的光影和运动，成为现在。

如果一位头脑客观的人纵观从法国起源到今天的时尚历史，他会发现没有什么值得震惊甚至惊讶的。他会发现时尚的过渡总是经过充分准备，如同动物界的进化一般。没有鸿沟，所以没有惊讶。如果对于代表每个时代的画，要有点哲学的冥想，比如，这个时代主要关注什么、被什么问题困扰，或者这幅画反映出什么，他就会看到，历史的所有分支里有着多么深沉的和谐，即使在我们看来最残暴、最混乱的历史时期，人们对美的渴求也总是能得到满足。

现在，我们正面临一个绝好的机会，建立一套理性和历史的美学理论。与唯一和绝对的美学理论相对，它认为美总是不可避免地由两个要素构成，尽管貌似是由单一要素构成的；构成美的可变要素共同传达出了一个美的统一印象，分辨它们固然困难，但绝不能因此否定美在构成上的多样性这一事实。一方面，美包含一种永恒和不变的要素，尽管很难说清它占多大比重；另一方面，美包含一种相对变动的因素，我们可以视情况或同时地称之为同时代性、时尚、道德性、激情。这后一个因素如同一块美味蛋糕上令人垂涎的糖衣，如果没有它，前一个因素将会难以消化、淡而无味、与人性龃龉。我敢说，不具备这两种要素的美是找不到的。

现在举两个极端的历史阶段的例子。在神圣风格的艺术中，这种二重性是一望即知的；美的永恒因素只有在艺术家所属的宗教的允许和控制下才会显现。在我们自负地称为文明的这个时代里，美的二重性在一位高明的艺术家最不重要的作品中也同样是显而易见的；美永恒不变的部分将同时被隐匿又得到表达，如果不是借由时尚，至少是通过艺术家的个人气质。艺术的二重性是人的二重性的必然结果。如果你喜欢，可以将艺术永恒存在的那部分视作它的灵魂，而将变动不居的那部分视为艺术的身体。这就是为什么司汤达，这位鲁莽无礼、爱调侃甚至令人反感的大师（他的无礼却常常是发人深思的），在说到“美就是对幸福的期望”时，与真理如此接近。这一定义无疑有点过分，因为它将美置于无限多变的幸福理想之下；它轻率地剥夺了美的高贵品格，但也让美远离了墨守成规的学究犯的错误。

我曾经不止一次地解释过这些事情，上面几行文字对那些乐于抽象思维的人想必已足够；但我很清楚大部分法国读者对此并无多少兴趣，我自己也急于进入这个话题积极和实在的部分。

二、风俗特写

对于风俗画和描绘中产阶级生活和时尚的画作而言，最快捷廉价的技术手段显然是最好的。艺术家注入的美越多，画作的价值就越高。然而，在生活的琐屑中，在永恒事物的每日变化中，有一种运动速度，它赋予了艺术家同样的执行速度。18世纪的彩色雕刻版画在今天再次赢得青睐，正如我刚才所说；蜡笔画、线蚀铜版画、尘蚀铜版画相继向这部大部头的散见于图书馆、艺术爱好者的收藏以及最简陋的商店橱窗里的现代生活的词典贡献了它们的语汇。平版印刷术一发明，很快便被视为非常适合这一看似轻松实则艰巨的任务。我们在这一领域有着真正的巨制。加瓦尔尼[7]和杜米埃[8]的作品，被认为是对《人间喜剧》的补充，这一评价可谓恰如其分。我敢说，巴尔扎克自己也不会反对这个观点，因为这些兼具艺术家与风俗画家双重身份的人，他们本身就是具有多面素质的天才，换句话说，是有着杰出文学素养的天才，从这个意义上讲，上述评价就更加恰如其分。观察者、路人、哲学家，随便你怎么称呼他，但是，要定义这样一位艺术家，你最终还是得给他找一个定语形容词，而这个词肯定不会用来形容一位创作永恒事物或至少是带有持久性质事物的英雄和宗教题材作品的画家。有时他可能是一位诗人，更多的时候他接近于小说家或道德家；他的作品定格了短暂的一瞬，而这一瞬让人想到了永恒。每个国家，为着愉悦或者名誉，都有过这样几个人。在我们这个时代，在几个首先会想起来的人比如杜米埃和加瓦尔尼之后，我们还可以加上德维利亚[9]、毛林[10]、努玛[11]，他们是波旁王朝复辟时期可疑魅力的记录者，还有瓦提埃[12]、塔塞贺[13]、欧仁·拉米[14]，最后这位在对贵族社会的热爱上几乎像个英国人，还有特里莫雷[15]和特拉维埃[16]，这两位是贫穷和普通人生活的记录者。

三、他是艺术家、入世之人、人群中的人和孩子今天，我想和我的读者谈一位非凡的人。他的个性强烈鲜明，达到了自足的程度，无须去寻求他人认同。他的画作没有一幅是签名的，如果签名指的是那几个容易伪造的组成名字的字母的话，太多的艺术家在他们最不负责任的画作上签下自己的大名。但是这位仁兄，他所有作品的签名就是他熠熠生辉的灵魂。看过并喜欢他作品的艺术爱好者，都会从我下面的描述中轻而易举地认出它们。M.C.G.[17]喜欢混迹在人群中，喜欢隐姓埋名，谦逊也是他的独特之处。众所周知，萨克雷先生对一切与艺术沾边的事物都感兴趣，他小说里的插图都是自己亲手绘制的，某一天，他在伦敦的一份小报上谈到G先生，这让G先生大为恼火，认为是对自己的谦逊的冒犯。最近，他听说我要写文章评价他的思想和才智，不容分说地要求我隐去他的姓名，谈论他的作品时，就像是谈论某个无名氏的作品一样。我将谦卑地遵从这一古怪的请求。读者和我都可以假装G先生并不存在，我们来谈论他的素描和水彩（他对自己这些作品显示出一种贵族的不屑），就像学者面临一项任务，要评价一些偶然发现的珍贵历史文件的重要性，而这些文件的作者也许永远不为人知。为了让我彻底安心，大家要认为，我对这位艺术家奇特而神秘的秉性作出的全部评价，大都是从他的作品中看出来的，完全是富有想象力的假设、臆测或重构。

G先生已是暮年之人。据说让·雅克[18]是42岁开始写作的，可能也是在差不多的年龄，G先生对图画的世界着了迷，他的头脑里塞满了图画，于是他鼓起勇气，用墨和水彩在一张白纸上涂抹。说实话，他画画的时候像一个野蛮人，一个孩子，愤怒地责骂自己笨拙的手指和不听话的工具。我曾经看过许多他早期的涂鸦，坦白说，大多数明智的人，或者自认为明智的人，都会毫不羞愧地宣称，在这些早期默默无闻的作品中，看不到其中蕴藏的潜在天赋。今天，G先生已经无师自通，发现了这个行当所有的小秘密，他在没有帮助和建议的情况下，自学成才，成为一位有强烈个性的大师；至于他早期质朴的作品，他只是保留了那种必需的东西，为自己的丰富天赋增加令人意想不到的趣味。在偶然看到一幅自己的早期作品时，他会撕掉或者烧毁它，显示出令人忍俊不禁的羞愧和愤怒。

有整十年的时间，我一直想结识G先生，他天性喜爱旅行，四海为家。我知道，他有很长一段时间为英国一家画报工作，他早期的旅行木版画（取材于在西班牙、土耳其和克里米亚的旅行中）就出现在那张画报上。从那时起，我看过许多这种取材于生活的即兴画作，我也因此能够“读到”一种对克里米亚战役的详细和日常的描述，远胜过所有其他报道。同样是在这张画报上，刊登了这位艺术家大量取材于新芭蕾和歌剧的画作，照例没有签名。在终于与他会面后，我立刻发现面前站着的不是一位艺术家，而是一位入世之人。在这个语境中，请把“艺术家”按狭义的概念来理解，而“入世之人”则以其广义的概念来理解。我所谓的“入世之人”，是指对全世界的事情都了解的人，一位理解世界，理解其所有习俗背后神秘和合理原因的人；而这里所谓的“艺术家”，指的是一位专家，他被绑在自己的调色板上，正如农奴被绑在土地上。G先生不喜欢被称为艺术家。从某种程度上说这也是有理的，不是吗？他对世界所有事情都感兴趣，他想知道、理解和评价我们这个地球上发生的一切。艺术家很少或根本不会活跃在知识分子圈子里和政治圈子里。如果他住在布雷达，对圣日耳曼郊区发生的事情便一无所知。除了两三个例外（不必指名道姓），直言不讳地说，大多数艺术家都是技能熟练的粗汉，只是手工劳动者，是乡村酒吧里有着乡巴佬头脑的谈客。他们的谈话不可避免地局限在一个狭窄的范围里，很快就会让一个入世之人、让一个宇宙的精神居民，感到厌倦。

所以，要开始理解G先生，首先要注意的一点是：好奇心可以被视为他天赋的起点。

你还记得那幅画吗？（它的确是一幅画！）它是由这个时代最强大的一支笔写下的，名为《人群中的人》[19]。一位康复期的病人坐在咖啡馆里，透过商店橱窗，望着来往的人群，他的思绪与周围人的思绪融为一体。他刚从死神的阴影下走出来，满怀兴奋地呼吸着生命所有的活力和味道；当他处在要忘却一切的时刻，他记起并狂热地想要记起所有一切。最后，他跑到人群中，寻找一个面孔瞬间吸引他的陌生人。好奇心已经成为一种压倒一切、无法抗拒的激情。

那么想象一位艺术家永远处于一个康复期病人的精神世界中，你就会找到了解G先生性格的钥匙。

但是康复期仿佛是回到童年。正在康复的病人就像孩子一样，最大限度地享受那种对所有事物都充满浓厚兴趣的天赋，即使是外表最不起眼的事物。如果可以，让我们通过想象力来回忆童年的我们对早晨的印象，我们会发现那与我们在一场疾病后获得的色彩生动的印象极其相似，当然前提是我们的感受力没有因病受到任何损害。孩子看待任何事物都是新鲜的；孩子总是“陶醉其中”。没有什么比孩子陶醉于形状和颜色中的感觉更接近于我们所谓的灵感。我会冒险更进一步，断言灵感与充血有某种联系，每一个崇高的思想都伴随着在大脑皮层中回响着的或多或少强劲的神经冲动。天才都有着强大的神经，孩子的神经都是脆弱的。在前者，理性的角色相当重要；在后者，感性几乎占据了全部。但是天赋不过是可以随意抓回的童年，这个孩子现在有着成人的自我表达能力，有着善于分析的头脑，能够让自己不自觉累积的经验变得井井有条。这种深刻而愉快的好奇心要表现为那种出神的目光，在狂喜中如野兽一般，每个孩子在看到一样新事物时都会有那种目光，不管这种事物是面孔还是风景、光亮、镀金、色彩、波纹绸，而服装的艺术更助长了这种狂喜。一天，我的一个朋友告诉我，他小时候，经常看父亲更衣，当他看到父亲胳臂的肌肉，呈玫瑰和黄色的肤色，还有那蓝色的网状静脉时，满心是夹杂着喜悦的惊异。外部世界的图画已经开始在他心里引起崇敬，掌控他的头脑。事物的形状让他着迷，让他为之倾倒。一种早熟的命运正崭露头角。他的命运已经注定。读者应该猜到了，今天，这个孩子已是一位著名的画家。

我刚才请求您把G先生看作一位永远处于康复期的病人；为了保持对他印象的完整，请将他也看作一个大孩子，一个每时每刻都拥有童年天赋的成人，换句话说，对这个天才而言，生活的任何一面都不曾失去锋芒。

我曾说过，我不愿把他称为纯粹的艺术家，他自己也带着一种贵族式矜持的谦恭，拒绝接受这一头衔。我愿意称他为浪荡子，这是有很多原因的：“浪荡子”这个词暗示着一种性格的典范，一种对这个世界所有道德机制的理解；但是，从另一个角度看，浪荡子渴望离群索居，而G先生有着强烈的不可满足的激情，渴望观察和感受，因而又激烈地与浪荡作风分道扬镳。圣·奥古斯丁[20]说，“我爱上了爱的感觉。”[21]“我满怀激情地热爱激情。”G先生也许会欣然附和。浪荡子是或假装是厌世者，这是一个方向，一种阶级态度。G先生痛恨厌世者。我说他拥有一种困难的本领：真诚而不致荒唐，久经世故的人懂得我的话。我愿意给予他哲学家的头衔，他有权获得这个头衔，原因不止一个；但是对肉眼可见的可变的有形事物过分热爱，让他理所当然地对构成形而上学家无形王国的事物产生反感。所以，让我们把他局限在纯粹的画面道德家的范围内吧，像拉布吕耶尔[22]。

人群是他的领地，就像天空对于鸟儿，水对于鱼儿一样。他的激情和职业就是融入人群中去。对于一个十足的漫游者、热情的观察者来说，生活在芸芸众生之中，在变动不居、熙来攘往、短暂和永恒之中，是一种巨大的愉悦。离开家，而又四海为家；观察世界，在世界的中心，而不为世界所见，这就是那些独立、热情、无偏见的灵魂的几桩小小的快乐，他们不会轻易屈从于语言的定义。观察者是一位微服出行的君王，在所到之处，享受着隐姓埋名之乐。他是热爱生活的人，将这个世界变成了自己的家，就像热爱女性的人，从他能发现的所有可爱女人，那些可以找到和不可能找到的女人那里创造了自己的世界；或者热爱画画的人，他们住在画在帆布上的梦幻世界中。因此，一个热爱各种生活的人，进入人群，就像进入一个巨大的电场。他，生活的热爱者，也可以被比作一面同芸芸众生一般的巨大镜子；或一个有思想的万花筒，每转动一下，就呈现出一种生活模式，呈现出它的丰富多彩，以及组成生活的所有成分所具有的流光溢彩。这是一个渴望无我境界的自我，它每时每刻都在用比永远变动不居和转瞬即逝的生活本身更生动的形象反映着自我。G先生曾在一次谈话中说过：“任何人，任何没有被一种痛彻心扉的悲伤击垮过的人，任何对人群感到厌倦的人，都是大傻瓜！大傻瓜！我鄙视他！”他说这话时目光炯炯，带着富有感染力的手势，令人难忘。

当G先生醒来，张开眼睛，看到明亮的阳光敲打着窗子，他懊恼地自语道：“多么强烈的命令！多么耀眼的光明！在过去几个小时里到处都是光明！而我却在睡梦中虚度了！无数沐浴在光明中的事物，我本可以看到却错过了！”于是他立刻出发！他凝视着生命力之河，那样地壮阔，那样地明亮。他欣赏着都市中的永恒之美和生活惊人的和谐，这种和谐神奇般地在人类自由的喧嚣之中得以保持。他凝视着这座伟大城市的风景，石头的风景，一会儿笼罩在雾中，一会儿沐浴在阳光下。他欣赏着那漂亮的马车，高傲的骏马，马夫整洁闪亮的装束，小听差熟练的动作，女人们有节奏的步伐，漂亮孩子对生活的热爱，以及像孔雀一样对自己漂亮衣服的骄傲，一句话，他热爱生活的全部。如果时尚发生转变，一件衣服的剪裁有了些许变化，缎带和丝结被玫瑰饰结取代；如果女帽变宽了，女人的发髻梳得更向下，到了颈背处；如果腰围线往上提，裙摆更大了，可以肯定，他那双如鹰般锐利的眼睛老远就会发现。一个军团列队走过，也许要开往地球尽头，林荫大道的空气中充满了军乐声，像希望一样轻盈活泼。毫无疑问，G先生已经看见，并在审视和分析这支部队的武器和军容。鞍辔、头发上阳光的闪光、乐队、坚定的面容、浓重的胡须，所有这些细节都纷乱地向他涌来，几分钟内，由此产生的诗就可能形成了。他的灵魂就这样和这支部队的灵魂发生了共鸣，这支部队向前行进，就好像是一个活着的生物，一个快乐和秩序井然的高傲形象。

夜幕降临了。这是充满魔力的时刻，闪闪烁烁的光，夜幕四合，城市的灯上了。煤气灯光映衬着夕阳的紫色背景。所有人，不论是诚实的还是不诚实的、智慧的或是不负责任的，都自言自语道：“这一天终于过去了！”好人和坏人都把思绪转向享乐，各人都忙着赶去最喜欢的老地方喝一杯遗忘之酒。而G先生会是从夕阳逗留、诗歌回响、生命搏动、音乐响起之地最后离开的那个人，任何地方，只要那里有人类的激情呈现在他的眼前，只要那里有自然之人和传统之人出现在一种古怪的美中，只要夕阳的光线照亮了“堕落的野兽”[23]一瞬的欢乐。“嗯，这真是充实的一天，”我们都熟悉的那种类型的读者自语道，“我们每个人一定都有足够的天赋，用同样的方式度过一天。”不！有这种观察天赋的人本就寥寥可数，有自我表达能力的人则更是少之又少。现在，当人们还在睡梦中，G先生俯在书桌上，凝视着一张纸，用与他刚才观察身边事物时相同的目光，挥舞着手中的铅笔、钢笔和画笔，把玻璃杯中的水泼向天花板，用衬衣擦笔，他是那样急不可耐，仿佛害怕那些画面会逃跑似的，虽然只身一人，他仍吵嚷不休，无情地鞭策着自己。事物在纸上得以重生，自然而又超越了自然，美又不止于美，奇特又具有一种像画者灵魂一样热情洋溢的生命。幻境从自然中提炼了出来。所有在记忆中杂乱储存的材料，都被分类、整理、融合，并经受了刻意的理想化，这种理想化出自孩子所特有的一种感受力，换句话说，是一种敏锐的、因质朴而变得神奇的感受力。

四、现代性

他就这样走啊，跑啊，永远在寻找着。寻找什么呢？我们可以确定，这个人，正如我所描述的，这个孤独而富有想象力的人，永远在人类浩瀚的荒漠漫游，他的目的比纯粹的漫游者更高尚，比追求一时的短暂欢愉更普遍。他在寻找那个难以定义的事物，我们姑且可以称之为“现代性”，因为找不到更好的词汇来表达这个概念。他的目的是，从诗歌中抽离出蕴含于其所处历史背景的时尚，从短暂中提炼出永恒。如果我们到现代画展上去，就会惊讶地发现，我们的艺术家有一个共同的倾向，即将所有主题都套上历史的外衣。几乎所有人都使用文艺复兴时期的时尚和装饰，比如大卫[24]用的就是罗马时期的时尚和装饰，但是大卫和其他画家有一个不同，他选择的主题都是希腊或罗马时代所特有的，所以只能用古典风格来诠释，而今天的画家选择的主题都是带有普遍性质的，适用于所有时代，而他们竟也坚持用中世纪、文艺复兴时期或东方的外衣来呈现。显然，这完全是惰性使然；因为严厉谴责这个时期一切都丑陋得令人绝望，比致力于找出隐藏于其中的神秘的美——不管它是多么贫乏和无足轻重——要方便得多。现代性是短暂的、飞逝的、偶然的；它构成艺术的一半，艺术的另一半则是永恒的、稳定的。对历史长河中的每一位画家而言，都有一种现代性的形式；流传至今的大多数名画，它们的外衣都属于其所处的时代。这些都是十分和谐的作品，因为那些服装、发型，甚至姿势、表情和微笑（每个时代都有它特有的仪态、表情、微笑）形成一个整体，充满生命力。你们没有权利蔑视这种转瞬即逝、变形频繁的元素，也不可把它弃诸一旁。如果这么做，将不可避免地跌入一种抽象和不可定义的美的空虚中，这种美就像原罪之前那个唯一的女人的美一样。如果你用另一件服装代替当时流行的服装，就会违背常理，这只在流行服饰舞会上才能被原谅。因此，18世纪的女神、仙女和苏丹的女眷，都是符合时代精神的作品。

研究历史上的大师之作无疑是学习绘画的绝好训练，但如果你的目的是理解今时今日之美，那这便是不必要的练习了。委罗内塞[25]和鲁本斯[26]画中的帷幔教不会你如何画水纹绸、高级绸缎，或者我们的纺织厂生产出的用摇摆的裙衬支撑的任何织料，又或者上浆的细布做的衬裙。这些织料的质地和纹理与古代威尼斯或者卡特琳[27]宫廷里的不同。另外，裙子和紧身胸衣的剪裁与过去是完全不同的，而裙褶也是新的样式，最后，今天女性的姿势、仪态给她的服装注入一种生命力和性格，同历史上的女性区别开来。简言之，为了使所有形式的现代性都值得成为古物，必须把人类生命无意中注入其中的神秘美提炼出来。G先生特别致力于的就是这样一项工作。我说过，每个时代都有它特有的仪态、表情和姿势。这个观点可以很容易在一家大型肖像美术馆（比如凡尔赛宫）得到证实。不过它还可以扩展得更广。在我们称为民族的这个统一体中，职业、社会阶级和时代不仅将多样性带进姿势和风度中，还带进了脸部整体的线条中。如此这般的鼻子、嘴和前额，在某段时期内会成为标准，它们的长度我不打算在这里确定，但肯定是可以计算的。肖像画家对于这种观点不够熟悉，安格尔先生[28]的最大弱点就是想强加给每种类型的模特一种或多或少全面的提升过程，换言之，取自古典主义宝库的强制美化过程。

在此类事情上，进行先验推理将会是容易的，甚至是合理的。所谓灵魂与所谓身体之间永恒的相互关系，很好地说明了物质的或散发自精神的东西如何体现并将永远体现着由它所产生的精神。如果一位耐心、一丝不苟然而想象力贫乏的画家，被委托画今天的一位交际花，而他选择从提香或拉斐尔笔下的交际花中汲取灵感（这是一个神圣词汇），他的作品很可能会是有欺骗性、难以捉摸和理解的。研究那个时代那个类型的名作，不会让他知道今天一位交际花的姿态、目光、怪相和有生气的一面，她们在时尚词典中相继被置于不贞洁的女子、被豢养的女人、名妓等粗鄙打趣的名目下。

同样的话也适用于对士兵、浪荡子，甚至动物（如狗或马），以及组成一个时代永恒生活的所有食物的研究。谁要是在古物中研究理想的艺术、逻辑和通用方法以外的东西，谁就要倒霉！因为如果太过沉浸其中，他的头脑中就不会有现在，他就会抛弃时代带来的价值观和特权。而我们几乎所有的原创性都来自于时代打在我们感觉上的印记。读者会很容易理解，因为我可以从女人之外的无数事物上轻而易举地印证这一观点。比如，我举个极端的例子，一个海景画家，他要表现一艘现代轮船朴素而简洁的美，居然去研究古船因装饰物过多而变形的外观和巨大的船尾，以及16世纪船只复杂的帆和索具，你们对此怎么看呢？或者，你委托一位画家画一匹在盛大赛马会上一举成名的纯种骏马，而他把研究范围限制在博物馆，满足于观察画廊中凡·戴克[29]、布吉尼昂[30]或者凡·德·默伦[31]笔下的马，你们又将作何感想？

G先生，在天性指引下，在时代掌控下，走了一条完全不同的道路。他以观察生活开始，后来才努力学习表现生活的方法。因此他的作品有一种惊人的独创性。在这种独创性中还存有外行的、质朴的东西，成了一种服从于印象的新证据，一种对真实的恭维。对于我们大多数人来说，特别是商人，若非与他们的生意有实用联系，自然就不存在。对生活现实的幻想衰退得尤其严重。G先生不断吸收着这种幻想，他把它们满满地存在记忆中、眼睛里。

五、易于记忆的艺术

“粗野”这个词在我的笔下出现得可能过于频繁，也许让有些人认为这指的是某些没有定型的、只有观者发挥想象力才能使之变为完美的画作。这是一种严重的误解。我指的是一种不可避免的、综合的、幼稚的粗野，在一些完美的艺术（墨西哥的、埃及的或者尼尼微[32]的粗野）里仍然经常能看到，它来自一种从宏观上观察事物的需要，尤其是从整体效果的角度来看作品。这里不妨多说一句，许多人把一切具有综合简化的目光的画家指为“粗野”。比如，柯罗先生[33]，他的风景画都是描摹景物的粗线条，其结构和特色。同样地，G先生忠实地描摹事物留给自己的印象，他会本能地意识到事物最重要的特色或部分（从一个戏剧化的角度看，它们可以是达到高潮的或明亮的）或者它的主要特点，有时甚至带着有利于人类记忆的一定程度的夸张；观者的想象力转而受到这种专制代码的影响，清晰地看到这一事物给G先生造成的印象。在这种情况下，观者成为一种总是清晰的、醉人的表达的表达者。

有一个因素，大大增加了这种对日常生活的图画记录的生命力。我指的是G先生的工作习惯。他画画依赖的是记忆，而非模型，除非在有些情况下（比如克里米亚战争），他必须刻不容缓地迅速做笔记，并确定主题的基本轮廓。事实上，所有真正的美术家创作的都是来自脑海中而非自然中的画面。如果有人举出拉斐尔、华托等许多画家的精彩速写来反驳，我们的回答是，它们确实是非常详细的笔记，但永远只能是笔记而已。当一位真正的艺术家到了最终创作的阶段，模型于他更多的是一种尴尬，而非帮助。像杜米埃和G先生这样多年来习惯用他们的记忆，并在其中填满画面的人，有时甚至会发现，在模特及随之的繁复细节面前，他们的主要感官似乎受到扰乱，仿佛瘫痪了一样。

于是就有了看到一切并忘记一切的决心与记忆的功能之间的抗争，记忆获得了一种习惯，要瞬间记下主要的色调、形状和外观样式。一个能够完美地把握形式但是尤其习惯于运用记忆和想象力的艺术家，会发现自己似乎被大量细节困扰，就像一群热爱绝对平等的人愤怒地要求得到公平一样。任何公平的形式都不可避免地受到侵犯，一切和谐都被破坏了，牺牲了；大量平庸的事物被放大，大量琐屑的事物分散了注意力。艺术家越是对细节平等对待，混乱状态就越严重。不管他是近视还是远视，所有的等级和从属关系都消失了。这是当今最走红的某位作家的作品中经常出现的意外事故，而这种缺陷与大众的缺陷如此相适应，竟使他越发受追捧了。这种类比在演员的艺术中我们也可以感觉到，那种神秘、深刻的艺术在今天已经跌到颓废的混乱中了。费雷德里克·乐迈特先生用一个天才的宽宏和胆识塑造了一个角色，虽然他的演技有闪光的细节装饰，却依然是综合的、有雕塑感的。布菲先生则以近视眼或政府官僚的琐细来塑造角色。在他身上，一切都是闪闪发亮的，但一切都不特别打眼，无法在我们的记忆中占据一席之地。

因此，在G先生的作品中，最突出的有两点：第一就是一种专注和强烈的记忆力，能够让事物复活，令人浮想联翩，这记忆对每一样事物说：“拉撒路，起身吧！”[34]第二就是一团火，一种铅笔或画笔产生的陶醉，几乎达到癫狂的状态。这是一种恐惧，害怕走得不够快，让幽灵在综合未被提炼和抓住的时候就溜掉。这种巨大的恐惧攫住了所有伟大的艺术家，让他们内心热切地希望占有一切表达手段，这样一来，头脑的命令就不会因为手的犹豫而打折扣，最终，理想的作画过程会变得自觉和流畅，就像一个健康人的头脑在饭后发出消化食物的指令一样。G先生作画时，首先用铅笔勾出线条，标示出物体在空间中的位置。然后用颜色润出基本的布局，先轻轻着色，成为隐约的大块，随后再重新上色，一次比一次浓重。最后，用铅笔和墨水清晰地勾画出物体的轮廓。要不是亲眼所见，没人能猜出他用如此简单和基本的方法就能营造出如此惊人的效果。这种方法有一种无可比拟的优势，那就是，在几乎每一个阶段，画似乎都已完成，在观者看来已经满意了；你可以把这种技法称为缩略草图，但这是完美的草图。所有的色调都是和谐的，如果他想要增强色调，所有的色调在通向理想的完美状态的过程中都会保持它们和谐的关系。他以这种方式，带着活泼和快乐，一次可以画20幅画，这种快乐不仅赏心悦目，对他自己来说也是有趣的；这些画作一幅幅地，数以十计、百计、千计地堆积起来。他不时会浏览一下，翻一翻、看一看，然后从中选择几幅，加深一下阴影部分，修饰一下明亮部分，给画作增加一些色饱和度。

他高度重视背景，不管它是浓墨重彩还是轻描淡写，总是有与画中人物相得益彰的特性。色调的变化和整体的和谐都严格地得到贯彻，其中显示出的天赋更多地来自天性而非后天习得。因为G先生拥有色彩画家的神秘天赋，这是一种真正的才能，后天的学习可以增强这一才能，然而却无法凭空得来。概括来说，我们这位奇特的艺术家既表现人类的举止也表现其或庄严或古怪的态度，以及人类在空间光彩夺目的爆发。

六、战争的编年史

保加利亚、土耳其、克里米亚和西班牙，这些国家的美景都曾经让G先生大饱眼福，或者说是那位我们商量好称作G先生的虚构艺术家，因为我不时会想到，为了照顾他的谦逊，我答应假装他并不存在。我曾经翻阅过那些有关东方战争的画作档案（尸横遍野的战场、辎重车、牲畜和马匹的搬运），那些充满生命悸动和兴味的场景，仿佛是直接从生活中移印下来的图画，构成一种珍贵的画面形式的要素，许多知名画家如果处于同样的环境可能会轻率地忽视。然而，在这些画家中，贺拉斯·威尔奈[35]先生是个例外，与其说他是一位艺术家，不如说是一位记者；G先生是一位更细腻的艺术家，跟他之间有着明显的关系，如果我们愿意只把他视为生活的档案管理员的话。我敢说，没有一张报纸，没有一份书面记录，没有一本书，在使人痛苦的细节和可怕的规模上，能够将克里米亚战争[36]这一伟大的史诗表现得更好。我们的目光依次掠过多瑙河岸到博斯普鲁斯海滨，刻尔松角，巴拉克拉瓦平原，因克尔曼的田野，英国人、法国人、土耳其人、皮埃蒙特人的营地，君士坦丁堡的街道，医院及各种各样庄严的宗教和军事盛典。

我记忆最深刻的一幅作品是《直布罗陀主教为斯库塔里墓地举行祝圣仪式》。画面的别致之处在于周围东方的田野和画中人物的西方仪态装束之间形成的对比，这种别致之处以一种动人、启人联想、充满梦幻的方式表现了出来。普通的士兵和军官都带着那种根深蒂固的“绅士”气质，他们无论走到天涯海角都带着那种坚毅含蓄的气质，不管是在非洲南端殖民地的兵营，还是在印度的殖民地；英国的传教士让人模糊地想到戴着帽子和领巾的引领员或股票经纪人。

另外还有一幅画，是奥马尔·帕沙在舒姆拉的宅邸。画面是土耳其的待客礼节，有烟斗和咖啡；所有客人都坐在床上，吸着和吹管一样长的烟斗，脚下放着烟锅。这就是《库尔德人在斯库塔里》，这支军队的奇怪模样让人想起蛮族入侵；另外一幅画，画的是19世纪土耳其野蛮的非正规军士兵，样子也同样古怪，他们的军官是欧洲人，来自匈牙利或者波兰，其浪荡子的外貌和士兵奇异的东方特征形成古怪的对比。

一幅宏伟巨作吸引了我的眼球，画面上是一个站立的人；那个人身材结实、精力充沛，他的表情里有沉思、有思虑、有快乐、有坚毅；他穿着过膝的高筒靴，制服藏在一件厚重宽大的大衣下，扣子一直扣到最后一颗；他的目光，透过雪茄的烟雾，投向阴森而迷茫的天际；他胳膊受了伤，吊着绷带。在画的下方，有一行铅笔字：因克尔曼战场上的康罗贝尔[37]，作于现场。

这个骑兵又是谁？他白色的胡须被刻画得那样刚劲有力，高昂着头，似乎在嗅着战场上可怕的诗意，而他的马，一边嗅着土地的气味，一边从成堆的尸体中间走过。这些尸体脚朝上，面孔扭曲，姿势奇怪。在画作下方的角落，有一行字：我在因克尔曼。

这个人，是巴拉圭-迪里埃先生[38]无疑。他正和总司令一起，在贝奇奇塔什检阅炮兵。我几乎没见过一幅比这更好的士兵肖像画，出自更大胆更有才智之手的。

在这幅画旁边，我看到一个自叙利亚之祸以来声名狼藉的名字：阿赫麦-帕夏将军，他站在营帐前，由部下簇拥着，接见欧洲官员。尽管这位将军大腹便便，但他的举止和脸上，都带着那种通常属于统治阶层的贵族气息。

在这个有趣的集子中，巴拉克拉瓦战役的场景出现过多次，分别是从不同的角度来描摹的。其中令人印象最深刻的一幅作品，是桂冠诗人阿尔弗雷德·丁尼生的英雄号角曾歌颂过的历史性骑兵冲锋：一群骑兵在炮火的浓烟中飞奔着冲向天际，背景是一带青山。

画作中不时会出现一个宗教人物，对于观众因为炮火和屠杀而变得悲伤的眼睛，这是很好的休息。在英国军队中，一位穿短褶裙的苏格兰人的别致军装很是引人注目，那是一位英国国教教士在做安息日弥撒；他面前的读经台是三面鼓，一面在上，两面在下。

单用一支笔很难将这首由上千幅画组成的广阔而复杂的诗表达出来，很难表达这几百张画的细节传递出的令人陶醉的感受；这些细节常常是令人痛苦的，并从来不是凄哀的。画上的污迹和裂口以独特的方式说明了艺术家将怎样的纷乱和喧嚣置于每日的记忆中。当傍晚来临时，邮差会将G先生的画送往伦敦，而他常常会这样委托邮差送走十多幅画在薄纸上的速写，雕工和报纸订户正在焦急等待着。

画面上有时会出现救护车，气氛是凝重、阴郁的，每张床都承载着苦痛；还有一张画的是佩拉的医院，我注意到，有两位仿佛出自勒絮埃尔[39]笔下的瘦长、苍白、僵直的修女，正在和一个穿着不正式的来访者谈话，这位来访者有一个古怪的说明：鄙人。现在，又是一长队畜群——骡子、驴或者马，在崎岖蜿蜒、布满战斗残骸的小道上，缓慢行走，背上挂着驮篮，里面是面色苍白、动弹不得的伤员。在广阔的雪原上，来了一群骆驼，它们挺着威严的胸，高昂着头，由鞑靼人牵着，在运送各种物资和弹药；一个战争的世界出现了，活跃、匆忙、沉默；还有营地和集市，摊着各种货物的样品，就像一个临时建成的野蛮城市。在临时搭起的棚子里，在崎岖或积雪的道路上，在峡谷间，在人群里，能看到多个国家的制服，都因为打仗而变得破烂不堪，外加的大皮袄和笨重的靴子使它走了样。

想到这些作品现在散落各处，其中一些珍贵画作被复制它们的雕工或者《伦敦画报》的编辑收藏，而没有呈送给皇帝陛下，真是颇为遗憾。我敢肯定，皇帝陛下一定很高兴看到这些关于他的士兵的画作。他们每日的活动，用了最精心的笔触描摹，从最辉煌的壮举，到生活中最琐碎平凡的事，都由这位士兵艺术家的妙手展现出来。

七、隆重典礼和盛大节日

土耳其也向我们亲爱的G先生贡献了一些绝妙的绘画题材，如拜兰节。拜兰节的景象华丽壮观，但在背景中出现了已过世的苏丹的身影，就像一轮苍白的太阳，令人厌倦；列于君王左侧的是文臣，右侧是武将。武将的首领是埃及苏丹萨义德-帕夏，他当时正身在君士坦丁堡；盛大的仪仗队伍正庄严地朝着王宫附近的一座小清真寺行进。队伍中可以看到一些土耳其官员，真是堕落的漫画肖像，他们臃肿的身体压在胯下华丽的骏马上；还有一些巨大笨重的车子，与路易十四时期的车子如出一辙，用东方元素装饰得金碧辉煌，不时有女子好奇的目光从面纱留在眼睛处的窄缝投出；还有“第三性”（巴尔扎克的幽默用语放在这里再适合不过了，因为在这些闪烁不定的灯光下，在肥大的服装飘扬的裙裾间，在面颊、眼睛和眉毛的浓妆下，在所有这些歇斯底里、不由自主的姿势中，在飘动在腰际的长发里，你会发现很难，且不说不可能，来猜出男子特征）；最后还有风流女人（如果可以对黎凡特地区[40]使用风流这个词的话），通常是匈牙利、瓦拉几亚、犹太、波兰、希腊和亚美尼亚的女人，因为在一个专制政府的统治下，受压迫的民族，尤其其中受苦最深重的女人，向卖淫行业输送了最多的人。在这些女人中，有些还穿着民族服装，绣花上衣、短袖、宽大的披肩、灯笼裤、前端上翘的土耳其鞋子、条纹或饰有亮片的头巾，以及所有来自她们家乡的装饰品；另外一些女人的人数更多，她们身上打上了文明的烙印，对于一个女人来说，就是穿着有裙撑的宽大裙子，不过，也会在服饰上加一些黎凡特地区的特色，结果就是让她们看起来像是一些试图乔装打扮的巴黎女人。

G先生善于刻画各种各样的官方仪式和国家典礼，他不像有些画家，将这种工作视为报酬不菲的苦差事，在笔触运用上冷漠且有说教意味。G先生在绘画时带着一个热爱空间、远景和光线的人的全部热情，他作品中的光线，反射在制服或宫廷服装上，就像泪珠或耀眼的宝石。《雅典大教堂的独立纪念节》便是G先生这一才能的有趣例证。所有画得很小的人物在这幅作品中都各得其所，巧妙的布局使得整个画面空间更加深邃。教堂很大，装饰着庄严的帷幔。奥托国王[41]和王后站在台上，穿着民族传统服装，他们对服装驾驭得无比自如，好像是为了证实他们选择的诚意和展示最高贵的希腊式爱国主义。国王就像最帅气的希腊民兵一样，腰带束得紧紧的，裙褶向外扩开，带着民族浪荡作风的夸张。在国王和王后的对面，主教正向他们走来，他是一位老人，有些驼背，雪白的胡子随风飘扬，小眼睛隐藏在绿色的镜片后，整个仪态展示出一种最极致的东方式冷静。画中所有的人物都是一幅肖像，其中一个最有趣，因为其古怪的面孔一点不像希腊人，她是站在王后身旁侍奉的一个德国女人。

在G先生的作品中，经常能看到一个人物，那就是法国国王。画家以速写的方式描画出他的脸，标志性地一挥而就，而又绝不失真。有时，国王在纵马奔驰，检阅军队，陪同人员是面貌容易辨认的官员，或者国外的（欧洲、亚洲或者非洲的）国家元首，国王好像是在向他们致以巴黎的敬意。有时，国王一动不动地骑在马上，马蹄就像桌子的四条腿，稳稳地站在地上；他的左边是皇后，保持着骑马的习惯；右边是小皇太子，头戴毛皮高帽子，身姿像军人一样笔挺，骑着一匹毛发乱蓬蓬的小马，就像英国画家喜欢放在风景画中的那种四处奔跑的小马。有时，他在布洛涅森林的小径上策马而行，夹杂着尘土的光线倾泻下来，笼罩着他。还有时候，我们看到他走在圣安东尼郊区的人群中，接受民众的热情欢呼。其中有一幅水彩画，好似有一种魔力，尤其令我倾倒。画面上，皇后坐在一个装饰华丽的包厢前方，面容平静而放松；国王的身子微微前倾，似乎是想更好地观看表演；下面站着两个卫兵，身姿笔挺，几乎是虔诚地一动不动，他们漂亮的制服闪耀出舞台脚灯反射的光。在舞台完美氛围的这束光后，演员在和谐地歌唱、念白和做各种手势；在画面近处，是一个弥漫着光线的深渊，那是枝形吊灯；每一排都是塞满层层人脸的圆形空间，那是观众。

1848年的民众游行、会所和庄严场合，为G先生提供了一系列场景的主题，其中大多都发表在《伦敦画报》上。几年前，他在西班牙旅居了一段时间，这对他的天赋大有裨益，他后来创作了同样性质的一个作品系列，我曾经看到过其中几张。他经常把自己的画随意送人，或者借给他人，这常常给他带来不可挽回的损失。

八、士兵

要再次定义这位艺术家最青睐的题材，且让我们称之为生活的隆重仪式，正如它在文明世界的首都、军事庆典、骄奢淫逸的生活中所展现出的那样。我们的见证人总是准时出现在他的观察岗，那里流淌出深沉、冲动的欲望，即人心、战争、爱情、博弈的伟大河流；那里作为喜悦和哀伤之外在形式的庆典正蓬勃进行。但是，这位艺术家对军事生活、对士兵表现出非常明显的偏好，我想这种热爱不仅源于军人的灵魂所必然给他的风度和面容带来的美德和品质，也来源于他的华丽制服。保罗·德·莫莱纳[42]先生曾经就军队的献媚和所有政府为其军队设计的炫目制服中蕴含的道德意义，写过几页充满智慧的文字，让人读完拍手称快。G先生会很愿意在这几页纸上签上自己的名字。

前面我们谈到过每个时代特有的美的风格，我们已经注意到，每个时代都有属于自己的优雅。这同样也适用于职业；每种职业都从统治它的道德法则中获取了它的外在美。对于某些职业而言，这种美是充满能量的；而对于另外一些职业，可能带着闲适的明显标记。这可以说是性格的特征、命运的印记。士兵整体上有一种美，正如镇上的浪荡子和女人一样，各有其特征。读者也自然会接受我在此忽略了那样一些职业，从业者的肌肉由于单一的激烈劳动而扭曲，脸上也有了奴役的印记。尽管士兵经常面临突发情况，但他们从不轻易失去冷静。因此，在这种情况下，美是一种无忧无虑、尚武的气质，一种平静与无畏的奇异结合；这是一种来自于随时牺牲自我的美的形式。但是理想的军人脸上必须有一种天真的神情，因为他们和僧侣和学生一样，过的是集体生活，习惯于将日常生活压力交给一个遥远的、家长式的组织。因此，士兵们在很多事情上都像孩子一样天真，而且像孩子一样，一旦任务完成，他们很容易开心，喜欢纵情享乐。所有这些道德思考都可以从G先生的素描和水彩画中自然得来，我这么说并非夸张。在这位艺术家的作品中，没有一种军人类型是缺失的。他是带着一种高昂的兴致来作画的：年老的步兵军官，面容悲伤，臃肿的身体压在战马上；养尊处优的军事参谋，俯身凑近坐在椅子上的女士，没有丝毫局促不安，肩部造作的动作，加上他的蜂腰，从后面看，让人想起某种苗条优雅的昆虫；轻步兵和步兵，他们整个的风度展现出大无畏和自立，以及一种更强烈的个人责任感；轻骑兵悠闲自在的举止，变化无常的喜悦；技术兵隐约有着学者和学院的特征，比如炮手和工兵，这常常可以在他们不好战的装备上得到证实。这些模特身上的细微的差别都没有被忽略，都被以同样的热爱和智慧来总结和定义。

现在，我的面前正放着这样一幅画。作品传递出英雄主义的整体印象，主题是步兵纵队；也许他们是从意大利出征归来，在林荫大道上稍作停留，正接受人群的热情欢呼；也许他们刚刚完成在伦巴第的长征；我不知道，但是人们能够充分感受到的，是这些古铜色的、饱经风霜的脸上那种坚定无畏的神情，即使在休息时也显而易见。

这无疑是由纪律、同甘共苦、长期巨大的压力所造成的无畏的稳重气质，卷起的裤腿塞进绑腿中，大衣破旧褪色，全部装备也有了那种远道归来、经历了非凡冒险后的不可毁灭的面貌。这些士兵似乎真的比普通人站得更稳更坚定，也更自信。如果一直在寻找也经常发现这种美的夏雷[43]看到了这张画作，他一定会印象深刻。

九、浪荡子

一个有钱有闲的人，对生活中的一切感到厌倦，除了追逐快乐外别无他事；自小便养尊处优，习惯了发号施令；最终这个除了优雅别无职业的人，必然总是带着一种特别的面部表情。浪荡作风是一种不明确的社会态度，与决斗一样奇怪；它要追溯到很久以前，恺撒、喀提林[44]、亚西比德[45]曾是其光辉榜样；自从夏多布里昂[46]在美洲的森林和湖畔找到了它，它便广泛地传播开来。浪荡作风是法律外的一个体制，有一套所有成员都必须严格遵守的法律准则，不管他们的个人性格是如何热情和独立。

英国的小说家在这种“上流社会”类型小说的创作上作出了突出贡献，而他们的法国同行，比如古斯丁侯爵[47]，也试图专门从事爱情小说的创作，并非常明智地安排小说人物都是有钱人，可以毫不迟疑地满足自己最不重要的欲望，而且让他们无须从事任何职业。这些人终日只是研究如何让自己更美，满足自己的热情，感受并思考。因此，他们尽情地享受着时间和金钱，如果没有这两样，幻想只能是转瞬即逝的白日梦，不太可能转化为行动。没有闲暇和金钱，爱情不过是普通人的狂欢，或者夫妻义务的完成，很不幸，但事实确实如此。爱情将不是充满激情和幻想的突如其来的冲动，而成为一件令人厌恶的功利的事情。

我之所以在浪荡作风的题目下谈到爱情，是因为爱情是有闲之人的天然职业。但是浪荡子自己并不认为爱情是一个特殊的生活目标。如果我谈到了金钱，是因为金钱对这些视自我喜好为唯一宗教的人来说，是不可或缺的；然而，浪荡子又不将财富本身作为目标，即使有未还清的银行欠款，对他们而言也无甚不同；他将这种低劣的喜好留给了俗人。与许多没有头脑的人的想法相反，浪荡作风甚至也不是对衣服和优雅物质生活的过分热衷。对于一个完美的浪荡子来说，这些事物不过是他思想的贵族优越性的象征符号。因此，由于他最看重的是自己的卓尔不群，在他眼中，完美的衣装应绝对地朴素，而这的确是体现高雅的最佳方式。那么这种具象化为一个教义并发展了一些杰出教徒的喜好，这一塑造出如此自负的群体的不成文法典，又是什么呢？它首先是一种在社会传统的外部限制下，创造出独创性个人形式的炽热欲望。它是一种自我主义，在对一种可以从他人身上（比如女人）获得的快乐形式的追寻中仍然保持不丧失，甚至在幻觉中仍可以存在。它是一种引起他人惊奇的乐趣，一种从不显露自我的扬扬自得。浪荡子也许厌烦了享乐，他甚至也许正遭受痛苦，但是在后一种情况下，他会保持微笑，就像那个被狐狸噬咬的斯巴达人[48]。

显然，浪荡作风在某些方面接近于灵性和斯多葛哲学，但是浪荡子绝不可以成为俗人。他如果犯罪，也许会被社会谴责，但如果是由于琐碎小事犯下的罪，这种耻辱便是无可弥补的了。请读者不要对这种庄重与玩乐的混合感到震惊；请大家想一想，其实在所有的蠢行中都有一种高尚，每种暴行的背后都有一股驱动力。果真是灵性的奇怪形式！对于那些既是它的领袖又是受害者的人，他们所置身的所有复杂的物质条件，不管是白日和夜晚任何时候都无可挑剔的衣装，还是最冒险的体育运动，都不过是适宜于锤炼意志和训练灵魂的一系列身体锻炼而已。我把浪荡作风比作一种宗教，确实也不算大错。最严苛的修道院的纪律，强迫信徒自杀的那位山中老人[49]最不容变更的命令，也不比这种关乎高雅和独创性的教义更专横，更让人甘心顺从。同其他教义一样，这一教义给它雄心勃勃而又谦卑的宗派成员，通常是一些充满活力、激情、勇气、克制的能量的人，灌输一个可怕的命令：做一个行尸走肉！[50]

难以取悦、不可思议、花花公子、社会名流或浪荡子，无论这些人给自己贴上哪一个标签，他们都来自同一处，都具有同样的反对和叛逆的特征，都包含着人类骄傲中所包含的最优秀成分，代表着一种击退并毁灭平凡的需要（这在现代人身上已经太罕见了）。在浪荡子身上，有那种傲慢、高贵态度的源头，即使冷淡也是咄咄逼人的。浪荡作风尤其会出现在民主势力尚未发展成熟的转型期，因为这个时候，贵族只是部分被削弱和丧失名誉。在这种时代的混乱状态下，某些感到幻灭和有闲同时也充满活力的“局外人”，可能都存着建立一个新的贵族阶层的念头，因为它建立在最宝贵、最不可毁灭的能力之上，建立在工作和金钱都无法赋予的非凡天赋之上，因此也更难瓦解。浪荡作风是堕落时代里最后一星英雄主义的光芒；旅行者在北美洲发现的浪荡子典型丝毫也削弱不了上述观念的价值，因为我们称之为野蛮人的部落可能是过去伟大文明的残余，我们没有理由不相信这一点。浪荡作风是一轮落日，就像正在陨落的星辰，它是壮丽的，没有热量，充满忧伤。但是，哎呀！民族大潮涌起，到处传播，荡平一切，每天都在带走人类骄傲最后的捍卫者，遗忘之水淹没了这些杰出追随者的最后踪迹。在法国，浪荡子变得越来越少了，而在我们的邻居英国，社会和宪法（真正的宪法，在社会习惯上表达出的宪法）的状况还将长久地为谢立丹[51]、布鲁梅尔[52]和拜伦的继承者留有一席之地。

读者可能觉得这是题外话，其实不是。在很多情况下，一位艺术家的画作所引发的道德思考和冥想，是批评家所能给出的最好解说；它们所暗示的理念是一个隐含思想的一部分，我们渐次发现这些理念，最终也许会发现那个根本的思想。如果不是因为我们处在这个时代，绘画被普遍认为是一种消遣，那么当G先生创作一幅浪荡子的画作时，总是赋予他历史的性格，几乎可以说是他传奇的性格，这一点还需要我多说吗？当我们从人海中瞥见这样一位享有特权的人，我们一定能看到他从容的态度，举手投足间的自信，习惯发出命令的坦率，穿礼服和驭马的特有方式，在任何情况下都保持着彰显力量的平静，这些打消了我们的疑问，引人注目和令人敬畏两者在他身上神奇般地混合：“他也许是一位富人，但肯定是一个无所事事的赫拉克勒斯[53]。”

浪荡子的特别之美尤其体现在他的冷酷外表上，这源于他时刻保持镇定的不可动摇的决心；他让人联想起一团隐伏的火，看似是可以忽略的存在，但如果愿意，却可以喷发出耀眼的光芒，但是他并不这样做。上述所有特质在这些画作中都得到了淋漓尽致的体现。

十、女人

对于大多数男人来说，女人是最活泼甚至最持久的快乐的源泉，尽管这样说会让哲学予人的乐趣颜面扫地。男人的所有努力都是为着女人，这个令人敬畏的生物，像上帝一样不可言说（不同之处在于，“无限”不显露自我，因为它会让“有限”昏聩和毁灭；而我们所说的这个生物，她的不可言说，只是因为没有什么可说的）；约瑟夫·德·迈斯特[54]在女人身上看到一头美丽的动物，她的魅力推动了严肃的政治游戏，为之增辉添彩；因为她的缘故，千金敛来又散去；为了她，艺术家和诗人创作出最高超的作品，然而，其中又以女性艺术家和诗人的成就最高；她们身上流淌出最销骨蚀魂的快乐和最使人充实的痛苦——总而言之，女人，对于所有艺术家而言，特别是对于G先生而言，不只是人类中的雌性。她是女神、是明星，主宰着男人头脑里的所有思想；她集天地灵秀之气于一身；她是生活阅历能给予男人的最强烈的仰慕和兴趣所指向的目标。她是偶像，也许头脑空空，但却千娇百媚、令人心醉，顾盼流转之下，便掌控了男人的命运和意志。我要再说一遍，她不是动物，只要四肢经过正确组合，便成为和谐的完美化身；她甚至也不是雕塑家在最严肃的沉思时刻所想象的那种纯粹的美；即使那也不足以解释她神秘莫测的迷人魅力。在这个问题上温克尔曼[55]和拉斐尔也帮不了我们；我肯定，即使博学多识如G先生（希望这么说不会冒犯他），也绝不会对一尊古代雕塑视而不见，即使他会因此失去欣赏一幅雷诺兹[56]和劳伦斯[57]肖像画的机会。女人的所有装饰，所有为她的美增色生辉的事物，都是女人的一部分；艺术家对这个谜一般的生物专门研究后，不仅会为女人倾倒，也会对女人的世界[58]着迷。无疑地，女人是一片光明，一道目光，一张通向幸福的请柬，有时是一句话；但是她首先是一个和谐的整体，不仅在她的仪态和举手投足间，也在她身上的细布、薄纱和大摆彩虹裙，这衣服可以说是她神圣地位的象征和支柱；这和谐还在她手臂和脖子上盘绕着的金属和宝石，既让她的双眸神采飞扬，又似在她耳边喁喁私语。当诗人描述一位美人带给他的愉悦时，他又如何能将她与她的衣装分而论之？你找不出一个男人，他在街上，在剧院，或者在林间，驻目于一件美丽的衣装，却只是超然地欣赏，最后留在脑海里的画面没有穿着这件衣服的美丽女子，因为这衣装和女子是不可分割的整体。现在似乎是时候回到关于时尚和修饰的某些问题上，在研究的开始我只是略有谈及，为的是反驳某些含糊其词的热爱自然者对服装艺术的愚蠢诋毁。

十一、赞化妆

我知道一首歌，因为太不足道，所以不敢在这个自命严肃的作品中引用它；然而，这首歌以杂耍表演的风格，非常恰如其分地表达出不习惯思考的人的美学观点：“本性装饰了美。”也许可以这样推测，一个“诗人”，如果可以恰当地驾驭语言，就会说“质朴装饰了美”，这等同于另一个完全是意料之外的真理：“存在的事物不需装饰。”

大多数关于美的错误观点源自于18世纪错误的道德观。在那时，“本性”被视为所有形式的“善”和“美”的基础、根源和原型。当时的普遍盲目很大程度上要归咎于对原罪的摒弃。但是，如果我们只打算考虑眼前的事实、所有时代的经验和《论坛报》，我们立即可以看到天性完全或几乎什么也没教给我们；换言之，它迫使人们吃喝睡觉，尽可能保护自己抵御严酷的天气。而同样也是“天性”，驱使人类自相残杀，噬食、囚禁和折磨同类；当人类脱离了求生存的窘境，开始可以追求享受和消遣，我们看到天性只是想到犯罪。就是这个所谓绝无谬误的天性，导致了弑亲和食人等千百种劣行，为谨慎和好意起见，我们在此不一一列举了。是哲学（我指的是正确的那种）和宗教教导我们照顾年迈可怜的父母，天性（不过是利己主义内心的声音）却让我们把他们打死。审视、分析一切天然的事物，一个完全“天然”之人的所有行动和欲望，你会发现无一处不恐怖。所有的美和高贵都是理智和周密思考的结果。犯罪从源头上是“天然”的，人类这种动物在母亲的子宫里就爱上了犯罪。另一方面，美德却是“人为的”、超自然的，因为在每个时代，每个国家，上帝和预言家都曾是必要的，因为他们将美德教给野蛮的人类，也因为人类无法靠自己发现美德。罪恶不需费力就能完成，这是“自然的”，它是命运的安排；善总是人工的产物。我把自然说成是道德方面的坏顾问，理性是救赎和改革的真正力量，都可以转移到美的范围中去。这也使得我将装饰视为人类灵魂原始高贵性的一个标志。被我们这个混乱而堕落的文明带着可笑的傲慢和自命不凡称为“野蛮人”的民族，却和孩子一样，能够欣赏衣服的高度精神特质。野蛮人和婴儿，他们对不同颜色的鲜艳羽毛，对闪闪发亮的织料，对人工形状的极度高贵表现出天真的喜爱，从而显示出对真实的厌恶，这不自觉地证明了他们灵魂的非物质性。如果有人像路易十五（远不是一个真正文明的结果，而是野蛮状态重归的结果），堕落到只欣赏未经修饰的自然的地步，那就悲哀了。[59]

因此，时尚必须被视为一种理想典范的品位的征象，它超越生活根据自然累积的粗野、鄙陋和令人厌恶的事物，被视为一种对自然的高尚变形，或者一种改造自然的持久且不断更新的努力。因为这个原因，有人曾明智地评价（尽管没有发现原因），所有时尚皆迷人，或者相对迷人，都是通向美的或多或少成功的努力，一种对理想的近似表现，一种不断缠绕着未得到满足的人类思想的欲望。但是，如果我们要很好地欣赏时尚，就一定不能把它视作僵死的事物，相反，我们要学会欣赏二手衣服店的衣橱里挂着的许多没有生气、一动不动，就像是圣巴多罗买[60]的皮的老衣服。我们必须想象这些衣服如曾经穿着它们的美丽女人那样充满活力和生命力。只有那样我们才能赋予它们意义和价值。如果你认为“所有时尚皆迷人”这句格言太过绝对，那可以改为，所有时尚在各自的时代都有其合理的迷人之处，这样就一点问题都没有了。

女人化妆完全是一种正当权利，我们甚至可以说，她们是在履行一种义务，致力于让自己的外表笼罩在一种迷人的、超自然的氛围中。她虽然是偶像，但也必须装扮自己以赢得青睐。所以，她必得从各类艺术中借来超越自然的手段，以更好地征服男人的心，在他们的脑海里留下深刻印象。这些计策和手段，如果成功是肯定的，效果是让男人无法抵御的，那它们为人所知也就无关紧要了。这种观点使得哲学的艺术家欣然将几个世纪来女人所采取的所有强调和神化自己纤巧之美的手段视为理所应当。如果加以详述，将会包括数不清的细节；但我们只限于讨论当下时代通常所称的化妆，谁会看不到，被无知哲学家愚蠢地加以谴责的粉饼，可以遮盖自然令人厌憎地散布在面部肌肤上的所有瑕疵，使皮肤的肌理和颜色呈现出形式上的协调？这种协调就像紧身裤营造出的效果，立刻便使人类接近于一尊雕塑，换言之，接近一种神性或优等的生物。至于眼部化妆所用的黑色铅笔，加深脸颊上半部分颜色的腮红，虽然它们的使用也源自同一原则，即超越自然的需要，其结果却注定是满足一个完全相反的需要。红色和黑色代表生命，一种超自然的、放纵的生命；眼部周围的黑圈让它们有一种更深邃、更奇怪的感觉，更让人感知到那是一扇通向无限的窗户；颧骨上深色的腮红让眼睛更有神采，让女人美丽的脸庞上多了一分女祭司的神秘激情。

所以，请听明白，我的意思是，化妆不能抱着庸俗的、遮遮掩掩地模仿自然中的美丽脸庞，或者拒绝衰老的目的。有人说，手段不修饰丑陋，它只为美丽服务。有谁敢派给艺术模仿自然的徒劳功能？化妆无须隐藏，不必害怕被发现；相反，它可以大摇大摆地招摇过市，如非装腔作势，至少是带着一种率真。

有些人的无趣严肃使得他们无法从最细微的表现中寻找美，我会容许这些人嘲笑我上面的思索，指责这些思索中有一种幼稚的严肃；对这些人的严厉批评我丝毫不以为意，我只愿意将它们诉诸真正的艺术家，以及那些在出生时即受了那圣火的火星、后佯装用来点亮外表的女人们。

十二、女人与少女

因此，在G先生承担了在现代性中寻找和解释美的使命后，他便喜欢画盛装打扮的女人，她们的美因为身上的每一处装饰而得到提升，勿论她们的社会阶层。而且，从整体上看他的作品，就像人类熙熙攘攘的生活一样，不管奢侈程度如何，画中人阶级和教养的不同，观者是一望便知的。

在一幅画中，我们看到在灯光弥漫的观众席，有一群最高级社交圈的年轻女人，光线反射在她们的双眸、佩戴的珠宝和肩膀上，包厢如同画框，她们就像一幅光彩夺目的肖像画。其中一些是庄重严肃的，另一些是美丽轻浮的。一些女子带着贵族的冷漠表现出早熟的迷人气质，其他女子则稚气未脱给人假小子的感觉。她们都咬着手中的扇子，目光或茫然或专注；她们的姿势是夸张和隆重的，就像她们正假装在聆听的话剧和歌剧。

另一幅画，是穿着时尚的一家人，正在沿着公园小路散步。无忧无虑的妻子倚在丈夫的手臂上，丈夫安然满足的气质显示出这是一个奋斗成功的男人，富有而自得。这里，富有的整体气质取代了傲慢。小女孩们手臂细如火柴棍，穿着大摆裙，举止形容像一个小妇人，她们蹦蹦跳跳，玩呼啦圈，或者过家家，在户外上演着她们的父母在家里上演的社交喜剧。

这一幅画展示的是更低一级的社会阶层，来自郊区剧院的少女演员，因为终于出现在舞台脚灯的强光中而如孔雀般骄傲，她们身材纤细、孱弱，几乎还没长大，用处女的病态的身体摇曳着身上可笑的演出服，这演出服说不上属于哪个时代，但却给它们的主人带来了快乐。

这一幅，在咖啡馆门口，我们看到宽大的窗子被房间内外的灯光照得通明，一个懒洋洋的笨蛋靠在窗子上，他的优雅是裁缝的功劳，他的仪表要感谢理发师。坐在他身边的是他的情妇，脚搭在必不可少的一张脚凳上，身材就像一头奶牛，身上几乎不缺什么（这里“不缺什么”意思是什么都缺，简言之，“气质”），让她看起来像一个出身高贵的女士。她和自己的漂亮男友一样，樱桃小口中塞着一支特大号雪茄。这两个人的头脑中都空无一物。谁也不能肯定他们是在看什么东西——除非，像蠢笨的纳喀索斯[61]一样，他们在凝视着人群，好像它是一条河，映出自己的倒影。在现实中，他们的存在更多是让旁观者而非自己感到快乐。

现在，瓦朗蒂诺、卡西诺、普拉多（即过去的提沃里、意达里、佛里、帕佛）打开了灯火通明、人声鼎沸的长廊，在这里，无所事事的有钱年轻人可以尽情释放自己的本能冲动。女人们把最新的潮流夸张到极致，破坏掉它线条的优雅，正在卖弄地走来走去，用她们披肩的幅摆和边缘擦着发亮的地板，眼睛里射出动物般野性的光芒，虽然表面上什么都没有看，其实却在观察一切。

在冥府之光或者北极光的背景下，即红色、橙色、硫黄的黄色、粉色（那种让人联想到轻浮中狂热的粉色），有时是紫罗兰色（像蓝色帷帐后余烬的颜色，为女牧师所钟爱）。在这种神秘的背景下，带着多种焰火的效果，展现在我们眼前的可疑之美的种种画面，一时高贵，一时嬉闹，一时苗条甚至瘦削，一时臃肿，一时像玩偶一样活泼可爱，一时又沉重如雕塑一般。这种可疑之美或者展示出她自创的一种充满诱惑的粗俗的优雅，或者她会多多少少模仿上流社会流行的简约。她朝我们走来，滑着、舞着、摇摆着，似乎全靠她那刺绣衬裙的重量，它既是钟摆又是基座；她的眼波从帽檐下流出，就像一幅加框的肖像画。她是生活在文明中的野蛮人的完美形象。她身上有一种罪恶带给她的美，总是缺乏灵性，但偶尔会有一种伪装成忧郁的疲乏。她的眼睛投向地平线，就像一头狩猎的野兽：同样的野蛮，同样的冷漠，有时又是同样的神情专注。她是吉卜赛类型的人，处在正常社会的边缘地带；浅薄是她充斥着欺诈和挣扎的生活的主要内容，不可避免地透过她的盛装暴露出来。那位无法模仿的大师拉布吕耶尔曾经说过一段话，也许正可以描述她，“一些女人身上有一种不自然的高贵，体现在她们转动眼睛和高昂着头的方式，或者走路的动作；但它行之不远，仅此而已……”

以上关于交际花的看法，在一定程度上，也适用于女演员；因为她也是爱表演的动物，向公众邀宠。但在后者，征服和猎获具有一种更高贵、更属精神的性质。她的目标是赢得公众喜爱，不仅通过纯粹的外在美，也通过罕有的才华。如果说女演员一方面接近交际花，她在另一方面却也接近于诗人。让我们不要忘记，除了自然美甚至人工美，所有人身上都打上了其从事的职业的烙印，这种特质可以表现为肉体的丑，但也可表现为某种职业的美。

在伦敦和巴黎这个广阔的生活画廊中，我们遇到各式各样处在不同阶段的单身女人，以及叛逆的女人：首先是刚刚长成的小镇千金，正在努力培养自己的贵族气质，炫耀着她的青春和奢华，使得她所拥有的天赋和灵魂不言自明；我们看到，她有各式料子的裙子，缎子、丝绸或天鹅绒无一不备，她用两根手指小心翼翼地拎着裙子上的荷叶边，露出一对尖尖的玉足，即使没有那艳丽的裙子，她脚上过分华丽的鞋子也足以暴露她的身份。沿着梯子下几级，我们会遇到困在装饰得像咖啡馆的破屋里的那些奴隶；这些不幸的人，遭受着最贪得无厌的管制，没有什么东西是属于自己的，甚至连身上装点美的古怪装饰也不是自己的。其中一些人，带着那种明显无辜但却可怕的愚昧，脸上和毫无廉耻地直视着你的眼睛里，有一种对活着的明显的喜悦（这实在让人诧异）。有时，她们可以轻松地摆出性感而又高贵的姿势，这会让最吹毛求疵的雕刻家都欢喜雀跃，假如今天的雕刻家有勇气和智慧在所有地方都找到高贵，即使是在泥潭；其他时候，她们表现出令人绝望的无聊，似乎对自己无能为力，或者张扬地摆出咖啡馆生活的懒散姿势，带着男人的厚颜无耻，抱着逆来顺受的东方宿命论，靠抽雪茄消磨时日；她们躺在沙发上，大大的裙摆在头上和脚下形成两个扇形，或者摇摇晃晃地坐在高脚凳或椅子上；身材臃肿、沮丧、愚蠢、缺乏理性的她们，喝着白兰地，目光呆滞无神，丰满的额头上写着固执。我们已经到达螺旋楼梯最下面一级，发现了拉丁讽刺诗人[62]所谓的“单纯女人”[63]。在某个时间，在这充满烟酒的氛围中，我们也不难发现这里有肺结核病人憔悴发热的面颊，那里有懒惰所导致的臃肿丑陋的身体曲线。在这烟雾缭绕的喧闹中，沐浴在金黄色光线下的是贫穷而纯洁的女人做梦都想象不到的场景，可怕的仙女和活着的玩偶穿行其中，扭曲着身体，孩子般的眼睛里射出冷酷险恶的光；而在放满酒瓶的柜台后，一个肥胖的悍妇懒洋洋地坐着，她的头发用一块脏兮兮的丝巾束起来，丝巾的棱角在墙上投下邪恶的影子，于是我们相信所有献给邪恶的事物一定都受到诅咒，长了角。

事实上，我把这些场景展现在读者眼前，既不是为了取悦也不为冒犯，因为两者都对读者缺乏尊重。赋予这些场景价值和一种神圣性的是它们所引起的无数思考，通常是严肃而阴郁的。但是如果碰巧某个不明智的读者，想在G先生的作品中寻找机会满足他病态的好奇心，虽然它们分散在各处，那么让我给他一个善意的警告，那就是，他不会找到任何挑起淫秽想象力的东西。他能找到的只有必然发生的恶行，换言之，藏在阴影中的恶魔的眼睛，或者在煤气灯下梅萨丽娜[64]白皙发亮的肩膀；她只有纯粹的艺术，换言之，即罪恶特有的那种美，恐怖中的美。顺便想起刚才所说的，这个大仓库传达出的整体印象更多是充满悲伤，而非乐趣。这些画作特有的美在于它丰富的道德意义。它们引人遐思，是残酷的思绪，虽然我已习惯将画面的感召诉诸笔端，但是这些文字也许仍不足够。

十三、马车

就这样，这些“上层社会”和“下层社会”的长长走廊向远处延伸开去，两边又有无数的侧廊。让我们暂时逃向一个世界，即使并不纯净，至少更加优雅；让我们呼吸芳香，也许并非更加健康，但是更清香。我曾说过，就像欧仁·拉米一样，G先生手中的画笔非常适合表现浪荡作风的排场和社交场上的优雅女人。富人的姿态他是熟悉的；只需轻轻几笔，他便能准确无误地捕捉住反映在特权阶层眼睛里、举手投足间和仪态上的那份无法言传的安全感，这源自于他们人生道路上一贯的好运。在这一特别的作品系列中，我们看到各种各样的运动、赛马和打猎的场景，比如一场在树林中举行的马车比赛，有骄傲的夫人和娇弱的小姐，娴熟地驾驭着一匹骏马，马儿的外形完美、漂亮、毛发亮泽，也像女人一样任性。G先生不仅了解关于马的一般知识，而且也同样成功地传达出每匹马的独特美。一些画作描绘了一场运动会，一次真正的露营和无数的马车，其中，俊男美女穿着应季的古怪服装，靠在垫子上，坐在座位上或包厢里，正在观看一场严肃的赛马会，赛马选手的身影消失在远处。在另一幅画上，一辆敞篷的四轮轻便马车旁，一个人在优雅地骑马慢跑，他的马好像是在以自己的方式腾跃嬉戏，马车则沿着一条光影斑驳的小道，轻快地跑着，车上是一群美人，穿着气球一样的裙子，看起来就像坐在贡多拉上似的，她们慵懒地倚着靠垫，漫不经心地听着赞美之词，懒洋洋地享受着拂面的微风。

她们穿着皮毛或者平纹细布的衣服，一直包到下颌，裙裾在马车门上方飞扬。仆人无一例外地表情呆板、身姿笔挺、一动不动；总是那种单调乏味的肖像画，满脸奴性，动作精确，训练有素；他们的性格就是没有性格。画作的背景上，树林被装点成绿色和棕色，根据时间和季节不同，闪着微光或逐渐变暗。树荫处笼罩着秋天的薄雾、蓝色的阴影、黄色的光线、玫瑰粉色的光辉，或者在黑暗中闪烁的像剑刺一样的一道道闪电。

如果以黎凡特战争为主题的无数水彩画，没有展示出G先生作为风景画家的能力，这些作品一定足够了。但是这里没有克里米亚半岛被战火蹂躏得千疮百孔的土地，没有博斯普鲁斯海峡戏剧性的海滨；我们又见到了环绕着我们的大城市的熟悉而亲切的翠绿景色，光线营造出的效果，是一个真正的浪漫艺术家不能轻视的。

另一点值得一提的是，G先生熟知马具和四轮大马车。在画每一辆和每一种马车时，G先生都带着同样的精心和轻松，就像一个娴熟的海洋风景画家熟悉每种船一样。他对马车的描画都是正确的，每一处细节都在正确的地方，无须重头来过。不管马车位置如何，速度怎样，一辆马车都像一艘船一样，从行驶中获得了一种神秘复杂的优雅，速写是很难捕捉这种优雅的。画家的眼睛从中获得的快感，显然来自于一系列几何图形，是那个本身已很复杂的物体——马车和船——在空间行进时创造出来的。

我们可以打赌，几年后，G先生的画作将成为文明生活的宝贵档案。他的作品会像第伯柯尔特、莫罗[65]、圣·欧邦、卡尔·韦尔内[66]、拉米、德维利亚、加瓦尔尼等技艺精湛的画家一样受到追捧，虽然这些画家创作的主题都局限于通俗和美丽的事物，然而，他们都以自己的方式，成为重要的历史学家。这些画家中有几个为了所谓的“美丽事物”牺牲了太多，有时还会在作品中引入了与主题不相关的古典风格；有几个特意磨平了棱角，缓和了生活的冷酷，让色调更柔和。G先生的技巧赶不上他们，但却有一个特有的深刻优点；他承担了一个其他画家轻视的工作，一个只有入世之人能完成的工作。他在我们这个时代的生活中四处去寻找昙花一现、稍纵即逝的美的形式，如果读者允许，我们把这种美的特性称为“现代性”。这种美经常是奇特的、狂暴的、过分的，但总是充满了诗意，他已经成功地将生活之酒的苦涩和醉人的滋味凝聚在他的作品中。

欧仁·德拉克洛瓦的人生与作品——致《国民舆论》编辑的一封信

先生：

这是我再一次，也是最后一次想向欧仁·德拉克洛瓦[67]的天才致敬，我恳求您，在您的报纸上留出几页，我将尽可能简短地记录下他的才能和他出类拔萃的原因，在我看来，这一点人们还没有完全认识到，最后还有几桩趣闻逸事和对他人生和性格的一些评论。

在我还很年轻的时候（那是在1845年，如果我没记错的话），我有幸与这位伟人有了密切接触，现在他已经去世了；我对他怀着尊敬，他对我则爱护有加，而这并未妨碍我们互相信任和亲近。从这种关系中，我可以随意汲取极为准确的观念，不仅关于他的创作方法，而且关于他伟大灵魂最隐私的特质。

先生，您不会看到我在这里对德拉克洛瓦的作品进行详细的分析。首先，我们每个人对此都会量力而行。其次，这位伟大画家一直在不断地向公众展示他思想的产物，他的作品清单实在太长，就算只对他的主要作品写上几行字，这种分析就差不多能成一本书了。所以，让我们满足于一个快速的概览吧。

他的不朽作品悬挂在众议院国王沙龙的墙上，还出现在众议院的图书馆、卢森堡宫的图书馆、卢浮宫的阿波罗画廊，以及城市酒店的和平沙龙里。这些装饰画包括大批寓言、宗教和历史题材，所有这些都属于人类智力的最高领域。至于他所谓的“画架作品”、素描、浮雕式灰色装饰画、水彩作品等，总数也大约有236幅。

在不同沙龙展出的表现重大主题的作品有77幅之多。我是从泰奥菲勒·西勒维斯特尔先生[68]所著的《当代画家史》一书中看到这些数字的，它们出现在关于欧仁·德拉克洛瓦的精辟研究的最后。

我自己曾不止一次试图整理一个清单出来，但是他的多产总是将我的耐心耗尽，最后我不得不放弃了这一不平等的抗争。如果泰奥菲勒·西勒维斯特尔先生犯了任何错误，那只能是遗漏了一些。

在我看来，先生，这里重要的是，寻找德拉克洛瓦天才的特质，并试图对它进行阐明；探究他与他同样杰出的前辈们的不同之处何在；最后，尽文字所能，展示他成功将言语转化成绘画作品的魔法艺术，他的作品比其他画家更充满生机、更恰如其分，简单来说，就是来展示在绘画的历史发展上，上天赋予了欧仁·德拉克洛瓦怎样的特质。

一

德拉克洛瓦是何许人也？他在这个世界上担负着怎样的角色和责任？这是我们必须研究的第一个问题。我不会长篇大论，将力图得出直接结论。佛兰德斯有鲁本斯，意大利有拉斐尔和委罗内塞，法国有勒布伦[69]、大卫和德拉克洛瓦。

肤浅的人乍一看到这几个名字放在一起，可能会感到吃惊，因为这几位画家的特点和手法截然不同。但是一个更有洞察力、更敏锐的人，立刻就能看到，他们之间有一个共同的关系，一种兄弟和亲戚的关系，这源自于他们对伟大、对民族、对无限和对宇宙的热爱，这种热爱总是能在所谓的装饰油画或宏伟“巨制”中表现出来。

无疑有很多人创作过宏伟“巨制”；但是我列出的这几个人，他们的作品是最有可能在人类记忆上打下永恒烙印的。这几位各有其伟大之处，而其中谁是最伟大的呢？每个人都可以给出自己的答案，在天性驱使下，他或是喜欢鲁本斯的多产、用色的丰富和几乎是快活的丰腴，或是拉斐尔的宁静高贵、比例协调，或是委罗内塞的天堂般的、仿佛午后的色彩，或是大卫朴实而紧张的严肃，抑或是伦勃朗戏剧的、近乎文学的优美流畅。

这几个人都是不可替代的。他们有着相似的目标，然而由于天性不同创作手法亦不同。德拉克洛瓦最晚出道，他的作品中有一种令人仰慕的激情和热心，这一点是其他几位的表达有所欠缺的。在创作中，他是否可能牺牲了其他的品质，就像他的前辈那样？也许吧，但我们需要关注的不是这个问题。

在我之外，有很多人都注意强调一种本质上是个人的天才所导向的宿命后果；它也可能是，天才在最纯洁的天国之外——即在人间，这里连完美都是不完美的——的最佳表达，只有作出不可避免的牺牲后才能完成。

但是，“得了，先生！”你无疑会这么说，“到底这种神秘的、无法言明的东西是什么，让德拉克洛瓦能够表达得比其他人更好，让我们这个时代得到荣耀？”那是一种无形的东西，一种无法触摸的东西，是幻想、是力量、是灵魂；他做到了这一点——先生，请注意——除了轮廓和色彩外没用其他任何手段；这一点他做得比所有人都要好；他的画表现出一个顶级画家的完美，一个精湛作家的严谨，一个激情音乐家的流畅。补充一句，我们这个时代精神气候的一个症状就是，各门艺术如果不是渴望替代彼此的话，至少也是渴望给彼此注入新的能力和力量。

在所有的画家中，德拉克洛瓦的作品是最具启发性的，即使是他二流或最差的作品，也能给人的思想提供最多的食粮，勾起人们最大的诗意感受，这种感受人们曾经有过，还以为已经被夜晚永远吞噬掉了。

有时，德拉克洛瓦的作品在我看来，就像是有助于记忆的卓越媒介和知识渊博之人与生俱来的激情。德拉克洛瓦先生这种独特而全新的优势，让他仅凭轮廓就能表达人的姿势，不论它是如何狂暴；仅凭颜色就能营造所谓“人间戏剧”的气氛或者创作者的思想感情——他这一特有的优势，总能引起所有诗人对他作品的共鸣。如果可以用一个纯粹物质的表现引出一种哲学的检验的话，我要请您注意，先生，在他去世时前来吊唁的人群中，作家的人数比画家要多得多。说白了，事实就是，画家从来没有完全理解他。

二

而这又有什么奇怪的呢？我们难道不知道，米开朗基罗、拉斐尔、列奥纳多·达·芬奇的时代，甚至是乔舒亚·雷诺兹的时代，都早已过去了？而艺术家的平均知识水平都明显地降低了？虽然从当代艺术家中寻找哲学家、诗人和科学家并不公平，但是期待他们对宗教、诗歌和科学表现出比现在更多的兴趣是合理的。

他们对工作室外的世界又知道什么？他们喜欢什么？他们想要表达什么？而欧仁·德拉克洛瓦，他除了是一位醉心艺术的画家外，还是一个受过全面教育的人；相反，大部分现代画家，不管年老的还是年轻的，大多不过是些有名或无名的画匠、忧郁的专家；他们是纯粹和简单的技工，有些擅于画学术人物肖像，有些擅于画水果，还有一些擅于画牲畜。欧仁·德拉克洛瓦热爱一切，可以就一切题材作画，能够欣赏每一种才智。他的头脑能接受所有观点、所有印象；他兼收并蓄、不偏不倚地热爱着所有经验。

他是个很好的读者，这是不消说的。阅读诗人的作品在他身上留下了崇高的、迅速确定了的形象，可以说，留下了已经完成的画。不管他和老师圭林[70]在创作手法和色彩运用上有多大不同，他还是从共和的、帝国的伟大流派中继承了对诗歌的热爱，以及一种说不清的与文字竞争的狂热精神。大卫、圭林和吉洛德从荷马、维吉尔、让·拉辛和奥西昂的作品中汲取感情。德拉克洛瓦是莎士比亚、但丁、拜伦和阿里奥斯托[71]动人的传达者。他们之间有重要的相似性和轻微的不同。

编辑先生，让我们在人们可称之为大师的教诲中追溯得更远些吧，对我来说，这种教诲不仅来自对他所有作品接连不断的观赏和对某些作品同时的观赏，就像人们在1855年万国博览会上欣赏到的那样，而且也来自我和画家本人进行的多次谈话。

三

德拉克洛瓦热烈地爱着激情，并冷静地寻找着表达激情最醒目的方式。顺便提一下，在这种双重性格中，我们找到了最坚实、极端的天才的两个标记，它不能取悦容易满足的胆怯灵魂，因为后者在松懈的、柔弱的、有瑕疵的作品中就找得到足够的营养。强烈的激情，再加上强大的意志力，这就是德拉克洛瓦。

他也喜欢重复说：“既然我把自然传递给艺术家的印象看作需要表达的最重要的事情，那么，艺术家事先以各种最迅速的表达手段把自己武装起来不就是很必要的吗？”

很明显，在他的眼里，想象力是最珍贵的礼物和最重要的才能，但是如果没有掌握一种迅速的技能，这种才能是无力和无用的，而那种迅速的灵巧是可以在这专制的伟大能力的不耐烦的任性中追随其后的。当然，他没有必要为他的想象力之火添加燃料，因为这火一直烧得很旺；但是他总觉得留给他研究表达的技术手段的时间太少了。

这种不断的考虑，表现在他对颜色和颜料质量的不懈研究、对化学问题的兴趣，以及与颜料制造商的讨论上。在这方面，他与列奥纳多·达·芬奇很像。

尽管他赞美虔诚的生活现象，但绝不可以将欧仁·德拉克洛瓦与那些庸俗的艺术家和作家混为一谈，他们肤浅的思想隐藏在“现实主义”这一含糊晦涩的词之后。如果没记错，我第一次见德拉克洛瓦先生是在1845年（真是时光荏苒，岁月如梭），我们谈了许多一般的话题，所谓一般，指的是话题宽泛，但也是最简单的。先生，话说到这里，我要请您允许我引用我写过的一句话，因为与其重新表述，不如直接把这句话拿来，它几乎是大师的口述，他说：“自然不过是一本字典。”他喜欢这么说。要透彻理解这句话蕴含的全部意思，我们必须记住字典的无数寻常的用途。我们查找单词的词义、衍生义和词源，最终，我们从一本词典中得到了句子所有的组成部分和有序叙事；但是从没有人想到从字典的诗义上将它视为一件作品。服从想象力的画家，他们查字典是寻找与他们理念相符的成分，在赋予其艺术效果后，给了它们一副全新的面孔。那些没有想象力的人抄袭字典，这又产生了一种很大的罪恶，即陈腐；流于陈腐的画家们，他们的专长最接近所谓的死气沉沉的性情。比如，风景画家，他们如果能在作品中隐藏自己的个性，通常便会将之视为胜利。他们太专注于观察，以致竟忘记了感觉和思考。

“对于这位伟大的画家而言，艺术的各个部分不过是一种卓越才能的最恭顺的仆人，其他人则从这众多部分中择取一个作为最重要的。如果准确的创作是必要的话，那是为了梦幻可以清晰地得到表达；如果创作速度要很快，那是为了完整保留灵感迸发之时的非凡印象；如果这位艺术家留意他的工具是否干净，那也很容易理解，那是为了作好充分准备，以确保创作的敏捷果断。”

顺便说一句，我从未见谁的调色板准备得像德拉克洛瓦的那样悉心和精巧，就像一束精心搭配过的花。

“依照这种从本质上合乎常理的方法，所有的人物，他们彼此间的关系，作为他们的背景或是地平线的风景或内景，他们的服装，简言之，所有一切都必须服务于作品主旨，都要呈现自身本色，也可以说是它们的制服。正如一个梦要有它合适的氛围，一个构想要成为作品，也需要构建一个专属于它的色彩环境。显然，一个既定色调适合画面某个部分，它就会成为关键，主导着画面的所有其他部分。人人都知道黄色、橙色和红色代表着欢乐、财富、荣耀和爱；但是黄色或红色营造的氛围多达几千种，那么其他所有颜色都要根据画面的主要氛围，合理并根据一定比例来修改。从一些方面来讲，这位色彩画家的艺术显然与数学和音乐有关系。

“而作画的最高境界是在某种情感支配下的一气呵成，这种莫可名状的娴熟是长久练习的结果。人们将会看到，在这种整体和谐的伟大法则之下，许多作品的花哨和生硬暴露无遗，即便它们是出自最杰出的画家之手。比如，鲁本斯的一些作品，让我们联想到的不只是一个彩色焰火，而是同一地点同时燃放的多个焰火。画面越大，色彩越丰富，这自不待言，但是色彩的融合最好不要有斧凿的痕迹，从远处看，它们应该是自然地融合在一起，支配它们的是和谐的法则。这样，色彩才会富有活力，别具一格。

“一幅好的画作，如果要忠于和配得起它所产生的梦境的话，必须创作得像一个世界。正如我们看到的，一幅作品是好几幅作品的结果，后面的作品总是对前面的进行补充，所以一个和谐的作品是好几幅作品叠加在一起的结果，每一幅都让那个梦境更加真实，更臻于完美。与之完全相反，我还记得在保罗·德拉罗什[72]和贺拉斯·威尔奈的工作室，看到过一些巨大的油画，它不是先总体构图，而是一部分一部分依次完成的，也就是说，某些部分已经完工，而其他部分还只有一些黑白线条。这种创作可以喻为一种完全手工的创作，即分配好在特定时间完成特定区域的工作，或者可以比喻为一条被分成许多段的长长的路。一旦某个路段完工，这段的工作也结束了，当这条路一段段修完，艺术家的作品也就完成了。

“当然，所有这些规则，根据艺术家的秉性不同，都或多或少地有所变化。但是，我相信，对于富有想象力的人来说，前面所说的那种方法是最保险的。因为，过分地偏离这种方法，也就表明，人们赋予了艺术的某些次要方面一种非正常和不合理的重视。

“我不怕有人诟病用单一方法教授不同的人。因为，修辞和韵律的教学体系显然不是随意创造出的专横形式，而是人们的精神世界所需规则的集合。同样，修辞和韵律体系也不会遏制人们的创造力。正相反，它们倒是会大大帮助开发人们的创造力。

“为了简明扼要，我必须略去不谈一些从这个主要原则派生出来的推论，这一主要原则，可以说，包含着真正美学的整套密码：肉眼可见的整个宇宙不过是一个储存图像和符号的仓库，人们的想象力会赋予它们一个地位和相对的价值；它就像一片牧场，想象力可以在其中吃草，进行能量转换。人类灵魂的所有功能必须从属于想象力，想象力统领它们协同作出贡献。就像对字典了如指掌，不代表就了解构图的艺术，能够进行艺术构图也不代表有广博想象力的天赋，所以一个好的画家可能不是一个伟大的画家，但是，一个伟大的画家一定是一个技巧娴熟的画家，因为拥有一种广博的想象力，一定意味着对所有技术手段的了解和占有这些手段的愿望。

“从我刚刚尽力表达的观点上（还有很多话没说，尤其是在艺术的共同点和它们所用方法的相似性上），显而易见，庞大的艺术家阵营，或者说，致力于艺术表达的人，可以分为两大截然不同的阵营。一个阵营是我们所谓的‘现实主义者’，这个词有双重含义，它的意义还没有精确界定；为了很清晰地显现出他们的错误，我们将称他们为‘实证主义者’。‘实证主义者’如是说：‘我想按照事物的本来面目，或者在假定我不存在的情况下它们的面目来表现它们。’一个没有人的世界。另一个阵营里的，则是那些富有想象力的人，他们说：‘我想用我的头脑点亮事物，并将它的影子投射在其他头脑上。’尽管这两种截然相反的方法可以增强和削弱任何主题，无论是宗教画还是最普通的风景画，但是在宗教画和幻想画中，富有想象力的人通常会脱颖而出。而所谓的风俗画和风景画，从表面上看，为懒惰的、不容易兴奋的头脑提供了丰富的资源。

“德拉克洛瓦的想象力啊！这是一种从不畏惧攀登宗教险峰的想象力。天堂属于它，就像地狱属于它一样，还有战争、奥林匹斯山和愉悦。他无疑是画家派诗人的典型！他无疑是为数不多的上帝的选民之一，他思想的广度将宗教也纳入其领地范围。他的想象力像点满蜡烛的小教堂一样明亮，辉煌而鲜红。激情中所有的悲伤吸引着他，教堂里的光辉让他心中充满光明。在他那充满灵感的画布上，他依次倾洒着鲜血、光明和黑暗。我相信，作为锦上添花之笔，他会乐意将自己与生俱来的高贵加诸《福音书》的崇高之上。

“我记得看到过德拉克洛瓦画的一幅小的《天使传报》[73]图，画上给马利亚送信的天使，不是一个，而是还有其他两个天使隆重地护送前来，这三个天使营造的效果很强烈，充满魅力。他早期的一幅画作《橄榄树下的基督》（‘父啊，你若愿意，就把这杯撤去’），充满了女性的温柔和诗意的愉悦。宗教中回荡着的苦难和庄严总是能引起他思想的共鸣。”

更近一些时候，他的最后一幅伟大作品《圣苏比的圣天使教堂》，受到了愚蠢的批评。对此我说道：“德拉克洛瓦从来没有像在这幅作品中一样，如此精彩、深入和超自然地展示出对色彩的感觉，在《图拉真皇帝的审判》中没有，甚至在《第四次十字军东征进入君士坦丁堡》中也没有；他从未用如此刻意的史诗般的笔触去创作一幅作品。我知道一些人，他们肯定是泥瓦匠，也许是建筑师，提到他最后的这幅作品时用到了‘颓废’一词。我由此想到，那些大师，不论是诗人还是画家，是雨果还是德拉克洛瓦，总是要比他们胆怯的仰慕者们超前好几年。[74]

“在对待天才上，公众就像一只走慢的钟。有见地的人们，谁不知道大师的第一幅画已经孕育了他其他所有作品的胚芽？然而，他应该不断地完善自己的天赋，慎重地使之更加敏锐，从中汲取新的感受；他应该尽力地驱策自己的天赋，这是必要发生、不可推卸和值得赞扬的。德拉克洛瓦的天才的主要特征正在于它绝不是衰颓的，它表现的只有进步。但是他原本的品质是如此强烈和丰富，即使是最平庸的头脑都感受到了它强大的冲击力，以至于后者忽视了他每天的进步；只有明智人士能清晰地看到他的进步。

“我刚才提到了某些泥瓦匠。在我看来，‘泥瓦匠’这个词描述了一个粗俗的唯物主义思想的群体（这个群体为数众多），他们欣赏事物只是从轮廓，或者更糟，从长宽高三维的角度来欣赏，就像野蛮人和农民一样。我经常听到这类人制定出一个我完全听不懂的品级级系。比如，他们会认为，那种让这个人创造出某个精确的轮廓，那个人创造出某个具有神性美的轮廓的能力，要优于将不同色彩以赏心悦目的方式组合在一起的能力。它们认为，色彩本身是没有梦想、思考和表达的能力的。这样看来，当我凝视着所谓‘色彩画家’的作品时，便是沉溺于一种不那么高贵的愉悦中；他们倒是很愿意把我称作唯物主义者，而将唯心论者这一贵族的称号留给自己。

“这些浅薄的人认识不到，上面所说的两种能力从来都不能完全分开，它们都是某个精心培育的原始种子的产物。外部的自然不过是为艺术家提供了一个不断重现的培育种子的机会；而人的天性只是一堆未经整合的素材，需要艺术家进行排列组合，成为那些沉睡的能力的一个闹钟。准确来说，天性中既无线条，也无色彩。是人创造了线条和色彩。两者都是从同一源头获得同等高尚地位的抽象概念。

“一个天生的画家，在孩提时，就能从自然中看到一些或静或动的错综复杂的形状，他从中感受到愉悦，并喜欢以线条的形式把它们呈现在纸上，在情绪变化的驱动下，突出或弱化某些部分。他以这种方式学会了如何在画作中表现曲线、优雅和人物。现在让我们想象一个注定要在‘色彩’这个艺术领域有所建树的孩子；他从两种色调的碰撞或联合中，从色彩带给他的愉悦中，获取了色彩组合的无穷无尽的知识。在这两种情形下，自然和天性扮演的都只是催化剂的角色。

“线条和色彩都可发人深思，引人幻想；两者传递出的愉悦感是不同的，但完全平等，并且绝对独立于画作的主题之外。

“德拉克洛瓦的一幅画作，如果离得太远，你也许无法看到轮廓的优点，抑或主题或多或少的戏剧化特点，然而却依然能感受到一种神性的愉悦。它就像一种神奇的氛围向你靠近，笼罩着你。这种感觉，幽暗而令人愉快，明亮但又平静，永驻于你的记忆中，这是一位真正娴熟的色彩画家的身份证明。这种最初的愉悦感在你凑近画作分析主题时不会有所增减，它的源头在别处，不存在于任何明确的思想中。

“我可以把这例子反过来说。一个画得很好的人物，能让你感受到一种与主题完全无关的愉悦。不管是性感的还是令人恐惧的，这个人物的魅力完全来自于它构筑的空间模式。一个被活活剥皮的殉难者的四肢，一个昏倒的仙女的身体，如果画得巧妙，会让人感受到一种愉悦，在其中画作主题是无足轻重的；如果您对此并不认同，我就不得不认为您是一个施刑者或者好色之徒了。

“但是，唉！老是重复这些无用的真理有什么好处呢？”

也许，先生，比起以上所有的高谈阔论，您的读者会更愿意知道这位伟大画家的个性和生活方式上的细节，而我也正迫不及待要说呢。

四

我前面提及的欧仁·德拉克洛瓦的双重天性，在他的文字中尤其能看得清楚。正如您所知，先生，许多人都对他笔下的睿智观点以及温和风格感到吃惊，这在一些人看来是遗憾的，在其他人看来则是值得称许的。《美的变奏曲》，对普桑[75]、普吕东[76]和夏雷的研究，以及发表在《艺术家》（当时还是利库先生在经营）或是《两世界评论》上的文章，都证实了伟大艺术家们的这种双重天性。这种双重性推动着他们像批评家一样津津有味地去赞扬和分析他们作为创造者最为需要、与他们所大量具有的素质相反的那些素质。如果欧仁·德拉克洛瓦大加颂扬自己身上为我们所欣赏的素质，比如他的激情、一挥而就的果决、构图的狂放不羁、用色的巧妙，那倒是让人感到惊讶了。为什么要去寻找自己拥有的丰富到过剩的东西呢？如何能不赞美那些对我们来讲罕见和难得的事物呢？编辑先生，不管是画家还是作家，创造性天才一旦把才能用在批评上时，我们总会看到同样的现象。在古典和浪漫这两大派别对峙的时代，头脑简单的人听到欧仁·德拉克洛瓦盛赞拉辛、拉·封丹[77]和布瓦洛[78]，会大为惊讶。我认识一位诗人，他天性喜欢暴风骤雨，却为马莱伯[79]的一行诗而狂喜不已，这行诗对称整齐，如音乐般方正牢固。这位伟大画家的文章在表达和主旨上睿智、合理、清晰明确，但如果我们认为这是轻易写就的，如他的画笔一样游刃有余，那就错了。他越是有把握把他之所想写在画布上，就越担心无法把思想画在纸上。他总爱说：“笔不是我的工具；我感觉我想的是对的，但是一到被迫要用井然有序的话将它表述出来时，我就被绊住了。你相信吗，被迫写一页文字，会让我偏头疼。”这种源于缺乏练习的笨拙，解释了这位在其他方面都很杰出的天才，笔下为什么会出现一些陈旧、乏味、平庸，甚至第一帝国时期[80]的表达的原因。

德拉克洛瓦的风格最显著的标志是简洁和一种不事张扬的艺术激情，这种激情通常在一个人把全部的精神力量集中到一点上时产生。“英雄就是那种矢志不移之人。”爱默生[81]如是说。这位大西洋彼岸的道德家，虽然顶着无聊的波士顿学派领导者的称号，身上却有塞内加[82]的影子，这足以成为驱策思考的力量。“英雄就是那种矢志不移之人。”——这句格言被爱默生这位美国“超验主义”[83]的倡导者用于生活准则和商业领域——应该也同样可以用于诗歌和艺术领域。我们也不妨这样说：“文学的英雄，即真正的作家，就是那种矢志不移之人。”因此，先生，当您发现德拉克洛瓦对行文简洁而专注的作家颇有好感时，也不会感觉惊讶了吧。这些作家的文章不为风格雕饰所牵绊，而似乎是在模仿思维的快速流动，他们笔下的句子有一种果决的姿态，如孟德斯鸠[84]。我可以就这种富有成果和诗性的简洁给您一个例子。相信您跟我一样，都读了保罗·德·圣维克托最近在《新闻报》上发表的那篇极有趣、极好的文章，研究了阿波罗画廊的天花板壁画。文章一一谈到关于洪水的不同观念，洪水的传说怎样被解读，组成这幅宏伟作品的场景和动作的内在意义；以这种迷人的方式对画作本身也进行了细致描述，既诙谐幽默，又妙趣横生，作者给我们举了很多例子。但是它在我们的记忆中留下的只是一个形体不明的影子，就像一张放大的相片上苍白的光。将这篇冗长的文章与下面几行文字比较，在我看来后者更加充满活力，更有助于在脑海中营造画面，即使这个画面并不真实存在。我只是将德拉克洛瓦先生在邀请朋友观看这幅画时所说的话放在这里：

阿波罗，巨蟒皮同的征服者

阿波罗跨上他的战车，已经射出了几支箭；妹妹戴安娜在他身后，正高喊着把自己的箭筒递给他。那条可怕的巨蟒，被这位光明与青春之神射出的箭所伤，伤口滴着血，正在垂死挣扎。它暴怒而绝望地扭动着身体，笼罩在一片火红的光中。大洪水已经开始消退，把人和动物的尸体留在山顶或席卷而去。大地被面目可憎的怪物、泥土的不洁产物所占据，神见此场景大怒。他们像阿波罗一样武装起来：密涅瓦和默丘利跳上前来诛灭怪物，那永恒的智慧会使这个孤寂的宇宙重新住满人类；大力神赫丘利用他的大棒打杀怪物；火神乌尔肯正在赶走黑夜和恶臭的水汽；而北风之神波瑞阿斯和西风之神仄费罗斯用他们的气息吹干洪水，驱散乌云；山林水泽仙女找到了她们的苇床和瓮，依然脏兮兮的，沾着泥和残渣；

几个比较害羞的神远远地看着这场神与自然之间的较量；同时，胜利女神维克托里亚从最高的天上飘然而下，为胜利者阿波罗加冕；众神的使者伊里丝在柔和的空气中展开了她的面纱，象征着光明战胜了黑暗和泛滥的洪水。

我知道读者将需要发挥想象力，可以说，将被迫与这段说明文字的作者合作。但是，先生，您真的认为，对这位画家的仰慕使我成了一个充满幻想的人？如果说我从上面的文字中看到了一种由高尚阅读获得的贵族态度的痕迹，一种精准思维的痕迹，它使得平头百姓、士兵、冒险家，甚至是宫廷侍从在不经意间写出了极好的书，就连我们这些专业作家都忍不住要拍手称赞的书，您真的认为我这样说是绝对错了吗？

五

欧仁·德拉克洛瓦是一种怀疑主义、谦恭有礼、浪荡作风、激情四射、狡猾多端和专制主义的奇怪混合，而且还是一种永远伴随着天才的特殊的宽厚和克制的温柔的奇异混合。他的父亲是我们小时候认识的最后一批绅士之一，他们属于一个强有力的群体；其中一些是让·雅克·卢梭主张的热忱倡导者，另外一些则是伏尔泰的忠实信徒，但是所有人都带着同样的决心参与到法国大革命中；他们中的幸存者，雅各宾党人或左翼激进派人士，都怀着一种完全的真诚（记得这一点很重要）支持拿破仑·波拿巴[85]的政策。

欧仁·德拉克洛瓦身上一直保留着这种宗教背景的痕迹。然而，他和司汤达一样，极其恐惧被卷入革命浪潮。尽管他是个怀疑论者，主张贵族统治，但他只是通过强制的幻想才认识了激情和超自然主义。他憎恨群体，认为他们不过是些造反派，他的一些作品在1848年受到群体的暴力对待[86]，这更不能让他转向我们这个时代的政治感伤主义。在他的态度、举止和观点中，有某种东西让我们想到维克多·雅克蒙[87]。我知道这种比较并不讨人喜欢，因此我这么说是有保留的。在雅克蒙身上，有一种中产阶级的机智，爱寻衅吵架；还有一种既能愚弄梵天[88]的教士，也能欺骗基督教牧师的幽默滑稽。德拉克洛瓦，在天才与生俱来的良好品味的指引下，永远不会堕落到使用这种不入流的诡计。因此，我在这里对两者的比较只是指他们共同具有的谨慎和中庸。同样的，18世纪赋予他性情上的遗传标志，似乎是来自一个既非乌托邦也非狂人的阶层，即温和的怀疑论者、胜利者和幸存者的阶层，一般来说，比之卢梭，他们更多地来自伏尔泰。因此，初看起来，欧仁·德拉克洛瓦表面只是一个“有教养”的人（这里是从这个词最好的含义上说），一个不存偏见的完美绅士。只有通过更经常的往来，人们才能透过表面，看清他灵魂更深的栖息处。另外一个跟他在仪态举止上真正可以相提并论的人，是梅里美先生[89]。他有着同样表面的冷淡，不容易激动；同样冰冷的外表下隐藏着温和的敏感和对善与美的似火热情；在同样自我主义的伪装下是对朋友和信仰的热爱和虔诚。

欧仁·德拉克洛瓦的身上有隐士的东西；这是他天性中最宝贵的一面，这一面完全致力于把他的梦想以绘画的形式表现出来，以及对艺术的崇拜。在他身上有社交人士的东西；这一部分注定要隐藏隐士的部分，并缓和它可能引起的任何不满。我相信，他人生最大的一项努力便是隐藏心底涌起的愤怒，以及让自己看起来不像个天才。他的控制欲，不仅完全合理，而且是不可避免的，几乎消失在无数的优雅之下，可以说是火山口艺术地隐藏在花束之下。

他与司汤达的另一个相似之处，就是喜欢简单的原则、简短的箴言以及良好的生活作风。就像所有热情、敏感的人一样，因为性情使他们远离方法，因此他们对方法的喜爱也更加强烈，德拉克洛瓦喜欢编造这类小小的实用道德的信条，没有生活目标的蠢人和懒汉可能会轻蔑地将之归于德·拉帕利斯先生[90]，但是天才不会鄙视这些信条，因为天才是朴素的；对于在天赋驱使下进入永恒战斗的人，明智、有力、简单和实际的箴言是他的胸甲和护盾。

正是这同样坚定不移和倨傲的智慧，形成了德拉克洛瓦先生在政治问题上的见解，这还用我说吗？他认为，一切都没有改变，尽管一切看似在变，在各民族历史上风起云涌的时期，总是会有相似的现象出现。事实上，他在这类问题上的看法与一位历史学家很接近，特别是从他那冷漠扫兴的顺从方面来看更为相近。我自己对这位历史学家非常尊重；而先生，您对这些论点如此熟悉，即使遭到反驳也依然可以欣赏对方的才能，一定也不止一次对他表示敬佩。我所说的这个人是费拉里先生[91]，《论以国家利益为名的理由》一书的思想缜密、博学多才的作者。毫无疑问，如果有谁在德拉克洛瓦先生面前，表露出对乌托邦的幼稚的狂热，很快会听到他的冷笑，夹杂着讽刺的同情；如果有谁冒冒失失地在他面前抛出现代的伟大空想、尚不明确的完善和进步这个大气球，他肯定会问：“你的菲迪亚斯[92]在哪儿？你的拉斐尔在哪儿？”

不过请相信，德拉克洛瓦先生的明智绝对无损他优雅的举止。这种强烈的怀疑态度，这种对谎言的拒绝，给他的谈话增添了一种拜伦式的味道，充满了诗意和色彩。他也从自身——即从他的天才，和对自身天才的认识中——而非长久的社交经验中获得了一种自信，一种完美的风度，以及一种彬彬有礼，它就像一面棱镜，从最热诚的友好到最无可指摘的拒绝中，都折射出这种彬彬有礼。他可以用20多种方式说“我亲爱的先生”，一个经过训练的耳朵能够从中听出有丰富差异的情感。我必须补充一下，因为这在我看来是另一个值得称赞的理由，欧仁·德拉克洛瓦，尽管是一个天才，或者说因为他是一个完全的天才，所以身上有一种浪荡子的气质。他自己也承认，自己在年轻时曾纵情享乐，沉溺在浪荡作风的各种物质浮华中，他自我解嘲（但也带着某种虚荣）地说到，在朋友伯宁顿的帮助下，他曾经努力在时尚年轻人中灌输对英式鞋类和衣服的品位。这个细节，我想您不会觉得是多余的话，因为当我们在描述某个人的性情时，所有记忆都不是多余的。

我前面已经说过，对于敏锐的观察者，给他们留下深刻印象的是德拉克洛瓦灵魂中天然的部分，尽管我们精致的生活方式给灵魂罩上了一层面纱，模糊了它的真面目。德拉克洛瓦精力充沛，但是这精力源于勇气和意志；因为就体质来说，他是孱弱的。当我们这位伟大的画家整个灵魂都集中在一个想法上，或者想要控制一个梦时，他的眼睛里闪射着光芒，肌肉不耐烦地抽搐着，就像一只追踪猎物的老虎。他的面部特征，他的像秘鲁人或马来人的肤色，他大而黑的眼睛，在专注时因为眨动变小了，似乎是在品咂阳光，他浓密而亮泽的头发，固执的神色，紧闭的嘴唇，因为精神总是处于专注状态，所以脸上有一种残忍的表情，总之，他整个人都传递出一种异域风度。不止一次，我站在那里看着他，脑海中出现墨西哥的古代统治者蒙特祖马的形象，他那熟练于祭礼的双手，能够在一天之内，将3000人送到金字塔形的太阳祭坛上；或者像一位出现在最盛大节日上的印度王子，在他的眼睛深处，有一种未满足的渴望和无可逃避的怀恋，某种对未知之物的回忆和惋惜的东西。请注意，德拉克洛瓦绘画作品的整体色调，与东方风景和室内装饰相协调，营造出一种与在热带地区的感受相似的印象，在一双敏锐的眼睛看来，尽管画面有很强的立体感，但大量弥漫的光线造成一种类似黄昏的整体效果。如果我们可以在绘画上谈论道德的话，他的作品的道德观与恐怖有着明显的联系；他作品中的一切无不在讲述荒凉、大屠杀和火；一切都在控诉人类永不停止和无可救药的暴行；火光和浓烟中的城市，谋杀和强奸，孩子被扔到马蹄下或被因恐惧而精神错乱的母亲杀死；整个作品，我再说一次，就像一曲为命运和无法逃避的哀痛而谱的骇人圣歌。有时，他发现自己也可以用画笔表达温柔和舒适的情感，因为他当然不缺乏温柔；但是那种无法消除的痛苦依然强烈地存在着，而那种常常与简单愉悦相伴的轻松愉快，却是缺席的。只有那么一次，我想，他试图走滑稽有趣的路线，然而，他似乎感到这于他的性情并不适合，所以再没作第二次尝试。

六

我认识一些人，他们有权利说“我蔑视那些庸人”[93]，但是其中有谁能胜利地加上一句“我远离他们”？太频繁的握手使性格堕落。如果真有人有一座铜墙铁壁的“象牙塔”，那就是欧仁·德拉克洛瓦。有谁比他更爱自己的“象牙塔”，即他的隐私？我相信他会愿意用炮弹来武装它，把它挪在森林深处或者高不可攀的岩石上。有谁比他更热爱那既是自己的庇护所也是私室的家？别人寻找私室也许是为了狂欢；他则是为了寻找灵感，他沉溺在真正的狂欢——工作之中。“生活中唯一的智慧是集中精力，唯一的罪恶是分散精力。”我们前面引述的那位美国哲学家这样说道。

德拉克洛瓦应该也能写出这句格言；不管怎样，他是在严格地执行这句格言。他太过入世，所以不能不蔑视社会；他为避免显露本色而作出的努力，自然而然地使他更愿意与我们为伍。“我们”不只是指这个行当的谦卑作家，也有其他一些或年轻或年老的人，有记者，有诗人，也有音乐家，在这些人之中他可以自由地放松，抛掉自我。

李斯特在他关于肖邦的美妙文章中，将德拉克洛瓦列为最频繁拜访这位音乐家兼诗人的人，说他喜欢沉醉在那美妙热烈的音乐中，这乐声让人想起一只盘旋在恐怖深渊之上的色彩鲜艳的鸟儿。

于是，由于我们发自内心地仰慕先生，尽管当时还很年轻，也得到许可进入那间画室。尽管外面天气恶劣，这里却洋溢着赤道的温暖。进入画室，首先感受到的是一种有节制的庄严气氛，以及老派人特有的朴素，就像我们童年时见过的大卫的那些老对手的画室，这些有着动人的英雄主义情怀的人已经逝去很久了。人们清楚地感觉到，这处私室不可能住着一个思想轻浮、反复无常的人。

这里没有生锈的盔甲，没有马来人的阔头弯刀，没有古哥特式铁制品，没有廉价装饰，没有古衣物，没有小古董摆设，没有任何显示出主人喜爱时新玩意儿和沉溺于幼稚空想的东西。在这间宽敞的画室，触目可及的装饰只有画家不知从哪儿淘来的一幅乔登斯[94]的精美肖像画、几幅习作和他自己的仿作，这里住着一个沉思的灵魂，沐浴在柔和宁静的光线下。

这几幅仿作很可能会出现在德拉克洛瓦的作品拍卖会上，我听说，拍卖会的时间定在一月份。他在模仿上采取了两种截然不同的态度。一种是自由奔放的，由忠实和不忠实组合而成，他在其中融入了大量自己的风格。这个方式诞生了一种奇怪的令人愉悦的产物，将头脑置于一种不确定的和谐状态之中。在这种矛盾的伪装中我第一次见到了那幅鲁本斯《圣徒伯努瓦的奇迹》的仿作。在另一种方式中，德拉克洛瓦成为他的模特最顺从谦卑的奴隶，他的模仿精确到了让那些未曾目睹这种奇迹的人可能不相信的程度。例如，对藏于卢浮宫的拉斐尔的两幅人头像的仿作，对人物的表情、仪表和举止的模仿完美自然，完全可以乱真。

在一顿清淡的午餐后，德拉克洛瓦就像一个卖花女或卖布商，在画板上精心打理各种颜色，他努力重新抓住被打断的思绪；但是在进入激烈的工作之前，他常常感受到一种倦怠或恐惧，抑或一种恼怒，类似于当人想起从上帝面前逃离的女祭司或者让·雅克·卢梭时感受到的恼怒，后者在写作前要花整整一小时来闲荡、整理报纸和书籍。然而，一旦艺术家进入状态，就一发不可收拾，直到身体疲劳到极点才停下。

一天，当我们谈到画家和作家永远感兴趣的问题，即工作的保健作用和生活方式问题时，他对我说：“多年以前，我还年轻，当时只有想到晚上有乐趣可寻，我才能沉下心来工作。这乐趣可以是音乐、跳舞等。现在，我已不是学校的小男生了；我可以不停地工作，而不索要任何回报。而且，”他补充道，“就乐趣来说，您知道努力工作会让人变得多么胸怀宽广和容易取悦！一个工作到酣畅淋漓之人，即使只有街上的搬运工陪他一起玩纸牌，他也会很高兴。”

这番话让我想起与农夫一起玩骰子的马基雅维利。有一个星期天，我在卢浮宫看到德拉克洛瓦，身边陪着的是他的老女仆，她尽心尽力照顾他已经有30年了。德拉克洛瓦，这个高雅、讲究、博学的人，却不带丝毫自负的神态，正在向这位可敬的妇人讲解亚述雕塑的奥秘，后者则在凝神聆听着。马基雅维利的形象和多年前一次谈话的记忆立刻在我的脑海中浮现。

事实是，在他的晚年，人们称为快乐的一切东西从他的生活中彻底消失了；替代它们的是唯一的、严苛的、糟糕的快乐——工作，这在当时不仅是一种热情，简直可以称为迷恋了。

在白天的所有时间里，德拉克洛瓦要么在画室，要么在脚手架上创作巨大的装饰画，即便如此，他依然从对艺术的热爱中找到了力量，如果晚上没有将在炉边的时间用来画画，没有借着台灯在画纸上挥洒梦想、计划和生活中偶然瞥见的形象，或者有时模仿与他气质完全相悖的画家的作品，他就会感觉这一天过得不充实；因为他喜欢做笔记和画素描，不管身在何处，都会致力于此。在相当长的时间里，他习惯晚上在朋友家做客时作画。这也解释了维洛先生[95]为什么拥有这位多产画家数量可观的精彩画作。

德拉克洛瓦先生曾对我认识的一个年轻人说：“如果你还没有掌握画一个正从四楼窗户坠落的人的诀窍，那你永远别指望有大成就。”我从这个极端夸张的说法中，发现了他一生致力的工作，众所周知，那就是，快速并精确地作画，不让一个粒子在动作的强度或思想中损失掉。

正如许多人看到的那样，德拉克洛瓦喜欢谈话。但有趣的是，他对谈话持怀疑态度，似乎那是一种堕落，一种自我放纵，担心这样是对精力的浪费。当你去到他的画室，他第一句话是：“如果你同意，今天早晨我们就不谈话了，或者就谈一小会儿。”

然后，他却连续谈了三个小时，他的谈话发人深省、洞察入微但又充满了事实、回忆和逸事，简言之，是一种富有教益的谈话。

当他受到反驳而情绪激动时，会立即收回自己的话；接下来，他不会向对手发起正面进攻，因为这可能将讲台上激烈的言辞交锋演变成画室里的冲突，他会选择与对手迂回一会儿，然后带着许多令人意想不到的论据和事实进行回击。这是一个以冲突为乐的人典型的谈话风格：先礼后兵，以退为进，惯用隐蔽和突袭。

在他的画室的亲切氛围中，他的谈话会无拘无束，甚至会谈到对同时代画家的看法，而特别在这些时候，我们常常会赞叹天才的宽容，这大约源自一种特殊的天真，或者一种对享乐的随和。

他对德岗[96]抱有一种不可思议的敬意，虽然德岗今天已不太受欢迎，但无疑由于记忆的力量，他在德拉克洛瓦的心中还占据着重要地位。他对夏雷也怀着同样的敬意。有一次，他把我叫到家里大加申斥，起因是我写的一篇对这位沙文主义的宠儿不敬的文章。我向他解释，这篇文章攻击的不是早期的夏雷，而是晚期颓废派的夏雷；那时的他不是研究拿破仑退伍军人的可敬历史学家，而是酒馆里的一位才子，但我的努力却徒劳无功。最终我也没有得到他的原谅。

他也欣赏安格尔[97]的一些作品，可以肯定的是，他需要一种强大的批判能力，才能通过理性的力量欣赏自己的气质本能排斥的事物。他甚至还曾精心模仿安格尔的一些笔触细腻的铅笔画，安格尔先生敏锐而卓越的天资，在这些画里最受好评，越是受限就越能看出功力。

贺拉斯·威尔奈作品的糟糕色调没有妨碍德拉克洛瓦感受画家笔触的自然力量，正是这力量赋予了他大多数画作以生命力，他还用惊人的语言对这种汩汩而出的不倦能量进行赞颂。他对梅松尼尔[98]的仰慕有些过分。他几乎是通过强力得到了《街垒》的草图，这是梅松尼尔最好的一幅作品。梅松尼尔的天才用铅笔来表现远比油画笔来得有力。关于梅松尼尔，德拉克洛瓦常说这么一句话，像是对前途感到一种不安似的：“在我们所有人中，最可能流芳百世的到底还是他。”看到一位创作出伟大作品的画家，几乎是嫉妒一位只是擅于小幅画作的画家，不是很奇怪的吗？

唯一一位能让这位画家的贵族嘴唇蹦出粗俗形容词的是保罗·德拉罗什。对这位画家的作品，他找不出一丁点儿可以原谅的东西。他对那肮脏而糟糕的画作让他遭受的折磨记忆深刻，正如特奥菲尔·戈蒂埃[99]所说，这些画是“用墨水和鞋油”创作出来的。

但是他最愿意与之高谈阔论的人，恰是与他在才能和观点上最不相像的，与他截然相反的人，这个人的头脑虽然像他家乡的天空一样被雾霾笼罩，面目难辨，却包含着许多令人钦佩的东西。我说的这个人是保罗·什纳瓦[100]。

这位来自里昂的画家和哲学家的深奥理论，让德拉克洛瓦忍俊不禁。这位抽象的教育家认为纯绘画带来的感官快感如果不是有罪的，也是轻佻的东西。然而，不管他们彼此相距如何遥远，也许正因为这种遥远，他们喜欢聚在一起，就像用铁链锁在一起的两条船，再也分不开了。而且，因为两人都很有学问，都具有杰出的交际能力，他们可以在学术上找到共识。众所周知，这并非画家通常具备的品质。

因此，保罗·什纳瓦是德拉克洛瓦的绝佳对手。在一旁看他们唇枪舌剑，真是一种乐趣。如果一个人说出的话像一头全副披挂的大象，拖着沉重的脚步走上阵去，另一个人的话则如同一柄剑那般充满生气，锋利、灵活地前来迎战。在临终前，我们这位伟大的画家想握一握他这位友好的反驳者的手，而后者那时却远离巴黎。

七

德拉克洛瓦像米开朗基罗一样（您还记得他的一首十四行诗的结尾吧：“雕塑！神圣的雕塑，汝之艺术是吾唯一之爱！”），将绘画视为自己唯一的缪斯、情人、独一无二和源源不断的乐趣源泉，得知这一点，也许会让多情和做作的女人大吃一惊。

无疑，在年少轻狂的岁月里，他也曾热衷于追逐女人。在这个危险偶像的圣坛上，谁没有作过牺牲呢？而不正是那些对女人服务最殷勤的男人，对她们的抱怨也最多？早在很久以前，德拉克洛瓦就将女人排除在他的生活之外。如果他是一个穆斯林，大概不会将女人逐出清真寺，但因为他压根不理解女人能与安拉有怎样的对话，所以看到女人进入清真寺就足以令他感到吃惊。

在这个问题上，他的思想完全是东方的，正如在其他许多问题上一样。女人在他眼中是一件艺术品，令人愉悦，激发灵感；然而，如果我们放任她走入心灵，她就变成了一个桀骜不驯的东西，贪婪地吞噬着我们的时间和精力。

我还记得曾经在某个公共场合，我指给他看一位神情忧伤的绝色美人。他勉强认同了她的美，但带着特有的笑声跟我说：“你怎么会觉得一个女人会忧伤？”这句话无疑在暗示，在女人身上，缺乏某种能够体验忧伤情绪的本质的东西。

很不幸，这是一个极不讨人喜欢的理论。我自己也不想去宣扬这些理论，去中伤另一个时常表现出强烈美德的性别；然而不得不承认这是一个谨慎的理论。在一个充满美女陷阱的世界上，一个才子再谨慎也不为过；一个天才有权利坚持某些理论（只要没有威胁公共秩序），而这些理论若出自普通公民或普通家庭的父亲，就会使我们产生反感。

我必须补充一句，他对孩子也同样没有好感，在忧郁的人看来，这会让人们对他的缅怀笼上阴影。在他的思想中，孩子总是手指上沾着果酱（弄脏画布和画纸），不停地敲鼓（扰乱人的思想），像猴子一样具有煽动性，充满了危险的动物情绪。

“我清楚记得，”他有时会谈到，“我小时候就是个小恶魔。责任感的获得是一个很缓慢的过程；只有在经过了苦难、惩罚和理智的漫长训练之后，人才能逐渐地销蚀掉他与生俱来的恶习。”

就这样，他只是通过简单的判断，回归了天主教的教义。他认为，比之于成人，孩子更为接近原罪。

八

德拉克洛瓦似乎将他所有的情感都珍藏起来，贡献给了严肃的友谊，这些情感是阳刚的、深沉的。有一些人很容易喜欢上第一个见到的人；其他人则把这种神圣能力留给庄重的大场合。我正在津津乐道的这位名人，他可能不愿意被小事烦扰，但是在紧要关头，他会雪中送炭、一往无前、古道热肠。那些与他熟识的人，曾无数次见证过他在社会交往中表现出的忠诚不渝、谨小慎微和值得信赖，这些都是英国人的典型美德。如果说他对别人苛刻，那他对自己也没有宽容半分。

在这里，我还要提一下对欧仁·德拉克洛瓦的指责，虽然这让我感觉难过和不悦。我曾听人说他自私甚至贪财。请注意，先生，这些话总是出自无数庸人之口，攻击那些不辞劳苦的慷慨济人者，这慷慨既出于友谊，也出于关心。

德拉克洛瓦在管理钱财上很仔细，因为只有这样才让他可以不时慷慨解囊。我可以举几个这方面的例子，但是没有他和那些应该感谢他的人的允许，我也不方便这么做。

还有一点请注意，有许多年，他的画只能卖到很低的价钱，他的那些装饰画几乎吞掉了他全部的薪水。当一些穷艺术家跟他索要作品时，他的表现也证明了对金钱的蔑视。这时，就像那些个性自由而慷慨的医生，有时坚持要求付费，有时免费赠送，他会白送他的画或随便收点钱。

先生，最后，请记住，卓越之人比之其他人，尤其要留心保护自己。如果说全社会都与他为敌也不为过，我们曾不止一次验证这一点。他的礼貌被人说成冷漠；他的讽刺，不论怎样柔和，都被视为恶意；他的节俭呢，就成了吝啬。如果反过来，这个不幸的人挥霍无度，那社会非但不会对他表示同情，还会说：“活该！他这样挥霍，迟早变成穷光蛋。”

我可以肯定地说，在金钱和节俭上，德拉克洛瓦的观点与司汤达完全一致，即将伟大与谨慎统一起来。

司汤达曾说：“智者应该致力于取得必要的金钱，使自己不必依靠任何人（在司汤达的时代，这笔钱指年收入6000法郎）。而如果获得了这种保障后，还要浪费时间继续积累财富，那这个人就是个恶棍了。”

追求必要的，蔑视多余的，这就是智者与坚忍克己之人的做法。

我们的这位画家，在晚年时，最关心的一件事是后世对他的评价，以及他的作品传世的不确定性。在某个时刻，想到不朽的荣耀，他的想象力会炽烈得像着了火；在另一个时刻，他会失落地谈到画布和色彩的虚弱性。而在其他时候，他会不无嫉妒地谈到历史上的大师，他们中几乎所有人的作品都被技术高超的雕刻家选中，雕刻家用手中的针和刻刀将大师的天才表现出来；德拉克洛瓦则悲叹他还没有找到自己作品的雕刻家。与印刷作品的持久相比，绘画艺术作品的易损，也是他经常谈到的一个话题。

这个既脆弱又顽强，既敏感又大胆的人，这个在欧洲艺术年鉴上独树一帜的人，这个身体虚弱、冷淡，永远梦想在墙上涂抹自己强大构想的艺术家，在一次肺炎发作后离开了人世，而他对此已有预感。他的离开，让我们感受到一种精神的消沉和不断增长的孤独感，就像夏多布里昂和巴尔扎克的离世，而最近又是维尼[101]的离世带给我们的那种感受。在这个举国哀悼的时刻，在人类整体的活力处于低潮之时，有一片类似日食的阴影笼罩了知识界，这是对世界末日的一次暂时的模仿。

然而，我想，对他的离去感受尤为强烈的是这样一些人，他们在灵魂高贵的孤独中，只是靠着思想的联系，成功地找到了自己的圈子。至于其他公民，只有在很长时间之后，他们才会慢慢了解，自己的国家因为这位伟人的离去而蒙受的巨大损失，以及他的离世所留下的空白。即使那时还需要向他们不断讲明这一点。

我衷心地感谢您，先生，谢谢您容许我在对这位杰出天才的缅怀中畅所欲言，他生活在一个不幸的时代，这个时代既贫穷又富庶，有时过于苛刻，有时又过分宽容，而过于常见的却是不公。

论1859年的沙龙——致《法兰西评论》编辑的信

一、现代艺术家

亲爱的M先生：

很荣幸受您之邀，就沙龙写一篇评论文章，您在信中说：“要简短；不要一一列举，而是写一篇概览，类似于在展览上轻松漫步式的文字。”好，您的愿望会完全得到满足，不是因为您的提议恰好与我对这类称为“沙龙”的无趣文章的看法一致（不过我们确实观点相同），也不是因为这种作文方式要更加容易，要知道，简短总是比冗长更费力气，而仅仅是因为，尤其是在目前情况下，其他方式都行不通。当然了，如果我发觉自己迷失在原创画作的森林中，如果现代法国人的性情突然发生变化，在它被净化了的、恢复活力的状态下，开放出绚烂而芬芳的各式花朵，我下笔会更加困难，因为那样我会发出一系列无法抑制的“噢啊”之类的惊奇之声，笔下流出溢美之词和堆砌辞藻的赞赏，并产生对批评语言中新类别的需求。然而对我而言幸运的是，这些都没有发生。没有情感的突然喷发，没有未经发掘的天才出现。由这个沙龙所引起的思考是如此简单，如此老式，如此传统，毫无疑问，只需寥寥数页，我就能把这些想法表达出来。不要感到惊讶，因为画家的平庸会导致作家的陈词滥调。在任何情况下，写陈词滥调都是安全的，因为没有什么东西比它更迷人、更富有成效和更令人兴奋了（我很高兴在这一点上您和我看法一致）。

在开始前，请允许我先表达一种难以言喻的遗憾。本来我们被告知，展览上会有一些我们不熟悉的客人；因为之前的蒙田大道展览，向常看展览的巴黎人介绍了一些他们相见恨晚的魅力四射的艺术家。所以，我一早就热切盼望着能与这些艺术家再见面，其中有莱斯利，那个富有、天真和高贵的幽默作家，他是英国思想最强有力的化身之一；大小亨特，一个是固执的自然主义画家[102]，另外一个是热切而坚定的拉斐尔前派的创始人[103]；麦克利斯[104]，那位大胆的绘画大师，他笔触的冲动鲁莽也透露出足够的自信；米莱斯[105]，一位在细节描绘上一丝不苟的诗人；约翰·夏隆[106]，他融合了克劳德·洛兰[107]和华多[108]的画风，记录了在美丽的意大利公园里举行下午游园会的场景；格兰特[109]，那位雷诺兹的天然继承人；胡克[110]，他给自己梦中的威尼斯笼罩上神奇的光线；那位奇怪的帕顿爵士[111]，他的作品把人们带回亨利·富塞利[112]时代，带着属于另一个时代的耐心，他精心描绘了众神混战的动人场面；乔治·卡特莫尔[113]，一位用水彩描画历史场景的画家；还有另外一位令人讶异的艺术家，名字我忘记了，他是一位建筑家和梦想家，在纸上建起了城市，里面的桥由大象雕塑支撑着，在大象腿下，带着三个桅杆的大型纵帆船正满帆而行！墙上甚至都为这些充满想象力、创造不寻常色彩效果的朋友们，为这些怪诞的缪斯所垂青的人们预留了地方；然而，唉！因为我所不知道的原因，我想也不适合在您的报纸上发表，我的希望破灭了。就这样，那些悲剧的火焰，基恩和麦克雷迪式的手势，对家的深刻研究，反映在英国人思想诗境中的东方辉煌，苏格兰的青翠草木，迷人的凉亭，富有层次的水彩画，它使有限的画面显得像舞台布景一样宽敞，我们是看不到你们了，起码这次是看不到了。噢！你们这些想象力和灵魂的最宝贵才能的热情代表，你们是在第一次到来时受到了无礼对待吗，还是认为我们不配理解你们？

所以，亲爱的M先生，我们将不得不满足于法国现有的作品；但是相信我，没什么比高声赞美自己国家的艺术家让我更愉悦；遗憾的是，对于一个有经验的批判的头脑来说，爱国主义没有起到绝对主宰的作用，我们要承认一些丢脸的事。这次，我刚进入沙龙，便在楼梯上遇到了一位最敏锐、最受敬重的批评家，对我问的第一个问题，你应该能猜到是什么，他回答道：“沉闷，平庸，我几乎从没见过这么令人沮丧的沙龙。”他的话不能说不正确，也不能说正确。一个展出大量欧仁·德拉克洛瓦、潘基利[114]和弗洛芒丹[115]作品的展览不会是令人沮丧的；但从整体上看，我发觉他的话也有道理。确实，在每一个时代唱主角的都是平庸的，这是无可辩驳的；正如展览令人沮丧一样，这也是事实，因为平庸的支配力量比以往更强大了，已经到了碍眼的程度。放眼望去，整个展览就是许多陈词滥调的大团圆，这许多垃圾都用画笔认真地涂抹过，许多愚蠢或华而不实的失误被熟练地构建。接下来，我想到了过去的艺术家，并与今天的艺术家放在一起比较；然而，就像往常一样，在我令人气馁的思考结束后，那个可怕的、永恒的“为什么”不可避免地摆在我面前。在艺术和文学这两大领域，卑微、幼稚、缺乏好奇心和乏味的愚蠢似乎已经取代了热情、高贵和奔涌的梦想；目前我们还不能奢望任何能与波旁王朝复辟时期相提并论的精神上的百花齐放出现。请相信，我不是唯一一个为这些令人不快的思考而在精神上感到压迫的人；马上我就会证明这一点。我自问道：“在过去，艺术家应该是什么样的呢（比如勒布伦或大卫）？”勒·布伦是博学、富有想象力、深谙历史和热爱富丽堂皇的代表。大卫，那位被自己的许多忠实追随者中伤的伟人，他不也是热爱历史、热爱富丽堂皇、博学多识吗？而今天，艺术家——这个诗人曾经的兄弟——又是怎样的呢？要圆满回答这个问题，亲爱的M先生，我们一定不能太宽容。不光彩的偏袒有时也需要同样的反作用力。艺术家身上缺少美德，他们在今天以及在过去许多年，都不过是一个被惯坏的孩子。想想那些浪费在没有灵魂和教养的人身上的荣誉和金钱吧！就我而言，我当然不支持引进一种与现有艺术手段不相融的手法；然而，举个例子，我会忍不住对什纳瓦这样的艺术家感到同情，他永远是那么讨人喜欢、令人愉快，就像好书一样，即使在最乏味的题材上也是那么优雅。至少我知道我能和他谈论维吉尔和柏拉图（就算他成为艺术学生的笑料我又怎么会介意？）。普雷奥特[116]有一种令人愉快的天赋，他在与生俱来的品位的引领下找到美，就像一头猛兽扑到它的天然猎物身上一样。奥诺雷·杜米埃被赋予了敏锐的辨识力，这让他的整个谈话都熠熠生辉。里卡尔[117]，虽然他的谈话令人炫目，有时会不连贯，但时时能让人感觉到他知识丰富，曾进行过许多对比性研究。我想，我不必再提欧仁·德拉克洛瓦的谈话了，那是充实的哲学内容、巧智和燃烧的热情的绝妙结合。除他们之外，我想不到任何够得上与哲学家或诗人对话的人了。除了他们，你能找到的几乎都是惯坏的孩子。请告诉我，我恳求您，在哪一个客厅、哪一个酒馆，在怎样的社交或私下聚会上，您从一个被惯坏的孩子口中听到过任何诙谐话，任何深刻、智慧、意味深长的言语，任何发人深省、引人幻想的言语，简言之，任何一句值得注意的话！如果这样一句话在交谈中出现，它也许不是出自一个政客或者哲学家之口，但说出这话的人一定从事着某个不寻常的职业，比如猎人、水手、修椅子的，但不会是一个艺术家——那个被惯坏的孩子，永远不会！

这个被惯坏的孩子从前辈那里继承了一种在那个时代是合理的特权。人们对大卫、圭林、吉洛德[118]、格罗[119]、德拉克洛瓦、波宁顿[120]的热情，他今天忝承余荫；当优秀的诗人和勤奋的历史学家辛苦谋生之时，愚蠢的金融家在花大价钱买这些被惯坏的孩子创作的不知所谓的作品。请不要误会，如果值得敬重的人获得这种恩惠，我是不会发牢骚的。如果是一位到达艺术巅峰的歌唱家或舞蹈家，他每天努力工作，承担风险，最后成为富翁，我是不会嫉妒的。否则，那我恐怕会步去世的吉哈丹的后尘，制造骗人的记忆，他曾谴责泰奥菲尔·戈蒂耶[121]给自己想象力的标价比专区区长的薪水还要高。如果你还记得，在一个倒霉的日子，他用拉丁语对吓坏的众人说道：畜生说话了！不，我不会那么不讲理；当德拉克洛瓦的一幅佳作标价1000法郎都无人问津，而梅松尼尔的一幅无足轻重的小画却能卖到10倍甚至20倍的价钱时，我们应该提高嗓门谴责今天人们的愚蠢。但是那些快乐的日子结束了；今天的我们已经愈加堕落，梅松尼尔先生尽管有其优点，但不幸的是，他首创了篇幅较小的画，并使之成为流行品味，不过跟今天那些华而不实的小画的创作者比起来，他是真正的大师。

想象力变得不可信，高贵受到蔑视，爱（不，这个词太美了）——一味追求技巧，这些，在我看来，是艺术家水准下降的主要原因。想象力越丰富，对技巧的掌握相应地一定要越娴熟，如果后者要在冒险征途上与前者步伐一致，就要成功克服想象力所热切寻找的困难。画家的技巧越娴熟，就越不该炫耀技巧，只有这样，他的想象力才能得以凸显，并熠熠生辉。智慧如是说，并补充道，空有技巧的人是笨蛋，而富有想象力却缺乏技巧的人是疯子。这些道理看似简单，但今天的艺术家却似乎并不懂。一个看门人的女儿自言自语道：“我要上音乐学校，首次登台演出要在国家大剧院[122]，我要演高乃依[123]剧作中的人物，像以前曾经扮演这些角色的人那样获得肯定。”她说到做到。她的嗓音无比单调，本人也是极度乏味和无知，但她却成功做到了一件十分容易的事，即靠着自己的耐性，成为了国家大剧院的正式演员。而那个被惯坏的孩子——现代画家——也自言自语道：“他们所谓的想象力是什么？既危险又令人厌倦。对历史的研究和思考又是什么？不过是浪费时间而已。我要走古典路线，不是伯汀[124]那种（因为古典改变它的地点和名字），而是像……康斯坦·特罗容[125]那样的。”他说到做到。他挥毫作画，缚住自己的灵魂，直到自己的风格和流行画家一样。就这样，他凭借自己的愚蠢和技巧，得到了公众的肯定和金钱。他靠模仿别人成名，别人又模仿他，这样，每个人都在做着成名的美梦，越来越紧地缚住自己的灵魂，尤其是什么书也不读了，甚至连烹饪书都不碰了，这至少可以让他得到一个即使不太多金也更为光明的前途。一旦他掌握了调味、盛盘、浇糖浆、调肉汁、炖（我说的是绘画）等技巧，这个被惯坏的孩子开始装腔作势，用比以往更笃定的口吻重复道，其他一切都是没有必要的。

曾经有个德国农夫去见一位画家，下面是他对画家所说的话：“先生，我想让您为我画这样一幅肖像。在我家农场的大门口，我坐在一张父亲传给我的宽扶手椅上，妻子拿着她的女红在我身边，女儿们在近旁忙着准备晚餐。画面左边是一条宽敞的道路，我的儿子正从那里走来，他们干完农活正回家来，牛已经牵回了牛圈；我其他几个儿子正同我的孙子们一起，把装满干草的农场大车遮盖起来。另外，请别忘记画上我烟管里冒出来的被夕阳染上红色的烟圈。我还想让看这幅画的人听到从附近教堂的钟楼传来的祈祷钟声，那里是我家祖祖辈辈结婚的地方。还有很重要的一点，你要画出我在一天的这一刻，看着我的家人和我的财富所感受到的满足，而又一天劳作的结束更增加了这种满足感。”

请为这位农夫大声喝彩！他自己可能意识不到，但他理解了绘画。对自己职业的热爱提升了他的想象力。在我们的流行画家中，有谁能画出这样一幅画来？又有谁的想象力能跟这位农夫媲美？

二、现代大众与摄影

亲爱的M先生：

如果要博你一笑，那真是易如反掌，只要随便翻阅一下目录，把其中博眼球的可笑题目和主题拉一个清单出来即可。这是典型的法国人的态度。对于没有绘画天分的人来说，通过那些与艺术不搭边的手段让观众瞠目，是很好的手段。有时，一些极富天分的人染上这种陋习，他们用一种近乎邪恶的组合羞辱艺术，而这种人总是出现在法国。我可以向你一一展示那些戏剧化的作品题目，就像歌舞杂耍表演游行队伍一样，在你眼前一一掠过，其中有充满感情色彩的题目，只差一个感叹号了；有双关语的题目；有深沉哲思的题目；还有一些误导人或者陷阱题目，如《布鲁图：卑鄙的恺撒》。

“噢，你们这个堕落和没有信仰的民族，”我们的主说，“我还要跟你们在一起多久，我还要继续受苦受难多久？”这个民族，不管是艺术家还是普通大众，对绘画如此缺乏信仰，因此永远尝试伪装，外面包上糖衣药丸，就像是某种难吃的药品——这是什么糖啊！是啊，上帝！请让我选出两张画作的题目，顺便说一句，这两幅画我还没见过：《爱与炖兔肉》！你的好奇心一下子就被勾了起来，不是吗？我也在努力将这两个概念联系起来，爱与一只被炖的剥皮兔子。你不能期望我来假设，画家的想象力超凡，在一只家畜的尸体上，加上一个箭袋、一对翅膀和一个眼罩；那样的话，它的寓意真的会晦涩了。我更倾向于相信这个题目是生搬硬套来的，循着《厌世与忏悔》的格式。所以真正的题目应该是“一对爱人吃炖兔肉”。这样问题又来了：他们是年轻的还是年老的，是一个工人和他的女朋友，还是一个老兵和他的情妇坐在一个覆满灰尘的棚架下？只有那幅画能告诉我了。我们还有《君主制、天主教徒与士兵》！这幅画属于那种夸张的骑士类型，《耶路撒冷的巴黎路线》的类型（查理大帝，我向你致歉！最高贵的事物能成为漫画的手段，一位帝国领导的话语会成为涂鸦者的讽刺画）。这幅画上一定有一个人同时在做三件事：战斗、参加圣餐仪式、参加路易十四的“起床前仪式”[126]。又或者画的是一个有百合花和宗教图案纹身的军人？然而胡乱猜想有什么好处呢？一个简单的事实是，这类题目只是一些令人反感和枯燥乏味的手段，目的是博人眼球。而尤为可叹的是，那幅画可能是一幅好画，不管它的题目听起来有多奇怪。这也适用于《爱与炖兔肉》那幅画。我还注意到一组精美的雕刻，但很可惜没有记下它的编号；当我想要查找这组雕刻的主题时，我仔细翻阅了目录四遍，却徒劳无功。最后还是您善意地告诉我，这组雕刻名为《永远与曾经》。看到一个天才居然取了这样一个字谜似的题目，我真的感觉难过。

请您一定原谅我以廉价报纸的方式来取乐。但是，不管这件事在您看来多么不值一提，仔细探究之下，您就会发现一种可悲的症状。请允许我用一种自相矛盾的方式来总结我的观点，让我问问您，或者那些比我更熟知艺术历史的朋友们，为愚人的品位和为智者的品位是否从来都是存在的，诸如“供出租的公寓”这样过分精练的观点是否在某个时代都有，并像今天一样引起同样程度的热情，委罗内塞和巴萨诺[127]的威尼斯是否也曾受过这种字谜的影响，朱利·罗曼诺[128]、米开朗基罗和班迪内利[129]是否都曾为类似的怪物而愕然；简单说，我就是想知道比亚德先生[130]是否像上帝一样永恒存在，并无处不在。我不相信，我把这些恐怖事物看作一种赋予法国人的恩惠的特殊形式。它们的艺术家确实赋予了它们这种品味，而它们确实也让艺术家满足了这一需要，因为如果艺术家愚弄了大众，那么大众也会以其人之道还治其人之身。他们形成环环相扣的两个条件，相互施加同等的影响。与此相应，让我们看看，我们正在“进步”的道路上以怎样的速度行进（这里所说的进步指的是对事物渐进的控制），也许仅凭耐心就能获得的平凡技能每天在以怎样的速度扩散。

在这个国家，天生的画家，就像天生的诗人一样，几乎是个怪物。我们对“真”的品味（这一品味如果限制在它正当的目的是如此高贵），压迫并扼杀了对“美”的品味。当只有该寻找美时——比如在一幅美丽的画上，任何人都能很容易猜到我想到的那种——我们的同胞却只寻找真。他们没有艺术品位，他们的品位不是与生俱来的，他们可能是哲学家，或者伦理学家、工程师、启发性逸事的爱好者等等，但一定不是天生有艺术鉴赏力的。他们会渐进地、分解式地去感受，或者不如说评判。其他一些更幸运的人，他们感受事物更快，能以一种综合的方式来感受。

我刚才提到一些艺术家，他们的目的就是要使观众瞠目结舌。想令人震惊或让自己感受震惊，这一欲望是完全合理的。“感到震惊是一种幸福”，而且“有梦想是一种幸福”。如果你坚持让我给你一个艺术家或艺术爱好者的头衔，那全部的问题就是，你打算通过何种手段来创造或感受这种震惊？因为美总是包含着使人震惊的成分，认为令人惊叹的总是美的，这种想法是荒唐的。现在的法国人，就像一些卑劣矮小的灵魂一样，尤其无法感受到梦想或者惊讶带来的快乐，而他们却想通过一些与艺术无关的手段来获得震惊带来的刺激，他们恭顺的艺术家向大众品位屈膝了；他们用一些小伎俩，目的就是吸引眼球，让人们惊讶，使人们目瞪口呆，因为他们知道，人们无法从真正的艺术的自然形式中获得陶醉。

在这个可悲的时代，一个新的工业形式发展起来，它很大程度地让愚人树立了自信，并毁掉了法国人头脑中残存的一点神圣痕迹。自然地，崇拜偶像的大众呼唤出现一个货真价实的理想，与自己的特性保持一致。在绘画和雕塑艺术领域，今天老于世故之人的信条，特别是在法国（我相信没人敢发表相反的说法），是这样说的：“我信仰自然，并且只信仰自然。”（对此我们有充足的理由。）“我相信艺术是，而且只能是，对自然的精确复制。”（如果有一些胆怯和持异议的人提出反例，那举出的一定是本身就令人讨厌的物件，比如便壶，或者骷髅）“如果一个工业程序能提供给我们一种与自然一模一样的产品，那将是绝对的艺术。”报复心重的上帝听到这些人的祈祷后，便派来他的弥赛亚——达盖尔[131]。然后，这些人说道：“既然摄影能绝对复制自然（他们居然相信，可怜的狂人！），那么艺术就是摄影。”从那一刻起，我们可厌的社会便像纳喀索斯一样，趋之若鹜地从相机的金属盘上看那些不值一提的影像了。愚蠢和狂热攫住了这些新时代的太阳崇拜者，一批令人讨厌的人出现了。人们集中起一群男男女女，把他们像狂欢节上的屠夫和洗衣女那样装扮起来，劝这些“主人公们”在摄像程序要求的时间内“保持”他们即兴做出的鬼脸，通过这种手段，就真的认为他们能代表古代历史上那些悲惨或者迷人的场景了。某个民主的作家一定能从中看到一种散播对历史的憎恶以及在大众中传播绘画的廉价手段，而这是一种双重亵渎，同时侮辱了绘画的神圣艺术以及演员的高端艺术。而就在不久前，几千双贪婪的眼睛似乎胶在立体镜的窥视孔上，好像它们是无限的天窗。对猥亵的热爱在人们心里疯狂地生长，就像自恋一样，它不会放过这样一个获得自我满足的好机会。请不要说，只有从学校回到家的孩子才会从这种愚蠢的举动中获得愉悦，它是整个社会的愤怒。我曾经听到一位智慧的女士跟她的朋友谈话，她是上流社会的女士，跟我属于不同的社会阶层。当时她的朋友试图藏起这样几张照片，不让她看到，而她说道：“给我看吧，没什么能让我惊讶的。”这是她亲口说的，我发誓，我是亲耳听到的，但是谁会相信我呢？大仲马说：“你能看到，她们都是高贵的女士。”“还有更加高贵的呢！”卡佐特[132]附和道。

失败的艺术家要么是天分不够，要么是太懒惰完不成学业，而摄影行业成了他们的庇护所，这种席卷全球的狂热不仅有了盲目和愚蠢的气质，而且有了某种复仇的意味。我不相信，或者至少我不能让自己相信，任何这种愚蠢的其中总有恶毒的坏人和骗局的阴谋，竟能够获得完全的胜利；但是我确信摄影的发展，就像所有纯物质的进步一样，大大穷尽了法国人的艺术天分，这天分本身是罕有的。现代的愚昧可以纵声大笑，它圆滚滚的肚子里发出响声，将近代哲学塞到它贪婪食道的所有消化不了的诡辩法吐将出来；当工业闯入艺术领域时，它便成为后者的死敌，这是一个简单的常识；在随之而来的功能混乱中，两者都不能很好地得到实现。诗歌与进步是两个雄心勃勃的人，对彼此有本能的仇恨，两虎相遇，必有一伤。如果摄影在一些艺术行为上被允许代表艺术，那么离它取代或完全毁灭艺术的日子也不远了，大众的愚蠢是它天然的盟友，对此功不可没。所以，摄影如回归到它真正的责任上，即作为艺术和科学的侍女，但一定是很谦恭的侍女，就像印刷和速记那样，既不能创造文学也不会对文学形成补充。让摄影快些充实旅行者的相册吧，他的记忆缺失的，让摄影来精确再现给他的眼睛；让它装饰自然学家的图书馆，放大显微镜下的昆虫，甚至增强天文学家的假设：简单来说，让它成为任何因为专业原因需要绝对的形态精确性的人的秘书和记录员。现在一切还好。让它挽救那些摇摇欲坠的废墟，使之不至于默默无闻地消失，还有书、雕塑、手稿、时间的猎物，所有这些珍贵的东西注定要消失，然而恳求在我们记忆的卷宗里保有一席之地；在所有这些事物上，摄影都应该得到我们的感谢和掌声。但是如果一旦它被允许侵犯无形和想象的领域，侵犯任何只是因为人们的灵魂而获得价值的事物，我们就该倒霉了！

我知道人们会说：“你刚刚描述的是傻瓜的疾病。任何当得起艺术家头衔的人，任何真正的艺术爱好者，怎么会将艺术和工业混淆？”这个我知道，但是让我来问问，他们是否相信善与恶是会传染的，相信个人会感受到社会压力，相信个人不自觉、不可避免地会屈从于社会。艺术家影响大众，而大众反作用于艺术家，这是一个不容辩驳、无法抗拒的法则；而且，这些事实，这些证人，很容易研究；我们可以估量这整个灾难的程度。随着一天天过去，艺术日益失落在自尊中，在永恒的现实面前屈服，画家越来越倾向于画那些他眼睛看到而非梦中的事物。但做梦是一种幸福啊，曾经，表达自己梦中所见是一种荣耀，但是现在，人们还能相信画家依然有那种快乐吗？

一个诚实的旁观者，他会认为摄影的入侵以及今天疯狂的工业与这一可悲后果全无关系吗？当一个人的眼睛习惯于接受有形科学的结果作为美的产品时，在一段时间后，他评判和感受那些最虚无缥缈和无形事物的能力会显著削弱，这难道不是合乎逻辑的推断吗？

The Painter of Modern Life

I. Beauty, Fashion and Happiness

In all social circles, and even in art circles, there are people who go to the Louvre, walk quickly past a large number of most interesting though secondary pictures, without throwing them so much as a look, and plant themselves, as though in a trance, in front of a Titian or a Raphael, one of those which the engraver's art has particularly popularized; then they go out satisfied, as often as not saying to themselves: 'I know my gallery thoroughly.' There are also people who, having once read Bossuet and Racine, think they have got the history of literature at their fingertips.

Happily from time to time knights errant step into the lists - critics, art collectors, lovers of the arts, curious-minded idlers - who assert that neither Raphael nor Racine has every secret, that minor poets have something to be said for them, substantial and delightful things to their credit, and finally that, however much we may like general beauty, which is expressed by the classical poets and artists, we nonetheless make a mistake to neglect particular beauty, the beauty of circumstance, the description of manners.

I am bound to admit that, for several years now, society has shown some improvement. The value that today's collectors attach to the delightful engraved and coloured trifles of the last century shows that a reaction has begun in the direction needed by the public; Debucourt, the Saint-Aubins and many others have achieved mention in the dictionary of artists worthy of study. But these represent the past, whereas my purpose at this moment is to discuss the painting of our contemporary social scene. The past is interesting, not only because of the beauty that the artists for whom it was the present were able to extract from it, but also as past, for its historical value. The same applies to the present. The pleasure we derive from the representation of the present is due, not only to the beauty it can be clothed in, but also to its essential quality of being the present.

I have here in front of me a series of fashion plates, the earliest dating from the Revolution, the most recent from the Consulate or thereabouts. These costumes, which many thoughtless people, the sort of people who are grave without true gravity, find highly amusing, have a double kind of charm, artistic and historical. They are very often beautiful and wittily drawn, but what to me is at least as important, and what I am glad to find in all or nearly all of them, is the moral attitude and the aesthetic value of the time. The idea of beauty that man creates for himself affects his whole attire, ruffles or stiffens his coat, gives curves or straight lines to his gestures and even, in process of time, subtly penetrates the very features of his face. Man comes in the end to look like his ideal image of himself. These engravings can be translated into beauty or ugliness: in ugliness they become caricatures; in beauty, antique statues.

The women who wore these dresses looked more or less like one or the other, according to the degree of poetry or vulgarity evident in their faces. The living substance gave suppleness to what appears too stiff to us. The viewer's imagination can even today see a marching man in this tunic or the shrug of a woman's shoulder beneath that shawl. One of these days perhaps some theatre or other will put on a play where we shall see a revival of the fashions in which our fathers thought themselves just as captivating as we ourselves think we are, in our modest garments (which also have their attractiveness, to be sure, but rather of a moral and spiritual kind); and, if they are worn and given life to by intelligent actors and actresses, we shall be surprised at our having laughed at them so thoughtlessly. The past, whilst retaining its ghostly piquancy, will recapture the light and movement of life, and become present.

If an impartially minded man were to look through the whole range of French fashions, one after the other, from the origins of France to the present day, he would find nothing to shock or even to surprise him. He would find the transition as fully prepared as in the scale of the animal kingdom. No gaps, hence no surprises. And if to the illustration representing each age he were to add the philosophic thought which that age was mainly preoccupied with or worried by, a thought which the illustration inevitably reflects, he would see what a deep harmony informs all the branches of history, and that, even in the centuries which appear to us the most outrageous and the most confused, the immortal appetite for beauty has always found satisfaction.

Here we have indeed a golden opportunity to establish a rational and historical theory of beauty, in contrast to the theory of a unique and absolute beauty, and to show that beauty is always and inevitably compounded of two elements, although the impression it conveys is one; for the difficulty we may experience in distinguishing the variable elements that go to make beauty's unity of impression does not in any way invalidate the need of variety in its composition. Beauty is made up, on the one hand, of an element that is eternal and invariable, though to determine how much of it there is is extremely difficult, and, on the other, of a relative circumstantial element, which we may like to call, successively or at one and the same time, contemporaneity, fashion, morality, passion. Without this second element, which is like the amusing, teasing, appetite-whetting coating of the divine cake, the first element would be indigestible, tasteless, unadapted and inappropriate to human nature. I challenge anyone to find any sample whatsoever of beauty that does not contain these two elements.

Let me take as an example the two extreme stages of history. In hieratic art duality is evident at the first glance; the eternal element of beauty reveals itself only by permission and under the control of the religion the artist belongs to. In the most frivolous work of a sophisticated artist, belonging to one of those ages we vaingloriously call civilized, the duality is equally apparent; the eternal part of beauty will be both veiled and expressed, if not through fashion, then at least through the individual temperament of the artist. The duality of art is an inevitable consequence of the duality of man. If you like it that way, you may identify the eternally subsisting portion as the soul of art, and the variable element as its body. That is why Stendhal, that impertinent, teasing, even repugnant mind (whose impertinences are, nevertheless, usefully thought-provoking), came close to the truth, much closer than many other people, when he said: 'The beautiful is neither more nor less than the promise of happiness.' No doubt this definition oversteps the mark; it subordinates beauty much too much to the infinitely variable ideal of happiness; it divests beauty too lightly of its aristocratic character; but it has the great merit of getting away from the mistake of the academicians.

More than once before I have explained these things; these few lines are explanation enough for those who enjoy these pastimes of abstract thought; but I am well aware that French readers for the most part take little pleasure in them, and I am myself keen to enter into the positive and solid part of my subject.

II. Manners and Modes

For sketches of manners, for the portrayal of bourgeois life and the fashion scene, the quickest and the cheapest technical means will evidently be the best. The more beauty the artist puts into it, the more valuable will the work be; but there is in the trivial things of life, in the daily changing of external things, a speed of movement that imposes upon the artist an equal speed of execution. The multi-coloured engravings of the eighteenth century are again enjoying the favour of current fashion, as I was saying just now; pastel, etching, aquatint have provided their successive quotas to this vast dictionary of modern life in libraries, in art collectors' portfolios and in the humblest shop windows. As soon as lithography was invented, it was quickly seen to be very suitable for this enormous task, so frivolous in appearance. We possess veritable national records in this class. The works of Gavarni and Daumier have been accurately described as complements to the Comédie humaine. Balzac himself, I feel sure, would not have been unwilling to adopt that idea, which is all the more accurate in proportion as the artist-portrayer of manners is a genius of mixed composition, in other words, a genius with a pronounced literary element. Observer, idler, philosopher, call him what you will, but, in order to define such an artist, you will surely in the end be brought to giving him an attributive adjective that you could not apply to a painter of things eternal, or at least things of a more permanent nature, of heroic or religious subjects. Sometimes he may be a poet; more often he comes close to the novelist or the moralist; he is the painter of the fleeting moment and of all that it suggests of the eternal. Every country, for its pleasure or its fame, has possessed a few men of that sort. In our own time, to Daumier, to Gavarni, the first names that come to mind, we may add Deveria, Maurin, Numa (all chroniclers of the Restoration's shady charms), Wattier, Tassaert, Eugène Lami, this last one almost English in his affection for aristocratic society, and even Trimolet and Traviès, the chroniclers of poverty and humble life.

III. An Artist, Man of the World, Man of Crowds, and Child

Today I want to talk to my readers about a singular man, whose originality is so powerful and clear-cut that it is self-sufficing, and does not bother to look for approval. None of his drawings is signed, if by signature we mean the few letters, which can be so easily forged, that compose a name, and that so many other artists grandly inscribe at the bottom of their most carefree sketches. But all his works are signed with his dazzling soul, and art-lovers who have seen and liked them will recognize them easily from the description I propose to give of them. M. C. G. [Monsieur Constantin Guys] loves mixing with the crowds, loves being incognito, and carries his originality to the point of modesty. M. Thackeray, who, as is well known, is very interested in all things to do with art, and who draws the illustrations for his own novels, one day spoke of M. G. in a London review, much to the irritation of the latter who regarded the matter as an outrage to his modesty. And again quite recently, when he heard that I was proposing to make an assessment of his mind and talent, he begged me, in a most peremptory manner, to suppress his name, and to discuss his works only as though they were the works of some anonymous person. I will humbly obey this odd request. The reader and I will proceed as though M. G. did not exist, and we will discuss his drawings and his water-colours, for which he professes a patrician's disdain, in the same way as would a group of scholars faced with the task of assessing the importance of a number of precious historical documents which chance has brought to light, and the author of which must for ever remain unknown. And even to reassure my conscience completely, let my readers assume that all the things I have to say about the artist's nature, so strangely and mysteriously dazzling, have been more or less accurately suggested by the works in question; pure poetic hypothesis, conjecture, or imaginative reconstructions.

M. G. is an old man. Jean-Jacques began writing, so they say, at the age of forty-two. Perhaps it was at about that age that M. G., obsessed by the world of images that filled his mind, plucked up courage to cast ink and colours on to a sheet of white paper. To be honest, he drew like a barbarian, like a child, angrily chiding his clumsy fingers and his disobedient tool. I have seen a large number of these early scribblings, and I admit that most of the people who know what they are talking about, or who claim to, could, without shame, have failed to discern the latent genius that dwelt in these obscure beginnings. Today, M. G., who has discovered unaided all the little tricks of the trade, and who has taught himself, without help or advice, has become a powerful master in his own way; of his early artlessness he has retained only what was needed to add an unexpected spice to his abundant gift. When he happens upon one of these efforts of his early manner, he tears it up or burns it, with a most amusing show of shame and indignation.

For ten whole years I wanted to make the acquaintance of M. G., who is by nature a great traveller and very cosmopolitan. I knew that he had for a long time been working for an English illustrated paper and that in it had appeared engravings from his travel sketches (Spain, Turkey, the Crimea). Since then I have seen a considerable mass of these on-the-spot drawings from life, and I have thus been able to 'read' a detailed and daily account, infinitely preferable to any other, of the Crimean campaign. The same paper had also published (without signature, as before) a large quantity of compositions by this artist from the new ballets and operas. When at last I ran him to ground I saw at once that I was not dealing exactly with an artist but rather with a man of the world. In this context, pray interpret the word 'artist' in a very narrow sense, and the expression 'man of the world' in a very broad one. By 'man of the world', I mean a man of the whole world, a man who understands the world and the mysterious and legitimate reasons behind all its customs; by 'artist', I mean a specialist, a man tied to his palette like a serf to the soil. M. G. does not like being called an artist. Is he not justified to a small extent? He takes an interest in everything the world over, he wants to know, understand, assess everything that happens on the surface of our spheroid. The artist moves little, or even not at all, in intellectual and political circles. If he lives in the Bréda quarter he knows nothing of what goes on in the Faubourg Saint-Germain. With two or three exceptions, which it is unnecessary to name, the majority of artists are, let us face it, very skilled brutes, mere manual labourers, village pub-talkers with the minds of country bumpkins. Their talk, inevitably enclosed within very narrow limits, quickly becomes a bore to the man of the world, to the spiritual citizen of the universe.

Thus to begin to understand M. G., the first thing to note is this: that curiosity may be considered the starting point of his genius.

Do you remember a picture (for indeed it is a picture!) written by the most powerful pen of this age and entitled The Man of the Crowd? Sitting in a café, and looking through the shop window, a convalescent is enjoying the sight of the passing crowd, and identifying himself in thought with all the thoughts that are moving around him. He has only recently come back from the shades of death and breathes in with delight all the spores and odours of life; as he has been on the point of forgetting everything, he remembers and passionately wants to remember everything. In the end he rushes out into the crowd in search of a man unknown to him whose face, which he had caught sight of, had in a flash fascinated him. Curiosity had become a compelling, irresistible passion.

Now imagine an artist perpetually in the spiritual condition of the convalescent, and you will have the key to the character of M. G.

But convalescence is like a return to childhood. The convalescent, like the child, enjoys to the highest degree the faculty of taking a lively interest in things, even the most trivial in appearance. Let us hark back, if we can, by a retrospective effort of our imaginations, to our youngest, our morning impressions, and we shall recognize that they were remarkably akin to the vividly coloured impressions that we received later on after a physical illness, provided that illness left our spiritual faculties pure and unimpaired. The child sees everything as a novelty; the child is always 'drunk'. Nothing is more like what we call inspiration than the joy the child feels in drinking in shape and colour. I will venture to go even further and declare that inspiration has some connection with congestion, that every sublime thought is accompanied by a more or less vigorous nervous impulse that reverberates in the cerebral cortex. The man of genius has strong nerves; those of the child are weak. In the one, reason has assumed an important role; in the other, sensibility occupies almost the whole being. But genius is no more than childhood recaptured at will, childhood equipped now with man's physical means to express itself, and with the analytical mind that enables it to bring order into the sum of experience, involuntarily amassed. To this deep and joyful curiosity must be attributed that stare, animal-like in its ecstasy, which all children have when confronted with something new, whatever it may be, face or landscape, light, gilding, colours, watered silk, enchantment of beauty, enhanced by the arts of dress. A friend of mine was telling me one day how, as a small boy, he used to be present when his father was dressing, and how he had always been filled with astonishment, mixed with delight, as he looked at the arm muscle, the colour tones of the skin tinged with rose and yellow, and the bluish network of the veins. The picture of the external world was already beginning to fill him with respect, and to take possession of his brain. Already the shape of things obsessed and possessed him. A precocious fate was showing the tip of its nose. His damnation was settled. Need I say that, today, the child is a famous painter.

I was asking you just now to think of M. G. as an eternal convalescent; to complete your idea of him, think of him also as a man-child, as a man possessing at every moment the genius of childhood, in other words a genius for whom no edge of life is blunted.

I told you that I was unwilling to call him a pure artist, and that he himself rejected this title, with a modesty tinged with aristocratic restraint. I would willingly call him a dandy, and for that I would have a sheaf of good reasons; for the word 'dandy' implies a quintessence of character and a subtle understanding of all the moral mechanisms of this world; but, from another aspect, the dandy aspires to cold detachment, and it is in this way that M. G., who is dominated, if ever anyone was, by an insatiable passion, that of seeing and feeling, parts company trenchantly with dandyism. Amabam amare, said St Augustine. 'I love passion, passionately,' M. G. might willingly echo. The dandy is blasé, or affects to be, as a matter of policy and class attitude, M. G. hates blasé people. Sophisticated minds will understand me when I say that he possesses that difficult art of being sincere without being ridiculous. I would willingly confer on him the title of philosopher, to which he has a right for more than one reason; but his excessive love of visible, tangible things, in their most plastic form, inspires him with a certain dislike of those things that go to make up the intangible kingdom of the metaphysician. Let us therefore reduce him to the status of the pure pictorial moralist, like La Bruyère.

The crowd is his domain, just as the air is the bird's, and water that of the fish. His passion and his profession is to merge with the crowd. For the perfect idler, for the passionate observer it becomes an immense source of enjoyment to establish his dwelling in the throng, in the ebb and flow, the bustle, the fleeting and the infinite. To be away from home and yet to feel at home anywhere; to see the world, to be at the very centre of the world, and yet to be unseen of the world, such are some of the minor pleasures of those independent, intense and impartial spirits, who do not lend themselves easily to linguistic definitions. The observer is a prince enjoying his incognito wherever he goes. The lover of life makes the whole world into his family, just as the lover of the fair sex creates his from all the lovely women he has found, from those that could be found, and those who are impossible to find, just as the picture-lover lives in an enchanted world of dreams painted on canvas. Thus the lover of universal life moves into the crowd as though into an enormous reservoir of electricity. He, the lover of life, may also be compared to a mirror as vast as this crowd; to a kaleidoscope endowed with consciousness, which with every one of its movements presents a pattern of life, in all its multiplicity, and the flowing grace of all the elements that go to compose life. It is an ego athirst for the non-ego, and reflecting it at every moment in energies more vivid than life itself, always inconstant and fleeting. 'Any man,' M. G. once said, in one of those talks he rendered memorable by the intensity of his gaze, and by his eloquence of gesture, 'any man who is not weighed down with a sorrow so searching as to touch all his faculties, and who is bored in the midst of the crowd, is a fool! A fool! and I despise him!'

When, as he wakes up, M. G. opens his eyes and sees the sun beating vibrantly at his window-panes, he says to himself with remorse and regret: 'What an imperative command! What a fanfare of light! Light everywhere for several hours past! Light I have lost in sleep! and endless numbers of things bathed in light that I could have seen and have failed to!' And off he goes! And he watches the flow of life move by, majestic and dazzling. He admires the eternal beauty and the astonishing harmony of life in the capital cities, a harmony so providentially maintained in the tumult of human liberty. He gazes at the landscape of the great city, landscapes of stone, now swathed in the mist, now struck in full face by the sun. He enjoys handsome equipages, proud horses, the spit and polish of the grooms, the skilful handling by the page boys, the smooth rhythmical gait of the women, the beauty of the children, full of the joy of life and proud as peacocks of their pretty clothes; in short, life universal. If in a shift of fashion, the cut of a dress has been slightly modified, if clusters of ribbons and curls have been dethroned by rosettes, if bonnets have widened and chignons have come down a little on the nape of the neck, if waist-lines have been raised and skirts become fuller, you may be sure that from a long way off his eagle's eye will have detected it. A regiment marches by, maybe on its way to the ends of the earth, filling the air of the boulevard with its martial airs, as light and lively as hope; and sure enough M. G. has already seen, inspected and analysed the weapons and the bearing of this whole body of troops. Harness, highlights, bands, determined mien, heavy and grim mustachios, all these details flood chaotically into him; and within a few minutes the poem that comes with it all is virtually composed. And then his soul will vibrate with the soul of the regiment, marching as though it were one living creature, proud image of joy and discipline!

But evening comes. The witching hour, the uncertain light, when the sky draws its curtains and the city lights go on. The gaslight stands out on the purple background of the setting sun. Honest men or crooked customers, wise or irresponsible, all are saying to themselves: 'The day is done at last!' Good men and bad turn their thoughts to pleasure, and each hurries to his favourite haunt to drink the cup of oblivion. M. G. will be the last to leave any place where the departing glories of daylight linger, where poetry echoes, life pulsates, music sounds; any place where a human passion offers a subject to his eye where natural man and conventional man reveal themselves in strange beauty, where the rays of the dying sun play on the fleeting pleasure of the 'depraved animal!' 'Well, there, to be sure, is a day well filled,' murmurs to himself a type of reader well-known to all of us; 'each one of us has surely enough genius to fill it in the same way'. No! few men have the gift of seeing; fewer still have the power to express themselves. And now, whilst others are sleeping, this man is leaning over his table, his steady gaze on a sheet of paper, exactly the same gaze as he directed just now at the things about him, brandishing his pencil, his pen, his brush, splashing water from the glass up to the ceiling, wiping his pen on his shirt, hurried, vigorous, active, as though he was afraid the images might escape him, quarrelsome though alone, and driving himself relentlessly on. And things seen are born again on the paper, natural and more than natural, beautiful and better than beautiful, strange and endowed with an enthusiastic life, like the soul of their creator. The weird pageant has been distilled from nature. All the materials, stored higgledy-piggledy by memory, are classified, ordered, harmonized, and undergo that deliberate idealization, which is the product of a childlike perceptiveness, in other words a perceptiveness that is acute and magical by its very ingenuousness.

IV. Modernity

And so, walking or quickening his pace, he goes his way, for ever in search. In search of what? We may rest assured that this man, such as I have described him, this solitary mortal endowed with an active imagination, always roaming the great desert of men, has a nobler aim than that of the pure idler, a more general aim, other than the fleeting pleasure of circumstance. He is looking for that indefinable something we may be allowed to call 'modernity', for want of a better term to express the idea in question. The aim for him is to extract from fashion the poetry that resides in its historical envelope, to distil the eternal from the transitory. If we cast our eye over our exhibitions of modern pictures, we shall be struck by the general tendency of our artists to clothe all manner of subjects in the dress of the past. Almost all of them use the fashions and the furnishings of the Renaissance, as David used Roman fashions and furnishings, but there is this difference, that David, having chosen subjects peculiarly Greek or Roman, could not do otherwise than present them in the style of antiquity, whereas the painters of today, choosing, as they do, subjects of a general nature, applicable to all ages, will insist on dressing them up in the fashion of the Middle Ages, of the Renaissance, or of the East. This is evidently sheer laziness; for it is much more convenient to state roundly that everything is hopelessly ugly in the dress of a period than to apply oneself to the task of extracting the mysterious beauty that may be hidden there, however small or light it may be. Modernity is the transient, the fleeting, the contingent; it is one half of art, the other being the eternal and the immovable. There was a form of modernity for every painter of the past; the majority of the fine portraits that remain to us from former times are clothed in the dress of their own day. They are perfectly harmonious works because the dress, the hairstyle, and even the gesture, the expression and the smile (each age has its carriage, its expression and its smile) form a whole, full of vitality. You have no right to despise this transitory fleeting element, the metamorphoses of which are so frequent, nor to dispense with it. If you do, you inevitably fall into the emptiness of an abstract and indefinable beauty, like that of the one and only woman of the time before the Fall. If for the dress of the day, which is necessarily right, you substitute another, you are guilty of a piece of nonsense that only a fancydress ball imposed by fashion can excuse. Thus the goddesses, the nymphs, and sultanas of the eighteenth century are portraits in the spirit of their day.

No doubt it is an excellent discipline to study the old masters, in order to learn how to paint, but it can be no more than a superfluous exercise if your aim is to understand the beauty of the present day. The draperies of Rubens or Veronese will not teach you how to paint watered silk à l'antique, or satin à la reine, or any other fabric produced by our mills, supported by a swaying crinoline, or petticoats of starched muslin. The texture and grain are not the same as in the fabrics of old Venice, or those worn at the court of Catherine. We may add that the cut of the skirt and bodice is absolutely different, that the pleats are arranged into a new pattern, and finally that the gesture and carriage of the woman of today give her dress a vitality and a character that are not those of the woman of former ages. In short, in order that any form of modernity may be worthy of becoming antiquity, the mysterious beauty that human life unintentionally puts into it must have been extracted from it. It is this task that M. G. particularly addresses himself to.

I have said that every age has its own carriage, its expression, its gestures. This proposition may be easily verified in a large portrait gallery (the one at Versailles, for example). But it can be yet further extended. In a unity we call a nation, the professions, the social classes, the successive centuries, introduce variety not only in gestures and manners, but also in the general outlines of faces. Such and such a nose, mouth, forehead, will be standard for a given interval of time, the length of which I shall not claim to determine here, but which may certainly be a matter of calculation. Such ideas are not familiar enough to portrait painters; and the great weakness of M. Ingres, in particular, is the desire to impose on every type that sits for him a more or less complete process of improvement, in other words a despotic perfecting process, borrowed from the store of classical ideas.

In a matter such as this, a priori reasoning would be easy and even legitimate. The perpetual correlation between what is called the soul and what is called the body is a quite satisfactory explanation of how what is material or emanates from the spiritual reflects and will always reflect the spiritual force it derives from. If a painter, patient and scrupulous but with only inferior imaginative power, were commissioned to paint a courtesan of today, and, for this purpose, were to get his inspiration (to use the hallowed term) from a courtesan by Titian or Raphael, the odds are that his work would be fraudulent, ambiguous, and difficult to understand. The study of a masterpiece of that date and of that kind will not teach him the carriage, the gaze, the come-hitherishness, or the living representation of one of these creatures that the dictionary of fashion has, in rapid succession, pigeonholed under the coarse or light-hearted rubric of unchaste, kept women, Lorettes.

The same remark applies precisely to the study of the soldier, the dandy, and even animals, dogs or horses, and of all things that go to make up the external life of an age. Woe betide the man who goes to antiquity for the study of anything other than ideal art, logic and general method! By immersing himself too deeply in it, he will no longer have the present in his mind's eye; he throws away the value and the privileges afforded by circumstance; for nearly all our originality comes from the stamp that time impresses upon our sensibility. The reader will readily understand that I could easily verify my assertions from innumerable objects other than women. What would you say, for example, of a marine painter (I take an extreme case) who, having to represent the sober and elegant beauty of a modern vessel, were to tire out his eyes in the study of the overloaded, twisted shapes, the monumental stern, of ships of bygone ages, and the complex sails and rigging of the sixteenth century? And what would you think of an artist you had commissioned to do the portrait of a thorough-bred, celebrated in the solemn annals of the turf, if he were to restrict his studies to museums, if he were to content himself with looking at equine studies of the past in the picture galleries, in Van Dyck, Bourguignon, or Van der Meulen?

M. G., guided by nature, tyrannized over by circumstance, has followed a quite different path. He began by looking at life, and only later did he contrive to learn how to express life. The result has been a striking originality, in which whatever traces of untutored simplicity may still remain take on the appearance of an additional proof of obedience to the impression, of a flattery of truth. For most of us, especially for businessmen, in whose eyes nature does not exist, unless it be in its strict utility relationship with their business interests, the fantastic reality of life becomes strangely blunted. M. G. registers it constantly; his memory and his eyes are full of it.

V. Mnemonic Art

The word 'barbarousness', which may have come too often from my pen, might lead some people to believe that I am alluding to a number of shapeless drawings that only the imagination of the viewer is capable of transforming into perfect things. This would be a serious misunderstanding of what I mean. I refer to a sort of inevitable, synthetic, childlike barbarousness, which can often still be seen in a perfect type of art (Mexican, Egyptian, or Ninevehite barbarousness) and derives from the need to see things big, to look at them particularly from the point of view of their effect as a whole. It is not superfluous to remark here that the accusation of barbarousness has often been made against all painters who have an eye for synthesis and abbreviation, M. Corot, for example, who begins by tracing the main lines of a landscape, its structure and features. Similarly, M. G., faithful interpreter of his own impressions, notes with instinctive vigour the culminating features or highlights of an object (they can be culminating or luminous from a dramatic point of view) or its main characteristics, sometimes even with a degree of exaggeration useful to human memory; and the imagination of the viewer, undergoing in its turn the influence of this imperious code, conjures up in clear outline the impression produced by objects on the mind of M. G. In this case, the viewer becomes the translator of a translation, which is always clear and always intoxicating.

There is a factor that adds greatly to the vitality of this pictorial record of everyday life. I refer to M. G.'s habit of work. He draws from memory, and not from the model, except in those cases (the Crimean War, for example) where there is an urgent need to take immediate, hurried notes and to establish the broad outlines of a subject. In fact all true draughtsmen draw from the image imprinted in their brain and not from nature. If the admirable sketches of Raphael, of Watteau and many others are quoted as examples to invalidate our contention, our reply is that these are indeed highly detailed notes, but mere notes they remain. When a true artist has reached the stage of the final execution of his work, the model would be more of an embarrassment to him than a help. It even happens that men like Daumier and M. G. who have been accustomed for years to using their memory, and filling it with images, find that, when confronted with a model and the multiplicity of detail this means, their main faculty is as though confused and paralysed.

Then begins a struggle between the determination to see everything, to forget nothing, and the faculty of memory, which has acquired the habit of registering in a flash the general tones and shape, the outline pattern. An artist with a perfect sense of form but particularly accustomed to the exercise of his memory and his imagination, then finds himself assailed, as it were, by a riot of details, all of them demanding justice, with the fury of a mob in love with absolute equality. Any form of justice is inevitably infringed; any harmony is destroyed, sacrificed; a multitude of trivialities are magnified; a multitude of little things become usurpers of attention. The more the artist pays impartial attention to detail, the greater does anarchy become. Whether he be short- or long-sighted, all sense of hierarchy or subordination disappears. This is an accident that often occurs in the works of one of our most fashionable painters, whose defects moreover are so well attuned to the defects of the crowd that they have greatly contributed to his popularity. The same sort of analogy may be sensed in the practice of the actor's art, that mysterious, profound art which in these days has fallen into the confusion of many forms of decadence. M. Frédérick-Lemaître builds up a role with the breadth and boldness of genius. Adorned as his acting is with brilliant detail, it nonetheless remains a unified sculptural composition. M. Bouffé builds his with the painstaking efforts of a myope or a bureaucrat. In him everything sparkles and crackles, but nothing strikes the eye, nothing claims a place in our memories.

Thus in M. G.'s execution two things stand out: the first is the absorbed intenseness of a resurrecting and evocative memory, a memory that says to every object: 'Lazarus, arise'; the second is a fire, an intoxication of pencil or brush, almost amounting to frenzy. This is the fear of not going fast enough, of letting the spectre escape before the synthesis has been extracted and taken possession of, the terrible fear that takes hold of all great artists and fills them with such an ardent desire to appropriate all means of expression, so that the commands of the mind may never be weakened by the hand's hesitation; so that, in the end, the ideal execution may become as unconscious, as flowing, as the process of digesting is for the brain of a healthy man after dinner. M. G. begins with a few light pencil touches, which scarcely do more than indicate the positions of the objects in space. The main planes are indicated next by a series of colour-washes, masses vaguely and lightly tinted at first, but worked over again later with applications of stronger colour. In the last stage, the outlines of objects are clearly traced with pencil and ink. Without having seen them, no one would guess the remarkable effects he can achieve by this so simple and almost elementary method. It has the incomparable advantage that, at almost any stage, each drawing seems to have reached a stage of completion satisfying enough to the viewer; you may call this a thumbnail sketch, but it is a perfect one. All the tone values are in harmony, and if he wants to work the tones up, they will always retain their relationship as they move towards the desired state of perfection. In this way he can work at up to twenty drawings at a time with a liveliness and joy charming to the eye and amusing even for him; the sketches pile up, one on top of the other, by tens, hundreds, by thousands. From time to time he runs through them, glancing at some, examining others, and then he chooses a few, to which he gives more intensity by giving greater depth to the shadow and touching up the highlights.

He attaches great importance to the backgrounds, which, whether strongly or lightly worked, are always of a quality and nature appropriate to the figures. The scale of tones and the general harmony are strictly observed, with a genius that derives more from instinct than from study. For M. G. possesses that mysterious talent of the colourist, by the light of nature, a veritable gift, which study can strengthen but which it cannot of itself, I believe, create. To sum it all up, our strange artist expresses both the gestures and attitudes, be they solemn or grotesque, of human beings and their luminous explosion in space.

VI. The Annals of War

Bulgaria, Turkey, the Crimea, Spain have all been a gorgeous feast for M. G.'s eyes, or rather for those of the imaginary artist we are agreed to call M. G.; for now and then it comes back to me that, to reassure his modesty, I promised to pretend he did not exist. I have looked through these archives of the Eastern War (battlefields strewn with the debris of death, heavy baggage trains, shipment of livestock and horses), scenes throbbing with life and interest, as though moulded on life itself, elements of a valuable form of picturesque, which many wellknown painters would have thoughtlessly neglected if they had found themselves in the same circumstances; amongst these, however, I would willingly make an exception of M. Horace Vernet, veritable journalist rather than true artist, with whom M. G., though a more delicate artist, has an evident relationship, assuming we want to think of him only as an archivist of life. No journal, I declare, no written record, no book could express so well this great epic of the Crimean War, in all its distressing detail and sinister breadth. The eye moves from the banks of the Danube to the shores of the Bosphorus, from Cape Kerson to the plain of Balaclava or the fields of Inkerman, and on to the English, French, Turkish and Piedmontese encampments, from the streets of Constantinople to the hospitals and to a variety of solemn religious and military ceremonies.

One of the drawings that sticks in my memory more than others is the Consécration d'un terrain funèbre à Scutari par l'évêque de Gibraltar. The picturesque character of the scene, which arises from the contrast between the surrounding oriental countryside and the western attitudes and uniforms of the participants, is brought out strikingly, and in a manner that gives food for thought and reverie. The ordinary soldiers and officers alike, all have that ineradicable air of 'gentlemen', that determined and reserved air they carry with them to the end of the earth, whether it be in the garrison towns of Cape Colony or the settlements in India; the Anglican clergy put one vaguely in mind of ushers or stockbrokers in cap and bands for the occasion.

And here in another drawing is the residence of Omar Pasha at Shumla. Turkish hospitality, pipes and coffee; all the visitors are seated on divans, sucking at pipes as long as blow-pipes, with the bowls at their feet. And here, Kurdes à Scutari depicts a weird-looking soldiery whose aspect suggests an invasion of barbarian hordes; and, no less strange, in another sketch are bashi-bazouks, with their European officers, Hungarian or Polish, veritable dandies in feature these latter, contrasting oddly with the curiously oriental character of their men.

One magnificent drawing that caught my eye is of a single standing figure; the man is stout and vigorous, his expression all at once thoughtful, carefree and bold; he is wearing high boots, which come up above his knees; his uniform is hidden under a heavy, ample topcoat, tightly buttoned up; his gaze, through his cigar smoke, is directed towards the threatening misty horizon; he has been wounded in the arm, and is wearing a sling. At the foot, a scribbled pencil note states: Canrobert on the battlefield of Inkerman. Taken on the spot.

And who might this horseman be? With white moustaches so vigorously drawn, with head erect, he seems to be scenting the terrible poetry of the battlefield, whilst his horse, sniffing the ground, picks his way between the heaps of corpses, feet upturned, faces contorted, in strange attitudes. At the bottom of the drawing, in a corner, are these words: Myself at Inkerman.

And who is this but M. Baraguay-d'Hilliers, with the Seraskier, inspecting the artillery at Béchichtash. Rarely have I seen a better likeness in the portrait of a soldier, done by a bolder or livelier hand.

Hard by, I caught sight of a name of sinister reputation since our Syrian disasters: Achmet Pasha, Commander-in-Chief, standing in front of his tent, surrounded by his staff, receives the European officers. Despite the generous extent of his Turkish paunch, Achmet-Pasha has, both in his bearing and in his face, the noble aristocratic air that usually belongs to the master races.

The battle of Balaclava figures several times, from different angles, in this interesting collection. There, amongst the most striking, is the historic cavalry charge sung by the heroic clarion of Alfred Tennyson, the Poet Laureate: a mass of cavalry are shown thundering at speed towards the horizon, between the rolling clouds of gunsmoke. The background is shut in by a line of green hills.

From time to time a religious subject provides a welcome change to the viewer's gaze, saddened by this chaos of gunpowder and restless carnage. In the midst of the British troops of all arms, amongst whom the picturesque uniform of the kilted Scots is conspicuous, an Anglican chaplain holds the Sunday service; three drums, the topmost resting on the other two, serve as a lectern.

It is difficult in all conscience for the mere pen to translate this vast and complex poem, composed of a thousand sketches, and to express the feelings of intoxication arising from all the picturesque details - often distressing but never maudlin - which are collected in these few hundred pages. The stained and torn condition of these is eloquent in its own way of the chaos and tumult in the midst of which the artist noted down his memories of each day. As evening came the mail would carry away towards London M. G.'s notes and drawings, and, often enough, he would thus entrust to the post ten or more quickly executed thumbnail sketches, done on thin paper, which the engravers and subscribers to the magazine were eagerly awaiting.

Sometimes ambulances are depicted, where the very atmosphere seems sick, gloomy and heavy, every bed a bed of pain; another time, it is the hospital at Pera, with two sisters of mercy, tall, pale and straight like the figures of Lesueur, talking, I notice, to an informally dressed visitor quaintly designated as 'my humble self'. Or again, on rough, winding paths strewn with the debris of a past engagement, a long string of pack animals - mules, donkeys, or horses - moves slowly, carrying in rough panniers, balanced on either flank, pale and inert wounded. Across vast expanses of snow come camels, with majestic dewlaps and heads held high. Led by Tartars, they are hauling provisions and munitions of all kinds; a whole warlike world appears, full of life and silent activity, encampments, bazaars, where samples of every type of supplies are displayed, like barbarian cities, conjured up for the circumstances. Amidst the huts, along the stony or snowy roads, in the defiles, can be seen the uniforms of several countries, more or less worn and torn by war, or altered in appearance by lumpy fur coats or heavy boots.

How sad it is to think that this album, which has now been scattered in a variety of places, and the precious pages of which have been kept by the engravers commissioned to reproduce them, or by the editors of the Illustrated London News, should not have been submitted to the Emperor. He, I am sure, would have been glad to see (not without emotion) this record of his soldiers, their day-in, day-out doings, expressed with minute care, from the most brilliant feats of arms to the most trivial occupations of life, by this soldier-artist's sure and intelligent hand.

VII. Pomp and Ceremony

Turkey has also contributed some admirable subjects to our dear G.: the festivals of Bairam, profound and rippling splendours, in the background of which appears, like a pallid sun, the ineradicable boredom of the late Sultan; ranged to the left of the sovereign stand all the officers of the civil order; to his right, all those of the military order, the chief of them being Said Pasha, Sultan of Egypt, who was at Constantinople at the time; processions, moving with solemn pomp to the little mosque near the palace, and in these throngs are to be seen a number of Turkish functionaries, veritable caricatures of decadence, crushing their splendid horses under the weight of their fantastic obesity; the heavy, massive carriages, not unlike coaches from the days of Louis XIV, gilded and otherwise adorned with oriental fantasy, from the inside of which curious feminine glances dart from time to time, through the narrow interval left to the eyes by muslin veils worn close to the face; the frenzied dances of mountebanks of the 'third sex' (never has Balzac's humorous phrase been more applicable than in the present case, for beneath these throbbing unsteady lights, under the generous waving folds of the garments, under the heavy make-up of cheeks, eyes and eyebrows, in all these hysterical and convulsive gestures, in the long hair down to the hips, you would find it difficult, not to say impossible, to guess that virility was there): and finally the women of easy virtue (if one can speak in such terms, where the Levant is concerned), generally provided by Hungarian, Walachian, Jewish, Polish, Greek and Armenian women; for under a despotic government, it is the oppressed races, and especially those amongst them that suffer the greatest privations, that provide the most recruits to prostitution. Amongst these women some have kept their national costumes, embroidered bodices, short sleeves, loosely hanging scarves, baggy trousers, Turkish slippers with upturned points, striped or spangled muslins, and all the tinsel of their homeland; others, by far the more numerous, have adopted the principal mark of civilization, which, for a woman, is invariably the crinoline, not, however, without introducing in their attire a faint reminiscence of the Levant, with the result that they have an air of Parisian women attempting to disguise themselves.

M. G. excels at depicting all the display of official ceremonies, the pomp and circumstance of national occasions, not coldly and didactically, like painters who see only lucrative drudgery in commissions of this kind, but with all the ardour of a man in love with space, perspective, great expanses or explosions of light, hanging like teardrops or sparkling diamonds on the asperities of the uniform or court dresses. La fête commémorative de l'indépendance dans la cathédrale d'Athènes affords an interesting example of this talent. All the little figures, each of them so well placed, give more depth to the space that contains them. The cathedral is vast and festooned with solemn draperies. King Otto and the Queen, standing on a dais, are depicted in the traditional dress, which they are wearing with marvellous ease, as though to bear witness to the sincerity of their adoption, and to the most refined Hellenic patriotism. The King is as tightly belted as the smartest palikar, and his kilt flares out with all the exaggeration of national dandyism. Opposite the royal couple, the patriarch is stepping towards them, an old man with bowed shoulders, flowing white beard, little eyes behind green glasses, his whole bearing betraying the most consummate oriental impassivity. All the figures that people this composition are portraits; one of the most interesting, on account of the oddness of the features, which are anything but Hellenic, is that of a German woman standing next to the Queen and attached to her service.

In all M. G.'s series of drawings, a figure often to be found is the French Emperor, whose face the artist has succeeded in reducing to an infallible shorthand sketch without losing the likeness, which he executes with all the sureness of a signature flourish. Now the Emperor, at full gallop, is holding a review, accompanied by officers with easily recognizable features, or by foreign potentates, European, Asiatic, or African, to whom he is doing, as it were, the honours of Paris. Sometimes he is shown motionless on his horse, whose hooves are as firmly on the ground as the four legs of a table, with the Empress on his left in riding habit, and on his right, the little Prince Imperial, in a busby, and holding himself militarily erect on a little rough-haired horse, like the ponies English artists love to show dashing about in their landscapes; at other times, cascades of light and dust enfold him as he rides in the alleys of the Bois de Boulogne; at others again, we see him greeted by the acclamations of the crowds as he moves amongst them in the faubourg Saint-Antoine. One of these water-colours in particular quite dazzled me by its magical quality: the Empress, composed and relaxed, is seen at the front of a richly and majestically decorated box at the theatre; the Emperor is leaning forward slightly, as though to get a better view of the theatre; below, two guardsmen stand erect in military, almost religious immobility, their brilliant uniforms sparkling with the reflections of the light from the footlights. Behind this band of light in the ideal atmosphere of the stage, the actors are singing, declaiming and gesticulating harmoniously; on the near side, there is an abyss of suffused light and a circular space full of human faces at every tier: the chandelier and the audience.

The mob demonstrations, the clubs, the solemn occasions of 1848 also provided M. G. with subjects for a series of scenes, most of which have been engraved for the Illustrated London News. A few years ago, after a sojourn in Spain, which was very fruitful for his genius, he compiled an album of the same kind, of which I have seen only a few fragments. The carelessness with which he gives away or lends his drawings often exposes him to irreparable losses.

VIII. The Soldier

To define once more the kind of subject this artist likes best, let us call it the pomp of life, as it is displayed in the capitals of the civilized world, the pageant of military life, of high life, of loose life. Our eye-witness is always punctually at his observation post, wherever flow the deep and impetuous desires, the great rivers of the human heart, war, love, gaming; wherever the festivities and figments which are the external form of these great elements of happiness and sorrow are in full swing. But the artist shows a very marked predilection for military life, for the soldier, and I think that this love of his derives, not only from the virtues and qualities that inevitably flow from the warrior's soul into his bearing and his face, but also from the showy apparel his profession clothes him in. M. Paul de Molènes has written a few pages, as delightful to read as they are full of good sense, on military coquetry and on the moral significance to be drawn from those dazzling costumes in which all governments like dressing their troops. M. G. would willingly sign these pages.

We have already spoken of the idiom of beauty peculiar to every age, and we have noted that every century had, so to speak, its own characteristic grace. The same observation may be applied to the professions; each one draws its external beauty from the moral laws that govern it. In some, this type of beauty will be marked by energy, and in others it will bear the visible signs of idleness. It is, as it were, the emblem of character, the stamp of fate. The soldier considered in general has his type of beauty, just as the dandy and the woman of the town have theirs, and each has its own distinctive quality. The reader will accept it as natural that I should ignore those professions where, as a result of a single form of violent exercise, muscles become distorted and the face is marked by servitude. Accustomed as he is to surprises, the soldier does not easily lose his composure. Thus, in this case, beauty will consist of a carefree, martial air, a strange mixture of calm and boldness; it is a form of beauty that comes from the need to be ready to die at any moment. But the face of the ideal military man must be stamped with a great air of simplicity; for living as they do in a community, like monks and schoolboys, accustomed as they are to unload the daily concern of living on to a remote, paternalist organization, soldiers are, in many matters, as simple as children; and like children, once duty has been done, they are easy to amuse, and given to boisterous forms of fun. I do not think I am exaggerating when I maintain that all these moral considerations spring naturally from the sketches and water-colours of M. G. Not a single military type is missing, and all of them have been caught by the artist with a kind of enthusiastic joy: the old infantry officer, of the sad countenance, distressing his horse by his obesity; the pampered staff officer, wasp-waisted and bending forward over ladies' chairs without bashfulness, with affected movements of the shoulders, and, seen from the rear, reminiscent of some slender and elegant insect; the zouave and the rifleman, whose whole bearing suggests outstanding audacity, self-reliance and, as it were, a more than ordinary sense of personal responsibility; and the free and easy manner, the mercurial gaiety of the light cavalry; the vaguely professorial and academic features of the technical arms, like the gunners and the sappers, often confirmed by the unwarlike apparatus of spectacles: none of these models, none of these nuances is neglected, and all of them are summed up, defined, with the same love and wit.

I have in front of me, as I write, one of these drawings; its subject, which conveys a general impression of heroism, is the head of an infantry column; maybe these men are back from Italy and have halted on the boulevards, basking in the enthusiasm of the crowds; maybe they have just accomplished long marches on the roads of Lombardy; I do not know, but what is dearly visible, what comes across fully, is the steadfast audacious character, even in repose, of all these sun-tanned, weather-beaten faces.

This is without a doubt the uniform expression produced by discipline, sufferings undergone together, the resigned air of courage, tempered by long periods of exhausting strain. Trousers turned up and tucked into gaiters, great-coats tarnished by dust and vaguely discoloured, the whole equipment in fact has itself taken on the indestructible appearance of beings that have returned from afar, and have experienced strange adventures. It really is as though these men were more solidly screwed on to their hips, more firmly planted on their feet, more self-assured than ordinary mortals. If Charlet, who was always on the look-out for just this kind of beauty, and who found it often enough, had seen this drawing, he would have been greatly impressed by it.

IX. The Dandy

The wealthy man, who, blasé though he may be, has no occupation in life but to chase along the highway of happiness, the man nurtured in luxury, and habituated from early youth to being obeyed by others, the man, finally, who has no profession other than elegance, is bound at all times to have a facial expression of a very special kind. Dandyism is an ill-defined social attitude as strange as duelling; it goes back a long way, since Caesar, Catilina, Alcibiades provide us with brilliant examples of it; it is very widespread, since Chateaubriand found examples of it in the forests and on the lake-sides of the New World. Dandyism, which is an institution outside the law, has a rigorous code of laws that all its subjects are strictly bound by, however ardent and independent their individual characters may be.

The English novelists, more than others, have cultivated the 'high life' type of novel, and their French counterparts who, like M. de Custine, have tried to specialize in love novels have very wisely taken care to endow their characters with purses long enough for them to indulge without hesitation their slightest whims; and they freed them from any profession. These beings have no other status but that of cultivating the idea of beauty in their own persons, of satisfying their passions, of feeling and thinking. Thus they possess, to their hearts' content, and to a vast degree, both time and money, without which fantasy, reduced to the state of ephemeral reverie, can scarcely be translated into action. It is unfortunately very true that, without leisure and money, love can be no more than an orgy of the common man, or the accomplishment of a conjugal duty. Instead of being a sudden impulse full of ardour and reverie, it becomes a distastefully utilitarian affair.

If I speak of love in the context of dandyism, the reason is that love is the natural occupation of men of leisure. But the dandy does not consider love as a special aim in life. If I have mentioned money, the reason is that money is indispensable to those who make an exclusive cult of their passions, but the dandy does not aspire to wealth as an object in itself; an open bank credit could suit him just as well; he leaves that squalid passion to vulgar mortals. Contrary to what a lot of thoughtless people seem to believe, dandyism is not even an excessive delight in clothes and material elegance. For the perfect dandy, these things are no more than the symbol of the aristocratic superiority of his mind. Thus, in his eyes, enamoured as he is above all of distinction, perfection in dress consists in absolute simplicity, which is, indeed, the best way of being distinguished. What then can this passion be, which has crystallized into a doctrine, and has formed a number of outstanding devotees, this unwritten code that has moulded so proud a brotherhood? It is, above all, the burning desire to create a personal form of originality, within the external limits of social conventions. It is a kind of cult of the ego which can still survive the pursuit of that form of happiness to be found in others, in woman for example; which can even survive what are called illusions. It is the pleasure of causing surprise in others, and the proud satisfaction of never showing any oneself. A dandy may be blasé, he may even suffer pain, but in the latter case he will keep smiling, like the Spartan under the bite of the fox.

Clearly, then, dandyism in certain respects comes close to spirituality and to stoicism, but a dandy can never be a vulgar man. If he were to commit a crime, he might perhaps be socially damned, but if the crime came from some trivial cause, the disgrace would be irreparable. Let the reader not be shocked by this mixture of the grave and the gay; let him rather reflect that there is a sort of grandeur in all follies, a driving power in every sort of excess. A strange form of spirituality indeed! For those who are its high priests and its victims at one and the same time, all the complicated material conditions they subject themselves to, from the most flawless dress at any time of day or night to the most risky sporting feats, are no more than a series of gymnastic exercises suitable to strengthen the will and school the soul. Indeed I was not far wrong when I compared dandyism to a kind of religion. The most rigorous monastic rule, the inexorable commands of the Old Man of the Mountain, who enjoined suicide on his intoxicated disciples, were not more despotic or more slavishly obeyed than this doctrine of elegance and originality, which, like the others, imposes upon its ambitious and humble sectaries, men as often as not full of spirit, passion, courage, controlled energy, the terrible precept: Perinde ac cadaver! [as a corpse].

Fastidious, unbelievables, beaux, lions or dandies: whichever label these men claim for themselves, one and all stem from the same origin, all share the same characteristic of opposition and revolt; all are representatives of what is best in human pride, of that need, which is too rare in the modern generation, to combat and destroy triviality. That is the source, in your dandy, of that haughty, patrician attitude, aggressive even in its coldness. Dandyism appears especially in those periods of transition when democracy has not yet become all-powerful, and when aristocracy is only partially weakened and discredited. In the confusion of such times, a certain number of men, disenchanted and leisured 'outsiders', but all of them richly endowed with native energy, may conceive the idea of establishing a new kind of aristocracy, all the more difficult to break down because established on the most precious, the most indestructible faculties, on the divine gifts that neither work nor money can give. Dandyism is the last flicker of heroism in decadent ages; and the sort of dandy discovered by the traveller in Northern America in no sense invalidates this idea; for there is no valid reason why we should not believe that the tribes we call savage are not the remnants of great civilizations of the past. Dandyism is a setting sun; like the declining star, it is magnificent, without heat and full of melancholy. But alas! the rising tide of democracy, which spreads everywhere and reduces everything to the same level, is daily carrying away these last champions of human pride, and submerging, in the waters of oblivion, the last traces of these remarkable myrmidons. Here in France, dandies are becoming rarer and rarer, whereas amongst our neighbours in England the state of society and the constitution (the true constitution, the one that is expressed in social habits) will, for a long time yet, leave room for the heirs of Sheridan, Brummell and Byron, always assuming that men worthy of them come forward.

What to the reader may have seemed a digression is not one in fact. The moral reflections and musings that arise from the drawings of an artist are in many cases the best interpretation that the critic can make of them; the notions they suggest are part of an underlying idea, and, by revealing them in turn, we may uncover the root idea itself. Need I say that when M. G. commits one of his dandies to paper, he always gives him his historical character, we might almost say his legendary character, were it not that we are dealing with our own day and with things that are generally held to be light-hearted? For here we surely have that ease of bearing, that sureness of manner, that simplicity in the habit of command, that way of wearing a frock-coat or controlling a horse, that calmness revealing strength in every circumstance, that convince us, when our eye does pick out one of those privileged beings, in whom the attractive and the formidable mingle so mysteriously: 'There goes a rich man perhaps, but quite certainly an unemployed Hercules.'

The specific beauty of the dandy consists particularly in that cold exterior resulting from the unshakeable determination to remain unmoved; one is reminded of a latent fire, whose existence is merely suspected, and which, if it wanted to, but it does not, could burst forth in all its brightness. All that is expressed to perfection in these illustrations.

X. Woman

The being who, for most men, is the source of the most lively, and even, be it said to the shame of philosophical delights, the most lasting joys; the being towards or for whom all their efforts tend; that awe-inspiring being, incommunicable like God (with this difference that the infinite does not reveal itself because it would blind and crush the finite, whereas the being we are speaking about is incommunicable only, perhaps, because having nothing to communicate); that being in whom Joseph de Maistre saw a beautiful animal, whose charm brightens and facilitates the serious game of politics; for whom and by whom fortunes are made and lost; for whom, but especially by whom, artists and poets compose their most delicate jewels; from whom flow the most enervating pleasures and the most enriching sufferings - woman, in a word, is not, for the artist in general and for M. G. in particular, only the female of the human species. She is rather a divinity, a star, that presides over all the conceptions of the male brain; she is like the shimmer of all graces of nature, condensed into one being; she is the object of the most intense admiration and interest that the spectacle of life can offer to man's contemplation. She is a kind of idol, empty-headed perhaps, but dazzling, enchanting, an idol that holds men's destinies and wills in thrall to her glances. She is not, I repeat, an animal whose limbs, correctly assembled, provide a perfect example of harmony; nor is she even that type of pure beauty which might be imagined by a sculptor, in his moments of most austere meditation; not even that would suffice to explain her mysterious and complex spellbinding power. Neither Winckelmann nor Raphael can help us in this context; and I am sure that M. G., in spite of the breadth of his intelligence (be it said without affront to him), would turn away from a piece of ancient statuary if, by looking at it, he were to lose the opportunity of enjoying a portrait by Reynolds or Lawrence. All the things that adorn woman, all the things that go to enhance her beauty, are part of herself; and the artists who have made a special study of this enigmatic being are just as enchanted by the whole mundus muliebris [world of women] as by woman herself. Woman is doubtless a light, a glance, an invitation to happiness, sometimes a spoken word; but above all, she is a harmonious whole, not only in her carriage and in the movement of her limbs, but also in the muslins and the gauzes, in the vast and iridescent clouds of draperies in which she envelops herself, and which are, so to speak, the attributes and the pedestal of her divinity; in the metal and precious stones that serpentine round her arms and neck, that add their sparkle to the fire of her eyes, or whisper softly at her ears. When he describes the pleasure caused by the sight of a beautiful woman, what poet would dare to distinguish between her and her apparel? Show me the man who, in the street, at the theatre, or in the Bois, has not enjoyed, in a wholly detached way, the sight of a beautifully composed attire, and has not carried away with him an image inseparable from the beauty of the woman wearing it, thus making of the two, the woman and the dress, an indivisible whole. This seems to me the moment to come back to certain questions relating to fashion and adornment, which I only briefly touched on at the beginning of this study, and to vindicate the art of dress against the inept slanders heaped upon it by certain highly equivocal nature-lovers.

XI. In Praise of Make-Up

I know a song so valueless and futile that I scarcely dare quote from it in a work with some claims to being serious; but it expresses very aptly, in vaudeville style, the aesthetic notions of people not given to thinking. 'Nature embellishes beauty.' It may be presumed that the 'poet', had he been able to write his own language properly, would have said: 'Simplicity embellishes beauty', which is tantamount to this truth of a wholly unexpected kind: 'Nothing embellishes what is.'

Most wrong ideas about beauty derive from the false notion the eighteenth century had about ethics. In those days, Nature was taken as a basis, source and prototype of all possible forms of good and beauty. The rejection of original sin is in no small measure responsible for the general blindness of those days. If, however, we are prepared merely to consult the facts that stare us in the face, the experience of all ages, and the Gazette des Tribunaux, we can see at once that natures teaches nothing or nearly nothing; in other words, it compels man to sleep, drink, eat and to protect himself as best he can against the inclemencies of the weather. It is nature too that drives man to kill his fellow-man, to eat him, to imprison and torture him; for as soon as we move from the order of necessities and needs to that of luxury and pleasures, we see that nature can do nothing but counsel crime. It is this so-called infallible nature that has produced parricide and cannibalism, and a thousand other abominations, which modesty and nice feeling alike prevent our mentioning. It is philosophy (I am referring to the right kind), it is religion that enjoins upon us to succour our poor and enfeebled parents. Nature (which is nothing but the inner voice of self-interest) tells us to knock them on the head. Review, analyse everything that is natural, all the actions and desires of absolutely natural man: you will find nothing that is not horrible. Everything that is beautiful and noble is the product of reason and calculation. Crime, which the human animal took a fancy to in his mother's womb, is by origin natural. Virtue, on the other hand, is artificial, supernatural, since in every age and nation gods and prophets have been necessary to teach it to bestialized humanity, and since man by himself would have been powerless to discover it. Evil is done without effort, naturally, it is the working of fate; good is always the product of an art. All I have said about nature, as a bad counsellor in matters of ethics, and about reason, as the true power of redemption and reform, can be transferred to the order of beauty. Thus I am led to regard adornment as one of the signs of the primitive nobility of the human soul. The races that our confused and perverted civilization so glibly calls savage, with a quite laughable pride and fatuity, appreciate, just as children do, the high spiritual quality of dress. The savage and the infant show their distaste for the real by their naive delight in bright feathers of different colours, in shimmering fabrics, in the superlative majesty of artificial shapes, thus unconsciously proving the immateriality of their souls. Woe to him who, like Louis XV (who far from being the product of a true civilization was that of a recurrence of barbarism), drives depravity to the point of appreciating nothing but nature unadorned.[〔1〕]

Fashion must therefore be thought of as a symptom of the taste for the ideal that floats on the surface in the human brain, above all the coarse, earthy and disgusting things that life according to nature accumulates, as a sublime distortion of nature, or rather as a permanent and constantly renewed effort to reform nature. For this reason, it has been judiciously observed (though without discovering the cause) that all fashions are charming, or rather relatively charming, each one being a new striving, more or less well conceived, after beauty, an approximate statement of an ideal, the desire for which constantly teases the unsatisfied human mind. But, if we want to enjoy fashions thoroughly, we must not look upon them as dead things; we might as well admire a lot of old clothes hung up, limp and inert, like the skin of St Bartholomew, in the cupboard of a second-hand-clothes dealer. They must be pictured as full of the life and vitality of the beautiful women who wore them. Only in that way can we give them meaning and value. If therefore the aphorism 'All fashions are charming' offends you as being too absolute, say - and then you can be sure of making no mistake - all were legitimately charming in their day.

Woman is well within her rights, we may even say she carries out a kind of duty, in devoting herself to the task of fostering a magic and supernatural aura about her appearance; she must create a sense of surprise, she must fascinate; idol that she is, she must adorn herself, to be adored. It follows, she must borrow, from all the arts, the means of rising above nature, in order the better to conquer the hearts and impress the minds of men. It matters very little that the ruse and the artifice be known of all, if their success is certain, and the effect always irresistible. These are the kind of reflections that lead the philosopher-artist to justify readily all the means employed by women, over the centuries, to consolidate and, so to speak, divinize their fragile beauty. Any enumeration would have to include countless details; but, to limit ourselves to what in our day is commonly called make-up, who can fail to see that the use of rice powder, so fatuously anathematized by innocent philosophers, has as its purpose and result to hide all the blemishes that nature has so outrageously scattered over the complexion, and to create an abstract unity of texture and colour in the skin, which unity, like the one produced by tights, immediately approximates the human being to a statue, in other words to a divine or superior being? As for black pencil for eye effects, and rouge for heightening the colour of the upper part of the cheek, although their use comes from the same principle, the need to surpass nature, the result is destined to satisfy a quite opposite need. Red and black represent life, a supernatural, excessive life; black rings round the eyes give them a deeper and stranger look, a more decisive appearance of a window open on the infinite; the rouge which heightens the glow of cheek-bones confers still greater brightness on the pupils, and gives to a lovely woman's face the mysterious passion of a priestess.

Thus, if I have been properly understood, painting the face is not to be used with the vulgar, unavowable intention of imitating the fair face of nature, or competing with youth. It has, moreover, been observed that artifice does not embellish ugliness, and can only serve beauty. Who would dare assign to art the sterile function of imitating nature? Make-up has no need of concealment, no need to avoid discovery; on the contrary, it can go in for display, if not with affectation, at least with a sort of ingenuousness.

I will readily allow people whose ponderous gravity prevents their looking for beauty in its very minutest manifestations to laugh at my reflections, and to condemn their childish solemnity; the austere judgements of such folk worry me not at all; I am content to appeal to the true artists, and to women who have received at birth a spark of that sacred fire they would feign use to light up their whole being.

XII. Women: Honest Ones, and Others

Thus M. G., having undertaken the task of seeking and explaining beauty in modernity, enjoys depicting women in all their finery, their beauty enhanced by every kind of artifice, regardless of what social class they belong to. Moreover, in the whole of his works, just as in the throng and bustle of human life itself, the differences of class and breeding, whatever may be the apparatus of luxury used by the individual, are immediately apparent to the eye of the spectator.

At one moment we see, bathed in the diffused light of the auditorium, a group of young women of the highest social circles, the brightness reflected in their eyes, in their jewellery and on their shoulders, framed in their boxes, resplendent as portraits. Some of them are grave and serious, others fair and feather-brained. Some display their precocious charms with aristocratic nonchalance, others, in all innocence, their boyish busts. All are biting their fans, and have a far-away look in their eyes, or a fixed stare; their postures are theatrical and solemn, like the play or opera they are pretending to listen to.

Another time we see smartly dressed families strolling along the paths of the public gardens, the wives without a care in the world, leaning on the arms of their husbands, whose solid contented air betrays the self-made man, full of money and self-satisfaction. Here the general air of wealth takes the place of haughty distinction. Little girls with match-stick arms and ballooning skirts, looking like little women by their gestures and appearance, are skipping, playing with hoops or pretending to be grown-ups on a visit, performing in the open air the social comedy their parents perform at home.

Or again, we are shown a lower level of society, where chits of actresses from the suburban theatres, proud as peacocks to appear at last in the glare of the footlights, slim, frail, scarcely grown-up, are shaking down, over their virginal, sickly bodies, absurd garments which belong to no period, but are the joy of their owners.

Or, at a café door, we see, leaning against the broad windows lit from without and within, one of those lounging halfwits; his elegance is the work of his tailor, and the distinguished cut of his jib, that of his hairdresser. Beside him, her feet resting on the indispensable footstool, sits his mistress, a great cow of a woman, in whom almost nothing is lacking (but that 'almost nothing' meaning almost everything, in a word: distinction) to make her look like a high-born lady. Like her pretty boyfriend, she has, filling the whole orifice of her little mouth, an outsize cigar. Neither of these two beings has a thought in his head. Can one even be sure they are looking at anything - unless, like Narcissuses of fat-headedness, they are contemplating the crowd, as though it were a river, offering them their own image. In reality they exist much more for the joy of the observer than for their own.

And now we get a glimpse of the amusement halls, your Valentinos, your Casinos, your Prados (the Tivolis, the Idalias, the Follies, the Paphoses of former days), glory-holes with their galleries full of light and hubbub, where the idle, gilded youth can give free rein to their animal spirits. Women, who have exaggerated the latest fashion to the point where its grace of line is spoilt, are ostentatiously sweeping the polished floors with their trains and the points of their shawls, as they come and go, pass and repass, wide-eyed like animals, apparently seeing nothing but in fact observing everything.

Against a background of light as from the infernal regions or of the aurora borealis, red, orange, sulphurous, pink (a pink suggesting a notion of ecstasy in frivolity), sometimes violet (that colour, like dying embers behind a blue curtain, so beloved of canonesses), against such magical backgrounds, with diversified firework effects, we are shown the varied image of the shadier type of beauty, now majestic, now frolicsome, now slim, thin even, now cyclopean, now doll-like and sparkling, now heavy and statuesque. This shady type of beauty either displays an alluring and barbaric form of elegance of her own invention, or she apes, more or less successfully, the simplicity current in higher circles. She moves towards us, glides, dances, sways as though by the weight of her embroidered petticoats, acting as both pendulum and pedestal to her; her eyes flash from under her hat like a portrait in its frame. She is a perfect image of savagery in the midst of civilization. She has a kind of beauty, which comes to her from sin; always lacking spirituality, but at times tinged with fatigue masquerading as melancholy. Her eyes are cast towards the horizon, like a beast of prey: the same wildness, the same indolent detachment, sometimes the same riveted attention. She is a gipsy type, dwelling on the fringes of regular society; the triviality which is the substance of her life of trickery and struggle inevitably betrays itself beneath the surface finery. To her may well be applied the words of the inimitable master La Bruyère: 'Some women have an artificial nobility, which is due to the way they move their eyes or hold their heads, or their manner of walking; and it goes no deeper...'

These reflections about the courtesan may, to a certain extent, be applied to the actress; for she too is a creature of show, an object of public pleasure. But in this case the conquest and the prey are of a nobler, more spiritual kind. The aim is to win public favour, not only by pure physical beauty, but also by talents of the rarest order. If, on the one hand, the actress comes close to the courtesan, on the other she reaches up to the poet. Let us not forget that, apart from natural beauty and even artificial beauty, all beings have the stamp of their trade, a characteristic which may, on the physical level, express itself as ugliness, but also as a kind of professional beauty.

In this extensive gallery of London and Paris life, we meet with the different types of unattached woman, of the woman in revolt, at every level: first the woman of the town in the first flower of her beauty, cultivating, as best she can, patrician airs, proud both of her youth and of her luxury, which expresses such genius and soul as she possesses; we see her delicately holding with two fingers a broad flounce of the satin, the silk or the velvet that floats about her, and showing off her pointed foot, in a shoe whose excessive ornateness would be enough to reveal her for what she is, even without the rather showy emphasis of her dress. Down the ladder a few rungs, and we come upon the slaves confined in those hovels, often enough decorated like cafés; unfortunate creatures these, subjected to the most avaricious tutelage, with nothing they can call their own, not even the eccentric adornments that act as condiment to their beauty. Amongst these, some, in whom an innocent yet monstrous sort of fatuity is only too apparent, carry in their faces and in their eyes, which look you brazenly in the face, the evident joy of being alive (in truth, one wonders why). Sometimes they effortlessly adopt poses, both provocative and dignified, that would be the joy of the most fastidious sculptor, if only the sculptor of today had the courage and the wit to seize hold of nobility everywhere, even in the mire; at others, they show themselves in prostrate attitudes of despairing boredom, or flaunt the indolent postures of café life, with masculine effrontery, and smoking cigarettes to pass away the hours with resigned, oriental fatalism; there they lie, sprawling on sofas, skirts ballooning to front and back double-fanwise, or they balance themselves precariously on stools or chairs; fat, dejected, empty-headed, absurd, their eyes glazed with brandy, and their obstinacy written across their rounded foreheads. We have reached the bottom step of the spiral to find the foemina simplex of the Latin satirist. Nor shall we fail, at some time, to discern through the drink and smoke-laden atmosphere, here the emaciated, feverish cheeks of the consumptive, there the curves of adiposity, that hideous form of health born of sloth. In this foggy chaos, bathed in golden light, undreamed of by indigent chastity, gruesome nymphs and living dolls, whose childlike eyes have sinister flashes, move and contort themselves; whilst behind a counter laden with liqueur bottles lolls a fat shrew, her hair tied up in a dirty silk scarf, which throws on the wall the shadow of its satanic points, thus convincing us that everything dedicated to Evil must be condemned to have horns.

In truth, my purpose in spreading out before the reader's eyes scenes such as these is neither to please nor to scandalize him; in either case, that would have been to show him scant respect. What gives these scenes value and a kind of sanctity is the innumerable thoughts they give rise to, usually austere and gloomy. But if, by chance, some ill-advised person were to seek an opportunity to satisfy an unhealthy curiosity in these works of M. G.'s, scattered as they are here, there and everywhere, let me give him a charitable warning that he will find nothing to excite a prurient imagination. He will find nothing but inevitable vice, in other words the eye of the devil hidden in the shadows, or Messalina's shoulder gleaming under the gaslight; nothing but pure art, in other words the type of beauty peculiar to evil, the beautiful in the horrible. And even, to recall in passing what has previously been said, the general impression conveyed by this great store-house is more full of sadness than fun. What constitutes the specifically beautiful quality of these pictures is their moral fecundity. They are big with suggestion, cruel, harsh suggestion, which my pen, accustomed though it is to struggle with the evocation of plastic images, may have rendered only inadequately.

XIII. Carriages

And so they extend into the distance, these long galleries of 'high life' and 'low life', with innumerable side galleries leading from them. Let us for a moment escape towards a world which, if not pure, is at least more refined; let us breathe perfumes, not more wholesome perhaps, but more delicate. I have already said that M. G.'s brush, like that of Eugène Lami, was wonderfully fitted to depict the glories of dandyism and the elegance of society lionesses. The attitudes of the rich man are well-known to him; he can, with a light stroke of the pen and a sureness of hand which is never at fault, capture that indefinable sense of security evident in eye, gesture and carriage which comes from the monotony of good fortune in the lives of privileged beings. In this particular series of drawings we are presented with sporting, racing, hunting occasions in their innumerable aspects, with horse and carriage exercise in the woods, with proud dames or a delicate miss controlling, with practised hand, steeds of impeccable contour, stylish, glossy, and themselves as capricious as women. For M. G. not only knows all about the horse in general, but applies himself with equal success to expressing the individual beauty of horses. Some drawings depict a meeting, a veritable encampment, of numerous equipages, where, perched up on the cushions, the seats, the boxes, shapely youths and women, attired in the eccentric costumes authorized by the season, are seen watching some solemn turf event, the runners disappearing in the distance; another shows a horseman cantering gracefully alongside an open light four-wheeler, his curveting mount bowing, it might seem, in his own way, whilst the carriage follows an alley streaked with light and shade, at a brisk trot, carrying along a bevy of beauties, cradled as in the gondola of a balloon, lolling on the cushions, lending an inattentive ear to compliments, and lazily enjoying the caresses of the breeze.

Fur or muslin wraps them to the chin and flows in waves over the carriage door. The domestics are stiff and perpendicular, motionless and all alike; as always, they are the monotonous and uncharacterized effigy of servility, precise and disciplined; their whole character consists in having none. In the background, the woods are decked in green or brown, shimmering with light or darkening, according to the hour and the season. Its bowers are full of autumn mists, blue shadows, yellow beams, rose-pink effulgence or thin streaks of lightning flashing through the darkness, like sword thrusts.

If the countless water-colours from the war in the Levant had not shown us M. G.'s powers as a landscape artist, these would certainly suffice to do so. But here no question of the war-torn ground of the Crimea, nor the theatrical shores of the Bosphorus; we are back in the familiar intimate landscapes that encircle any of our big cities with verdure, and where the play of light produces effects that a truly romantic artist cannot disdain.

Another merit which is not unworthy of mention here is the remarkable knowledge of harness and coachwork. M. G. draws and paints a carriage, and every kind of carriage, with the same care and the same ease as a skilled marine artist displays over every kind of ship. All his coachwork is correct, every detail is in its right place, and does not need to be gone over again. In whatever position it is drawn, at whatever speed it may be going, a carriage, like a vessel, derives, from the fact of motion, a mysterious and complex gracefulness which is very difficult to note down in shorthand. The pleasure that the artist's eye gets from it comes apparently from the series of geometrical figures that the object, already so complex in itself, vessel or carriage, describes successively in space.

We are betting on a certainty when we say that in a few years the drawings of M. G. will become precious archives of civilized life. His works will be sought after by discerning collectors, as much as those of Debucourt, of Moreau, of Saint-Aubin, of Carle Vernet, of Lami, of Deveria, of Gavarni, and of all those exquisite artists who, although they have confined themselves to recording what is familiar and pretty, are nonetheless, in their own ways, important historians. Several of them have even sacrificed too much to the 'pretty-pretty', and have sometimes introduced into their compositions a classic style foreign to the subject; several have deliberately rounded the angles, smoothed over the harshness of life, toned down its flashing colours. Less skilful than they, M. G. retains a profound merit, which is all his own; he has deliberately filled a function which other artists disdain, and which a man of the world above all others could carry out. He has gone everywhere in quest of the ephemeral, the fleeting forms of beauty in the life of our day, the characteristic traits of what, with the reader's permission, we have called 'moder-nity'. Often bizarre, violent, excessive, but always full of poetry, he has succeeded, in his drawings, in distilling the bitter or heady flavour of the wine of life.

注　释

〔1〕It is recorded that when Madame Dubarry wanted to avoid receiving the King, she was careful to put on rouge. That was enough; it meant she was closing her door. In beautifying herself she used to put to flight the royal disciple of nature.

The Life and Work of Eugène Delacroix

To the Editor of L'Opinion nationale

Sir,

Once more, and for the last time, I want to pay tribute to the genius of Eugène Delacroix, and I beg you to be good enough to find space in your paper for these few pages, where I shall endeavour to set down as briefly as possible the record of his talent, the reasons for his superiority (which, in my opinion, is not yet properly recognized), and finally some anecdotes and some observations on his life and character.

I had the good fortune when still very young (as early as 1845, if I remember rightly) to have friendly contact with this great man, now dead; and in this relationship, where respect on my side and kindness on his did not exclude mutual confidence and familiarity, I was able to form at leisure extremely accurate notions not only on his method but also on the most intimate qualities of his great soul.

You will not expect me, sir, to embark here on a detailed analysis of the works of Delacroix. Apart from the fact that each of us has done that according to his power, as and when the great painter showed the public the successive productions of his thought, the list of these is so long that, even allowing only a few lines to each of his major works, an analysis of this sort would well nigh fill a volume. Let it suffice for us to give a rapid summary.

His monumental paintings cover the walls of the Salon du Roi at the Chambre des Députés, of the Library of the Chambre des Députés, of the Library of the Luxemburg Palace, of the Galerie d'Apollon at the Louvre, and of the Salon de la Paix at the Hôtel de Ville. These decorative pieces include an enormous mass of allegorical, religious and historical subjects, all of which belong to the highest spheres of human intelligence. As for his so-called easel pictures, his sketches, grisailles, water-colours, etc. - the total reaches an approximate figure of 236.

The great compositions exhibited at different Salons number seventy-seven. I am taking these facts from the catalogue that M. Théophile Silvestre published at the end of his excellent study of Eugène Delacroix in his book entitled Histoire des Peintres Vivants.

I have myself tried more than once to draw up this enormous catalogue; but my patience was invariably exhausted by this unbelievable fecundity, and in the end I gave up the unequal struggle. If M. Théophile Silvestre has made any mistakes, it can be only by omission.

To my mind, sir, the important thing here is simply to look for the characteristic quality of Delacroix's genius and to try and define it; to ask ourselves in what way he differs from his illustrious predecessors, whilst equalling them; and finally to show, in so far as the written word allows, the magical art thanks to which he succeeded in translating the spoken word into plastic images, more full of life and more appropriate than those of any other creator of the same profession: in short, to show what speciality Providence had entrusted to Eugène Delacroix in the historical development of painting.

I

What is Delacroix? What was his role and what his duty in this world? That is the first question we must examine. I shall be brief, and I aim to arrive at immediate conclusions. Flanders has Rubens, Italy has Raphael and Veronese; France has Lebrun, David and Delacroix.

A superficial mind may be shocked, at first sight, by my bracketing together these names, which stand for such different qualities and methods. But a more penetrating spiritual eye will see at once that there is, between them all, a common relationship, a kind of brotherhood or cousinage, stemming from their love of the great, the national, the immense and the universal, a love that has always found expression in so-called decorative painting and in what are known as great machines.

Many others, no doubt, have executed great machines; but those I have named did them in the manner most likely to leave an eternal mark in human memory. Which is the greatest of these men, so diverse in their greatness? Each of us is free to decide that as he pleases, according to whether by nature he is inclined to prefer the prolific, shining, almost jovial abundance of Rubens, or the soft majesty and eurhythmic order of Raphael, the paradisal and land-of-afternoon colours of Veronese, the austere and intense severity of David, or the dramatic and quasiliterary fluency of Lebrun.

None of these men can be replaced; they had a similar aim but used different methods, drawn from their personal natures. Delacroix, the last-comer, expressed with admirable vehemence and fervour what the others had conveyed only incompletely. In doing so, did he perhaps sacrifice other qualities, as his predecessors, for that matter, did before him? It may be so, but that is not the question that claims our attention.

Many others besides me have taken care to emphasize the inevitable consequences of an essentially personal genius; and it could also well be, after all, that the finest expressions of genius elsewhere than in purest heaven - here below, in other words, where even perfection is imperfect - can be achieved only at the price of inevitable sacrifice.

But 'Come, sir!' you will doubtless be saying, 'what then is this mysterious, indefinable something that Delacroix, to the great glory of our age, has communicated better than anyone else?' The answer is: the invisible, the impalpable, reverie, the nerves, the soul; and this he did - pray, sir, take good note of this - without any means other than contour and colour; he did it better than anyone you care to mention; he did it with the perfection of a consummate painter, with the rigour of a subtle writer, the eloquence of a passionate musician. It is one element in the diagnosis of the spiritual climate of our age, be it added, that the arts strive, if not to substitute for one another, at least to lend each other new power and strength, by the help of their own.

Delacroix is the most suggestive of all painters, the one whose works, even those chosen from amongst the minor or inferior ones, give the most food for thought, and recall to mind the greatest sum of poetic feelings and thought already experienced, but believed to have been engulfed for ever in the night of time.

The work of Delacroix sometimes seems to me to be like a mnemonic device of the greatness and the inborn passions of universal man. This peculiar and wholly new merit of M. Delacroix, which enabled him to express simply by contour man's gesture, however violent, and to evoke with colour alone what might be called the atmosphere of the human drama, or the spiritual mood of the creator - this quality, peculiar to him, has always drawn to him the sympathy of all poets; and, if it were legitimate to draw a philosophic proof from a purely material phenomenon, I would ask you to notice, sir, that in the crowd that gathered to pay him the last honours, many more writers could be counted than painters. To put it crudely, the truth is that the latter have never fully understood him.

II

And what, after all, is so surprising about that? Do we not know that the age of the Michelangelos, the Raphaels, the Leonardo da Vincis, yes, and even of the Reynoldses, is long since passed, and that the general intellectual level of artists has gone down markedly? Doubtless it would be unfair to look for philosophers, poets and scientists amongst contemporary artists; but it would be legitimate to expect from them a greater degree of interest than they evince in religion, poetry and the sciences.

Beyond the walls of their studios what do they know? What do they like? What do they want to express? Eugène Delacroix, on the other hand, was, as well as a painter devoted to his art, a man of general culture, in contrast to other modern artists, who are for the most part scarcely more than well-known or obscure daubers, gloomy specialists, be they old or young; craftsmen pure and simple, some of them with the knack of producing academic figures, others fruit, others again cattle. Eugène Delacroix loved everything, could paint everything and was capable of appreciating every kind of talent. His was a mind open to all ideas and to all impressions; he was the most eclectic and impartial lover of all experience.

A great reader, that goes without saying. His readings from the poets left him with awe-inspiring visions, quickly achieving sharpness of outline: ready-made pictures, so to speak. However different he may have been from his master, Guérin, in his method and his colour, he inherited, from the great republican and imperial school, the love of the poets and an indefinably vigorous spirit of rivalry with the written word. David, Guérin and Girodet set their minds aflame by contact with Homer, Virgil, Racine and Ossian. Delacroix was the moving translator of Shakespeare, Dante, Byron and Ariosto. There is an important similarity, and a slight difference.

But let us now, by your leave, Mr Editor, go more deeply into what might be called the teaching of the master, teaching that, for me, arises not only from the successive contemplation of all his works and of several side by side, as one was able to enjoy them at the Universal Exhibition of 1855, but also from many a conversation I had with the artist himself.

III

Delacroix was passionately in love with passion, and coldly determined to seek the means of expressing passion in the most visible manner. In this dual character, be it said in passing, we find the two distinguishing marks of the most substantial geniuses, extreme geniuses, scarcely created to please timorous souls who are easy to satisfy, and find adequate nourishment in flabby, soft, imperfect works. An immense thrust of passion coupled with formidable will-power, such was the man.

And he was fond of repeating: 'Since I consider the impression communicated by nature to the artist as the most important thing to translate, is it not necessary that he should be forearmed with all the quickest means of translation?'

It is clear that, in his eyes, imagination was the most precious gift, the most important faculty, but that this faculty remained powerless and sterile if it did not have at its command a swift technical skill, capable of following the great despotic faculty in its impatient flights of fancy. There was certainly no need for him to stoke up the fires of his imagination, constantly at white heat; but he always found the day too short for the study of the technical means of expression.

To that ceaseless preoccupation must be attributed his unremitting researches into colour and the quality of colours, his interest in problems of chemistry and his discussion with colour manufacturers. In this matter he comes close to Leonardo da Vinci, who was also a prey to these obsessions.

In spite of his admiration for the ardent phenomena of life, never can Eugène Delacroix be confused with that mob of vulgar artists and writers whose myopic intelligence shelters behind that vague and obscure word realism. The first time I saw M. Delacroix, in 1845, I believe it was (how the swift and voracious years flow away!), we talked about many commonplace subjects, in other words, questions vast in scope and yet of the simplest: nature, for example. At this point, sir, I shall, with your permission, quote a passage of my own, for a paraphrase would not be as good as the words I once wrote, almost under the master's dictation: 'Nature is but a dictionary,' he was fond of saying. To understand clearly the full meaning implied in this remark, we must bear in mind the numerous and ordinary uses a dictionary is put to. We look up the meaning of words, the derivation of words, the etymology of words; and, finally, we get from a dictionary all the component parts of sentences and ordered narrative; but no one has ever thought of a dictionary as a composition in the poetic sense of the word. Painters who obey imagination consult their dictionaries in search of elements that fit in with their conceptions; and even then, in arranging them with artistry, they give them a wholly new appearance. Those who have no imagination copy the dictionary, from which arises a very great vice, the vice of banality, to which are particularly exposed those painters whose speciality lies nearest to socalled inanimate nature: the landscape artists, for example, who regard it generally as a triumph if they can conceal their personalities. They contemplate so much that in the end they forget to feel and to think.

'For this great painter, all the areas of art, of which one man selects this one, and another that one, as the most important, were - are, I mean - no more than the most humble handmaids of a unique and superior faculty. If a very neat execution is necessary, that is so that the dream may be very clearly translated; if it should be very quick, that is to ensure that nothing is lost of the extraordinary impression that accompanied the birth of the idea; if the artist should pay attention to the cleanness of his tools, that too is easily understood, since every precaution should be taken to ensure that the execution is nimble and decisive.'

In passing be it added that, never in my life, did I see a palette so minutely and delicately prepared as Delacroix's. It looked like a bouquet of skilfully assorted flowers.

'In such a method, which is essentially logical, all the figures, their grouping in relation to each other, the landscape or interior that provides their background or horizon, their clothes, everything, in short, must serve to shed light on the general idea, and wear its original colour - its livery, so to speak. Just as a dream is bathed in its own appropriate atmosphere, so a conception, become composition, needs to have its being in a setting of colour peculiar to itself. Obviously a given tone will be attributed to some portion or other of the picture, and this then becomes the key, controlling all the others. Everyone knows that yellow, orange and red inspire and represent ideas of joy, wealth, glory and love; but there are thousands of yellow or red atmospheres, and all the other colours will be modified logically and in given proportions by the dominant atmosphere. The art of the colourist is evidently connected, in some respects, with mathematics and music.

'Yet its most delicate operations are the result of a sentiment which long practice has brought to a degree of sureness that defeats description. It will be seen that this great law of overall harmony condemns many garish efforts and raw daubings, even though by the hand of the most illustrious painters. There are some paintings by Rubens that remind us, not only of a coloured firework, but of several fireworks set off on the same ground. The bigger the picture, the broader must be the touches of colour, that goes without saying; but the touches are better not worked into each other; they melt naturally together, at a given distance, by the law of sympathy that brought them together. In this way colour gains in energy and freshness.

'A good picture, faithful and worthy of the dreams that gave it birth, must be created like a world. Just as the creation, as we see it, is the result of several creations, the earlier ones always being completed by the later, so a harmonically fashioned picture consists of a series of superimposed pictures, each fresh surface giving added reality to the dream, and raising it by one degree towards perfection. In complete contrast, I remember seeing, in the studios of Paul Delaroche and Horace Vernet, enormous canvases, not broadly sketched in, but begun piecemeal, in other words, completely finished in certain areas whilst others existed only in a black or white outline. This sort of product could be compared to a purely manual type of work, to which is assigned the job of covering a given area in a given time, or to a long road divided into a large number of stages. As soon as one stage has been completed, that is the end of that, and when the road has been followed throughout its whole length, the artist is delivered of his picture.

'All these precepts are, of course, modified, more or less, by the different temperaments of the artists. But I am convinced that the foregoing is the surest method for men with rich imaginations. It follows that too great deviations from the method in question are proof that an abnormal and unjustified importance is being attributed to some secondary aspect of art.

'I am not afraid of its being said that it is absurd to imagine a single system of teaching being applied to a crowd of different individuals. For it is evident that systems of rhetoric and prosody are not arbitrarily invented forms of tyranny, but collections of rules demanded by the very structure of a man's spiritual being. Nor have systems of rhetoric and prosody ever prevented originality from showing itself clearly. The contrary, namely that they have helped the flowering of originality, would be infinitely truer.

'For the sake of brevity, I must omit a number of corollaries deriving from the main principle, which, so to speak, contains within itself the whole code of true aesthetics, and may be expressed as follows: the whole visible universe is nothing but a storehouse of images and signs, to which man's imagination will assign a place and relative value; it is a kind of pasture for the imagination to digest and transform. All the faculties of the human soul must be subordinated to the imagination, which puts them all under contribution at once. Just as a good knowledge of the dictionary does not necessarily imply a knowledge of the art of composition, and the art of composition itself does not imply the gift of universal imagination, so a good painter may well not be a great painter, but a great painter is of necessity a skilful painter, because a universal imagination comprises the understanding of all technical means and the desire to acquire them.

'From the ideas I have just explained to the best of my ability (and how many more things there would be to say, particularly on the areas of common ground between the arts and the similarities between their methods), it is evident that the immense group of artists, or, in other words, of men dedicated to artistic expression, may be divided into two very distinct camps. In one, we have those who call themselves "realists", a word with a double meaning, and the sense of which is not precisely determined; to bring out more clearly their error, we will call them "positivists". The "positivist" says: "I want to represent things as they are, or as they would be on the assumption that I did not exist." The universe without man. In the other camp, there are the imaginative ones who say: "I want to illuminate things with my mind and cast its reflection on other minds." Although both these methods, which are diametrically opposed, may enhance or diminish any subject, from a religious scene to the most modest landscape, yet the imaginative man must usually have come to the fore in religious painting and in fantasy, whereas genre paintings, so-called, and landscape must, on the face of it, have offered vast resources to lazy minds not easily stimulated...

'Delacroix's imagination! Here was an imagination that never feared to scale the difficult heights of religion; heaven belongs to it, just as hell does, and war, and Olympus and pleasure. He surely is the archetype of the painter-poet! He surely is one of the rare elect, and the breadth of his mind brings religion into its domain. His imagination, as fiercely bright as a mortuary chapel, is alight with every shade of flame and crimson. All the grief in the Passion enthrals him; all the splendours in the Church fill him with light. Onto his inspired canvases he pours blood, light and darkness, by turns. I believe he would gladly add his own natural magnificence to the majesty of the Gospel, as an extra offering.

'I remember seeing a little Annonciation by Delacroix, where the angel, messenger to Mary, was not alone but ceremoniously escorted by two other angels, and the impact of this heavenly company was powerful and full of charm. One of his early paintings, Le Christ aux Oliviers ("Lord, take thou this cup from me"), is suffused with feminine tenderness and poetic suavity. The suffering and the majesty which resound so loudly in religion always awaken an echo in his mind.'

And still more recently, with reference to the Chapel of the Holy Angels at St Sulpice (Héliodore, chassé du Temple and La Lutte de Jacob avec l'Ange), his last great work, so inanely criticized, I said: 'Never, not even in the Clémence de Trajan, not even in L'Entrée des Croisés à Constantinople, has Delacroix displayed a sense of colour more splendidly and more learnedly supernatural; never has he executed a drawing more deliberately epic. I am well aware that some people, stonemasons, no doubt, architects perhaps, have pronounced the word decadence with reference to this last work. This is the place for me to recall that the great masters, poets or painters, Hugo or Delacroix, are always several years ahead of their timid admirers.

'In relation to genius the public are like a clock that is losing. Amongst perceptive people, who does not understand that the first picture by the Master contained all the others in embryo? But that he should constantly perfect his natural gifts, that he should sharpen them with care, draw new effects from them, that he should himself drive his nature to the utmost, that is inevitable, inescapable, and praiseworthy. The principal feature of Delacroix's genius is precisely that it knows not decadence; it displays only progress. But his original qualities were so powerful and so rich, and they made such a vigorous impact on even the most commonplace minds, that the latter are insensitive to his daily progress; only informed minds can perceive it clearly.

'I referred just now to the remarks of certain masons. For me, the word describes that class of gross materialistic minds (their number is legion) that take an appreciative interest in objects only by their contour or worse still on a three-dimensional basis: breadth, length and depth, just as savages or peasants do. I have often heard people of that sort draw up a hierarchy of qualities, which was totally unintelligible to me; they would maintain, for example, that the faculty that enables this man to create an exact contour or that man a contour of supernatural beauty is superior to the faculty that can assemble colours in an enchanting manner. According to these people colour has no power to dream, to think or speak. It would appear that when I contemplate the works of those men especially known as colourists, I am giving myself up to a pleasure that is not of a noble kind; for twopence they would stamp me as a materialist, reserving for themselves the aristocratic epithet of spiritualists.

'These shallow minds do not reflect that the two faculties can never be entirely separated and that both are the result of an original seed carefully cultivated. External nature does no more than provide the artist with an ever-recurring chance of cultivating the seed; nature is no more than an uncoordinated mass of material that the artist is invited to assemble and put in order, an incitamentum, an alarm-clock for the slumbering faculties. To speak with precision, there is in nature neither line nor colour. It is man that creates line and colour. Both are abstractions drawing their equal dignity from the same origin.

'As a child, a draughtsman born will see in nature, whether still or moving, a number of sinuous shapes from which he gets some pleasure and which he enjoys recording by lines on paper, accentuating or reducing as the spirit moves him their inflections. In this way he learns how to produce curves, elegance and character in drawing. Now let us imagine the case of a child destined to perfect that part of art called colour: it is from the collision or happy union of two tones and the pleasure he gets from it that he will derive the inexhaustible knowledge of tone combinations. In both cases nature has acted exclusively as a stimulus.

'Both line and colour arouse thought and induce reverie; the pleasures that flow from these are different in kind, but perfectly equal and absolutely independent of the subject of the picture.

'A picture by Delacroix, placed too far away for you to be able to assess the merits of the contours or the greater or lesser dramatic quality of the subject, offers even at that distance a supernatural pleasure. It is as though a magical atmosphere has moved towards you and is enveloping you. This impression, gloomy and yet delightful, luminous but calm, and planted for ever in your memory, is the proof of the genuine, the perfect colourist. Nor will the act of analysing the subject when you come closer take anything away from this initial pleasure, or add anything to it, its source being elsewhere and far removed from any defined thought.

'I can reverse the example. A well-drawn figure inspires in you a pleasure that is quite foreign to the subject. Be it voluptuous or frightening, this figure owes its charm exclusively to the pattern it describes in space. The limbs of a martyr being flayed alive, or the body of a nymph in a swoon, provided they are skilfully drawn, offer a species of pleasure in which the nature of the subject counts for nothing; if it were otherwise for you, you would oblige me to write you down as a torturer or an amorist.

'But alas! what is the good, what is the good of for ever repeating these useless truths?'

Yet perhaps, sir, your readers will value all this rhetoric less than the details I am myself impatient to give them on the personality and the way of life of our lamented great painter.

IV

It is particularly in the writings of Eugène Delacroix that the duality of nature I was referring to emerges. Many people, as you yourself know, sir, were surprised at the wisdom of his written opinions and the moderation of his style, a matter of regret for some people, for others a reason for approval. Les Variations du beau, the studies on Poussin, Prud'hon and Charlet, and the other pieces published either in L'Artiste, which then belonged to M. Ricourt, or even in the Revue des Deux Mondes, only serve to confirm this dual character of great artists, which leads them, as critics, to praise and analyse with special relish the qualities which they stand in most need of as creative artists and which are the antithesis of those they possess in abundance. If Eugène Delacroix had praised and commended the things we particularly admire in him, his violence, the decisive gesture, the tumultuousness of his composition, the magic of his colour, that in truth would have been good reason for astonishment. Why look for the things we possess superabundantly, and how may we avoid the urge to extol the things that seem rarer to us and more difficult to acquire? We shall always see the same phenomenon emerge, Mr Editor, in creative geniuses, whether painters or writers, every time they apply their faculties to criticism. At the time of the great struggle between the two schools, the classic and the romantic, the simpletons gaped in surprise when they heard Eugène Delacroix constantly vaunting Racine, La Fontaine and Boileau. I know a poet, naturally given to storm and stress, who goes into prolonged ecstasy over a line of Malherbe, symmetrical and musically four-square.

Moreover, however wise, sensible, and clearly defined in expression and intention the great painter's literary fragments may seem to us, it would be absurd for us to think they were written easily and with the same sureness of attack as his brush displays. He was as confident of writing what he thought on canvas as he was worried at his inability to paint his thought on paper. 'The pen', he was fond of saying, 'is not my tool; I feel that I am thinking right, but the need for ordered argument, which I am forced to observe, puts me off. Would you believe it, but the fact of having to write a page of text gives me a migraine?' This awkwardness, which comes from lack of practice, accounts for certain rather threadbare, rather poncif, and even First Empire expressions that fell too often from a pen otherwise distinguished.

The most obviously characteristic features of Delacroix's style are conciseness, and a kind of intensity without ostentation, the usual type of thing arising from concentrating the whole of one's spiritual powers on a given point. 'The hero is he who is immovably centred,' says Emerson, the transatlantic moralist, who may have the reputation of being the leader of the boring Bostonian school, but who nonetheless has a certain touch of Seneca about him, which can well be a spur to meditation. 'The hero is he who is immovably centred' - the maxim that the leader of American 'transcendentalism' applies to the conduct of life and to the sphere of business - may equally well be applied to the domain of poetry and art. One could just as well say: 'The hero of literature, the true writer, in other words, is he who is immovably centred.' You will not therefore be surprised to learn, sir, that Delacroix had a very pronounced sympathy for concise and concentrated writers, those whose prose, little encumbered with ornaments of style, appears to imitate the quick movement of thought, and whose sentences have the decisiveness of a gesture, Montesquieu, for example. I can give you a curious example of this fruitful and poetic brevity. No doubt you have read, as I have, a very interesting and very fine study by M. Paul de Saint-Victor, which appeared recently in La Presse, on the ceiling of the Galerie d'Apollon. The various conceptions of the flood, the way the legends about the deluge should be interpreted, the inner meaning of the scenes and actions that go to make up the whole of this marvellous piece of painting, nothing has been forgotten; and the painting itself is minutely described in that charming style, as witty as it is colourful, of which the author has given us so many examples. Yet the whole thing will leave only a formless shadow of itself in our memories, something like the very pale light of a photographic enlargement. Compare this lengthy passage with the following few lines, to my mind much more vigorous and more conducive to creating a mental picture, even if one were to suppose that the picture they sum up did not exist. I am simply giving what is said in the programme distributed by M. Delacroix to his friends when he invited them to come and see the work in question:

Apollo, conqueror of the serpent Python

Mounted on his chariot, the god has already shot a number of his arrows; his sister Diana behind him, in full cry, offers him her quiver. The hideous reptile, bleeding from wounds already inflicted by the arrows of the god of heat and life, is seen in its death throes, writhing with impotent rage, and enveloped in a fiery haze. The waters of the deluge are beginning to recede, leaving the corpses of men and animals behind them on the mountain tops, or carrying them away. The gods are indignant at the sight of the earth delivered over to ill-shapen monsters, foul spawn of primeval slime. They have armed themselves, as Apollo has done; Minerva and Mercury are seen springing forward to exterminate them, that eternal wisdom may in time repeople the solitude of the universe. Hercules is crushing them with his club; Vulcan, the god of fire, is driving night and its fetid vapours before him, while Boreas and the Zephyrs dry up the waters with their breath and scatter the remnants of the clouds. The nymphs of the rivers and the streams have returned to their withy beds and their urn, still soiled with mire and debris. A number of shyer divinities are watching from a distance this struggle between the gods and the elements. Meanwhile, from highest heaven, Victory is shown coming down to crown Apollo victor, and Iris, messenger of the gods, unfurls in the soft air her veil, symbol of light's triumph over darkness and the rebellion of the waters.

I know the reader will have to imagine a great deal and collaborate, so to speak, with the author of the explanatory note; but do you honestly think, sir, that my admiration for the painter has transformed me into a visionary in this case, and that I am wholly wrong in claiming to see here the traces of aristocratic habits, acquired by reading good books, and of that precision of thought which has enabled society folk, soldiers, adventurers and even courtiers to write, with careless unconcern, mighty fine books, which we professional writers cannot help admiring?

V

Eugène Delacroix was a strange mixture of scepticism, courtesy, dandyism, fiery will, guile, despotism, and, withal, of a species of particular kindness and restrained tenderness that always accompanies genius. His father belonged to that race of strong men, the last of whom we knew in our childhood: some of them were fervent apostles of Jean-Jacques, others were convinced disciples of Voltaire, but all of them took part with equal determination in the French Revolution; and their survivors, Jacobins or left-wing progressives, rallied in perfect good faith (it is important to remember) to the policies of Bonaparte.

Eugène Delacroix always retained traces of this revolutionary background. It may be said of him, as of Stendhal, that he was frightened to death of being taken in. Sceptical and aristocratic as he was, his experience of passion and the supernatural came to him only through his enforced acquaintance with reverie. A hater of the masses, he thought of them only as iconoclasts, and the violence suffered at their hands by some of his own works in 1848 was scarcely calculated to convert him to the political sentimentality of our times. In his bearing, manners and opinions, there was even something in him reminiscent of Victor Jacquemont. I know that the comparison is slightly unflattering, and I therefore intend it to be taken only with reserve. There was, in Jacquemont, a suggestion of a middle-class wit, with a chip on his shoulder, and a waggishness that was as ready to fool the priests of Brahma as those of Jesus Christ. Delacroix, guided by the good taste always inherent in genius, could never have stooped to such low tricks. My comparison, therefore, refers only to the spirit of cautiousness and moderation that marks them both. In the same way, the hereditary traits which the eighteenth century had left in his nature seemed to be borrowed particularly from that class as far removed from utopians as from madmen, the class of polite sceptics, the victors and survivors, who, generally, derived from Voltaire, rather than Jean-Jacques. Thus at first sight, Eugène Delacroix appeared simply as a man of the 'Enlightenment' in the best sense of the word, a perfect gentleman without prejudices and without passions. Only by cultivating his society more assiduously could one penetrate the veneer, and become aware of the deeper recesses of his soul. A man to whom he could more legitimately be compared, in his outward bearing and manners, is M. Mérimée. He had the same apparent coldness, slightly affected, the same icy mantle covering modest sensitiveness and an ardent passion for what is good and beautiful; under the same simulated egoism was to be found the same devotion to personal friends and dearly held ideas.

There was something of the recluse in Eugène Delacroix; that was the most precious side of his nature, the side entirely dedicated to giving pictorial form to his dreams, and to the worship of his art. There was something in him of the society man; that part of him was destined to hide the other, and to allay any resentment it could cause. I believe it to have been one of the great preoccupations of his life to conceal the waves of anger welling up in his heart, and to appear not to be a man of genius. His spirit of domination, which was perfectly legitimate, inevitable moreover, had almost disappeared under the cloak of countless kindnesses. One could have compared him to the crater of a volcano artistically hidden under a bouquet of flowers.

Another point of resemblance with Stendhal was his liking for simple formulas, brief maxims, for the good conduct of life. Like all people whose liking for method is all the greater because their ardent and sensitive temperament seems to turn them away from it, Delacroix liked fashioning those little catechisms of practical morality, which nit-wits and layabouts without an aim in life are likely to attribute disdainfully to M. de la Palisse, but which genius does not despise because genius is related to simplicity; sound, strong, simple, hard maxims that are a breast-plate and shield for the man driven by genius into an everlasting battle.

Need I tell you that the same spirit of unshakeable and disdainful wisdom inspired the opinions of M. Delacroix in political matters? He believed that nothing changes, although everything appears to change, and that certain climacteric periods in the history of nations invariably bring back analogous phenomena. In fact, his thought in this sort of question came very close, especially in its aspects of cold and distressing resignation, to the thought of a historian I, for my part, have a great respect for, and whom you, sir, who are so familiar with these arguments and can appreciate talent even when it contradicts you, have surely been constrained to admire more than once. I refer to M. Ferrari, the subtle and learned author of the Histoire de la Raison d'État. Inevitably, any talker who, in the presence of M. Delacroix, let himself go in childish utopian enthusiasms very soon felt the effect of his bitter laugh, informed with sarcastic pity; and if, incautiously, one were, in his hearing, to launch the grand chimera of modern times, the monster-balloon of perfectibility and indefinite progress, he was fond of asking: 'Where then are your Phidiases? Where are your Raphaels?'

You may be sure, on the other hand, that M. Delacroix's robust good sense in no way detracted from his charm of manner. This vigorous incredulity, this refusal to be taken in, gave a kind of Byronic flavour to his conversation, so full of poetry and colour. He had also, drawn from within himself much more than derived from his long experience of society - from himself, that is his genius, and from the knowledge of his genius - a self-confidence, a wonderful ease of manner, and with them a politeness that emitted, like a prism, every shade from the most cordial bonhomie to the most irreproachable brush-off. He had a good twenty ways of saying 'Mon cher monsieur', in which a practised ear could detect a remarkable scale of feelings. For after all, I must add, since the fact strikes me as another reason for praise, Eugène Delacroix, although a man of genius, or because he was a complete man of genius, had much of the dandy about him. He himself admitted that, in his youth, he had indulged with joy in all the material vanities of dandyism, and, laughing at himself but not without a suspicion of self-glorification, told how, with the help of his friend Bonington, he had worked hard to implant in the fashionable younger set the taste for English cut in footwear and clothes. This detail, I presume, will not seem out of place to you; for no memories are superfluous when we are portraying the nature of certain men.

I have told you that what particularly struck the attentive observer was the natural part of Delacroix's soul, in spite of the obscuring veil cast over it by our refined way of life. He was full of energy, but an energy that came from the nerves and the will; for physically he was frail and delicate. The tiger, shadowing his prey, has less glint in his eyes and impatient twitching of his muscles than our great painter showed, when his whole soul was pinpointed on an idea, or wanted to take possession of adream. The physical character of his features, his Peruvian or Malaysian complexion, his big dark eyes, which seemed to get smaller as they blinked in concentration, appeared to be sipping at the light, his mass of glossy hair, his obstinate brow, his tight lips, to which the constant tension of his will imparted a cruel expression, his whole person, in fact, conveyed the idea of an exotic origin. More than once, as I stood looking at him, there came into my mind a vision of the ancient rulers of Mexico, of Montezuma, whose hand, practised in sacrificial rites, could dispatch, in the space of a single day, three thousand human creatures on the pyramidal altar of the sun, or one of the Hindu princes who, in the splendours of the most glorious festivals, have, in the depths of their eyes, a look of unsatisfied greed and an inexplicable nostalgia, something that might be the memory of things unknown and yearning for them. Pray note that the general tonality of Delacroix's paintings also conforms to the colour appropriate to eastern landscapes and interiors, and that it produces an impression analogous to that felt in tropical lands, where a vast diffusion of light creates, for the sensitive eye, a general effect that is quasicrepuscular in spite of the intensity of local tones. The morality of his works, if in fact one may legitimately speak of morality in painting, also has a visible connection with Moloch; nothing in his work that does not tell of desolation, massacres, fire; everything bears witness against the everlasting and incorrigible barbarity of man; cities set alight and smoking, murder and rape, children thrown under the horses' hooves, or stabbed by mothers unhinged with horror; the whole work, I repeat, is like a terrible hymn composed in honour of fate and inescapable grief. Sometimes he found it possible to apply his brush to the expression of tender and voluptuous feelings, for he certainly did not lack tenderness; but there too the incurable sense of bitterness was present in strong degree, whilst carefree joy, the usual companion of simple pleasure, was absent. Only once, I think, did he make a tentative incursion into drollery and buffoonery, and, as though he had guessed that to be beyond and beneath his nature, he never came back to it.

VI

I know a number of people who have the right to say Odi profanum vulgus; but which of them can add triumphantly et arceo [I hate the vulgar crowd ... and keep at a distance]? Handshakes, too freely given, debase the character. If ever a man had an 'ivory tower', well defended by bars and bolts, it was Eugène Delacroix. Who more than he has loved his 'ivory tower', his privacy, in other words? I believe he would willingly have armed it with cannon, and removed it to the depth of a forest or to the top of an inaccessible rock. Who more than he has loved his home, both sanctuary and den? Others may seek privacy for the sake of debauchery; he sought it for the sake of inspiration, and he indulged in veritable orgies, of work. 'The one prudence in life is concentration; the one evil is dissipation,' says the American philosopher we have already quoted.

M. Delacroix could have been the author of that maxim; in any case he certainly practised it with austerity. He was too much a man of society not to despise society; and the efforts he made to avoid being too visibly himself drove him naturally to enjoy our society most. 'Our' does not imply merely the humble author of these lines; but also some others, young or old, journalists, poets, musicians, amongst whom he could freely relax and let himself go.

In his delightful monograph study on Chopin, Liszt numbers Delacroix amongst the musician-poet's most frequent visitors, and says that he loved to fall into deep reverie at the sound of that delicate and passionate music, which evokes a brightly coloured bird, hovering over the horrors of a bottomless pit.

And so it came about that, owing to our very genuine admiration, we were admitted, though still very young at the time, into that well-guarded studio, where the temperature, despite our inclement climate, was equatorial, and where the first thing that struck the visitor's eye was the air of restrained solemnity, and that austerity peculiar to the old school. Exactly similar were the studios, seen in our childhood, of the former rivals of David, men of touching heroism, long since gone. To penetrate this retreat was to feel at once that it could not be the abode of a frivolous mind excited by a thousand incoherent whims.

No rusty armour, no Malayan kukris, no old Gothic ironwork, no trinkets, no old clothes, no bric-à-brac, nothing that reveals in its owner a liking for the latest trifle, or for wandering away in childish dreaming. A wonderful portrait by Jordaens, which he had unearthed heaven knows where, a few studies, and a number of copies, done by the master himself, were all the decoration to be seen in this vast studio, where reigned a spirit of reflection, bathed in a soft, peaceful light.

These copies will probably be seen at the sale of Delacroix's drawings and pictures due to take place, so I am told, next January. He had two very distinct manners in copying. One, the free and broad, was compounded of fidelity and infidelity, and into it he put a great deal of himself. From this manner a bastard and delightful product emerged, throwing the mind into an agreeable state of uncertainty. It is in this paradoxical guise that I first saw a copy of the Miracles de Saint Benoît by Rubens. In his other manner, Delacroix becomes his model's most obedient and humble slave, and he achieved an exactness of imitation that those people may well doubt who have not seen these miracles. Such, for example, are the copies made of two heads by Raphael in the Louvre, where the expression, the style and manner are imitated with such perfect naturalness that nothing could be easier than to take the originals for the translations and vice versa.

After a luncheon lighter than an Arab's, and having arranged the colours on his palette with as much care as a flower girl or a cloth vendor, Delacroix would strive once more to recapture the interrupted flow of ideas; but before launching into his stormy work, he would often experience a feeling of languor or of terror, or of exasperation that recalls the pythoness fleeing the presence of the God, or Jean-Jacques Rousseau frittering his time away or tidying up papers and books for a whole hour before putting pen to paper. But once the fascination had gripped the artist, he would stop only when overcome by physical fatigue.

One day as we were discussing a matter of abiding interest to artists and writers, namely the tonic effect of work and the conduct of life, he said to me: 'Years ago, when I was young, I could settle down to work only when I had some pleasure in prospect for the evening. Some music, or dancing, or any other sort of entertainment. But nowadays I am no longer like a schoolboy; I can work without ceasing and without any hope of reward. Moreover,' he added, 'if only you knew how broad-minded and easy to please hard work makes one when it comes to pleasures! The man who has filled his working day to his own satisfaction will be quite happy in the company of the local street porter, playing cards with him!'

This remark made me think of Machiavelli playing at dice with the peasants. One day, a Sunday, I caught sight of Delacroix in the Louvre; with him was his old maid, the one who looked after him so devotedly, and served him for thirty years. He, the man of fashion, the dandy, the scholar, was not at all above showing and explaining the mysteries of Assyrian sculpture to this worthy woman, who, moreover, was listening to him with unaffected attention. The image of Machiavelli and the memory of my conversation years before at once came into my mind.

The truth is that in his last years, all the things we commonly call pleasure had disappeared from his life. One pleasure only, harsh, demanding, terrible, had replaced them all: work, which by then was no longer merely a passion but could well have been called a craving.

After devoting all the hours of daylight to painting, either in his studio or on the scaffoldings to which his big decorative work called him, Delacroix still found strength in his love of art, and he would have felt his day had been badly filled if the evening hours at his fireside had not been used, by the light of the lamp, to draw, to cover his paper with dreams, with projects, with figures he had chanced to catch a glimpse of in the daily round, sometimes to copy the drawings of other artists with temperaments wholly opposed to his; for he had a passion for notes and sketches, and used to busy himself with them wherever he might be. For quite a long time, he had a habit of drawing at the houses of friends with whom he was spending the evening. That is how M. Villot comes to own quite a number of excellent drawings from this prolific pen.

He once said to a young man I know: 'If you have not got the knack of making a sketch of a man who has thrown himself out of the window whilst he is falling from the fourth storey to the ground, you will never be able to go in for the big stuff.' I perceive in that colossal hyperbole the central preoccupation of his whole life, which, as is well known, was to execute a drawing with enough speed and enough exactness to let no particle evaporate of the action's intensity or of the idea.

As many other people have been able to observe, Delacroix was fond of conversation. But the funny thing is that he was suspicious of conversation, as if it were a kind of debauchery, a sort of dissipation in which he ran the risk of wasting his strength. His first words when you went to see him at his studio were: 'We won't have a talk this morning, if you agree? Or else only a very short one.'

And then he would talk for three hours on end. His conversation was startling, subtle but full of facts, memories and anecdotes: in short, full of nourishment.

When he was roused by contradiction, he would withdraw momentarily, and then, instead of delivering a frontal attack on his adversary, a manoeuvre that carries the danger of introducing the brutality of platform oratory into the skirmishes of the drawing-room, he would sport for a while with his opponent, and then return to the attack with a whole lot of unexpected arguments and facts. It was the characteristic talk of a man delighting in conflict, but a slave to courtesy of a wily kind, yielding by design, full of unexpected ruses in flight and attack.

In the intimacy of his studio, he would willingly let himself go to the point of confiding his opinion about living painters, and it was particularly on those occasions that we often had a chance to admire the generosity of genius, which stems perhaps from a particular form of simplicity, or from a capacity to enjoy things easily.

He had an astonishing weakness for Decamps, much out of favour today, but who doubtless still reigned over Delacroix's mind by the power of memory. The same applies to Charlet. He once summoned me to his house for the express purpose of hauling me over the coals about a disrespectful article I had been guilty of on that spoilt child of chauvinism. In vain did I try to explain that it was not the Charlet of the earlier manner that I had been attacking, but the Charlet of the later decadent period: not the noble historian of Napoleon's veterans but the tavern wit. I never succeeded in getting myself forgiven.

He admired Ingres for certain parts of his work, and, to be sure, he needed a powerful critical faculty to admire by force of reason what he must have rejected by temperament. He even went so far as to copy with care the photographs of some of those pencil portraits done with such minute delicacy, where the hard and penetrating talent of M. Ingres, which gains in skill the more circumscribed it is, is to be seen at its best.

The horrible colour tones of Horace Vernet did not prevent Delacroix from feeling the artist's natural strength, which gives life to most of his pictures; and he used to find surprising expressions of praise for this bubbling and indefatigable energy. His admiration for Meissonier went a little too far. He had acquired almost by violence the preparatory drawings for the composition called La Barricade, the best picture by Meissonier, whose talent, moreover, expresses itself much more vigorously in pencil than with the brush. Of Meissonier he often used to say, as though thinking anxiously of the future: 'After all, of all of us, he is the most certain to survive!' Is it not strange to see the author of such great works casting an envious eye on someone who excels only in little ones?

The only man whose name had the power to draw a few coarse epithets from those aristocratic lips was Paul Delaroche. For the works of that painter he could certainly find no excuse whatever, and he had an ineradicable recollection of what he had suffered at the sight of all that grimy, sour painting, done 'with ink and boot polish', as Théophile Gautier once said.

But the man he liked to choose particularly for launching into lengthy discussions with was the man who was the least like him in talent as in ideas, his diametrical opposite, whose brain, though clouded by the smoky skies of his native town, contains a host of admirable things. I refer to M. Paul Chenavard.

The abstruse theories of this painter-philosopher from Lyons made Delacroix smile, and the abstract principle-chasing pedagogue, on his side, looked upon the sensuous joys of pure painting as frivolous, not to say guilty things. But however distant from each other - and even because of that distance - they liked to come together, and, like two ships locked together by grappling irons, they could no longer part company. Both, moreover, being highly cultivated and endowed with great sociability, they met on the common ground of scholarship. That, as is well known, is not the quality for which artists usually shine.

Chenavard was therefore for Delacroix a great stand-by. It was a real pleasure to see them fighting it out in harmless warfare, the words of the one tramping heavily along like an elephant in full panoply of war, the words of the other as vibrant, as pointed and flexible as a fencing foil. In the last hours of his life, our great painter expressed the wish to shake his friendly gainsayer by the hand. But the latter was far away at the time.

VII

Sentimental and affected women may perhaps be shocked to learn that, like Michelangelo (pray recall the ending of one of his sonnets: 'Sculpture! Divine sculpture, thou art my only love!'), Delacroix had made of painting his unique muse, his mistress, his sole and sufficient pleasure.

No doubt women had been a major preoccupation in the stormy hours of his youth. Who has not sacrificed too much at the altar of this dangerous idol? And who does not know that it is just those men who have served the idol best who complain of her most? But already long before his end he had cut women out of his life. Had he been a Moslem, he would perhaps not have driven her out of his mosque, but in his inability to understand what sort of dialogue she could have with Allah, he would have felt surprised to see her enter it.

In this matter, as in many others, oriental ideas were coming to take a lively and despotic hold of him. He looked upon woman as an object of art, delightful and made to excite the mind, but an unruly and disturbing object if we allow her to cross the threshold of our hearts, devouring greedily our time and strength.

I remember once in some public place, as I was pointing out to him a woman's face of uncommon beauty and melancholy expression, he condescended to admire its beauty, but said to me, with that characteristic laugh of his: 'How can you think that a woman could be melancholy?' thereby insinuating, no doubt, that women lack an essential something to be capable of experiencing the sentiment of melancholy.

That, unfortunately, is a most unflattering theory, and, for my part, I would not wish to commend opinions of a kind defamatory to a sex that has so often shown ardent virtues. But who will not agree that it is a theory full of caution; that talent cannot be too cautious in a world where booby-traps abound; and that a man of genius has the privilege of holding certain opinions (provided they do not threaten public order) which would scandalize us in the citizen pure and simple, or the ordinary father of a family.

I must add, at the risk of casting a shadow over his memory, at least in the opinion of wistful souls, that he showed no greater tenderness for children either. In his mind, children always had jam on their fingers (which dirties canvases and paper) or were for ever beating drums (which disturbs meditation), or were as incendiary, and full of dangerous animal spirits, as monkeys.

'I remember well,' he used sometimes to say, 'that when I was a child I was a little monster. The understanding of duty is acquired only very slowly; and only through suffering, punishment and the developing exercise of reason does man diminish, little by little, his natural wickedness.'

Thus, by simple good sense, he was coming back towards the Catholic idea. For it may be said that children in general, and relatively to the grown man in general, are much closer to original sin.

VIII

It was as though Delacroix had treasured up all his sensibility, which was manly and deep, for the austere feeling of friendship. There are some people who take easily to the first-comer; others allow the divine faculty to operate only on great occasions. The famous man I am speaking to you about with so much pleasure may not have liked being bothered with little things, but he could be helpful, courageous, ardent when important matters were at stake. Those who have known him well have had numerous opportunities of appreciating his wholly English sense of loyalty, punctiliousness and dependability, in social relationships. If he was demanding towards others, he was no less strict with himself.

It is only with sadness and ill-humour that I come to say a few words of certain accusations levelled against Eugène Delacroix. I have heard people tax him with selfishness and even avarice. Pray note, sir, that this reproach is always made, by innumerable hordes of mediocrities, against those who take the trouble to administer their generosity with no less care than their friendship.

Delacroix was very careful with his money; that was the only way for him to be very generous on occasion. I could give several examples of that, but I would hesitate to do it without his authority and that of the people who have had good cause to be glad of him.

Observe too that for many years his paintings fetched poor prices, and that his decorative works swallowed nearly the whole of his salary, when he was not actually out of pocket. He gave many proofs of his own disdain for money when impecunious artists showed their desire to possess one or other of his works. Then, like physicians of a liberal and generous temper, who sometimes insist on being paid for their services and at other times give them for nothing, he would make a present of his pictures or let them go at a knock-down figure.

And finally, sir, let us emphasize that the superior man, more than any other, has to take particular care to defend himself. It is no exaggeration to say that the whole of society is at war with him. More than once we have been able to see how true that is. His politeness is called coldness; his irony, however subdued, becomes spite; his economy, meanness. But if, on the other hand, the unfortunate man shows himself to be improvident, then, far from showing pity for him, society will say: 'Serve him right; his penury is a punishment for his prodigality.'

I can confidently say that in matters of money and economy Delacroix entirely shared Stendhal's opinion, which reconciled greatness with prudence.

'The intelligent man,' the latter used to say, 'should apply himself to acquiring what is strictly necessary to avoid his having to depend on anybody' (in Stendhal's day, this meant an annual income of 6,000 francs); 'but if, having achieved that degree of security, he wastes time in increasing his fortune, the man's a scoundrel.'

The pursuit of what is necessary, disdain for what is superfluous, that is the conduct of a wise man and a stoic.

One of the great preoccupations of our painter in his latter days, was the thought of what posterity's verdict on him would be, and of the uncertain durability of his works. At one moment his lively imagination would catch fire at the thought of immortal glory; at another, he would speak bitterly of the fragility of canvases and colours. At other times again, he would refer with envy to the old masters, nearly all of whom had had the luck to be translated by skilful engravers who had understood how to adapt their own needles and burins to the nature of the master's talent, and he ardently deplored the fact that he had not found his translator. This friability of the painted work of art, compared with the solidity of the printed work, was one of his habitual themes of conversation.

When this man, who was so frail and so stubborn, so highly strung and so stout-hearted, this man unique in the annals of European art, the sickly, the chilly artist, for ever dreaming of covering great walls with his powerful conceptions, was carried off by one of those attacks of inflammation of the lungs of which he had an instinctive foreboding, we were all overcome with a feeling similar to the depression of soul, to the growing sense of solitude, that the deaths of Chateaubriand and of Balzac had already made us feel, an experience quite recently renewed by the death of Vigny. There is, in a time of great national mourning, a lowering of the general vitality, a shadow comes over the intellect similar to a solar eclipse, that momentary imitation of the end of the world.

I think, however, that this impression particularly comes to those men who, in their exalted solitariness of soul, succeed in gathering a family about them only by their intellectual relationships. As for other citizens, they learn to know only slowly the great loss their country has suffered by the death of the great man, and the gap he has created by his going. Even then they need telling.

I thank you heartily, sir, for having allowed me to say freely all the things that were suggested to me by the memory of one of the rare geniuses of our unhappy age, both so poor and so rich, now too demanding, now over-generous, and unjust too often.

From The Salon of 1859

Letters to the Editor of the Revue Française

I. The Modern Artist

My dear M★★★★,

When you did me the honour of asking for a critical review of the Salon you said: 'Be brief; do not produce a catalogue but a general survey, something like the account of a brisk philosophic walk round the exhibition.' Well, your wishes will be fully satisfied; not because your programme fits in, which in fact it does, with my own conception of this boring type of article called a 'Salon'; not because this way of tackling it is easier than the other, brevity always demanding greater efforts than prolixity; but simply because, especially in the present case, no other way is possible. Certainly, my quandary would have been more serious if I had found myself lost in a forest of original works, if the modern French temperament had suddenly undergone a change, and, in its purified, rejuvenated state, had put forth such vigorous and variously scented flowers that the result would have been a series of irrepressible Ohs and Ahs of astonishment, abundant praise, a flow of wordy admiration, and the need for new categories in the language of criticism. But fortunately (for me), nothing of that sort happened. No explosions; no unknown geniuses. The thoughts generated by the sight of this Salon are so simple, so ancient, so classic, that relatively few pages will, no doubt, be all I need to develop them. Do not be surprised, therefore, if banality in the painter has engendered commonplaces in the writer. In any case, you will lose nothing by that; for is there anything (and I am delighted to note that you agree with me in this), anything more charming, more productive, more positively exciting, than the commonplace?

Before I begin, allow me to express a regret that will, I believe, only rarely find expression. We had been told that we were to have some guests to welcome, guests not exactly unknown to us; for the Exhibition in the Avenue Montaigne had already introduced to Parisian exhibitiongoers a number of those charming artists who had been unknown to them far too long. I had therefore looked forward eagerly to renewing my acquaintance with Leslie, that rich, naive and noble humorist, one of the most vigorous embodiments of the British mind; with the two Hunts, one of them a stubborn naturalist, the other the ardent and determined creator of Pre-Raphaelitism; with Maclise, that bold master of composition, as impetuous as he is sure of himself; with Millais, that poet of minute detail; with J. Chalon, that mixture of Claude and Watteau, chronicler of lovely afternoon fêtes in the great Italian parks; with Grant, that natural heir of Reynolds; with Hook, who has the secret of filling his dreams of Venice with a magic light; with that strange Paton, who carries the mind back to Fuseli, and who, with a patience characteristic of another age, embroiders graceful visions of pantheistic chaos; with Cattermole, the painter of historical scenes in water-colour, and with that other astonishing artist, whose name escapes me, architect and dreamer, who builds, on paper, cities with bridges supported by elephants - colossi, under whose legs pass great three-masted schooners in full sail! Wall space had even been reserved for these friends of the imagination and of unusual colour effects, for these, the beloved of the bizarre muse; but alas! for reasons which are unknown to me, and which would, I think, be out of place in your paper, my hopes were disappointed. And so, tragic fires, gestures in the manner of Kean and Macready, intimate studies of the home, oriental splendours, reflected in the poetic mirror of the English mind, Scottish verdures, enchanting arbours, receding depths in water-colours, as spacious as a stage set and yet so small, we shall not gaze on you, not this time at least. Oh! enthusiastic representatives of the imagination and of the most precious faculties of the soul, were you so badly received at your first coming, and do you think us unworthy of understanding you?

And so, my dear M★★★★, we shall have to content ourselves with France; and, believe me, nothing would give me more intense pleasure than to rise to lyrical heights in speaking of my own country's artists; unhappily, in a critical mind with some experience, patriotism does not play an absolutely tyrannical role, and we have certain humiliating admissions to make. The first time I set foot in this Salon, on the very staircase, I met one of our most subtle and most esteemed critics, and to my first question, the question I could naturally be expected to ask, he replied: 'Flat, mediocre; I have seldom seen so depressing a Salon.' He was both right and wrong. An exhibition that can boast a large number of works by Delacroix, by Penguilly and Fromentin cannot be depressing; but looking at the thing as a whole I came to see that there was truth in what he said. True, mediocrity has always dominated the scene in every age, that is beyond dispute; but what is also as true as it is distressing is that the reign of mediocrity is stronger than ever, to the point of triumphant obtrusiveness. After allowing my gaze to wander round for some time on a crowd of platitudes brought to successful conclusions, so many bits of rubbish carefully licked over with the brush, so many stupid or specious things skilfully constructed, I was led, by the natural trend of my reflections, to consider the artist in the past, setting him alongside the artist of today; and then, as usual, at the end of my discouraging meditations, the terrible, the eternal 'Why?' arose inevitably before me. It would seem that meanness, puerility, incuriosity, the flat calm of fatuity have taken the place of ardour, nobility, and turbulent ambition, both in the fine arts and in literature; and that nothing, for the moment, gives us grounds for hope of seeing any spiritual flowering comparable with that of the Restoration. Nor am I alone in feeling oppressed by these sour reflections, believe me; and I shall prove it to you presently. I was accordingly saying to myself: in former days, what manner of man was the artist (Lebrun or David, for example)? Lebrun stands for erudition, imagination, knowledge of the past, love of grandeur. David, that colossus, maligned by a crowd of myrmidons, was he not also love of the past, love of grandeur, allied to erudition? And today, what is the artist, that ancient brother-in-arms of the poet? To answer that question well, my dear M★★★★, we must not be afraid of being too harsh. Scandalous favouritism sometimes calls for a reaction of equal force. Despite his lack of merit, the artist is today, and for many years has been, simply a spoilt child. Just think of the honours, the money squandered on soulless and uncultivated men! For my part, I certainly do not support introducing into a given art means that are foreign to it; and yet, to give an example, I cannot help feeling some sympathy for an artist like Chenavard, always agreeable, agreeable, that is, like good books, and graceful even when most ponderous. At least with him (and what do I care if he be the target of art students' jokes?) I know I can discuss Virgil or Plato. Préault has a delightful talent; it is his instinctive good taste that flings him on the beautiful like a beast of prey on its natural victim. Daumier is endowed with luminous good sense, and this colours his whole conversation. Ricard, in spite of the dazzling and disjointed nature of his talk, reveals at every turn that he knows a lot, and has done a lot of comparative study. There is no need, I think, for me to mention Eugène Delacroix's conversation, which is an admirable mixture of philosophic solidity, light wit and burning enthusiasm. Beyond them I can remember no one worthy of conversing with a philosopher or a poet. Apart from them, you will scarcely find anyone but spoiled children. Tell me, I beg, I entreat you, in what drawing-room, in what tavern, in what social or intimate gathering you have ever heard any witty remark come from the lips of a spoilt child, any profound, brilliant, pregnant remark, a thought- or reverie-provoking one, in short a significant remark! If such a remark has been flung out in conversation, it may not have come from a politician or a philosopher, but certainly from a man of some unusual profession, a hunter, a sailor, a chair-mender; but from an artist, a spoilt child - never!

The spoilt child has inherited from his predecessors a privilege which was legitimate in their day. The enthusiasm that greeted David, Guérin, Girodet, Gros, Delacroix, Bonington, still sheds a kindly afterglow on his mean little person; and while good poets and vigorous historians painfully earn a living, the dunder-headed financier pays sumptuous prices for the spoilt child's indecent bits of impertinence. And please note, that if such favours came the way of worthy recipients, I should not complain. I am not one of those people who begrudge a singer or a dancer who has reached the peak of her art a fortune earned by the hard work and the risks that are her daily portion. If I were, I should be afraid of falling into the pernicious ways of the late Girardin, of fraudulent memory, who one day reproached Théophile Gautier for setting a higher price on his imagination than a Sous-Préfet for his services. That, if you remember rightly, happened on one of those ill-starred days when a terrified public heard him talking in Latin: pecudesque locutae [and the beasts spoke]! No, I am not as unjust as all that; but it is a good thing to raise one's voice and denounce present-day folly when a lovely picture by Delacroix could scarcely find a buyer at a thousand francs, and, at the very same time, the insignificant little figures of Meissonier were fetching ten or even twenty times more. But those happy days are over; now we have sunk even lower, and M. Meissonier, who, in spite of his merits, had the misfortune of introducing and popularizing the taste for the diminutive, is a veritable giant in comparison with our creators of little baubles today.

Imagination discredited, grandeur disdained, love (no, that word is too beautiful) - exclusive concentration on technique, such, I believe, are the main reasons, so far as the artist is concerned, for his decline. The greater the degree of imagination, the surer must be the corresponding mastery of technique, if the latter is to keep pace with the former in its adventurous flights, and to conquer the difficulties imagination eagerly seeks. And the surer his technical mastery, the less the painter should boast and make a parade of it, so that his imagination may shine with its full brilliance. Thus speaks wisdom, and wisdom adds: the man who has mere skill is a fathead, and the man with imagination who tries to do without skill is a lunatic. But simple though such things may be, they are above or below our present-day artist. The daughter of a concierge says to herself: 'I shall go to the Conservatoire, I shall make my début at the Comédie-Française, and I shall speak the lines of Corneille, until such time as I win the same recognition as those who have been speaking them for a long time.' And she is as good as her word. Most classically monotonous, most classically boring and ignorant she is too; but she has succeeded in what was perfectly easy, namely obtaining, by her patience, the privileges of full membership of the Comédie-Française troupe. And the spoilt child, the modern painter, says to himself: 'What is this imagination they talk about? Something dangerous and tiring. What is the study and contemplation of the past? A waste of time. I shall be classical, not like Bertin (for the classical changes its place and its name), but like ... Troyon, for example.' And he does what he said he would. He paints away, and he stops up his soul, and he goes on painting until at last his manner is like that of the artist in fashion, and by his stupidity and skill he deserves the public's favour and money. The imitator of the imitator finds imitators in his turn, and in this way each chases after his own dream of greatness, stopping up more and more tightly his own soul, and above all reading nothing, not even a cookery book, which could at least have provided him with a more glorious, if less lucrative, career. Once he has mastered the art of sauces, patinas, glazes, rubbings, gravies, stews (I am speaking of painting), the spoilt child starts striking attitudes, and repeats, with more conviction than ever, that all the rest is unnecessary.

Once upon a time a German peasant went to see a painter, and this is what he said to him: 'Sir, I want you to paint my portrait. You will show me sitting at the main entrance of my farm in the big armchair I inherited from my father. You will paint my wife by my side, with her distaff; behind us, coming and going, my daughters preparing the family supper. To the left, you will depict the grand avenue, and emerging from it those of my sons who are returning from the fields, after having brought the cows back to the cowshed; others of them, with my grandsons, are busy putting the farm carts stacked with hay under cover. As I contemplate the scene, please do not forget the puffs of smoke from my pipe, tinted by the rays of the setting sun. I should also like the viewer to hear the sounds of the Angelus ringing from the church belfry close by. That is where we all got married, father and sons. It is important that you should paint the satisfied air I enjoy at that time of the day, as I look upon my family and my wealth, increased by the labour of another day.'

Loud cheers for that peasant! Without knowing it, he had understood painting. The love of his profession had heightened his imagination. Which of our fashionable painters would be worthy of executing that portrait, and which of them has an imagination on a level with that one?

II. The Modern Public and Photography

My dear M★★★★,

If I had time to amuse you, I could easily do so by thumbing through the pages of the catalogue, and extracting a list of all the ridiculous titles and laughable subjects that aim to attract the eye. That is so typical of French attitudes. The attempt to provoke astonishment by means that are foreign to the art in question is the great resource of people who are not painters born. Sometimes even, but always in France, this form of vice takes hold of men who are by no means devoid of talent, and who dishonour it, in this way, by an adulterous mixture. I could parade before your eyes the comic title in the manner of the vaudevillist, the sentimental title, lacking only an exclamation mark, the pun-title, the deep and philosophical title, the misleading or trap title such as Brutus, lâche César.

'Oh ye depraved and unbelieving race,' says Our Lord, 'how long must I remain with you, how long shall I continue to suffer?' This people, artists and public, has so little faith in painting that it is for ever trying to disguise it, and wrap it up in sugar-coated pills, like some unpalatable physick - and what sugar! Ye Gods! Let me pick out the titles of two pictures which, by the way, I have not seen: Amour et gibelotte [Love and rabbit fricassee]! How your curiosity is at once whetted, is it not? I am groping about in an effort to relate intimately these two ideas, the idea of love and the idea of a skinned rabbit dished up as a stew. You can scarcely expect me to suppose that the painter's imagination has gone to the length of fixing a quiver, wings and an eye bandage on the corpse of a domestic animal; the allegory would really be too obscure. I am more inclined to think the title must have been composed, following the formula of Misanthropie et repentir [Misanthropy and repentance]. The true title should therefore be 'Lovers eating rabbit stew'. Then comes the question: are they young or old, a workman and his girl friend, or an old soldier and his moll sitting under a dusty arbour? Only the picture could tell me. Then we have Monarchique, Catholique et Soldat! This title belongs to the high-falutin, paladin type, the Itinéraire de Paris à Jerusalem type (oh Chateaubriand, my apologies to you! the most noble things can become means for caricature, and the words of a leader of Empire for daubers' squibs). The picture boasting this title must surely represent a personage doing three things at once: fighting, attending communion, and being present at the 'petit lever' of Louis XIV. Or could it be a warrior, tattooed with a fleur de lys and devotional pictures? But what is the good of losing oneself in speculation? The simple truth is that titles such as these are a perfidious and sterile means of creating an impact of surprise. And what is particularly deplorable is that the picture may be good, however strange that may sound. This applies to Amour et gibelotte too. And I noticed an excellent little group of sculpture, but unfortunately did not take down its number; and when I wanted to look up what the subject of the piece was, I read through the catalogue four times in vain. In the end you told me, of your kindness, that the piece was called Toujours et jamais. It really distressed me to see that a man with genuine talent could go in for the rebus sort of title.

You must forgive my having allowed myself a few moments' amusement in the manner of cheap newspapers. But, however frivolous the matter may seem to you, you will nonetheless discover there, if you examine it carefully, a deplorable symptom. To sum up my thought in a paradoxical way, let me ask you, and those of my friends who are more learned than I in the history of art, whether the taste for the silly, the taste for the witty (which comes to the same thing) have always existed, whether Appartement à louer and other such alembicated notions have appeared in every age, to provoke the same degree of enthusiasm as today, if the Venice of Veronese and Bassano was affected by these sorts of logogriph, if the eyes of Giulio Romano, Michelangelo and Bandinelli were astounded by similar monstrosities; in short I would like to know whether M. Biard is eternal and omnipresent, like God. I do not believe it, and I regard these horrors as a special form of grace granted to the French. It is true that their artists inoculate them with this taste; and it is no less true that they in their turn call upon the artists to satisfy this need; for if the artist makes dullards of the public, the latter pays him back in his own coin. They form two co-relative terms, which act upon one another with equal force. Accordingly let us watch with wonder the rate at which we are moving downwards along the road of progress (and by progress I mean the progressive domination of matter), the wonderful diffusion, occurring daily, of commonplace skill, of the skill that may be acquired simply by patience.

In this country, the natural painter, like the natural poet, is almost a monster. Our exclusive taste for the true (so noble a taste when limited to its proper purposes) oppresses and smothers the taste for the beautiful. Where only the beautiful should be looked for - shall we say in a beautiful painting, and anyone can easily guess the sort I have in mind - our people look only for the true. They are not artistic, naturally artistic; philosophers, perhaps, or moralists, engineers, lovers of instructive anecdotes, anything you like, but never spontaneously artistic. They feel, or rather judge, successively, analytically. Other more favoured peoples feel things quickly, at once, synthetically.

I was referring just now to the artists who seek to astonish the public. The desire to astonish or be astonished is perfectly legitimate. 'It is a happiness to wonder': but also 'It is a happiness to dream.' If you insist on my giving you the title of artist or art-lover, the whole question is by what means you intend to create or to feel this impact of wonder? Because beauty always contains an element of wonder, it would be absurd to assume that what is wonderful is always beautiful. Now the French public, which, in the manner of mean little souls, is singularly incapable of feeling the joy of dreaming or of admiration, wants to have the thrill of surprise by means that are alien to art, and its obedient artists bow to the public's taste; they aim to draw its attention, its surprise, stupefy it, by unworthy stratagems, because they know the public is incapable of deriving ecstasy from the natural means of true art.

In these deplorable times, a new industry has developed, which has helped in no small way to confirm fools in their faith, and to ruin what vestige of the divine might still have remained in the French mind. Naturally, this idolatrous multitude was calling for an ideal worthy of itself and in keeping with its own nature. In the domain of painting and statuary, the present-day credo of the worldly wise, especially in France (and I do not believe that anyone whosoever would dare to maintain the contrary), is this: 'I believe in nature, and I believe only in nature.' (There are good reasons for that.) 'I believe that art is, and can only be, the exact reproduction of nature.' (One timid and dissenting sect wants naturally unpleasing objects, a chamber pot, for example, or a skeleton, to be excluded.) 'Thus if an industrial process could give us a result identical to nature, that would be absolute art.' An avenging God has heard the prayers of this multitude; Daguerre was his messiah. And then they said to themselves: 'Since photography provides us with every desirable guarantee of exactitude' (they believe that, poor madmen!), 'art is photography.' From that moment onwards, our loathsome society rushed, like Narcissus, to contemplate its trivial image on the metallic plate. A form of lunacy, an extraordinary fanaticism, took hold of these new sun-worshippers. Strange abominations manifested themselves. By bringing together and posing a pack of rascals, male and female, dressed up like carnival-time butchers and washerwomen, and in persuading these 'heroes' to 'hold' their improvised grimaces for as long as the photographic process required, people really believed they could represent the tragic and the charming scenes of ancient history. Some democratic writer must have seen in that a cheap means of spreading the dislike of history and painting amongst the masses, thus committing a double sacrilege, and insulting, at one and the same time, the divine art of painting and the sublime art of the actor. It was not long before thousands of pairs of greedy eyes were glued to the peepholes of the stereoscope, as though they were the skylights of the infinite. The love of obscenity, which is as vigorous a growth in the heart of natural man as self-love, could not let slip such a glorious opportunity for its own satisfaction. And pray do not let it be said that children, coming home from school, were the only people to take pleasure in such tomfooleries; it was the rage of society. I once heard a smart woman, a society woman, not of my society, say to her friends, who were discreetly trying to hide such pictures from her, thus taking it upon themselves to have some modesty on her behalf: 'Let me see; nothing shocks me.' That is what she said, I swear it, I heard it with my own ears; but who will believe me? 'You can see that they are great ladies,' says Alexandre Dumas. 'There are greater ones still!' echoes Cazotte.

As the photographic industry became the refuge of all failed painters with too little talent, or too lazy to complete their studies, this universal craze not only assumed the air of blind and imbecile infatuation, but took on the aspect of revenge. I do not believe, or at least I cannot bring myself to believe, that any such stupid conspiracy, in which, as in every other, wicked men and dupes are to be found, could ever achieve a total victory; but I am convinced that the badly applied advances of photography, like all purely material progress for that matter, have greatly contributed to the impoverishment of French artistic genius, rare enough in all conscience. Modern fatuity may roar to its heart's content, eruct all the borborygmi of its pot-bellied person, vomit all the indigestible sophistries stuffed down its greedy gullet by recent philosophy; it is simple common-sense that, when industry erupts into the sphere of art, it becomes the latter's mortal enemy, and in the resulting confusion of functions none is well carried out. Poetry and progress are two ambitious men that hate each other, with an instinctive hatred, and when they meet along a pathway one or other must give way. If photography is allowed to deputize for art in some of art's activities, it will not be long before it has supplanted or corrupted art altogether, thanks to the stupidity of the masses, its natural ally. Photography must, therefore, return to its true duty, which is that of handmaid of the arts and sciences, but their very humble handmaid, like printing and shorthand, which have neither created nor supplemented literature. Let photography quickly enrich the traveller's album, and restore to his eyes the precision his memory may lack; let it adorn the library of the naturalist, magnify microscopic insects, even strengthen, with a few facts, the hypotheses of the astronomer; let it, in short, be the secretary and record-keeper of whomsoever needs absolute material accuracy for professional reasons. So far so good. Let it save crumbling ruins from oblivion, books, engravings, and manuscripts, the prey of time, all those precious things, vowed to dissolution, which crave a place in the archives of our memories; in all these things, photography will deserve our thanks and applause. But if once it be allowed to impinge on the sphere of the intangible and the imaginary, on anything that has value solely because man adds something to it from his soul, then woe betide us!

I know perfectly well I shall be told: 'The disease you have just described is a disease of boneheads. What man worthy of the name of artist, and what true art-lover has ever confused art and industry?' I know that, but let me, in my turn, ask them if they believe in the contagion of good and evil, in the pressure of society on the individual, and the involuntary, inevitable obedience of the individual to society. It is an indisputable and irresistible law that the artist acts upon the public, that the public reacts on the artist; besides, the facts, those damning witnesses, are easy to study; we can measure the full extent of the disaster. More and more, as each day goes by, art is losing in self-respect, is prostrating itself before external reality, and the painter is becoming more and more inclined to paint, not what he dreams, but what he sees. And yet it is a happiness to dream, and it used to be an honour to express what one dreamed; but can one believe that the painter still knows that happiness?

Will the honest observer declare that the invasion of photography and the great industrial madness of today are wholly innocent of this deplorable result? Can it legitimately be supposed that a people whose eyes get used to accepting the results of a material science as products of the beautiful will not, within a given time, have singularly diminished its capacity for judging and feeling those things that are most ethereal and immaterial?